<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "syndication_xml.dtd">
<article articleid="100888" articletypeid="1" language="en_us" lastupdate="2021-Jul-01 03:09:38" url="/article/cave-art/100888" version="7">
 <title>
  cave art
 </title>
 <p>
  <e type="bold">
   cave art
  </e>
  , generally, the numerous
  <xref articleid="108604">
   paintings
  </xref>
  and
  <xref articleid="32673">
   engravings
  </xref>
  found in caves and shelters dating back to the
  <xref articleid="41958">
   Ice Age
  </xref>
  (Upper
  <xref articleid="58083">
   Paleolithic
  </xref>
  ), roughly between 40,000 and 14,000 years ago.
  <e type="italic">
   See also
  </e>
  <xref articleid="473205">
   rock art
  </xref>
  .
 </p>
 <p>
  <assembly id="a194789" url="/assembly/view/194789">
   <title>
    bison drawing at Altamira cave
   </title>
   <media mediaid="10135" type="image" url="/35/10135-004-D1A6B3B2.jpg"/>
   <caption>
    Cave painting of bison, c. 15,000
    <e type="smallcap">
     bce
    </e>
    ; in Altamira cave, near Santander, Spain.
   </caption>
   <credit>
    A. Held/J.P. Ziolo, Paris
   </credit>
  </assembly>
  <assemblyref assemblyid="a194789"/>
  The first painted cave acknowledged as being Paleolithic, meaning from the
  <xref articleid="109432">
   Stone Age
  </xref>
  , was
  <xref articleid="5917">
   Altamira
  </xref>
  in
  <xref articleid="108580">
   Spain
  </xref>
  . The art discovered there was deemed by experts to be the work of modern humans (
  <e type="italic">
   Homo sapiens
  </e>
  ). Most examples of cave art have been found in
  <xref articleid="110436">
   France
  </xref>
  and in Spain, but a few are also known in
  <xref articleid="105994">
   Portugal
  </xref>
  ,
  <xref articleid="110752">
   England
  </xref>
  ,
  <xref articleid="106448">
   Italy
  </xref>
  ,
  <xref articleid="110568">
   Romania
  </xref>
  ,
  <xref articleid="106260">
   Germany
  </xref>
  ,
  <xref articleid="109504">
   Russia
  </xref>
  , and Indonesia. The total number of known decorated sites is about 400.
 </p>
 <p>
  Most cave art consists of paintings made with either red or black pigment. The reds were made with iron oxides (hematite), whereas manganese dioxide and charcoal were used for the blacks. Sculptures have been discovered as well, such as the clay statues of bison in the Tuc d’Audoubert cave in 1912 and a statue of a bear in the Montespan cave in 1923, both located in the
  <xref articleid="106060">
   French Pyrenees
  </xref>
  . Carved walls were discovered in the shelters of Roc-aux-Sorciers (1950) in Vienne and of Cap Blanc (1909) in Dordogne. Engravings were made with fingers on soft walls or with flint tools on hard surfaces in a number of other caves and shelters.
 </p>
 <p>
  Representations in caves, painted or otherwise, include few humans, but sometimes human heads or genitalia appear in isolation. Hand stencils and handprints are characteristic of the earlier periods, as in the Gargas cave in the French Pyrenees. Animal figures always constitute the majority of images in caves from all periods. During the earliest millennia when cave art was first being made, the species most often represented, as in the
  <xref articleid="623492">
   Chauvet–Pont-d’Arc
  </xref>
  cave in France, were the most-formidable ones, now long extinct—cave lions,
  <xref articleid="50411">
   mammoths
  </xref>
  ,
  <xref articleid="77447">
   woolly rhinoceroses
  </xref>
  ,
  <xref articleid="21907">
   cave bears
  </xref>
  . Later on,
  <xref articleid="106287">
   horses
  </xref>
  ,
  <xref articleid="80311">
   bison
  </xref>
  ,
  <xref articleid="11290">
   aurochs
  </xref>
  ,
  <xref articleid="29728">
   cervids
  </xref>
  , and
  <xref articleid="41890">
   ibex
  </xref>
  became prevalent, as in the
  <xref articleid="47247">
   Lascaux
  </xref>
  and
  <xref articleid="55689">
   Niaux
  </xref>
  caves. Birds and fish were rarely depicted. Geometric signs are always numerous, though the specific types vary based on the time period in which the cave was painted and the cave’s location.
 </p>
 <p>
  Cave art is generally considered to have a symbolic or religious function, sometimes both. The exact meanings of the images remain unknown, but some experts think they may have been created within the framework of
  <xref articleid="109509">
   shamanic
  </xref>
  beliefs and practices. One such practice involved going into a deep cave for a ceremony during which a shaman would enter a trance state and send his or her soul into the otherworld to make contact with the spirits and try to obtain their benevolence.
 </p>
 <p>
  Examples of paintings and engravings in deep caves—i.e., existing completely in the dark—are rare outside Europe, but they do exist in the Americas (e.g., the
  <xref articleid="51572">
   Maya
  </xref>
  caves in Mexico, the so-called mud-glyph caves in the southeastern United States), in
  <xref articleid="110544">
   Australia
  </xref>
  (Koonalda Cave, South Australia), and in
  <xref articleid="110518">
   Asia
  </xref>
  (the
  <xref articleid="44401">
   Kalimantan
  </xref>
  caves in
  <xref articleid="80765">
   Borneo
  </xref>
  , Indonesia, with many hand stencils). Art in the open, on shelters or on rocks, is extremely abundant all over the world and generally belongs to much later times.
 </p>
 <signature>
  Jean Clottes
 </signature>
 <signature>
  EB Editors
 </signature>
 <h1 id="h325729">
  <title>
   Bibliography
  </title>
  <p>
   General books on Paleolithic cave art include
   <e type="smallcap">
    Peter J. Ucko
   </e>
   and
   <e type="smallcap">
    Andrée Rosenfeld
   </e>
   ,
   <e type="italic">
    Paleolithic Cave Art
   </e>
   (1967);
   <e type="smallcap">
    Jean Clottes
   </e>
   ,
   <e type="italic">
    Cave Art
   </e>
   (2008); and
   <e type="smallcap">
    Christine Desdemaines-Hugon
   </e>
   ,
   <e type="italic">
    Stepping Stones: A Journey Through the Ice Age Caves of the Dordogne
   </e>
   (2010). Books that discuss interpretation and meanings are
   <e type="smallcap">
    Jean Clottes
   </e>
   and
   <e type="smallcap">
    J. David Lewis-Williams
   </e>
   ,
   <e type="italic">
    The Shamans of Prehistory: Trance and Magic in the Painted Caves
   </e>
   , trans. by
   <e type="smallcap">
    Sophie Hawkes
   </e>
   (1998);
   <e type="smallcap">
    J. David Lewis-Williams
   </e>
   ,
   <e type="italic">
    The Mind in the Cave: Consciousness and the Origins of Art
   </e>
   (2002); and
   <e type="smallcap">
    R. Dale Guthrie
   </e>
   ,
   <e type="italic">
    The Nature of Paleolithic Art
   </e>
   (2005).
   <e type="smallcap">
    Andrea Joyce Stone
   </e>
   ,
   <e type="italic">
    Images from the Underworld: Naj Tunich and the Tradition of Maya Cave Painting
   </e>
   (1995); and
   <e type="smallcap">
    Jean Clottes
   </e>
   ,
   <e type="italic">
    World Rock Art
   </e>
   , trans. by
   <e type="smallcap">
    Guy Bennett
   </e>
   (2002), are books about rock art outside Europe.
  </p>
  <signature>
   Jean Clottes
  </signature>
 </h1>
 <copyright>
  Encyclopædia Britannica
 </copyright>
</article>