<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "syndication_xml.dtd">
<article articleid="101148" articletypeid="1" language="en_us" lastupdate="2021-Oct-27 08:02:19" url="/article/electromagnetic-spectrum/101148" version="4">
 <title>
  electromagnetic spectrum
 </title>
 <p>
  <assembly id="a106806" url="/assembly/view/106806">
   <media mediaid="276" type="image" url="/76/276-004-404D8CFF.jpg"/>
   <caption>
    The electromagnetic spectrum. The narrow range of visible light is shown enlarged at the right.
   </caption>
   <credit>
    Encyclopædia Britannica, Inc.
   </credit>
  </assembly>
  <e type="bold">
   electromagnetic spectrum
  </e>
  ,
  <assemblyref assemblyid="a106806"/>
  the entire distribution of
  <xref articleid="106022">
   electromagnetic radiation
  </xref>
  according to
  <xref articleid="35365">
   frequency
  </xref>
  or
  <xref articleid="76325">
   wavelength
  </xref>
  . Although all electromagnetic waves travel at the
  <xref articleid="471069">
   speed of light
  </xref>
  in a vacuum, they do so at a wide range of frequencies, wavelengths, and
  <xref articleid="59817">
   photon
  </xref>
  energies. The electromagnetic spectrum comprises the span of all electromagnetic radiation and consists of many subranges, commonly referred to as portions, such as visible light or ultraviolet radiation. The various portions bear different names based on differences in behaviour in the emission, transmission, and absorption of the corresponding waves and also based on their different practical applications. There are no precise accepted boundaries between any of these contiguous portions, so the ranges tend to overlap.
 </p>
 <p>
  <assembly id="a123640" url="/assembly/view/123640">
   <title>
    types of electromagnetic radiation
   </title>
   <media mediaid="95275" type="image" url="/75/95275-004-E6143582.jpg"/>
   <caption>
    Radio waves, infrared rays, visible light, ultraviolet rays, X-rays, and gamma rays are all types of electromagnetic radiation. Radio waves have the longest wavelength, and gamma rays have the shortest wavelength.
   </caption>
   <credit>
    Encyclopædia Britannica, Inc.
   </credit>
  </assembly>
  <assemblyref assemblyid="a123640"/>
  The entire electromagnetic spectrum, from the lowest to the highest frequency (longest to shortest wavelength), includes all radio waves (e.g., commercial
  <xref articleid="106101">
   radio
  </xref>
  and
  <xref articleid="106102">
   television
  </xref>
  ,
  <xref articleid="52523">
   microwaves
  </xref>
  ,
  <xref articleid="109463">
   radar
  </xref>
  ),
  <xref articleid="42403">
   infrared radiation
  </xref>
  , visible
  <xref articleid="110443">
   light
  </xref>
  ,
  <xref articleid="74181">
   ultraviolet radiation
  </xref>
  ,
  <xref articleid="77656">
   X-rays
  </xref>
  , and
  <xref articleid="35974">
   gamma rays
  </xref>
  . Nearly all frequencies and wavelengths of electromagnetic radiation can be used for
  <xref articleid="110407">
   spectroscopy
  </xref>
  .
 </p>
 <copyright>
  Encyclopædia Britannica
 </copyright>
</article>