<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "syndication_xml.dtd">
<article articleid="101223" articletypeid="1" language="en_us" lastupdate="2021-Jul-01 03:10:07" url="/article/form/101223" version="2">
 <title>
  form
 </title>
 <p>
  <e type="bold">
   form
  </e>
  , in crystallography, all
  <xref articleid="110297">
   crystal
  </xref>
  faces having similar symmetry. Those forms that enclose space are called closed forms; those that do not, open forms. The faces that comprise a form will be similar in appearance, even though of different shapes and sizes; this similarity may be evident from natural striations, etchings, or growths, or it may be apparent only after etching with acid.
 </p>
 <p>
  The forms in all crystal systems except the isometric are similar and may be generally described as follows:
 </p>
 <list type="ul">
  <item>
   Pedion: a single face;
  </item>
  <item>
   Pinacoid: pair of opposite faces parallel to two of the principal crystallographic axes;
  </item>
  <item>
   Dome: two nonparallel faces symmetrical to a plane of symmetry;
  </item>
  <item>
   Sphenoid: two nonparallel faces symmetrical to a 2- or 4-fold axis of symmetry;
  </item>
  <item>
   Disphenoid: four-faced closed form in which the two faces of a sphenoid alternate above two faces of another sphenoid;
  </item>
  <item>
   Prism: 3, 4, 6, 8, or 12 faces the intersection lines of which are parallel and (except for some monoclinic prisms) are parallel to a principal crystallographic axis;
  </item>
  <item>
   Pyramid: 3, 4, 6, 8, or 12 nonparallel faces that meet in a point;
  </item>
  <item>
   Scalenohedron: 8-faced (tetragonal) or 12-faced (hexagonal) closed form in which the faces are grouped in symmetrical pairs; in perfect crystals, each face is a scalene triangle;
  </item>
  <item>
   Trapezohedron: 6-, 8-, 12-, or 24-faced closed form in which half the faces are offset above the other half; in well-developed crystals, each face is a trapezium;
  </item>
  <item>
   Dipyramid: 6-, 8-, 12-, 16-, or 24-faced closed form in which the lower pyramid is a reflection of the upper;
  </item>
  <item>
   Rhombohedron: closed form of six identical faces in which none of the intersection edges is perpendicular.
  </item>
 </list>
 <copyright>
  Encyclopædia Britannica
 </copyright>
</article>