<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "syndication_xml.dtd">
<article articleid="102608" articletypeid="1" language="en_us" lastupdate="2021-Jul-01 03:11:04" url="/article/reflection-nebula/102608" version="3">
 <title>
  reflection nebula
 </title>
 <p>
  <assembly id="a3001" url="/assembly/view/3001">
   <title>
    Pleiades
   </title>
   <media mediaid="2958" type="image" url="/58/2958-004-D3B94115.jpg"/>
   <caption>
    Bright nebulosity in the Pleiades (M45, NGC 1432), distance 490 light-years. Cluster stars provide the light, and surrounding clouds of dust reflect and scatter the rays from the stars.
   </caption>
   <credit>
    Courtesy of Palomar Observatory/California Institute of Technology
   </credit>
  </assembly>
  <e type="bold">
   reflection nebula
  </e>
  ,
  <assemblyref assemblyid="a3001"/>
  interstellar cloud that would normally be a dark
  <xref articleid="108754">
   nebula
  </xref>
  (or
  <xref articleid="474098">
   molecular cloud
  </xref>
  ) but whose dust reflects the light from a nearby bright
  <xref articleid="110472">
   star
  </xref>
  that is not hot enough to ionize the cloud’s
  <xref articleid="110604">
   hydrogen
  </xref>
  . The famous nebulosity in the
  <xref articleid="60393">
   Pleiades
  </xref>
  <xref articleid="110473">
   star cluster
  </xref>
  is of this type; it was discovered in 1912 that the
  <xref articleid="69040">
   spectrum
  </xref>
  of this nebula mimics the absorption lines of the nearby stars, whereas bright nebulae that emit their own light show their own characteristic emission lines. The brightest reflection nebulae are illuminated by B-type stars that are very luminous but have temperatures lower than about 25,000 K, cooler than the O-type stars that would ionize the hydrogen in the gas and produce an
  <xref articleid="38666">
   H II region
  </xref>
  . The extent and brightness of reflection nebulae show conclusively that dust grains are excellent reflectors in the broad range of wavelengths extending from the
  <xref articleid="74181">
   ultraviolet
  </xref>
  (as determined from observations from space) through the visible. Optical observations suggest that about 60–70 percent of the light is reflected rather than absorbed, while the corresponding fraction for
  <xref articleid="110147">
   Earth
  </xref>
  is only 35 percent and for the
  <xref articleid="53598">
   Moon
  </xref>
  a mere 5 percent. Grains reflect light almost as well as fresh
  <xref articleid="68389">
   snow
  </xref>
  , more because of their favourable size (which promotes scattering rather than absorption) than their chemical composition. Calculations show that even
  <xref articleid="37755">
   graphite
  </xref>
  , which is black in bulk, reflects visible light well when dispersed into small particles.
 </p>
 <signature>
  John S. Mathis
 </signature>
 <copyright>
  Encyclopædia Britannica
 </copyright>
</article>