<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "syndication_xml.dtd">
<article articleid="102624" articletypeid="1" language="en_us" lastupdate="2021-Jul-01 03:11:05" url="/article/In-Search-of-Lost-Time/102624" version="3">
 <title>
  In Search of Lost Time
 </title>
 <p>
  <e type="bold">
   In Search of Lost Time
  </e>
  , also translated as
  <e type="bold">
   Remembrance of Things Past
  </e>
  , novel in seven parts by
  <xref articleid="61641">
   Marcel Proust
  </xref>
  , published in French as
  <e type="italic">
   À la recherche du temps perdu
  </e>
  from 1913 to 1927. The novel is the story of Proust’s own life, told as an allegorical search for truth. It is the major work of French fiction of the early 20th century.
 </p>
 <p>
  In January 1909 Proust experienced the involuntary recall of a childhood memory when he tasted a rusk (a twice-baked bread, which in his novel became a
  <xref articleid="49884">
   madeleine
  </xref>
  ) dipped in tea. In July he retired from the world to write his novel, finishing the first draft in September 1912. The first volume,
  <e type="italic">
   Du côté de chez Swann
  </e>
  (
  <e type="italic">
   Swann’s Way
  </e>
  also translated as
  <e type="italic">
   The Way by Swann’s
  </e>
  ), was refused on several occasions but was finally issued at the author’s expense in November 1913. Proust at this time planned only two further volumes.
 </p>
 <p>
  During the war years he revised the remainder of his novel, enriching and deepening its feeling, texture, and construction, enhancing the realistic and satirical elements, and tripling its length. In so doing he transformed it into one of the most profound achievements of the human imagination. In June 1919
  <e type="italic">
   À l’ombre des jeunes filles en fleurs
  </e>
  (
  <e type="italic">
   Within a Budding Grove
  </e>
  , also published as
  <e type="italic">
   In the Shadow of Young Girls in Flower
  </e>
  ) appeared simultaneously with a reprint of
  <e type="italic">
   Swann
  </e>
  . In December 1919
  <e type="italic">
   À l’ombre
  </e>
  received the
  <xref articleid="98981">
   Prix Goncourt
  </xref>
  , and Proust suddenly became world famous. Two more installments appeared in his lifetime and had the benefit of his final revision:
  <e type="italic">
   Le Côté de Guermantes
  </e>
  (1920;
  <e type="italic">
   The Guermantes Way
  </e>
  ) and
  <e type="italic">
   Sodome et Gomorrhe
  </e>
  (1921;
  <e type="italic">
   Cities of the Plain
  </e>
  , or
  <e type="italic">
   Sodom and Gomorrah
  </e>
  ). The last three parts of
  <e type="italic">
   À la recherche
  </e>
  were published posthumously in an advanced but not final stage of revision:
  <e type="italic">
   La Prisonnière
  </e>
  (1923;
  <e type="italic">
   The Captive
  </e>
  ),
  <e type="italic">
   Albertine disparue
  </e>
  (1925;
  <e type="italic">
   The Sweet Cheat Gone
  </e>
  , originally called
  <e type="italic">
   La Fugitive
  </e>
  ), and
  <e type="italic">
   Le Temps retrouvé
  </e>
  (1927;
  <e type="italic">
   Time Regained
  </e>
  , or
  <e type="italic">
   Finding Time Again
  </e>
  ). The first authoritative edition of the entire work was published in 1954.
 </p>
 <p>
  The novel begins with the middle-aged narrator’s memories of his happy childhood. The narrator tells the story of his life, introducing along the way a series of memorable characters, among them
  <xref articleid="486779">
   Charles Swann
  </xref>
  , who forms a stormy alliance with the prostitute
  <xref articleid="485948">
   Odette
  </xref>
  ; their daughter, Gilberte Swann, with whom young Marcel falls in love; the aristocratic
  <xref articleid="485041">
   Guermantes family
  </xref>
  , including the dissolute
  <xref articleid="484245">
   Baron de Charlus
  </xref>
  and his nephew Robert de Saint-Loup; and
  <xref articleid="483760">
   Albertine
  </xref>
  , to whom Marcel forms a passionate attachment. Marcel’s world expands to encompass both the cultivated and the corrupt, and he sees the full range of human folly and misery. At his lowest ebb, he feels that time is lost; beauty and meaning have faded from all he ever pursued and won; and he renounces the book he has always hoped to write. At a reception after the war, the narrator realizes, through a series of incidents of unconscious memory, that all the beauty he has experienced in the past is eternally alive. Time is regained, and he sets to work, racing against death, to write the very novel the reader has just experienced. In his quest for time lost, he invented nothing but altered everything, selecting, fusing, and transmuting the facts so that their underlying unity and universal significance would be revealed.
 </p>
 <copyright>
  Encyclopædia Britannica
 </copyright>
</article>