<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "syndication_xml.dtd">
<article articleid="105842" articletypeid="1" language="en_us" lastupdate="2021-Jul-01 03:18:28" url="/article/engineering/105842" version="7">
 <title>
  engineering
 </title>
 <p>
  <e type="bold">
   engineering
  </e>
  , the application of
  <xref articleid="66286">
   science
  </xref>
  to the optimum conversion of the resources of nature to the uses of humankind. The field has been defined by the Engineers Council for Professional Development, in the United States, as the creative application of “scientific principles to design or develop structures, machines, apparatus, or manufacturing processes, or works utilizing them singly or in combination; or to construct or operate the same with full cognizance of their design; or to forecast their behaviour under specific operating conditions; all as respects an intended function, economics of operation and safety to life and property.” The term
  <e type="italic">
   engineering
  </e>
  is sometimes more loosely defined, especially in Great Britain, as the manufacture or assembly of engines, machine tools, and machine parts.
 </p>
 <p>
  The words
  <e type="italic">
   engine
  </e>
  and
  <e type="italic">
   ingenious
  </e>
  are derived from the same Latin root,
  <e type="italic">
   ingenerare
  </e>
  , which means “to create.” The early English verb
  <e type="italic">
   engine
  </e>
  meant “to contrive.” Thus, the engines of war were devices such as
  <xref articleid="20771">
   catapults
  </xref>
  , floating bridges, and assault towers; their designer was the “engine-er,” or military engineer. The counterpart of the
  <xref articleid="52677">
   military engineer
  </xref>
  was the
  <xref articleid="105844">
   civil engineer
  </xref>
  , who applied essentially the same knowledge and skills to designing buildings, streets, water supplies, sewage systems, and other projects.
 </p>
 <p>
  Associated with engineering is a great body of special knowledge; preparation for professional practice involves extensive training in the application of that knowledge. Standards of engineering practice are maintained through the efforts of professional societies, usually organized on a national or regional basis, with all members acknowledging a responsibility to the public over and above responsibilities to their employers or to other members of their society.
 </p>
 <p>
  The function of the scientist is to know, while that of the engineer is to do. Scientists add to the store of verified systematized knowledge of the physical world, and engineers bring this knowledge to bear on practical problems. Engineering is based principally on
  <xref articleid="108654">
   physics
  </xref>
  ,
  <xref articleid="108655">
   chemistry
  </xref>
  , and
  <xref articleid="109827">
   mathematics
  </xref>
  and their extensions into
  <xref articleid="109860">
   materials science
  </xref>
  , solid and
  <xref articleid="110311">
   fluid mechanics
  </xref>
  ,
  <xref articleid="108582">
   thermodynamics
  </xref>
  , transfer and rate processes, and
  <xref articleid="473436">
   systems analysis
  </xref>
  .
 </p>
 <p>
  Unlike scientists, engineers are not free to select the problems that interest them. They must solve problems as they arise, and their solutions must satisfy conflicting requirements. Usually, efficiency costs money, safety adds to complexity, and improved performance increases weight. The engineering solution is the optimum solution, the end result that, taking many factors into account, is most desirable. It may be the most reliable within a given weight limit, the simplest that will satisfy certain safety requirements, or the most efficient for a given cost. In many engineering problems the social and environmental costs are significant.
 </p>
 <p>
  Engineers employ two types of natural resources—materials and energy. Materials are useful because of their properties: their strength, ease of fabrication, lightness, or durability; their ability to insulate or conduct; their chemical, electrical, or acoustical properties. Important sources of energy include
  <xref articleid="35002">
   fossil fuels
  </xref>
  (
  <xref articleid="110442">
   coal
  </xref>
  ,
  <xref articleid="110438">
   petroleum
  </xref>
  ,
  <xref articleid="110439">
   natural gas
  </xref>
  ),
  <xref articleid="443102">
   wind
  </xref>
  ,
  <xref articleid="68559">
   sunlight
  </xref>
  ,
  <xref articleid="41726">
   falling water
  </xref>
  , and
  <xref articleid="110414">
   nuclear fission
  </xref>
  . Since most resources are limited, engineers must concern themselves with the continual development of new resources as well as the efficient utilization of existing ones.
 </p>
 <h1 id="h64713">
  <title>
   History of engineering
  </title>
  <p>
   <assembly id="a120352" url="/assembly/view/120352">
    <title>
     Pont du Gard, Nîmes, France
    </title>
    <media mediaid="112156" type="image" url="/56/112156-004-C898B6B4.jpg"/>
    <caption>
     Pont du Gard, an ancient Roman aqueduct in Nîmes, France.
    </caption>
    <credit>
     © Karel Gallas/Shutterstock.com
    </credit>
   </assembly>
   <assemblyref assemblyid="a120352"/>
   The first engineer known by name and achievement is
   <xref articleid="42182">
    Imhotep
   </xref>
   , builder of the Step Pyramid at Ṣaqqārah, Egypt, probably about 2550
   <e type="smallcap">
    bce
   </e>
   . Imhotep’s successors—Egyptian, Persian, Greek, and Roman—carried civil engineering to remarkable heights on the basis of empirical methods aided by arithmetic, geometry, and a smattering of physical science. The
   <xref articleid="59588">
    Pharos (lighthouse) of Alexandria
   </xref>
   ,
   <xref articleid="43565">
    Solomon’s Temple
   </xref>
   in Jerusalem, the
   <xref articleid="24848">
    Colosseum
   </xref>
   in Rome, the Persian and Roman road systems, the
   <xref articleid="36051">
    Pont du Gard
   </xref>
   aqueduct in France, and many other large structures, some of which endure to this day, testify to their skill, imagination, and daring. Of many treatises written by them, one in particular survives to provide a picture of engineering education and practice in classical times:
   <xref articleid="75580">
    Vitruvius
   </xref>
   ’s
   <e type="italic">
    De architectura
   </e>
   , published in Rome in the 1st century
   <e type="smallcap">
    ce
   </e>
   , a 10-volume work covering building materials, construction methods, hydraulics, measurement, and town planning.
  </p>
  <p>
   In construction, medieval European engineers carried technique, in the form of the Gothic
   <xref articleid="9254">
    arch
   </xref>
   and
   <xref articleid="472352">
    flying buttress
   </xref>
   , to a height unknown to the Romans. The sketchbook of the 13th-century French engineer
   <xref articleid="75376">
    Villard de Honnecourt
   </xref>
   reveals a wide knowledge of mathematics, geometry, natural and physical science, and draftsmanship.
  </p>
  <p>
   In Asia, engineering had a separate but very similar development, with more and more sophisticated techniques of construction,
   <xref articleid="41715">
    hydraulics
   </xref>
   , and
   <xref articleid="110658">
    metallurgy
   </xref>
   helping to create advanced civilizations such as the
   <xref articleid="631484">
    Mongol empire
   </xref>
   , whose large, beautiful cities impressed
   <xref articleid="60660">
    Marco Polo
   </xref>
   in the 13th century.
  </p>
  <p>
   <xref articleid="105844">
    Civil engineering
   </xref>
   emerged as a separate discipline in the 18th century, when the first professional societies and schools of engineering were founded. Civil engineers of the 19th century built structures of all kinds, designed water-supply and sanitation systems, laid out railroad and highway networks, and planned cities. England and Scotland were the birthplace of
   <xref articleid="105845">
    mechanical engineering
   </xref>
   , as a derivation of the inventions of the Scottish engineer
   <xref articleid="76296">
    James Watt
   </xref>
   and the textile machinists of the
   <xref articleid="42370">
    Industrial Revolution
   </xref>
   . The development of the British machine-tool industry gave tremendous impetus to the study of mechanical engineering both in Britain and abroad.
  </p>
  <p>
   <assembly id="a220061" url="/assembly/view/220061">
    <title>
     Alessandro Volta
    </title>
    <media mediaid="147448" type="image" url="/48/147448-004-D20E32C7.jpg"/>
    <caption>
     Alessandro Volta demonstrating his battery’s generation of electric current before Napoleon (seated) in Paris in 1801.
    </caption>
    <credit>
     © Photos.com/Thinkstock
    </credit>
   </assembly>
   <assemblyref assemblyid="a220061"/>
   The growth of knowledge of
   <xref articleid="106019">
    electricity
   </xref>
   —from
   <xref articleid="75699">
    Alessandro Volta
   </xref>
   ’s original electric cell of 1800 through the experiments of
   <xref articleid="109756">
    Michael Faraday
   </xref>
   and others, culminating in 1872 in the Gramme dynamo and electric motor (named after the Belgian
   <xref articleid="37634">
    Zénobe-Théophile Gramme
   </xref>
   )—led to the development of electrical and electronics engineering. The electronics aspect became prominent through the work of such scientists as
   <xref articleid="108468">
    James Clerk Maxwell
   </xref>
   of Britain and
   <xref articleid="40253">
    Heinrich Hertz
   </xref>
   of Germany in the late 19th century. Major advances came with the development of the vacuum tube by
   <xref articleid="29588">
    Lee de Forest
   </xref>
   of the United States in the early 20th century and the invention of the
   <xref articleid="73201">
    transistor
   </xref>
   in the mid-20th century. In the late 20th century electrical and electronics engineers outnumbered all others in the world.
  </p>
  <p>
   <xref articleid="105846">
    Chemical engineering
   </xref>
   grew out of the 19th-century proliferation of industrial processes involving chemical reactions in metallurgy, food, textiles, and many other areas. By 1880 the use of chemicals in manufacturing had created an industry whose function was the
   <xref articleid="106304">
    mass production
   </xref>
   of chemicals. The design and operation of the plants of this industry became a function of the chemical engineer.
  </p>
  <p>
   In the late 20th and early 21st centuries the field of
   <xref articleid="2526">
    environmental engineering
   </xref>
   expanded to address
   <xref articleid="37044">
    global warming
   </xref>
   and sustainability. The development and deployment of
   <xref articleid="443101">
    renewable energy
   </xref>
   , such as
   <xref articleid="68559">
    solar
   </xref>
   and
   <xref articleid="599345">
    wind power
   </xref>
   , the creation of new technologies for
   <xref articleid="474250">
    carbon sequestration
   </xref>
   and
   <xref articleid="474194">
    pollution control
   </xref>
   , and the design of
   <xref articleid="443098">
    green architecture
   </xref>
   and environmentally friendly
   <xref articleid="74444">
    urban planning
   </xref>
   are all recent developments.
  </p>
 </h1>
 <h1 id="h64714">
  <title>
   Engineering functions
  </title>
  <p>
   Problem solving is common to all engineering work. The problem may involve quantitative or qualitative factors; it may be physical or economic; it may require abstract mathematics or common sense. Of great importance is the process of creative synthesis or design, putting ideas together to create a new and optimum solution.
  </p>
  <p>
   Although engineering problems vary in scope and complexity, the same general approach is applicable. First comes an analysis of the situation and a preliminary decision on a plan of attack. In line with this plan, the problem is reduced to a more categorical question that can be clearly stated. The stated question is then answered by deductive reasoning from known principles or by creative synthesis, as in a new design. The answer or design is always checked for accuracy and adequacy. Finally, the results for the simplified problem are interpreted in terms of the original problem and reported in an appropriate form.
  </p>
  <p>
   In order of decreasing emphasis on science, the major functions of all engineering branches are the following:
  </p>
  <list type="ul">
   <item>
    <e type="italic">
     Research
    </e>
    . Using mathematical and scientific concepts, experimental techniques, and inductive reasoning, the research engineer seeks new principles and processes.
   </item>
   <item>
    <e type="italic">
     Development
    </e>
    . Development engineers apply the results of research to useful purposes. Creative application of new knowledge may result in a working model of a new electrical circuit, a chemical process, or an industrial machine.
   </item>
   <item>
    <e type="italic">
     Design
    </e>
    . In designing a structure or a product, the engineer selects methods, specifies materials, and determines shapes to satisfy technical requirements and to meet performance specifications.
   </item>
   <item>
    <e type="italic">
     Construction
    </e>
    . The construction engineer is responsible for preparing the site, determining procedures that will economically and safely yield the desired quality, directing the placement of materials, and organizing the personnel and equipment.
   </item>
   <item>
    <e type="italic">
     Production
    </e>
    . Plant layout and equipment selection are the responsibility of the production engineer, who chooses processes and tools, integrates the flow of materials and components, and provides for testing and inspection.
   </item>
   <item>
    <e type="italic">
     Operation
    </e>
    . The operating engineer controls machines, plants, and organizations providing power, transportation, and communication; determines procedures; and supervises personnel to obtain reliable and economic operation of complex equipment.
   </item>
   <item>
    <e type="italic">
     Management and other functions
    </e>
    . In some countries and industries, engineers analyze customers’ requirements, recommend units to satisfy needs economically, and resolve related problems.
   </item>
  </list>
  <signature>
   Ralph J. Smith
  </signature>
  <signature>
   EB Editors
  </signature>
 </h1>
 <h1 id="h64715">
  <title>
   Bibliography
  </title>
  <p>
   Works on the history of engineering in general include
   <e type="smallcap">
    A.P.M. Fleming
   </e>
   and
   <e type="smallcap">
    H.J. Brocklehurst
   </e>
   ,
   <e type="italic">
    A History of Engineering
   </e>
   (1925);
   <e type="smallcap">
    Richard Shelton Kirby
   </e>
   <e type="italic">
    et al.,
   </e>
   <e type="italic">
    Engineering in History
   </e>
   (1956, reprinted 1990);
   <e type="smallcap">
    James K. Finch
   </e>
   ,
   <e type="italic">
    The Story of Engineering
   </e>
   (1960);
   <e type="smallcap">
    Donald Hill
   </e>
   ,
   <e type="italic">
    A History of Engineering in Classical and Medieval Times
   </e>
   (1984); and
   <e type="smallcap">
    E. Garrison
   </e>
   ,
   <e type="italic">
    A History of Engineering and Technology: Artful Methods
   </e>
   (1991). Histories of the engineering profession in the United States include
   <e type="smallcap">
    Edwin T. Layton, Jr.
   </e>
   ,
   <e type="italic">
    The Revolt of the Engineers: Social Responsibility and the American Engineering Profession
   </e>
   (1971);
   <e type="smallcap">
    David F. Noble
   </e>
   ,
   <e type="italic">
    America by Design: Science, Technology, and the Rise of Corporate Capitalism
   </e>
   (1977);
   <e type="smallcap">
    Monte A. Calvert
   </e>
   ,
   <e type="italic">
    The Mechanical Engineer in America, 1830–1910
   </e>
   (1967); and
   <e type="smallcap">
    A. Michal Mcmahon
   </e>
   ,
   <e type="italic">
    The Making of a Profession: A Century of Electrical Engineering in America
   </e>
   (1984).
  </p>
  <p>
   General descriptions of the engineering profession may be found in
   <e type="smallcap">
    Theodore Jesse Hoover
   </e>
   and
   <e type="smallcap">
    John Charles Lounsbury Fish
   </e>
   ,
   <e type="italic">
    The Engineering Profession
   </e>
   , 2nd ed. (1950); and
   <e type="smallcap">
    Ralph J. Smith
   </e>
   ,
   <e type="smallcap">
    Blaine R. Butler
   </e>
   , and
   <e type="smallcap">
    William K. Lebold
   </e>
   ,
   <e type="italic">
    Engineering as a Career
   </e>
   , 4th ed. (1983).
   <e type="smallcap">
    Richard C. Dorf
   </e>
   (ed.),
   <e type="italic">
    The Engineering Handbook
   </e>
   (1996), is an extensive reference work.
  </p>
  <signature>
   Ralph J. Smith
  </signature>
  <signature>
   EB Editors
  </signature>
 </h1>
 <copyright>
  Encyclopædia Britannica
 </copyright>
</article>