<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "syndication_xml.dtd">
<article articleid="106265" articletypeid="1" language="en_us" lastupdate="2021-Nov-17 13:56:07" url="/article/gravity/106265" version="28">
 <title>
  gravity
 </title>
 <p>
  <assembly id="a17790" url="/assembly/view/17790">
   <title>
    gravitational lens
   </title>
   <media mediaid="21250" type="image" url="/50/21250-004-7E580D28.jpg"/>
   <caption>
    In this picture a galactic cluster, about five billion light-years away, produces a tremendous gravitational field that “bends” light around it. This lens produces multiple copies of a blue galaxy about twice as distant. Four images are visible in a circle surrounding the lens; a fifth is visible near the centre of the picture, which was taken by the Hubble Space Telescope.
   </caption>
   <credit>
    Photo AURA/STScI/NASA/JPL (NASA photo # STScI-PRC96-10)
   </credit>
  </assembly>
  <e type="bold">
   gravity
  </e>
  , also called
  <e type="bold">
   gravitation
  </e>
  ,
  <assemblyref assemblyid="a17790"/>
  in mechanics, the universal force of attraction acting between all matter. It is by far the weakest known force in nature and thus plays no role in determining the internal properties of everyday matter. On the other hand, through its long reach and universal action, it controls the trajectories of bodies in the solar system and elsewhere in the universe and the structures and evolution of stars, galaxies, and the whole
  <xref articleid="109637">
   cosmos
  </xref>
  . On Earth all bodies have a weight, or downward force of gravity, proportional to their mass, which Earth’s mass exerts on them. Gravity is measured by the acceleration that it gives to freely falling objects. At Earth’s surface the acceleration of gravity is about 9.8 metres (32 feet) per second per second. Thus, for every second an object is in free fall, its speed increases by about 9.8 metres per second. At the surface of the Moon the acceleration of a freely falling body is about 1.6 metres per second per second.
 </p>
 <p>
  <assembly id="a158977" url="/assembly/view/158977">
   <title>
    Understand the concept of gravitational force using Newton’s theory of gravitation
   </title>
   <media mediaid="151070" thumburl="/70/151070-049-C4B36C27.jpg" type="video" url=""/>
   <caption>
    Explanation of gravitational force.
   </caption>
   <credit>
    Encyclopædia Britannica, Inc.
   </credit>
  </assembly>
  <assemblyref assemblyid="a158977"/>
  The works of
  <xref articleid="108764">
   Isaac Newton
  </xref>
  and
  <xref articleid="106018">
   Albert Einstein
  </xref>
  dominate the development of gravitational theory. Newton’s classical theory of gravitational force held sway from his
  <e type="italic">
   Principia
  </e>
  , published in 1687, until Einstein’s work in the early 20th century. Newton’s theory is sufficient even today for all but the most precise applications. Einstein’s theory of general relativity predicts only minute quantitative differences from the Newtonian theory except in a few special cases. The major significance of Einstein’s theory is its radical conceptual departure from classical theory and its implications for further growth in physical thought.
 </p>
 <p>
  The launch of space vehicles and developments of research from them have led to great improvements in measurements of gravity around Earth, other planets, and the Moon and in experiments on the nature of gravitation.
 </p>
 <h1 id="h61463">
  <title>
   Development of gravitational theory
  </title>
  <h2 id="h61464">
   <title>
    Early concepts
   </title>
   <p>
    Newton argued that the movements of celestial bodies and the free fall of objects on Earth are determined by the same force. The classical Greek philosophers, on the other hand, did not consider the celestial bodies to be affected by gravity, because the bodies were observed to follow perpetually repeating nondescending trajectories in the sky. Thus,
    <xref articleid="108312">
     Aristotle
    </xref>
    considered that each heavenly body followed a particular “natural” motion, unaffected by external causes or agents. Aristotle also believed that massive earthly objects possess a natural tendency to move toward Earth’s centre. Those Aristotelian concepts prevailed for centuries along with two others: that a body moving at constant speed requires a continuous force acting on it and that force must be applied by contact rather than interaction at a distance. These ideas were generally held until the 16th and early 17th centuries, thereby impeding an understanding of the true principles of motion and precluding the development of ideas about universal gravitation. This impasse began to change with several scientific contributions to the problem of earthly and celestial motion, which in turn set the stage for Newton’s later gravitational theory.
   </p>
   <p>
    The 17th-century German astronomer
    <xref articleid="105767">
     Johannes Kepler
    </xref>
    accepted the argument of
    <xref articleid="105759">
     Nicolaus Copernicus
    </xref>
    (which goes back to
    <xref articleid="9438">
     Aristarchus of Samos
    </xref>
    ) that the planets orbit the Sun, not Earth. Using the improved measurements of planetary movements made by the Danish astronomer
    <xref articleid="16148">
     Tycho Brahe
    </xref>
    during the 16th century, Kepler described the planetary orbits with simple geometric and arithmetic relations. Kepler’s three quantitative laws of planetary motion are:
   </p>
   <list type="ul">
    <item>
     The planets describe elliptic orbits, of which the Sun occupies one focus (a focus is one of two points inside an
     <xref articleid="1541">
      ellipse
     </xref>
     ; any ray coming from one of them bounces off a side of the ellipse and goes through the other focus).
    </item>
    <item>
     The line joining a planet to the Sun sweeps out equal areas in equal times.
    </item>
    <item>
     The square of the period of revolution of a planet is proportional to the cube of its average distance from the Sun.
    </item>
   </list>
   <p>
    During this same period the Italian astronomer and natural philosopher
    <xref articleid="105766">
     Galileo Galilei
    </xref>
    made progress in understanding “natural”
    <xref articleid="53959">
     motion
    </xref>
    and simple accelerated motion for earthly objects. He realized that bodies that are uninfluenced by forces continue indefinitely to move and that force is necessary to change motion, not to maintain constant motion. In studying how objects fall toward Earth, Galileo discovered that the motion is one of constant
    <xref articleid="3469">
     acceleration
    </xref>
    . He demonstrated that the distance a falling body travels from rest in this way varies as the square of the time. As noted above, the acceleration due to gravity at the surface of Earth is about 9.8 metres per second per second. Galileo was also the first to show by experiment that bodies fall with the same acceleration whatever their composition (the weak principle of equivalence).
   </p>
  </h2>
  <h2 id="h61465">
   <title>
    Newton’s law of gravity
   </title>
   <p>
    <assembly id="a141791" url="/assembly/view/141791">
     <title>
      effects of gravity on the Moon and Earth
     </title>
     <media mediaid="94581" type="image" url="/81/94581-004-F3DAF261.jpg"/>
     <caption>
      Effects of gravity on Earth and the Moon.
     </caption>
     <credit>
      Encyclopædia Britannica, Inc.
     </credit>
    </assembly>
    <assemblyref assemblyid="a141791"/>
    Newton discovered the relationship between the motion of the Moon and the motion of a body falling freely on Earth. By his dynamical and gravitational theories, he explained Kepler’s laws and established the modern quantitative science of gravitation. Newton assumed the existence of an attractive force between all massive bodies, one that does not require bodily contact and that acts at a distance. By invoking his law of
    <xref articleid="42378">
     inertia
    </xref>
    (bodies not acted upon by a force move at constant speed in a straight line), Newton concluded that a force exerted by Earth on the Moon is needed to keep it in a circular motion about Earth rather than moving in a straight line. He realized that this force could be, at long range, the same as the force with which Earth pulls objects on its surface downward. When Newton discovered that the acceleration of the Moon is 1/3,600 smaller than the acceleration at the surface of Earth, he related the number 3,600 to the square of the radius of Earth. He calculated that the circular orbital motion of radius
    <e type="italic">
     R
    </e>
    and period
    <e type="italic">
     T
    </e>
    requires a constant inward acceleration
    <e type="italic">
     A
    </e>
    equal to the product of 4π
    <sup>
     2
    </sup>
    and the ratio of the radius to the square of the time:
    <formula>
     <inlinemedia id="i15560" mediaid="15560" url="/60/15560-004-4AFAF363.jpg"/>
    </formula>
   </p>
   <p>
    <assembly id="a161888" url="/assembly/view/161888">
     <title>
      gravitational force
     </title>
     <media mediaid="106990" type="image" url="/90/106990-004-7B99A996.jpg"/>
     <caption>
      Earth’s gravitational force weakens with increasing distance.
     </caption>
     <credit>
      Encyclopædia Britannica, Inc.
     </credit>
    </assembly>
    <assemblyref assemblyid="a161888"/>
    The Moon’s orbit has a radius of about 384,000 km (239,000 miles; approximately 60 Earth radii), and its period is 27.3 days (its
    <xref articleid="70755">
     synodic period
    </xref>
    , or period measured in terms of lunar phases, is about 29.5 days). Newton found the Moon’s inward acceleration in its orbit to be 0.0027 metre per second per second, the same as (1/60)
    <sup>
     2
    </sup>
    of the acceleration of a falling object at the surface of Earth.
   </p>
   <p>
    In Newton’s theory every least particle of matter attracts every other particle gravitationally, and on that basis he showed that the attraction of a finite body with spherical symmetry is the same as that of the whole mass at the centre of the body. More generally, the attraction of any body at a sufficiently great distance is equal to that of the whole mass at the centre of mass. He could thus relate the two accelerations, that of the Moon and that of a body falling freely on Earth, to a common interaction, a gravitational force between bodies that diminishes as the inverse square of the distance between them. Thus, if the distance between the bodies is doubled, the force on them is reduced to a fourth of the original.
   </p>
   <p>
    Newton saw that the gravitational force between bodies must depend on the masses of the bodies. Since a body of mass
    <e type="italic">
     M
    </e>
    experiencing a force
    <e type="italic">
     F
    </e>
    accelerates at a rate
    <e type="italic">
     F
    </e>
    /
    <e type="italic">
     M
    </e>
    , a force of gravity proportional to
    <e type="italic">
     M
    </e>
    would be consistent with Galileo’s observation that all bodies accelerate under gravity toward Earth at the same rate, a fact that Newton also tested experimentally. In Newton’s equation
    <formula>
     <inlinemedia id="i15559" mediaid="15559" url="/59/15559-004-42067BB2.jpg"/>
    </formula>
    <e type="italic">
     F
    </e>
    <sub>
     12
    </sub>
    is the magnitude of the gravitational force acting between masses
    <e type="italic">
     M
    </e>
    <sub>
     1
    </sub>
    and
    <e type="italic">
     M
    </e>
    <sub>
     2
    </sub>
    separated by distance
    <e type="italic">
     r
    </e>
    <sub>
     12
    </sub>
    . The force equals the product of these masses and of
    <e type="italic">
     G
    </e>
    , a universal constant, divided by the square of the distance.
   </p>
   <p>
    The constant
    <e type="italic">
     G
    </e>
    is a quantity with the physical dimensions (length)
    <sup>
     3
    </sup>
    /(mass)(time)
    <sup>
     2
    </sup>
    ; its numerical value depends on the physical units of length, mass, and time used. (
    <e type="italic">
     G
    </e>
    is discussed more fully in subsequent sections.)
   </p>
   <p>
    The force acts in the direction of the line joining the two bodies and so is represented naturally as a vector,
    <e type="bolditalic">
     F
    </e>
    . If
    <e type="bolditalic">
     r
    </e>
    is the vector separation of the bodies, then
    <formula>
     <inlinemedia id="i15558" mediaid="15558" url="/58/15558-004-847D93BA.jpg"/>
    </formula>
    In this expression the factor
    <e type="bolditalic">
     r
    </e>
    /
    <e type="italic">
     r
    </e>
    <sup>
     3
    </sup>
    acts in the direction of
    <e type="bolditalic">
     r
    </e>
    and is numerically equal to 1/
    <e type="italic">
     r
    </e>
    <sup>
     2
    </sup>
    .
   </p>
   <p>
    The attractive force of a number of bodies of masses
    <e type="italic">
     M
    </e>
    <sub>
     1
    </sub>
    on a body of mass
    <e type="italic">
     M
    </e>
    is
    <formula>
     <inlinemedia id="i15557" mediaid="15557" url="/57/15557-004-8990EC54.jpg"/>
    </formula>
    where Σ
    <sub>
     1
    </sub>
    means that the forces because of all the attracting bodies must be added together vectorially. This is Newton’s gravitational law essentially in its original form. A simpler expression, equation (5), gives the surface acceleration on Earth. Setting a mass equal to Earth’s mass
    <e type="italic">
     M
    </e>
    <sub>
     E
    </sub>
    and the distance equal to Earth’s radius
    <e type="italic">
     r
    </e>
    <sub>
     E
    </sub>
    , the downward acceleration of a body at the surface
    <e type="italic">
     g
    </e>
    is equal to the product of the universal gravitational constant and the mass of Earth divided by the square of the radius:
    <formula>
     <inlinemedia id="i15556" mediaid="15556" url="/56/15556-004-2A4C8F53.jpg"/>
    </formula>
   </p>
   <h3 id="h61466">
    <title>
     Weight and mass
    </title>
    <p>
     The weight
     <e type="italic">
      W
     </e>
     of a body can be measured by the equal and opposite force necessary to prevent the downward acceleration; that is
     <e type="italic">
      M
     </e>
     <sub>
      <e type="italic">
       g
      </e>
     </sub>
     . The same body placed on the surface of the Moon has the same mass, but, as the Moon has a mass of about
     <fraction>
      <num>
       1
      </num>
      <den>
       81
      </den>
     </fraction>
     times that of Earth and a radius of just 0.27 that of Earth, the body on the lunar surface has a weight of only
     <fraction>
      <num>
       1
      </num>
      <den>
       6
      </den>
     </fraction>
     its Earth weight, as the
     <xref articleid="8019">
      Apollo program
     </xref>
     astronauts demonstrated. Passengers and instruments in orbiting satellites are in free fall. They experience weightless conditions even though their masses remain the same as on Earth.
    </p>
    <p>
     Equations (
     <inlinemediaref inlinemediaid="i15560">
      1
     </inlinemediaref>
     ) and (
     <inlinemediaref inlinemediaid="i15559">
      2
     </inlinemediaref>
     ) can be used to derive Kepler’s third law for the case of circular planetary orbits. By using the expression for the acceleration
     <e type="italic">
      A
     </e>
     in equation (1) for the force of gravity for the planet
     <e type="italic">
      G
     </e>
     <e type="italic">
      M
     </e>
     <sub>
      <e type="italic">
       P
      </e>
     </sub>
     <e type="italic">
      M
     </e>
     <sub>
      S
     </sub>
     /
     <e type="italic">
      R
     </e>
     <sup>
      2
     </sup>
     divided by the planet’s mass
     <e type="italic">
      M
     </e>
     <sub>
      <e type="italic">
       P
      </e>
     </sub>
     , the following equation, in which
     <e type="italic">
      M
     </e>
     <sub>
      S
     </sub>
     is the mass of the Sun, is obtained:
     <formula>
      <inlinemedia id="i15555" mediaid="15555" url="/55/15555-004-B2FEE82C.jpg"/>
     </formula>
    </p>
    <p>
     Kepler’s very important second law depends only on the fact that the force between two bodies is along the line joining them.
    </p>
    <p>
     Newton was thus able to show that all three of Kepler’s observationally derived laws follow mathematically from the assumption of his own laws of motion and gravity. In all observations of the motion of a celestial body, only the product of
     <e type="italic">
      G
     </e>
     and the mass can be found. Newton first estimated the magnitude of
     <e type="italic">
      G
     </e>
     by assuming Earth’s average mass density to be about 5.5 times that of water (somewhat greater than Earth’s surface rock density) and by calculating Earth’s mass from this. Then, taking
     <e type="italic">
      M
     </e>
     <sub>
      E
     </sub>
     and
     <e type="italic">
      r
     </e>
     <sub>
      E
     </sub>
     as Earth’s mass and radius, respectively, the value of
     <e type="italic">
      G
     </e>
     was
     <formula>
      <inlinemedia id="i15554" mediaid="15554" url="/54/15554-004-AC929561.jpg"/>
     </formula>
     which numerically comes close to the accepted value of 6.6743 × 10
     <sup>
      −11
     </sup>
     m
     <sup>
      3
     </sup>
     s
     <sup>
      −2
     </sup>
     kg
     <sup>
      −1
     </sup>
     , first directly measured by
     <xref articleid="21916">
      Henry Cavendish
     </xref>
     .
    </p>
    <p>
     Comparing equation (
     <inlinemediaref inlinemediaid="i15556">
      5
     </inlinemediaref>
     ) for Earth’s surface acceleration
     <e type="italic">
      g
     </e>
     with the
     <e type="italic">
      R
     </e>
     <sup>
      3
     </sup>
     /
     <e type="italic">
      T
     </e>
     <sup>
      2
     </sup>
     ratio for the planets, a formula for the ratio of the Sun’s mass
     <e type="italic">
      M
     </e>
     <sub>
      S
     </sub>
     to Earth’s mass
     <e type="italic">
      M
     </e>
     <sub>
      E
     </sub>
     was obtained in terms of known quantities,
     <e type="italic">
      R
     </e>
     <sub>
      E
     </sub>
     being the radius of Earth’s orbit:
     <formula>
      <inlinemedia id="i15553" mediaid="15553" url="/53/15553-004-D6CCC91B.jpg"/>
     </formula>
    </p>
    <p>
     The motions of the moons of Jupiter (discovered by Galileo) around Jupiter obey Kepler’s laws just as the planets do around the Sun. Thus, Newton calculated that Jupiter, with a radius 11 times larger than Earth’s, was 318 times more massive than Earth but only
     <fraction>
      <num>
       1
      </num>
      <den>
       4
      </den>
     </fraction>
     as dense.
    </p>
   </h3>
   <h3 id="h61467">
    <title>
     Interaction between celestial bodies
    </title>
    <p>
     When two celestial bodies of comparable mass interact gravitationally, both orbit about a fixed point (the centre of mass of the two bodies). This point lies between the bodies on the line joining them at a position such that the products of the distance to each body with the mass of each body are equal. Thus, Earth and the Moon move in complementary orbits about their common centre of mass. The motion of Earth has two observable consequences. First, the direction of the Sun as seen from Earth relative to the very distant stars varies each month by about 12 arc seconds in addition to the Sun’s annual motion. Second, the line-of-sight velocity from Earth to a freely moving spacecraft varies each month by 2.04 metres per second, according to very accurate data obtained from radio tracking. From these results the Moon is found to have a mass
     <fraction>
      <num>
       1
      </num>
      <den>
       81
      </den>
     </fraction>
     times that of Earth. With slight modifications Kepler’s laws remain valid for systems of two comparable masses; the foci of the elliptical orbits are the two-body centre-of-mass positions, and, putting
     <e type="italic">
      M
     </e>
     <sub>
      1
     </sub>
     +
     <e type="italic">
      M
     </e>
     <sub>
      2
     </sub>
     instead of
     <e type="italic">
      M
     </e>
     <sub>
      S
     </sub>
     in the expression of Kepler’s third law, equation (
     <inlinemediaref inlinemediaid="i15555">
      6
     </inlinemediaref>
     ), the third law reads:
     <formula>
      <inlinemedia id="i15552" mediaid="15552" url="/52/15552-004-28CBE2F5.jpg"/>
     </formula>
    </p>
    <p>
     That agrees with equation (
     <inlinemediaref inlinemediaid="i15555">
      6
     </inlinemediaref>
     ) when one body is so small that its mass can be neglected. The rescaled formula can be used to determine the separate masses of binary stars (pairs of stars orbiting around each other) that are a known distance from the solar system. Equation (
     <inlinemediaref inlinemediaid="i15552">
      9
     </inlinemediaref>
     ) determines the sum of the masses; and, if
     <e type="italic">
      R
     </e>
     <sub>
      1
     </sub>
     and
     <e type="italic">
      R
     </e>
     <sub>
      2
     </sub>
     are the distances of the individual stars from the centre of mass, the ratio of the distances must balance the inverse ratio of the masses, and the sum of the distances is the total distance
     <e type="italic">
      R
     </e>
     . In symbols
     <formula>
      <inlinemedia id="i15551" mediaid="15551" url="/51/15551-004-4DD4B78A.jpg"/>
     </formula>
    </p>
    <p>
     Those relations are sufficient to determine the individual masses. Observations of the orbital motions of double stars, of the dynamic motions of stars collectively moving within their galaxies, and of the motions of the galaxies themselves verify that Newton’s law of gravity is valid to a high degree of accuracy throughout the visible universe.
    </p>
    <p>
     Ocean
     <xref articleid="72409">
      tides
     </xref>
     , phenomena that mystified thinkers for centuries, were also shown by Newton to be a consequence of the universal law of gravitation, although the details of the complicated phenomena were not understood until comparatively recently. They are caused specifically by the gravitational pull of the Moon and, to a lesser extent, of the Sun.
    </p>
    <p>
     Newton showed that the equatorial bulge of Earth was a consequence of the balance between the
     <xref articleid="22100">
      centrifugal forces
     </xref>
     of the rotation of Earth and the attractions of each particle of Earth on all others. The value of gravity at the surface of Earth increases in a corresponding way from the Equator to the poles. Among the data that Newton used to estimate the size of the equatorial bulge were the adjustments to his pendulum clock that the English astronomer
     <xref articleid="38943">
      Edmond Halley
     </xref>
     had to make in the course of his astronomical observations on the southern island of Saint Helena. Jupiter, which rotates faster than Earth, has a proportionally larger equatorial bulge, the difference between its polar and equatorial radii being about 10 percent. Another success of Newton’s theory was his demonstration that
     <xref articleid="110156">
      comets
     </xref>
     move in parabolic orbits under the gravitational attraction of the Sun. In a thorough analysis in the
     <e type="italic">
      Principia
     </e>
     , he showed that the great comet of 1680–81 did indeed follow a parabolic path.
    </p>
    <p>
     It was already known in Newton’s day that the Moon does not move in a simple Keplerian orbit. Later, more-accurate observations of the planets also showed discrepancies from Kepler’s laws. The motion of the Moon is particularly complex; however, apart from a long-term acceleration due to tides on Earth, the complexities can be accounted for by the gravitational attraction of the Sun and the planets. The gravitational attractions of the planets for each other explain almost all the features of their motions. The exceptions are nonetheless important. Uranus, the seventh planet from the Sun, was observed to undergo variations in its motion that could not be explained by perturbations from Saturn, Jupiter, and the other planets. Two 19th-century astronomers,
     <xref articleid="3668">
      John Couch Adams
     </xref>
     of Britain and
     <xref articleid="47487">
      Urbain-Jean-Joseph Le Verrier
     </xref>
     of France, independently assumed the presence of an unseen eighth planet that could produce the observed discrepancies. They calculated its position within a degree of where the planet Neptune was discovered in 1846. Measurements of the motion of the innermost planet, Mercury, over an extended period led astronomers to conclude that the major axis of this planet’s elliptical orbit precesses in space at a rate 43 arc seconds per century faster than could be accounted for from perturbations of the other planets. In this case, however, no other bodies could be found that could produce this discrepancy, and very slight modification of Newton’s law of gravitation seemed to be needed. Einstein’s theory of relativity precisely predicts this observed behaviour of Mercury’s orbit.
    </p>
   </h3>
  </h2>
  <h2 id="h61468">
   <title>
    Potential theory
   </title>
   <p>
    For irregular, nonspherical mass distributions in three dimensions, Newton’s original vector equation (
    <inlinemediaref inlinemediaid="i15557">
     4
    </inlinemediaref>
    ) is inefficient, though theoretically it could be used for finding the resulting gravitational field. The main progress in classical gravitational theory after Newton was the development of potential theory, which provides the mathematical representation of gravitational fields. It allows practical as well as theoretical investigation of the gravitational variations in space and of the anomalies due to the irregularities and shape deformations of Earth.
   </p>
   <p>
    Potential theory led to the following elegant formulation: the gravitational acceleration
    <e type="bolditalic">
     g
    </e>
    is a function of position
    <e type="bolditalic">
     R
    </e>
    ,
    <e type="bolditalic">
     g
    </e>
    (
    <e type="bolditalic">
     R
    </e>
    ), which at any point in space is given from a function Φ called the gravitational potential, by means of a generalization of the operation of differentiation:
    <formula>
     <inlinemedia id="i15550" mediaid="15550" url="/50/15550-004-1CB7F770.jpg"/>
    </formula>
    in which
    <e type="bolditalic">
     i
    </e>
    ,
    <e type="bolditalic">
     j
    </e>
    , and
    <e type="bolditalic">
     k
    </e>
    stand for unit basis vectors in a three-dimensional Cartesian coordinate system. The potential and therefore
    <e type="bolditalic">
     g
    </e>
    are determined by an equation discovered by the French mathematician
    <xref articleid="60562">
     Siméon-Denis Poisson
    </xref>
    :
    <formula>
     <inlinemedia id="i15549" mediaid="15549" url="/49/15549-004-26E09A66.jpg"/>
    </formula>
    where ρ(
    <e type="bolditalic">
     R
    </e>
    ) is the density at the vector position
    <e type="bolditalic">
     R
    </e>
    .
   </p>
   <p>
    The significance of this approach is that Poisson’s equation can be solved under rather general conditions, which is not the case with Newton’s equation. When the mass density ρ is nonzero, the solution is expressed as the definite integral:
    <formula>
     <inlinemedia id="i15548" mediaid="15548" url="/48/15548-004-18D304B4.jpg"/>
    </formula>
    where the integral is a three-dimensional integral over the volume of all space. When ρ = 0 (in particular, outside Earth), Poisson’s equation reduces to the simpler equation of Laplace.
   </p>
   <p>
    The appropriate coordinates for the region outside the nearly spherical Earth are spherical polar coordinates:
    <e type="bolditalic">
     R
    </e>
    , the distance from the centre of Earth; θ, the colatitude measured from the North Pole; and the longitude measured from Greenwich. The solutions are series of powers of
    <e type="bolditalic">
     R
    </e>
    multiplied by trigonometric functions of colatitude and longitude, known as spherical harmonics; the first terms are:
    <formula>
     <inlinemedia id="i15547" mediaid="15547" url="/47/15547-004-078974B5.jpg"/>
    </formula>
   </p>
   <p>
    The constants
    <e type="italic">
     J
    </e>
    <sub>
     2
    </sub>
    ,
    <e type="italic">
     J
    </e>
    <sub>
     3
    </sub>
    , and so forth are determined by the detailed mass distribution of Earth; and, since Newton showed that for a spherical body all the
    <e type="italic">
     J
    </e>
    <sub>
     <e type="italic">
      n
     </e>
    </sub>
    are zero, they must measure the deformation of Earth from a spherical shape.
    <e type="italic">
     J
    </e>
    <sub>
     2
    </sub>
    measures the magnitude of Earth’s rotational equatorial bulge,
    <e type="italic">
     J
    </e>
    <sub>
     3
    </sub>
    measures a slight pear-shaped deformation of Earth, and so on. The orbits of spacecraft around Earth, other planets, and the Moon deviate from simple Keplerian ellipses in consequence of the various spherical harmonic terms in the potential. Observations of such deviations were made for the very first artificial spacecraft. The parameters
    <e type="italic">
     J
    </e>
    <sub>
     2
    </sub>
    and
    <e type="italic">
     J
    </e>
    <sub>
     3
    </sub>
    for Earth have been found to be 1,082.7 × 10
    <sup>
     −6
    </sup>
    and −2.4 × 10
    <sup>
     −6
    </sup>
    , respectively. Very many other harmonic terms have been found in that way for Earth and also for the Moon and for other planets. Halley had already pointed out in the 18th century that the motions of the moons of Jupiter are perturbed from simple ellipses by the variation of gravity around Jupiter.
   </p>
   <p>
    <assembly id="a90695" url="/assembly/view/90695">
     <title>
      variation in Earth’s gravitational field
     </title>
     <media mediaid="96320" type="image" url="/20/96320-004-3FC5219A.jpg"/>
     <caption>
      The variation in the gravitational field, given in milliGals (mGal), over the Earth’s surface gives rise to an imaginary surface known as the geoid. The geoid expresses the height of an imaginary global ocean not subject to tides, currents, or winds. Such an ocean would vary by up to 200 metres (650 feet) in height because of regional variations in gravitation.
     </caption>
     <credit>
      Encyclopædia Britannica, Inc.
     </credit>
    </assembly>
    <assemblyref assemblyid="a90695"/>
    The surface of the oceans, if tides and waves are ignored, is a surface of constant potential of gravity and rotation. If the only spherical harmonic term in gravity were that corresponding to the equatorial bulge, the sea surface would be just a spheroid of revolution (a surface formed by rotating a two-dimensional curve about some axis; for example, rotating an ellipse about its major axis produces an
    <xref articleid="32442">
     ellipsoid
    </xref>
    ). Additional terms in the potential give rise to departures of the sea surface from that simple form. The actual form may be calculated from the sum of the known harmonic terms, but it is now possible to measure the form of the sea surface itself directly by laser ranging from spacecraft. Whether found indirectly by calculation or directly by measurement, the form of the sea surface may be shown as contours of its deviation from the simple spheroid of revolution.
   </p>
   <h3 id="h61469">
    <title>
     Effects of local mass differences
    </title>
    <p>
     Spherical harmonics are the natural way of expressing the large-scale variations of potential that arise from the deep structure of Earth. However, spherical harmonics are not suitable for local variations due to more-superficial structures. Not long after Newton’s time, it was found that the gravity on top of large mountains is less than expected on the basis of their visible mass. The idea of isostasy was developed, according to which the unexpectedly low acceleration of gravity on a mountain is caused by low-density rock 30 to 100 km underground, which buoys up the mountain. Correspondingly, the unexpectedly high force of gravity on ocean surfaces is explained by dense rock 10 to 30 km beneath the ocean bottom.
    </p>
    <p>
     Portable gravimeters, which can detect variations of one part in 10
     <sup>
      9
     </sup>
     in the gravitational force, are in wide use today for mineral and oil prospecting. Unusual underground deposits reveal their presence by producing local gravitational variations.
    </p>
   </h3>
   <h3 id="h61470">
    <title>
     Weighing the Earth
    </title>
    <p>
     The mass of Earth can be calculated from its radius and
     <e type="italic">
      g
     </e>
     if
     <e type="italic">
      G
     </e>
     is known.
     <e type="italic">
      G
     </e>
     was measured by the English physicist-chemist
     <xref articleid="21916">
      Henry Cavendish
     </xref>
     and other early experimenters, who spoke of their work as “weighing the Earth.” The mass of Earth is about 5.98 × 10
     <sup>
      24
     </sup>
     kg, while the mean densities of Earth, the Sun, and the Moon are, respectively, 5.52, 1.43, and 3.3 times that of water.
    </p>
    <signature>
     Kenneth L. Nordtvedt Jr.
    </signature>
    <signature>
     Sir Alan H. Cook
    </signature>
   </h3>
  </h2>
 </h1>
 <h1 id="h61471">
  <title>
   Acceleration around Earth, the Moon, and other planets
  </title>
  <p>
   The value of the attraction of gravity or of the potential is determined by the distribution of matter within Earth or some other celestial body. In turn, as seen above, the distribution of matter determines the shape of the surface on which the potential is constant. Measurements of gravity and the potential are thus essential both to
   <xref articleid="36451">
    geodesy
   </xref>
   , which is the study of the shape of Earth, and to
   <xref articleid="36479">
    geophysics
   </xref>
   , the study of its internal structure. For geodesy and global geophysics, it is best to measure the potential from the orbits of artificial satellites. Surface measurements of gravity are best for local geophysics, which deals with the structure of mountains and oceans and the search for minerals.
  </p>
  <h2 id="h61472">
   <title>
    Variations in
    <e type="italic">
     g
    </e>
   </title>
   <h3 id="h61473">
    <title>
     Changes due to location
    </title>
    <p>
     The acceleration
     <e type="italic">
      g
     </e>
     varies by about
     <fraction>
      <num>
       1
      </num>
      <den>
       2
      </den>
     </fraction>
     of 1 percent with position on Earth’s surface, from about 9.78 metres per second per second at the Equator to approximately 9.83 metres per second per second at the poles. In addition to this broad-scale variation, local variations of a few parts in 10
     <sup>
      6
     </sup>
     or smaller are caused by variations in the density of Earth’s crust as well as height above sea level.
    </p>
   </h3>
   <h3 id="h61474">
    <title>
     Changes with time
    </title>
    <p>
     The gravitational potential at the surface of Earth is due mainly to the mass and rotation of Earth, but there are also small contributions from the distant Sun and Moon. As Earth rotates, those small contributions at any one place vary with time, and so the local value of
     <e type="italic">
      g
     </e>
     varies slightly. Those are the diurnal and semidiurnal tidal variations. For most purposes it is necessary to know only the variation of gravity with time at a fixed place or the changes of gravity from place to place; then the tidal variation can be removed. Accordingly, almost all gravity measurements are relative measurements of the differences from place to place or from time to time.
    </p>
   </h3>
  </h2>
  <h2 id="h61475">
   <title>
    Measurements of
    <e type="italic">
     g
    </e>
   </title>
   <h3 id="h61476">
    <title>
     Unit of gravity
    </title>
    <p>
     Because gravity changes are far less than 1 metre per second per second, it is convenient to have a smaller unit for relative measurements. The gal (named after Galileo) has been adopted for this purpose; a gal is one-hundredth metre per second per second. The unit most commonly used is the milligal, which equals 10
     <sup>
      −5
     </sup>
     metre per second per second—i.e., about one-millionth of the average value of
     <e type="italic">
      g
     </e>
     .
    </p>
   </h3>
   <h3 id="h61477">
    <title>
     Absolute measurements
    </title>
    <p>
     Two basic ways of making absolute measurements of gravity have been devised: timing the free fall of an object and timing the motion under gravity of a body constrained in some way, almost always as a pendulum. In 1817 the English physicist Henry Kater, building on the work of the German astronomer
     <xref articleid="78931">
      Friedrich Wilhelm Bessel
     </xref>
     , was the first to use a reversible pendulum to make absolute measurements of
     <e type="italic">
      g
     </e>
     . If the periods of swing of a rigid pendulum about two alternative points of support are the same, then the separation of those two points is equal to the length of the equivalent simple pendulum of the same period. By careful construction, Kater was able to measure the separation very accurately. The so-called reversible pendulum was used for absolute measurements of gravity from Kater’s day until the 1950s. Since that time, electronic instruments have enabled investigators to measure with high precision the half-second time of free fall of a body (from rest) through one metre. It is also possible to make extremely accurate measurements of position by using interference of light. Consequently, direct measurements of free fall have replaced the pendulum for absolute measurements of gravity.
    </p>
    <p>
     Nowadays, lasers are the sources of light for interferometers, while the falling object is a retroreflector that returns a beam of light back upon itself. The falling object can be timed in simple downward motion, or it can be projected upward and timed over the upward and downward path. Transportable versions of such apparatuses have been used in different locations to establish a basis for measuring differences of gravity over the entire Earth. The accuracy attainable is about one part in 10
     <sup>
      8
     </sup>
     .
    </p>
    <p>
     More recently, interferometers using beams of atoms instead of light have given absolute determinations of gravity. Interference takes place between atoms that have been subject to different gravitational potentials and so have different energies and wavelengths. The results are comparable to those from bodies in free fall.
    </p>
   </h3>
   <h3 id="h61478">
    <title>
     Relative measurements
    </title>
    <p>
     From the time of Newton, measurements of differences of gravity (strictly, the ratios of values of gravity) were made by timing the same pendulum at different places. During the 1930s, however, static
     <xref articleid="37790">
      gravimeters
     </xref>
     replaced pendulums for local measurements over small ranges of gravity. Today, free-fall measurements have rendered the pendulum obsolete for all purposes.
    </p>
    <p>
     Spring gravimeters balance the force of gravity on a mass in the gravity field to be measured against the elastic force of the spring. Either the extension of the spring is measured, or a servo system restores it to a constant amount. High sensitivity is achieved through electronic or mechanical means. If a thin wire is stretched by a mass hung from it, the tension in the wire, and therefore the frequency of transverse oscillations, will vary with the force of gravity upon the mass. Such vibrating string gravimeters were originally developed for use in submarines and were later employed by the Apollo 17 astronauts on the Moon to conduct a gravity survey of their landing site. Another relatively recent development is the superconducting gravimeter, an instrument in which the position of a magnetically levitated superconducting sphere is sensed to provide a measure of
     <e type="italic">
      g
     </e>
     . Modern gravimeters may have sensitivities better than 0.005 milligal, the standard deviation of observations in exploration surveys being of the order of 0.01–0.02 milligal.
    </p>
    <p>
     Differences in gravity measured with gravimeters are obtained in quite arbitrary units—divisions on a graduated dial, for example. The relation between these units and milligals can be determined only by reading the instrument at a number of points where
     <e type="italic">
      g
     </e>
     is known as a result of absolute or relative pendulum measurements. Further, because an instrument will not have a completely linear response, known points must cover the entire range of gravity over which the gravimeter is to be used.
    </p>
    <p>
     Since
     <e type="italic">
      g
     </e>
     is an acceleration, the problem of its measurement from a vehicle that is moving, and therefore accelerating relative to Earth, raises a number of fundamental problems. Pendulum, vibrating-string, and spring-gravimeter observations have been made from submarines; using gyrostabilized platforms, relative gravity measurements with accuracies approaching a few milligals have been and are being made from surface ships. Experimental measurements with various gravity sensors on fixed-wing aircraft as well as on helicopters have been carried out.
    </p>
   </h3>
  </h2>
  <h2 id="h61480">
   <title>
    Gravimetric surveys and geophysics
   </title>
   <p>
    As a result of combining all available absolute and relative measurements, it is now possible to obtain the most probable gravity values at a large number of sites to high accuracy. The culmination of gravimetric work begun in the 1960s has been a worldwide gravity reference system having an accuracy of at least one part in 10
    <sup>
     7
    </sup>
    (0.1 milligal or better).
   </p>
   <p>
    The value of gravity measured at the terrestrial surface is the result of a combination of factors:
   </p>
   <list type="ul">
    <item>
     The gravitational attraction of Earth as a whole
    </item>
    <item>
     Centrifugal force caused by Earth’s rotation
    </item>
    <item>
     Elevation
    </item>
    <item>
     Unbalanced attractions caused by surface topography
    </item>
    <item>
     Tidal variations
    </item>
    <item>
     Unbalanced attractions caused by irregularities in underground density distributions
    </item>
   </list>
   <p>
    Most geophysical surveys are aimed at separating out the last of these in order to interpret the geologic structure. It is therefore necessary to make proper allowance for the other factors. The first two factors imply a variation of gravity with latitude that can be calculated for an assumed shape for Earth. The third factor, which is the decrease in gravity with elevation, due to increased distance from the centre of Earth, amounts to −0.3086 milligal per metre. This value, however, assumes that material of zero density occupies the whole space between the point of observation and sea level, and it is therefore termed the free-air correction factor. In practice the mass of rock material that occupies part or all of this space must be considered. In an area where the topography is reasonably flat, this is usually calculated by assuming the presence of an infinite slab of thickness equal to the height of the station
    <e type="italic">
     h
    </e>
    and having an appropriate density σ; its value is +0.04185 σ
    <e type="italic">
     h
    </e>
    milligal per metre. This is commonly called the Bouguer correction factor.
   </p>
   <p>
    Terrain or topographical corrections also can be applied to allow for the attractions due to surface relief if the densities of surface rocks are known. Tidal effects (the amplitudes are less than 0.3 milligal) can be calculated and allowed for.
   </p>
   <signature>
    James E. Faller
   </signature>
   <signature>
    Sir Alan H. Cook
   </signature>
  </h2>
  <h2 id="h61481">
   <title>
    The Moon and the planets
   </title>
   <p>
    Although the Apollo astronauts used a gravimeter at their lunar landing site, most scientific knowledge about the gravitational attractions of the Moon and the planets has been derived from observations of their effects upon the accelerations of spacecraft in orbit around or passing close to them. Radio tracking makes it possible to determine the accelerations of spacecraft very accurately, and the results can be expressed either as terms in a series of spherical harmonics or as the variation of gravity over the surface. As in the case of Earth, spherical harmonics are more effective for studying gross structure, while the variation of gravity is more useful for local features. Spacecraft must descend close to the surface or remain in orbit for extended periods in order to detect local gravity variations; such data had been obtained for the Moon, Venus, Mars, and Jupiter by the end of the 20th century.
   </p>
   <p>
    The Moon’s polar flattening is much less than that of Earth, while its equator is far more elliptical. There are also large, more-local irregularities from visible and concealed structures. Mars also exhibits some large local variations, while the equatorial bulges of Mercury and Venus are very slight.
   </p>
   <p>
    By contrast, the major planets, all of which rotate quite fast, have large equatorial bulges, and their gravity is dominated by a large increase from equator to pole. The polar flattening of Jupiter is about 10 percent and was first estimated from telescopic observation by
    <xref articleid="20655">
     Gian Domenico Cassini
    </xref>
    about 1664. As mentioned above, Edmond Halley subsequently realized that the corresponding effect on gravity would perturb the orbits of the satellites of Jupiter (those discovered by Galileo). The results of gravity measurements are crucial to understanding the internal properties of the planets.
   </p>
  </h2>
 </h1>
 <h1 id="h61482">
  <title>
   Gravitational theory and other aspects of physical theory
  </title>
  <p>
   The Newtonian theory of gravity is based on an assumed force acting between all pairs of bodies—i.e., an action at a distance. When a mass moves, the force acting on other masses had been considered to adjust instantaneously to the new location of the displaced mass. That, however, is inconsistent with
   <xref articleid="109465" refid="h252878">
    special relativity
   </xref>
   , which is based on the axiom that all knowledge of distant events comes from electromagnetic signals. Physical quantities have to be defined in such a way that certain combinations of them—in particular, distance, time, mass, and momentum—are independent of choice of space-time coordinates. This theory, with the field theory of electrical and magnetic phenomena, has met such empirical success that most modern gravitational theories are constructed as field theories consistent with the principles of special relativity. In a field theory the gravitational force between bodies is formed by a two-step process: (1) One body produces a gravitational field that permeates all surrounding space but has weaker strength farther from its source. A second body in that space is then acted upon by this field and experiences a force. (2) The Newtonian force of reaction is then viewed as the response of the first body to the gravitational field produced by the second body, there being at all points in space a superposition of gravitational fields due to all the bodies in it.
  </p>
  <h2 id="h61483">
   <title>
    Field theories of gravitation
   </title>
   <p>
    In the 1970s the physicists
    <xref articleid="65021">
     Abdus Salam
    </xref>
    of Pakistan and
    <xref articleid="76452">
     Steven Weinberg
    </xref>
    and
    <xref articleid="36986">
     Sheldon L. Glashow
    </xref>
    of the United States were able to show that the electromagnetic forces and the weak force responsible for
    <xref articleid="78953">
     beta decay
    </xref>
    were different manifestations of the same basic interaction. That was the first successful
    <xref articleid="74254">
     unified field theory
    </xref>
    . Physicists are actively seeking other possible unified combinations. The possibility that gravitation might be linked with the other forces of nature in a unified theory of forces greatly increased interest in gravitational field theories during the 1970s and ’80s. Because the gravitational force is exceedingly weak compared with all others and because it seems to be independent of all physical properties except mass, the unification of gravitation with the other forces remains the most difficult to achieve. That challenge has provided a tremendous impetus to experimental investigations to determine whether there may be some failure of the apparent independence.
   </p>
   <p>
    The prime example of a field theory is Einstein’s
    <xref articleid="109465" refid="h252889">
     general relativity
    </xref>
    , according to which the acceleration due to gravity is a purely geometric consequence of the properties of space-time in the neighbourhood of attracting masses. (As will be seen below, general relativity makes certain specific predictions that are borne out well by observation.) In a whole class of more-general theories, these and other effects not predicted by simple Newtonian theory are characterized by free parameters; such formulations are called parameterized post-Newtonian (PPN) theories. There is now considerable experimental and observational evidence for limits to the parameters. So far, no deviation from general relativity has been demonstrated convincingly.
   </p>
   <p>
    Field theories of gravity predict specific corrections to the Newtonian force law, the corrections taking two basic forms: (1) When matter is in motion, additional gravitational fields (analogous to the magnetic fields produced by moving electric charges) are produced; also, moving bodies interact with gravitational fields in a motion-dependent way. (2) Unlike electromagnetic field theory, in which two or more electric or magnetic fields superimpose by simple addition to give the total fields, in gravitational field theory nonlinear fields proportional to the second and higher powers of the source masses are generated, and gravitational fields proportional to the products of different masses are created. Gravitational fields themselves become sources for additional gravitational fields. Examples of some of these effects are shown below. The acceleration
    <e type="italic">
     A
    </e>
    of a moving particle of negligible mass that interacts with a mass
    <e type="italic">
     M
    </e>
    , which is at rest, is given in the following formula, derived from Einstein’s gravitational theory.
   </p>
   <p>
    The expression for
    <e type="italic">
     A
    </e>
    now has, as well as the Newtonian expression from equation (
    <inlinemediaref inlinemediaid="i15560">
     1
    </inlinemediaref>
    ), further terms in higher powers of
    <e type="italic">
     G
    </e>
    <e type="italic">
     M
    </e>
    /
    <e type="bolditalic">
     R
    </e>
    <sup>
     2
    </sup>
    —that is, in
    <e type="italic">
     G
    </e>
    <sup>
     2
    </sup>
    <e type="italic">
     M
    </e>
    <sup>
     2
    </sup>
    /
    <e type="bolditalic">
     R
    </e>
    <sup>
     4
    </sup>
    . As elsewhere,
    <e type="bolditalic">
     V
    </e>
    is the particle’s velocity vector,
    <e type="bolditalic">
     A
    </e>
    is its acceleration vector,
    <e type="bolditalic">
     R
    </e>
    is the vector from the mass
    <e type="italic">
     M
    </e>
    , and
    <e type="italic">
     c
    </e>
    is the speed of light. When written out, the sum is
    <formula>
     <inlinemedia id="i15546" mediaid="15546" url="/46/15546-004-6DBB6DC1.jpg"/>
    </formula>
   </p>
   <p>
    This expression gives only the first post-Newtonian corrections; terms of higher power in 1/
    <e type="italic">
     c
    </e>
    are neglected. For planetary motion in the solar system, the 1/
    <e type="italic">
     c
    </e>
    <sup>
     2
    </sup>
    terms are smaller than Newton’s acceleration term by at least a factor of 10
    <sup>
     −8
    </sup>
    , but some of the consequences of these correction terms are measurable and important tests of Einstein’s theory. It should be pointed out that prediction of new observable gravitational effects requires particular care; Einstein’s pioneer work in gravity has shown that gravitational fields affect the basic measuring instruments of experimental physics—clocks, rulers, light rays—with which any experimental result in physics is established. Some of these effects are listed below:
   </p>
   <list type="ul">
    <item>
     The rate at which clocks run is reduced by proximity of massive bodies; i.e., clocks near the Sun will run slowly compared with identical clocks farther away from it.
    </item>
    <item>
     In the presence of gravitational fields, the spatial structure of physical objects is no longer describable precisely by Euclidean geometry; for example, in the arrangement of three rigid rulers to form a triangle, the sum of the subtended angles will not equal 180°. A more-general type of geometry,
     <xref articleid="111076">
      Riemannian geometry
     </xref>
     , seems required to describe the spatial structure of matter in the presence of gravitational fields.
    </item>
    <item>
     Light rays do not travel in straight lines, the rays being deflected by gravitational fields. To distant observers the light-propagation speed is observed to be reduced near massive bodies.
    </item>
   </list>
  </h2>
  <h2 id="h61484">
   <title>
    Gravitational fields and the theory of general relativity
   </title>
   <p>
    In Einstein’s theory of general relativity, the physical consequences of gravitational fields are stated in the following way. Space-time is a four-dimensional non-Euclidean continuum, and the curvature of the Riemannian geometry of space-time is produced by or related to the distribution of matter in the world. Particles and light rays travel along the geodesics (shortest paths) of this four-dimensional geometric world.
   </p>
   <p>
    There are two principal consequences of the geometric view of gravitation: (1) the accelerations of bodies depend only on their masses and not on their chemical or nuclear constitution, and (2) the path of a body or of light in the neighbourhood of a massive body (the Sun, for example) is slightly different from that predicted by Newton’s theory. The first is the weak principle of equivalence. Newton himself performed experiments with pendulums that demonstrated the principle to better than one part in 1,000 for a variety of materials, and, at the beginning of the 20th century, the Hungarian physicist
    <xref articleid="32749">
     Roland, Baron von Eötvös
    </xref>
    , showed that different materials accelerate in Earth’s field at the same rate to within one part in 10
    <sup>
     9
    </sup>
    . More-recent experiments have shown the equality of accelerations in the field of the Sun to within one part in 10
    <sup>
     11
    </sup>
    . Newtonian theory is in accord with these results because of the postulate that gravitational force is proportional to a body’s mass.
   </p>
   <p>
    Inertial mass is a mass parameter giving the inertial resistance to acceleration of the body when responding to all types of force. Gravitational mass is determined by the strength of the gravitational force experienced by the body when in the gravitational field
    <e type="italic">
     g
    </e>
    . The Eötvös experiments therefore show that the ratio of gravitational and inertial mass is the same for different substances.
   </p>
   <p>
    In Einstein’s theory of special relativity, inertial mass is a manifestation of all the forms of energy in a body, according to his fundamental relationship
    <e type="italic">
     E
    </e>
    =
    <e type="italic">
     m
    </e>
    <e type="italic">
     c
    </e>
    <sup>
     2
    </sup>
    ,
    <e type="italic">
     E
    </e>
    being the total energy content of a body,
    <e type="italic">
     m
    </e>
    the inertial mass of the body, and
    <e type="italic">
     c
    </e>
    the speed of light. Dealing with gravitation, then, as a field phenomenon, the weak principle of equivalence indicates that all forms of nongravitational energy must identically couple to or interact with the gravitational field, because the various materials in nature possess different fractional amounts of nuclear, electrical, magnetic, and kinetic energies, yet they accelerate at identical rates.
   </p>
   <p>
    In the theory of general relativity, the gravitational field also interacts with gravitational energy in the same manner as with other forms of energy, an example of that theory’s universality not possessed by most other theories of gravitation.
   </p>
   <p>
    The Sun has an appreciable fraction of internal gravitational energy, and the repetitions of the Eötvös experiments during the 1970s, with the Sun instead of Earth as the attracting mass, revealed that bodies accelerate at identical rates in the Sun’s field as well as in that of Earth. Extremely accurate laser measurements of the distance of the Moon from Earth have made possible a further test of the weak principle of equivalence. The chemical constitutions of Earth and the Moon are not the same, and so, if the principle did not hold, they might accelerate at different rates under the Sun’s attraction. No such effect has been detected.
   </p>
   <p>
    Newton’s third law of dynamics states that every force implies an equal and opposite reaction force. Modern field theories of force contain this principle by requiring every entity that is acted upon by a field to be also a source of the field. An experiment by the American physicist Lloyd Kreuzer established to within 1 part in 20,000 that different materials produce gravitational fields with a strength the same as that of gravitational fields acting upon them. In this experiment a sphere of solid material was moved through a liquid of identical weight density. The absence of a gravitational effect on a nearby Cavendish balance instrument during the sphere’s motion is interpreted as showing that the two materials had equal potency in producing a local gravitational-field anomaly.
   </p>
   <p>
    Other experiments have confirmed Einstein’s predictions to within a few percent. Using the Mössbauer effect to monitor the nuclear reabsorption of resonant gamma radiation, a shift of wavelength of the radiation that traveled vertically tens of metres in Earth’s gravitational field was measured, and the slowing of clocks (in this case the nuclear vibrations are clocks) as predicted by Einstein was confirmed to 1 percent precision. If ν and Δν are clock frequency and change of frequency, respectively,
    <e type="italic">
     h
    </e>
    is the height difference between clocks in the gravitational field
    <e type="italic">
     g
    </e>
    . Then
    <formula>
     <inlinemedia id="i15545" mediaid="15545" url="/45/15545-004-AB7FBC29.jpg"/>
    </formula>
   </p>
  </h2>
  <h2 id="h61485">
   <title>
    The paths of particles and light
   </title>
   <p>
    <assembly id="a86707" url="/assembly/view/86707">
     <title>
      experimental evidence for general relativity
     </title>
     <media mediaid="91965" type="image" url="/65/91965-004-116CAD96.jpg"/>
     <caption>
      In 1919 observation of a solar eclipse confirmed Einstein’s prediction that light is bent in the presence of mass. This experimental support for his general theory of relativity garnered him instant worldwide acclaim.
     </caption>
     <credit>
      Encyclopædia Britannica, Inc.
     </credit>
    </assembly>
    <assemblyref assemblyid="a86707"/>
    The idea that light should be deflected by passing close to a massive body had been suggested by the British astronomer and geologist
    <xref articleid="52474">
     John Michell
    </xref>
    in the 18th century. However, Einstein’s general relativity theory predicted twice as much deflection as Newtonian physics. Quick confirmation of Einstein’s result came from measuring the direction of a star close to the Sun’s direction during an expedition led by the British astronomer
    <xref articleid="31962">
     Sir Arthur Stanley Eddington
    </xref>
    to observe the solar eclipse of 1919. Optical determinations of the change of direction of a star are subject to many systematic errors, and far better results have been obtained of the directions of spacecraft with radio interferometers of very long baselines. The effect comes from the decrease in the speed of light near a massive object (the Sun). That decrease has also been found directly from the round-trip travel times for radar pulses between Earth and other inner planets or artificial satellites passing behind the Sun and has confirmed to about 4 percent the prediction of an additional time delay Δ
    <e type="italic">
     t
    </e>
    given by the following formula, in which
    <e type="italic">
     M
    </e>
    <sub>
     S
    </sub>
    is the Sun’s mass,
    <e type="italic">
     R
    </e>
    <sub>
     1
    </sub>
    and
    <e type="italic">
     R
    </e>
    <sub>
     2
    </sub>
    are the distances from the Sun to Earth and to the other reflecting body, and
    <e type="italic">
     D
    </e>
    is the distance of closest approach of the radar pulses to the Sun (ln stands for natural logarithm):
    <formula>
     <inlinemedia id="i15544" mediaid="15544" url="/44/15544-004-8F0CC4AF.jpg"/>
    </formula>
   </p>
   <p>
    The additional precession of the orbit of Mercury of 43 arc seconds per century was known before the development of the theory of general relativity. With radar measurements of the distances to the planets, similar anomalous precessions have been estimated for Venus and Earth and have been found to agree with general relativity.
   </p>
  </h2>
  <h2 id="h61486">
   <title>
    Gravitational radiation
   </title>
   <p>
    According to general relativity, the curvature of space-time is determined by the distribution of masses, while the motion of masses is determined by the curvature. In consequence, variations of the gravitational field should be transmitted from place to place as waves, just as variations of an electromagnetic field travel as waves. If the masses that are the source of a field change with time, they should radiate energy as waves of curvature of the field. There are strong grounds for believing that such radiation exists. One particular double-star system has a
    <xref articleid="61887">
     pulsar
    </xref>
    as one of its components, and, from measurements of the shift of the pulsar frequency due to the
    <xref articleid="30955">
     Doppler effect
    </xref>
    , precise estimates of the period of the orbit show that the period is changing, corresponding to a decrease in the energy of the orbital motion. Gravitational radiation is the only known means by which that could happen.
   </p>
   <p>
    <assembly id="a90798" url="/assembly/view/90798">
     <title>
      Laser Interferometer Space Antenna (LISA)
     </title>
     <media mediaid="96321" type="image" url="/21/96321-004-15F802E4.jpg"/>
     <caption>
      Laser Interferometer Space Antenna (LISA), a Beyond Einstein Great Observatory, is scheduled for launch in 2034. Funded by the European Space Agency, LISA will consist of three identical spacecraft that will trail the Earth in its orbit by about 50 million km (30 million miles). The spacecraft will contain thrusters for maneuvering them into an equilateral triangle, with sides of approximately 5 million km (3 million miles), such that the triangle’s centre will be located along the Earth’s orbit. By measuring the transmission of laser signals between the spacecraft (essentially a giant Michelson interferometer in space), scientists hope to detect and accurately measure gravity waves.
     </caption>
     <credit>
      Encyclopædia Britannica, Inc.
     </credit>
    </assembly>
    <assemblyref assemblyid="a90798"/>
    Double stars in their regular motions (such as that for which a change in period has been detected) and massive stars collapsing as
    <xref articleid="70402">
     supernovas
    </xref>
    have been suggested as sources of gravitational radiation, and considerable theoretical effort has gone into calculating the signals to be expected from those and other sources.
   </p>
   <p>
    Gravitational radiation is very weak. The changes of curvature would correspond to a dilation in one direction and a contraction at right angles to that direction. One scheme, first tried out about 1960, employed a massive cylinder that might be set in mechanical oscillation by a gravitational signal. The authors of this apparatus argued that signals had been detected, but their claim was not substantiated. In a more fruitful scheme an optical interferometer is set up with freely suspended reflectors at the ends of long paths that are at right angles to each other. Shifts of interference fringes corresponding to an increase in length of one arm and a decrease in the other would indicate the passage of gravitational waves. Such an interferometer, the Laser Interferometer Gravitational-Wave Observatory (LIGO), made the first detection of gravitational radiation in 2015. Two black holes about 1.3 billion light-years away spiralled into each other. The black holes were 36 and 29 times the mass of the Sun and formed a new black hole 62 times the mass of the Sun. In the merger, three solar masses were converted to energy in gravitational waves; the amount of power radiated was 50 times more than that of all the stars shining in the universe in that moment. As of 2020, LIGO has made 47 detections of gravitational radiation. Forty-four were from mergers of a black hole binary, two were the merger of a neutron star binary, and one was the possible merger of a black hole with a neutron star.
   </p>
   <signature>
    Kenneth L. Nordtvedt Jr.
   </signature>
   <signature>
    Sir Alan H. Cook
   </signature>
  </h2>
 </h1>
 <h1 id="h61487">
  <title>
   Some astronomical aspects of gravitation
  </title>
  <p>
   <assemblyref assemblyid="a17790"/>
   As stated above, studies of gravity allow the masses and densities of celestial bodies to be estimated and thereby make it possible to investigate the physical constitutions of stars and planets. Because gravitation is a very weak force, however, its distinctive effects appear only when masses are extremely large. The idea that light might be attracted gravitationally had been suggested by
   <xref articleid="52474">
    Michell
   </xref>
   and examined by the French mathematician and astronomer
   <xref articleid="47167">
    Pierre-Simon Laplace
   </xref>
   . Predictions by classical physics and general relativity that light passing close to the Sun might be deflected are described above. There are two further consequences for astronomy. Light from a distant object may pass close to objects other than the Sun and be deflected by them. In particular, they may be deflected by a massive galaxy. If some object is behind a massive galaxy, as seen from Earth, deflected light may reach Earth by more than one path. Operating like a lens that focuses light along different paths, the gravity of the galaxy may make the object appear multiple; examples of such apparently double objects have been found.
  </p>
  <p>
   Both Michell and Laplace pointed out that the attraction of a very dense object upon light might be so great that the light could never escape from the object, rendering it invisible. Such a phenomenon is a
   <xref articleid="15483">
    black hole
   </xref>
   . The relativistic theory of black holes has been thoroughly developed in recent years, and astronomers have conducted extensive observations of them. One possible class of black holes comprises very large stars that have used up all of their nuclear energy so that they are no longer held up by radiation pressure and have collapsed into black holes (less-massive stars may collapse into
   <xref articleid="55410">
    neutron stars
   </xref>
   ). Supermassive black holes with masses millions to billions times that of the Sun are thought to exist at the centres of most galaxies.
  </p>
  <p>
   <assembly id="a239625" url="/assembly/view/239625">
    <title>
     black hole in M87
    </title>
    <media mediaid="205226" type="image" url="/26/205226-004-E0B95A1E.jpg"/>
    <caption>
     Black hole at the centre of the massive galaxy M87, about 55 million light-years from Earth, as imaged by the Event Horizon Telescope (EHT). The black hole is 6.5 billion times more massive than the Sun. This image was the first direct visual evidence of a supermassive black hole and its shadow. The ring is brighter on one side because the black hole is rotating, and thus material on the side of the black hole turning toward Earth has its emission boosted by the Doppler effect. The shadow of the black hole is about five and a half times larger than the event horizon, the boundary marking the black hole’s limits, where the escape velocity is equal to the speed of light. This image was released in 2019 and created from data collected in 2017.
    </caption>
    <credit>
     Event Horizon Telescope collaboration et al.
    </credit>
   </assembly>
   <assemblyref assemblyid="a239625"/>
   Black holes, from which no radiation is able to escape, cannot be seen by their own light, but there are observable secondary effects. If a black hole were one component of a double star, the orbital motion of the pair and the mass of the invisible member might be derived from the oscillatory motion of a visible companion. Because black holes attract matter, any gas in the vicinity of an object of this kind would fall into it and acquire, before vanishing into the hole, a high velocity and consequently a high temperature. The gas may become hot enough to produce
   <xref articleid="77656">
    X-rays
   </xref>
   and
   <xref articleid="35974">
    gamma rays
   </xref>
   from around the hole. Such a mechanism is the origin of at least some powerful X-ray and radio astronomical sources, including those at the centres of galaxies and quasars. In the case of the massive galaxy M87, the supermassive black hole at its centre, which has a mass 6.5 billion times that of the Sun has been directly observed.
  </p>
 </h1>
 <h1 id="h61488">
  <title>
   Experimental study of gravitation
  </title>
  <p>
   The essence of Newton’s theory of gravitation is that the force between two bodies is proportional to the product of their masses and the inverse square of their separation and that the force depends on nothing else. With a small modification, the same is true in general relativity. Newton himself tested his assumptions by experiment and observation. He made pendulum experiments to confirm the principle of equivalence and checked the inverse square law as applied to the periods and diameters of the orbits of the satellites of Jupiter and Saturn.
  </p>
  <p>
   During the latter part of the 19th century, many experiments showed the force of gravity to be independent of temperature, electromagnetic fields, shielding by other matter, orientation of crystal axes, and other factors. The revival of such experiments during the 1970s was the result of theoretical attempts to relate gravitation to other forces of nature by showing that general relativity was an incomplete description of gravity. New experiments on the equivalence principle were performed, and experimental tests of the inverse square law were made both in the laboratory and in the field.
  </p>
  <p>
   There also has been a continuing interest in the determination of the constant of gravitation, although it must be pointed out that
   <e type="italic">
    G
   </e>
   occupies a rather anomalous position among the other constants of physics. In the first place, the mass
   <e type="italic">
    M
   </e>
   of any celestial object cannot be determined independently of the gravitational attraction that it exerts. Thus, the combination
   <e type="italic">
    G
   </e>
   <e type="italic">
    M
   </e>
   , not the separate value of
   <e type="italic">
    M
   </e>
   , is the only meaningful property of a star, planet, or galaxy. Second, according to general relativity and the principle of equivalence,
   <e type="italic">
    G
   </e>
   does not depend on material properties but is in a sense a geometric factor. Hence, the determination of the constant of gravitation does not seem as essential as the measurement of quantities like the electronic charge or
   <xref articleid="60293">
    Planck’s constant
   </xref>
   . It is also much less well determined experimentally than any of the other constants of physics.
  </p>
  <p>
   Experiments on gravitation are in fact very difficult, as a comparison of experiments on the inverse square law of electrostatics with those on gravitation will show. The electrostatic law has been established to within one part in 10
   <sup>
    16
   </sup>
   by using the fact that the field inside a closed conductor is zero when the inverse square law holds. Experiments with very sensitive electronic devices have failed to detect any residual fields in such a closed cavity. Gravitational forces have to be detected by mechanical means, most often the
   <xref articleid="72987">
    torsion balance
   </xref>
   , and, although the sensitivities of mechanical devices have been greatly improved, they are still far below those of electronic detectors. Mechanical arrangements also preclude the use of a complete gravitational enclosure. Last, extraneous disturbances are relatively large because gravitational forces are very small (something that Newton first pointed out). Thus, the inverse square law is established over laboratory distances to no better than one part in 10
   <sup>
    4
   </sup>
   .
  </p>
  <h2 id="h61489">
   <title>
    The inverse square law
   </title>
   <p>
    Recent interest in the inverse square law arose from two suggestions. First, the gravitational field itself might have a mass, in which case the constant of gravitation would change in an exponential manner from one value for small distances to a different one for large distances over a characteristic distance related to the mass of the field. Second, the observed field might be the superposition of two or more fields of different origin and different strengths, one of which might depend on chemical or nuclear constitution. Deviations from the inverse square law have been sought in three ways:
   </p>
   <list type="ul">
    <item>
     The law has been checked in the laboratory over distances up to about 1 metre.
    </item>
    <item>
     The effective value of
     <e type="italic">
      G
     </e>
     for distances between 100 metres and 1 km has been estimated from geophysical studies.
    </item>
    <item>
     There have been careful comparisons of the value of the attraction of Earth as measured on the surface and as experienced by artificial satellites.
    </item>
   </list>
   <p>
    Early in the 1970s an experiment by the American physicist Daniel R. Long seemed to show a deviation from the inverse square law at a range of about 0.1 metre. Long compared the maximum attractions of two rings upon a test mass hung from the arm of a torsion balance. The maximum attraction of a ring occurs at a particular point on the axis and is determined by the mass and dimensions of the ring. If the ring is moved until the force on the test mass is greatest, the distance between the test mass and the ring is not needed. Two later experiments over the same range showed no deviation from the inverse square law. In one, conducted by the American physicist Riley Newman and his colleagues, a test mass hung on a torsion balance was moved around in a long hollow cylinder. The cylinder approximates a complete gravitational enclosure and, allowing for a small correction because it is open at the ends, the force on the test mass should not depend on its location within the cylinder. No deviation from the inverse square law was found. In the other experiment, performed in Cambridge, Eng., by Y.T. Chen and associates, the attractions of two solid cylinders of different mass were balanced against a third cylinder so that only the separations of the cylinders had to be known; it was not necessary to know the distances of any from a test mass. Again no deviation of more than one part in 10
    <sup>
     4
    </sup>
    from the inverse square law was found. Other, somewhat less-sensitive experiments at ranges up to one metre or so also have failed to establish any greater deviation.
   </p>
   <p>
    The geophysical tests go back to a method for the determination of the constant of gravitation that had been used in the 19th century, especially by the British astronomer
    <xref articleid="5227">
     Sir George Airy
    </xref>
    . Suppose the value of gravity
    <e type="italic">
     g
    </e>
    is measured at the top and bottom of a horizontal slab of rock of thickness
    <e type="italic">
     t
    </e>
    and density
    <e type="italic">
     d
    </e>
    . The values for the top and bottom will be different for two reasons. First, the top of the slab is
    <e type="italic">
     t
    </e>
    farther from the centre of Earth, and so the measured value of gravity will be less by 2(
    <e type="italic">
     t
    </e>
    /
    <e type="italic">
     R
    </e>
    )
    <e type="italic">
     g
    </e>
    , where
    <e type="italic">
     R
    </e>
    is the radius of Earth. Second, the slab itself attracts objects above and below it toward its centre; the difference between the downward and upward attractions of the slab is 4π
    <e type="italic">
     G
    </e>
    <e type="italic">
     t
    </e>
    <e type="italic">
     d
    </e>
    . Thus, a value of
    <e type="italic">
     G
    </e>
    may be estimated. Frank D. Stacey and his colleagues in Australia made such measurements at the top and bottom of deep mine shafts and claimed that there may be a real difference between their value of
    <e type="italic">
     G
    </e>
    and the best value from laboratory experiments. The difficulties lie in obtaining reliable samples of the density and in taking account of varying densities at greater depths. Similar uncertainties appear to have afflicted measurements in a deep bore hole in the Greenland ice sheet.
   </p>
   <p>
    New measurements have failed to detect any deviation from the inverse square law. The most thorough investigation was carried out from a high tower in Colorado. Measurements were made with a gravimeter at different heights and coupled with an extensive survey of gravity around the base of the tower. Any variations of gravity over the surface that would give rise to variations up the height of the tower were estimated with great care. Allowance was also made for deflections of the tower and for the accelerations of its motions. The final result was that no deviation from the inverse square law could be found.
   </p>
   <p>
    A further test of the inverse square law depends on the theorem that the divergence of the gravity vector should vanish in a space that is free of additional gravitational sources. An experiment to test this was performed by M.V. Moody and H.J. Paik in California with a three-axis superconducting gravity gradiometer that measured the gradients of gravity in three perpendicular directions. The sum of the three gradients was zero within the accuracy of the measurements, about one part in 10
    <sup>
     4
    </sup>
    .
   </p>
   <p>
    The absolute measurements of gravity described earlier, together with the comprehensive gravity surveys made over the surface of Earth, allow the mean value of gravity over Earth to be estimated to about one part in 10
    <sup>
     6
    </sup>
    . The techniques of space research also have given the mean value of the radius of Earth and the distances of artificial satellites to the same precision. Thus, it has been possible to compare the value of gravity on Earth with that acting on an artificial satellite. Agreement to about one part in 10
    <sup>
     6
    </sup>
    shows that, over distances from the surface of Earth to close satellite orbits, the inverse square law is followed.
   </p>
   <p>
    Thus far, all of the most reliable experiments and observations reveal no deviation from the inverse square law.
   </p>
  </h2>
  <h2 id="h61490">
   <title>
    The principle of equivalence
   </title>
   <p>
    <assembly id="a157877" url="/assembly/view/157877">
     <title>
      Newton’s law of gravitation: Apollo 15 gravitation experiment
     </title>
     <media mediaid="148908" thumburl="/08/148908-049-2D402C89.jpg" type="video" url=""/>
     <caption>
      Apollo 15 commander David Scott dropping a 1.32-kg (2.91-pound) aluminum geological hammer and a 0.03-kg (0.07-pound) falcon feather on the surface of the Moon and proving that objects undergo the same acceleration in gravity, August 2, 1971.
     </caption>
     <credit>
      NASA
     </credit>
    </assembly>
    <assemblyref assemblyid="a157877"/>
    Experiments with ordinary pendulums test the principle of equivalence to no better than about one part in 10
    <sup>
     5
    </sup>
    . Eötvös obtained much better discrimination with a torsion balance. His tests depended on comparing gravitational forces with inertial forces for masses of different composition. Eötvös set up a torsion balance to compare, for each of two masses, the gravitational attraction of Earth with the inertial forces due to the rotation of Earth about its polar axis. His arrangement of the masses was not optimal, and he did not have the sensitive electronic means of control and reading that are now available. Nonetheless, Eötvös found that the weak equivalence principle (
    <e type="italic">
     see above
    </e>
    <xref articleid="106265" refid="h61484">
     Gravitational fields and the theory of general relativity
    </xref>
    ) was satisfied to within one part in 10
    <sup>
     9
    </sup>
    for a number of very different chemicals, some of which were quite exotic. His results were later confirmed by the Hungarian physicist János Renner. Renner’s work has been analyzed recently in great detail because of the suggestion that it could provide evidence for a new force. It seems that the uncertainties of the experiments hardly allow such analyses.
   </p>
   <p>
    Eötvös also suggested that the attraction of the Sun upon test masses could be compared with the inertial forces of Earth’s orbital motion about the Sun. He performed some experiments, verifying equivalence with an accuracy similar to that which he had obtained with his terrestrial experiments. The solar scheme has substantial experimental advantages, and the American physicist
    <xref articleid="30334">
     Robert H. Dicke
    </xref>
    and his colleagues, in a careful series of observations in the 1960s (employing up-to-date methods of servo control and observation), found that the weak equivalence principle held to about one part in 10
    <sup>
     11
    </sup>
    for the attraction of the Sun on gold and aluminum. A later experiment by the Russian researcher Vladimir Braginski, with very different experimental arrangements, gave a limit of about one part in 10
    <sup>
     12
    </sup>
    for platinum and aluminum.
   </p>
   <p>
    Galileo’s supposed experiment of dropping objects from the
    <xref articleid="47524">
     Leaning Tower of Pisa
    </xref>
    has been reproduced in the laboratory with apparatuses used to determine the absolute value of gravity by timing a falling body. Two objects, one of uranium, the other of copper, were timed as they fell. No difference was detected.
   </p>
   <p>
    Laser-ranging observations of the Moon in the LAGEOS (
    <e type="italic">
     la
    </e>
    ser
    <e type="italic">
     geo
    </e>
    dynamic
    <e type="italic">
     s
    </e>
    atellites) experiment have also failed to detect deviations from the principle of equivalence. Earth and the Moon have different compositions, the Moon lacking the iron found in Earth’s core. Thus, if the principle of equivalence were not valid, the accelerations of Earth and the Moon toward the Sun might be different. The very precise measurements of the motion of the Moon relative to Earth could detect no such difference.
   </p>
   <p>
    By the start of the 21st century, all observations and experiments on gravitation had detected that there are no deviations from the deductions of general relativity, that the weak principle of equivalence is valid, and that the inverse square law holds over distances from a few centimetres to thousands of kilometres. Coupled with observations of electromagnetic signals passing close to the Sun and of images formed by gravitational lenses, those observations and experiments make it very clear that general relativity provides the only acceptable description of gravitation at the present time.
   </p>
  </h2>
  <h2 id="h61491">
   <title>
    The constant of gravitation
   </title>
   <p>
    The constant of gravitation has been measured in three ways:
   </p>
   <list type="ul">
    <item>
     The comparison of the pull of a large natural mass with that of Earth
    </item>
    <item>
     The measurement with a laboratory balance of the attraction of Earth upon a test mass
    </item>
    <item>
     The direct measurement of the force between two masses in the laboratory
    </item>
   </list>
   <p>
    The first approach was suggested by Newton; the earliest observations were made in 1774 by the British astronomer
    <xref articleid="51263">
     Nevil Maskelyne
    </xref>
    on the mountain of Schiehallion in Scotland. The subsequent work of Airy and more-recent developments are noted above. The laboratory balance method was developed in large part by the British physicist
    <xref articleid="61147">
     John Henry Poynting
    </xref>
    during the late 1800s, but all the most recent work has involved the use of the torsion balance in some form or other for the direct laboratory measurement of the force between two bodies. The torsion balance was devised by Michell, who died before he could use it to measure
    <e type="italic">
     G
    </e>
    . Cavendish adapted Michell’s design to make the first reliable measurement of
    <e type="italic">
     G
    </e>
    in 1798; only in comparatively recent times have clearly better results been obtained. Cavendish measured the change in deflection of the balance when attracting masses were moved from one side to the other of the torsion beam. The method of deflection was analyzed most thoroughly in the late 1800s by
    <xref articleid="16078">
     Sir Charles Vernon Boys
    </xref>
    , an English physicist, who carried it to its highest development, using a delicate suspension fibre of fused silica for the pendulum. In a variant of that method, the deflection of the balance is maintained constant by a servo control.
   </p>
   <p>
    The second scheme involves the changes in the period of oscillation of a torsion balance when attracting masses are placed close to it such that the period is shortened in one position and lengthened in another. Measurements of period can be made much more precisely than those of deflection, and the method, introduced by Carl Braun of Austria in 1897, has been used in many subsequent determinations. In a third scheme the acceleration of the suspended masses is measured as they are moved relative to the large attracting masses.
   </p>
   <p>
    In another arrangement a balance with heavy attracting masses is set up near a free test balance and adjusted so that it oscillates with the same period as the test balance. The latter is then driven into resonant oscillations with an amplitude that is a measure of the constant of gravitation. The technique was first employed by J. Zahradnicek of Czechoslovakia during the 1930s and was effectively used again by C. Pontikis of France some 40 years later.
   </p>
   <p>
    Suspensions for two-arm balances for the comparison of masses and for torsion balances have been studied intensively by T.J. Quinn and his colleagues at the International Bureau of Weights and Measures, near Paris, and they have found that suspensions with thin ribbons of metal rather than wires provide the most stable systems. They have used balances with such suspensions to look for deviations from the predictions of general relativity and have most recently used a torsion balance with ribbon suspension in two new determinations of the constant of gravitation.
   </p>
   <p>
    Many new determinations of
    <e type="italic">
     G
    </e>
    were made in the five years from 1996 to 2001 and are summarized in the . However, despite the great attention given to systematic errors in those experiments, it is clear from the range of the results that serious discrepancies, much greater than the apparent random errors, still afflict determinations of
    <e type="italic">
     G
    </e>
    . In 2001 the best estimate of
    <e type="italic">
     G
    </e>
    was taken to be 6.67553 × 10
    <sup>
     −11
    </sup>
    m
    <sup>
     3
    </sup>
    s
    <sup>
     −2
    </sup>
    kg
    <sup>
     −1
    </sup>
    . Results before 1982 indicate a lower value, perhaps 6.670, but those from 1996 onward suggest a higher value.
   </p>
  </h2>
  <h2 id="h61492">
   <title>
    The variation of the constant of gravitation with time
   </title>
   <p>
    The 20th-century English physicist
    <xref articleid="30591">
     P.A.M. Dirac
    </xref>
    , among others, suggested that the value of the constant of gravitation might be proportional to the age of the universe; other rates of change over time also have been proposed. The rates of change would be extremely small, one part in 10
    <sup>
     11
    </sup>
    per year if the age of the universe is taken to be 10
    <sup>
     11
    </sup>
    years; such a rate is entirely beyond experimental capabilities at present. There is, however, the possibility of looking for the effects of any variation upon the orbit of a celestial body, in particular the Moon. It has been claimed from time to time that such effects may have been detected. As yet, there is no certainty.
   </p>
  </h2>
  <h2 id="h61493">
   <title>
    Fundamental character of
    <e type="italic">
     G
    </e>
   </title>
   <p>
    The constant of gravitation is plainly a fundamental quantity, since it appears to determine the large-scale structure of the entire universe. Gravity is a fundamental quantity whether it is an essentially geometric parameter, as in general relativity, or the strength of a field, as in one aspect of a more-general field of unified forces. The fact that, so far as is known, gravitation depends on no other physical factors makes it likely that the value of
    <e type="italic">
     G
    </e>
    reflects a basic restriction on the possibilities of physical measurement, just as special relativity is a consequence of the fact that, beyond the shortest distances, it is impossible to make separate measurements of length and time.
   </p>
   <signature>
    Sir Alan H. Cook
   </signature>
  </h2>
 </h1>
 <h1 id="h12076">
  <title>
   Bibliography
  </title>
  <h2 id="h12077">
   <title>
    General introductions to gravitation
   </title>
   <p>
    <e type="smallcap">
     Isaac Newton
    </e>
    ,
    <e type="italic">
     The Principia: Mathematical Principles of Natural Philosophy
    </e>
    , trans. by
    <e type="smallcap">
     I. Bernard Cohen
    </e>
    and
    <e type="smallcap">
     Anne Whitman
    </e>
    (1999), often referred to as the
    <e type="italic">
     Principia
    </e>
    , is the origin of all fundamental work on gravity.
    <e type="smallcap">
     Stephen W. Hawking
    </e>
    and
    <e type="smallcap">
     W. Israel
    </e>
    (eds.),
    <e type="italic">
     Three Hundred Years of Gravitation
    </e>
    (1987, reissued 1989), provides many authoritative review articles in commemoration of the tercentenary of the publication of Newton’s
    <e type="italic">
     Principia
    </e>
    .
    <e type="smallcap">
     Stephen W. Hawking
    </e>
    ,
    <e type="italic">
     A Brief History of Time: From the Big Bang to Black Holes
    </e>
    (1988), is a nonmathematical book by an outstanding author that features a chapter on black holes. Expositions of theory and the results of relevant experiments are presented in
    <e type="smallcap">
     Ignazio Ciufolini
    </e>
    and
    <e type="smallcap">
     John Archibald Wheeler
    </e>
    ,
    <e type="italic">
     Gravitation and Inertia
    </e>
    (1995).
    <e type="smallcap">
     Alan Cook
    </e>
    ,
    <e type="italic">
     The Motion of the Moon
    </e>
    (1988), discusses theories of the lunar orbit, with a chapter on applications that includes an account of gravitational studies.
   </p>
  </h2>
  <h2 id="h258361">
   <title>
    Gravity fields around the Earth, Moon, and planets
   </title>
   <p>
    <e type="smallcap">
     Alan Cook
    </e>
    ,
    <e type="italic">
     Physics of the Earth and Planets
    </e>
    (1973), includes a chapter on methods and results of gravity measurements, and
    <e type="italic">
     Interiors of the Planets
    </e>
    (1980) summarizes knowledge of the gravity fields of the planets and their interpretation.
   </p>
  </h2>
  <h2 id="h258362">
   <title>
    Gravitational experiments
   </title>
   <p>
    <e type="smallcap">
     Henry Cavendish
    </e>
    , “Experiments to Determine the Density of the Earth,”
    <e type="italic">
     Philosophical Transactions of the Royal Society of London
    </e>
    , 88:469–526 (June 21, 1798), details the first measurement of
    <e type="italic">
     G
    </e>
    .
    <e type="smallcap">
     Clifford M. Will
    </e>
    ,
    <e type="italic">
     Theory and Experiment in Gravitational Physics
    </e>
    , rev. ed. (1993), is a thorough treatment.
    <e type="smallcap">
     Y.T. Chen
    </e>
    and
    <e type="smallcap">
     Alan Cook
    </e>
    ,
    <e type="italic">
     Gravitational Experiments in the Laboratory
    </e>
    (1993), includes a detailed discussion of experimental methods, their design, and sources of error.
   </p>
   <signature>
    Sir Alan H. Cook
   </signature>
  </h2>
 </h1>
 <copyright>
  Encyclopædia Britannica
 </copyright>
</article>