<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "syndication_xml.dtd">
<article articleid="109683" articletypeid="1" language="en_us" lastupdate="2022-Aug-03 08:12:54" url="/article/mineral/109683" version="23">
 <title>
  mineral
 </title>
 <p>
  <assembly id="a238644" url="/assembly/view/238644">
   <title>
    azurite
   </title>
   <media mediaid="140893" type="image" url="/93/140893-004-AB190A9E.jpg"/>
   <caption>
    Azurite, also called chessylite, is a basic copper carbonate ordinarily found with malachite in the oxidized zone of copper lodes.
   </caption>
   <credit>
    © Rainer Walter Schmied/Dreamstime.com
   </credit>
  </assembly>
  <e type="bold">
   mineral
  </e>
  ,
  <assemblyref assemblyid="a238644"/>
  naturally occurring homogeneous
  <xref articleid="68592">
   solid
  </xref>
  with a definite chemical composition and a highly ordered
  <xref articleid="110411">
   atomic
  </xref>
  arrangement; it is usually formed by inorganic processes. There are several thousand known mineral species, about 100 of which constitute the major mineral components of
  <xref articleid="109695">
   rocks
  </xref>
  ; these are the so-called rock-forming minerals.
 </p>
 <h1 id="h80352">
  <title>
   Definition
  </title>
  <p>
   A mineral, which by definition must be formed through natural processes, is distinct from the synthetic equivalents produced in the laboratory. Artificial versions of minerals, including
   <xref articleid="32522">
    emeralds
   </xref>
   ,
   <xref articleid="65706">
    sapphires
   </xref>
   ,
   <xref articleid="30264">
    diamonds
   </xref>
   , and other valuable
   <xref articleid="36349">
    gemstones
   </xref>
   , are regularly produced in industrial and research facilities and are often nearly identical to their natural counterparts.
  </p>
  <p>
   By its definition as a homogeneous solid, a mineral is composed of a single solid substance of uniform composition that cannot be physically separated into simpler
   <xref articleid="110804">
    chemical compounds
   </xref>
   . Homogeneity is determined relative to the scale on which it is defined. A specimen that appears homogeneous to the unaided eye, for example, may reveal several mineral components under a
   <xref articleid="108723">
    microscope
   </xref>
   or upon exposure to
   <xref articleid="77657">
    X-ray diffraction
   </xref>
   techniques. Most rocks are composed of several different minerals; e.g.,
   <xref articleid="37718">
    granite
   </xref>
   consists of
   <xref articleid="109684">
    feldspar
   </xref>
   ,
   <xref articleid="62182">
    quartz
   </xref>
   ,
   <xref articleid="109689">
    mica
   </xref>
   , and
   <xref articleid="109686">
    amphibole
   </xref>
   . In addition,
   <xref articleid="110302">
    gases
   </xref>
   and
   <xref articleid="110301">
    liquids
   </xref>
   are excluded by a strict interpretation of the above definition of a mineral.
   <xref articleid="108437">
    Ice
   </xref>
   , the solid state of
   <xref articleid="76210">
    water
   </xref>
   (H
   <sub>
    2
   </sub>
   O), is considered a mineral, but liquid water is not; liquid
   <xref articleid="52102">
    mercury
   </xref>
   , though sometimes found in mercury ore deposits, is not classified as a mineral either. Such substances that resemble minerals in
   <xref articleid="108655">
    chemistry
   </xref>
   and occurrence are dubbed mineraloids and are included in the general domain of
   <xref articleid="52833">
    mineralogy
   </xref>
   .
  </p>
  <p>
   Since a mineral has a definite composition, it can be expressed by a specific chemical formula. Quartz (silicon dioxide), for instance, is rendered as SiO
   <sub>
    2
   </sub>
   , because the
   <xref articleid="110602">
    elements
   </xref>
   <xref articleid="67764">
    silicon
   </xref>
   (Si) and
   <xref articleid="57841">
    oxygen
   </xref>
   (O) are its only constituents and they invariably appear in a 1:2 ratio. The chemical makeup of most minerals is not as well defined as that of quartz, which is a pure substance.
   <xref articleid="67639">
    Siderite
   </xref>
   , for example, does not always occur as pure
   <xref articleid="42794">
    iron
   </xref>
   carbonate (FeCO
   <sub>
    3
   </sub>
   );
   <xref articleid="50015">
    magnesium
   </xref>
   (Mg),
   <xref articleid="50515">
    manganese
   </xref>
   (Mn), and, to a limited extent,
   <xref articleid="18627">
    calcium
   </xref>
   (Ca) may sometimes substitute for the iron. Since the amount of the replacement may vary, the composition of siderite is not fixed and ranges between certain limits, although the ratio of the
   <xref articleid="52266">
    metal
   </xref>
   <xref articleid="21830">
    cation
   </xref>
   to the
   <xref articleid="7647">
    anionic
   </xref>
   group remains fixed at 1:1. Its chemical makeup may be expressed by the general formula (Fe, Mn, Mg, Ca)CO
   <sub>
    3
   </sub>
   , which reflects the variability of the
   <xref articleid="52266">
    metal
   </xref>
   content.
  </p>
  <p>
   <assembly id="a2405" url="/assembly/view/2405">
    <title>
     pyrite
    </title>
    <media mediaid="2608" type="image" url="/08/2608-004-A36F0AC5.jpg"/>
    <caption>
     Schematic representation of the structure of pyrite (FeS
     <sub>
      2
     </sub>
     ) as based on a cubic array of ferrous iron cations (Fe
     <sup>
      2+
     </sup>
     ) and sulfur anions (S
     <sup>
      −
     </sup>
     ).
    </caption>
    <credit>
     Encyclopædia Britannica, Inc.
    </credit>
   </assembly>
   <assemblyref assemblyid="a2405"/>
   Minerals display a highly ordered internal atomic structure that has a regular geometric form. Because of this feature, minerals are classified as crystalline solids. Under favourable conditions, crystalline materials may express their ordered internal framework by a well-developed external form, often referred to as
   <xref articleid="110297">
    crystal
   </xref>
   form or morphology. Solids that exhibit no such ordered internal arrangement are termed amorphous. Many amorphous natural solids, such as
   <xref articleid="36988">
    glass
   </xref>
   , are categorized as mineraloids.
  </p>
  <p>
   Traditionally, minerals have been described as resulting exclusively from inorganic processes; however, current mineralogic practice often includes as minerals those compounds that are organically produced but satisfy all other mineral requirements.
   <xref articleid="9174">
    Aragonite
   </xref>
   (CaCO
   <sub>
    3
   </sub>
   ) is an example of an inorganically formed mineral that also has an organically produced, yet otherwise identical, counterpart; the shell (and the
   <xref articleid="58874">
    pearl
   </xref>
   , if it is present) of an
   <xref articleid="57857">
    oyster
   </xref>
   is composed to a large extent of organically formed aragonite. Minerals also are produced by the human body:
   <xref articleid="41758">
    hydroxylapatite
   </xref>
   [Ca
   <sub>
    5
   </sub>
   (PO
   <sub>
    4
   </sub>
   )
   <sub>
    3
   </sub>
   (OH)] is the chief component of
   <xref articleid="110163">
    bones
   </xref>
   and
   <xref articleid="72898">
    teeth
   </xref>
   , and calculi are concretions of mineral substances found in the
   <xref articleid="110631">
    urinary system
   </xref>
   .
  </p>
 </h1>
 <h1 id="h80353">
  <title>
   Nomenclature
  </title>
  <p>
   <assembly id="a223113" url="/assembly/view/223113">
    <title>
     franklinite, willemite, and calcite
    </title>
    <media mediaid="59736" type="image" url="/36/59736-004-D9E7A868.jpg"/>
    <caption>
     Specimen showing bright fluorescent colour resulting from ultraviolet irradiation of calcite (calcium carbonate; red fluorescence) with grains of franklinite (a zinc, manganese, and iron oxide; black coloration), which is nonfluorescent. Veins and grains of willemite (a zinc silicate; green fluorescence) also appear.
    </caption>
    <credit>
     Benjamin M. Shaub
    </credit>
   </assembly>
   <assemblyref assemblyid="a223113"/>
   While minerals are classified in a logical manner according to their major
   <xref articleid="7647">
    anionic
   </xref>
   (negatively charged) chemical constituents into groups such as
   <xref articleid="57833">
    oxides
   </xref>
   ,
   <xref articleid="67760">
    silicates
   </xref>
   , and
   <xref articleid="55936">
    nitrates
   </xref>
   , they are named in a far less scientific or consistent way. Names may be assigned to reflect a physical or chemical property, such as colour, or they may be derived from various subjects deemed appropriate, such as, for example, a locality, public figure, or mineralogist. Some examples of mineral names and their derivations follow:
   <xref articleid="5461">
    albite
   </xref>
   (NaAlSi
   <sub>
    3
   </sub>
   O
   <sub>
    8
   </sub>
   ) is from the
   <xref articleid="47290">
    Latin
   </xref>
   word (
   <e type="italic">
    albus
   </e>
   ) for “white” in reference to its colour; goethite (FeO ∙ OH) is in honour of
   <xref articleid="108453">
    Johann Wolfgang von Goethe
   </xref>
   , the German poet;
   <xref articleid="50518">
    manganite
   </xref>
   (MnO ∙ OH) reflects the mineral’s composition; franklinite (ZnFe
   <sub>
    2
   </sub>
   O
   <sub>
    4
   </sub>
   ) is named after Franklin, New Jersey, U.S., the site of its occurrence as the dominant ore mineral for
   <xref articleid="78379">
    zinc
   </xref>
   (Zn); and
   <xref articleid="67789">
    sillimanite
   </xref>
   (Al
   <sub>
    2
   </sub>
   SiO
   <sub>
    4
   </sub>
   ) is in honour of the American chemist
   <xref articleid="67788">
    Benjamin Silliman
   </xref>
   . Since 1960 the Commission on New Minerals and Mineral Names of the International Mineralogical Association has reviewed descriptions of new minerals and proposals for new mineral names and has attempted to remove inconsistencies. Any new mineral name must be approved by this committee, and the type material is usually stored in a
   <xref articleid="117302">
    museum
   </xref>
   or
   <xref articleid="74363">
    university
   </xref>
   collection.
  </p>
 </h1>
 <h1 id="h80354">
  <title>
   Occurrence and formation
  </title>
  <p>
   <assembly id="a2406" url="/assembly/view/2406">
    <title>
     pyrite crystals
    </title>
    <media mediaid="2612" type="image" url="/12/2612-004-A3610994.jpg"/>
    <caption>
     Pyrite crystal shape depends on the amount of iron and sulfur in the sample. Iron-rich pyrite forms cube-shaped crystals, whereas samples that contain increasing amounts of sulfur form duodecahedral-shaped crystals.
    </caption>
    <credit>
     Encyclopædia Britannica, Inc.
    </credit>
   </assembly>
   <assemblyref assemblyid="a2406"/>
   Minerals form in all geologic environments and thus under a wide range of chemical and physical conditions, such as varying
   <xref articleid="71632">
    temperature
   </xref>
   and
   <xref articleid="61303">
    pressure
   </xref>
   . The four main categories of mineral formation are: (1)
   <xref articleid="109696">
    igneous
   </xref>
   , or magmatic, in which minerals crystallize from a melt, (2)
   <xref articleid="109697">
    sedimentary
   </xref>
   , in which minerals are the result of
   <xref articleid="66556">
    sedimentation
   </xref>
   , a process whose raw materials are particles from other
   <xref articleid="109695">
    rocks
   </xref>
   that have undergone
   <xref articleid="76370">
    weathering
   </xref>
   or
   <xref articleid="32940">
    erosion
   </xref>
   , (3)
   <xref articleid="109698">
    metamorphic
   </xref>
   , in which new minerals form at the expense of earlier ones owing to the effects of changing—usually increasing—temperature or pressure or both on some existing rock type, and (4)
   <xref articleid="41753">
    hydrothermal
   </xref>
   , in which minerals are
   <xref articleid="22783">
    chemically precipitated
   </xref>
   from hot
   <xref articleid="68634">
    solutions
   </xref>
   within
   <xref articleid="110147">
    Earth
   </xref>
   . The first three processes generally lead to varieties of rocks in which different mineral grains are closely intergrown in an interlocking fabric. Hydrothermal solutions, and even solutions at very low temperatures (e.g., groundwater), tend to follow fracture zones in rocks that may provide open spaces for the chemical precipitation of minerals from solution. It is from such open spaces, partially filled by minerals deposited from solutions, that most of the spectacular mineral specimens have been collected. If a mineral that is in the process of growth (as a result of precipitation) is allowed to develop in a free space, it will generally exhibit a well-developed crystal form, which adds to a specimen’s aesthetic beauty. Similarly,
   <xref articleid="36449">
    geodes
   </xref>
   , which are rounded, hollow, or partially hollow bodies commonly found in
   <xref articleid="48303">
    limestones
   </xref>
   , may contain well-formed crystals lining the central cavity. Geodes form as a result of mineral deposition from solutions such as
   <xref articleid="38222">
    groundwater
   </xref>
   .
  </p>
 </h1>
 <h1 id="h80355">
  <title>
   The nature of minerals
  </title>
  <h2 id="h80356">
   <title>
    Morphology
   </title>
   <p>
    Nearly all minerals have the internal ordered arrangement of
    <xref articleid="110411">
     atoms
    </xref>
    and
    <xref articleid="42688">
     ions
    </xref>
    that is the defining characteristic of crystalline solids. Under favourable conditions, minerals may grow as well-formed
    <xref articleid="110297">
     crystals
    </xref>
    , characterized by their smooth plane surfaces and regular geometric forms. Development of this good external shape is largely a fortuitous outcome of growth and does not affect the basic properties of a crystal. Therefore, the term
    <e type="italic">
     crystal
    </e>
    is most often used by material scientists to refer to any solid with an ordered internal arrangement, without regard to the presence or absence of external faces.
   </p>
   <h3 id="h80357">
    <title>
     Symmetry elements
    </title>
    <p>
     The external shape, or morphology, of a crystal is perceived as its aesthetic beauty, and its geometry reflects the internal atomic arrangement. The external shape of well-formed crystals expresses the presence or absence of a number of
     <xref articleid="70723">
      symmetry
     </xref>
     elements. Such symmetry elements include rotation axes, rotoinversion axes, a centre of symmetry, and mirror planes.
    </p>
    <p>
     <assembly id="a2407" url="/assembly/view/2407">
      <title>
       symmetry elements
      </title>
      <media mediaid="2614" type="image" url="/14/2614-004-A37E8135.jpg"/>
      <caption>
       Translation-free symmetry elements as expressed by the morphology of crystals showing a sixfold axis of rotation, fourfold axis of inversion, centre of symmetry, and mirror/symmetry plane.
      </caption>
      <credit>
       Encyclopædia Britannica, Inc.
      </credit>
     </assembly>
     <assemblyref assemblyid="a2407"/>
     A rotation axis is an imaginary line through a crystal around which it may be rotated and repeat itself in appearance one, two, three, four, or six times during a complete rotation. (For example, a sixfold rotation occurs when the crystal repeats itself each 60°—that is, six times in a 360° rotation.)
    </p>
    <p>
     A rotoinversion axis combines rotation about an axis of rotation with inversion. Rotoinversion axes are symbolized as
     <overbar>
      1
     </overbar>
     ,
     <overbar>
      2
     </overbar>
     ,
     <overbar>
      3
     </overbar>
     ,
     <overbar>
      4
     </overbar>
     , and
     <overbar>
      6
     </overbar>
     , where
     <overbar>
      1
     </overbar>
     is equivalent to a centre of symmetry (or inversion),
     <overbar>
      2
     </overbar>
     is equivalent to a mirror plane, and
     <overbar>
      3
     </overbar>
     is equivalent to a threefold rotation axis plus a centre of symmetry. When the axis of the crystal is vertical,
     <overbar>
      4
     </overbar>
     is characterized by two top faces with identical faces upside down underneath.
     <overbar>
      6
     </overbar>
     is equivalent to a threefold rotation axis with a mirror plane perpendicular to the axis.
    </p>
    <p>
     A centre of symmetry exists in a crystal if an imaginary line can be extended from any point on its surface through its centre and a similar point is present along the line equidistant from the centre. This is equivalent to
     <overbar>
      1
     </overbar>
     , or inversion. There is a relatively simple procedure for recognizing a centre of symmetry in a well-formed crystal. With the crystal laid down on any face on a tabletop, the presence of a face of equal size and shape, but inverted, in a horizontal position at the top of the crystal proves the existence of a centre of symmetry. An imaginary
     <xref articleid="52946">
      mirror
     </xref>
     plane (or symmetry plane) can also be used to separate a crystal into halves. In a perfectly developed crystal, the halves are mirror images of one another.
    </p>
    <p>
     Morphologically, crystals can be grouped into 32 crystal classes that represent the 32 possible symmetry elements and their combinations. These crystal classes, in turn, are grouped into six crystal systems. In decreasing order of overall symmetry content, beginning with the system with the highest and most complex crystal symmetry, they are
     <xref articleid="42957">
      isometric
     </xref>
     (or cubic),
     <xref articleid="40331">
      hexagonal
     </xref>
     ,
     <xref articleid="71853">
      tetragonal
     </xref>
     ,
     <xref articleid="57496">
      orthorhombic
     </xref>
     ,
     <xref articleid="53392">
      monoclinic
     </xref>
     , and
     <xref articleid="73360">
      triclinic
     </xref>
     . (Many sources list seven crystal systems by dividing the hexagonal crystal system into two parts—
     <xref articleid="73374">
      trigonal
     </xref>
     and hexagonal.)
    </p>
    <p>
     <assembly id="a2408" url="/assembly/view/2408">
      <title>
       examples of well-shaped crystals
      </title>
      <media mediaid="2616" type="image" url="/16/2616-004-9B03FC8E.jpg"/>
      <caption>
       Each of these examples of well-shaped crystals belongs to a different crystal class because of its overall symmetry content.
      </caption>
      <credit>
       Encyclopædia Britannica, Inc.
      </credit>
     </assembly>
     <assemblyref assemblyid="a2408"/>
     The systems may be described in terms of crystallographic axes used for reference. The
     <e type="italic">
      c
     </e>
     axis is normally the vertical axis. The isometric system exhibits three mutually perpendicular axes of equal length (
     <e type="italic">
      a
     </e>
     <sub>
      1
     </sub>
     ,
     <e type="italic">
      a
     </e>
     <sub>
      2
     </sub>
     , and
     <e type="italic">
      a
     </e>
     <sub>
      3
     </sub>
     ). The orthorhombic and tetragonal systems also contain three mutually perpendicular axes; in the former system all the axes are of different lengths (
     <e type="italic">
      a
     </e>
     ,
     <e type="italic">
      b
     </e>
     , and
     <e type="italic">
      c
     </e>
     ), and in the latter system two axes are of equal length (
     <e type="italic">
      a
     </e>
     <sub>
      1
     </sub>
     and
     <e type="italic">
      a
     </e>
     <sub>
      2
     </sub>
     ) while the third (vertical) axis is either longer or shorter (
     <e type="italic">
      c
     </e>
     ). The hexagonal system contains four axes: three equal-length axes (
     <e type="italic">
      a
     </e>
     <sub>
      1
     </sub>
     ,
     <e type="italic">
      a
     </e>
     <sub>
      2
     </sub>
     , and
     <e type="italic">
      a
     </e>
     <sub>
      3
     </sub>
     ) intersect one another at 120° and lie in a plane that is perpendicular to the fourth (vertical) axis of a different length. Three axes of different lengths (
     <e type="italic">
      a
     </e>
     ,
     <e type="italic">
      b
     </e>
     , and
     <e type="italic">
      c
     </e>
     ) are present in both the monoclinic and triclinic systems. In the monoclinic system, two axes intersect one another at an oblique angle and lie in a plane perpendicular to the third axis; in the triclinic system, all axes intersect at oblique angles.
    </p>
   </h3>
   <h3 id="h80358">
    <title>
     Twinning
    </title>
    <p>
     If two or more crystals form a symmetrical intergrowth, they are referred to as twinned crystals. A new symmetry operation (called a twin element), which is lacking in a single untwinned crystal, relates the individual crystals in a twinned position. There are three twin elements that may relate the crystals of a twin: (1) reflection by a mirror plane (twin plane), (2) rotation about a crystal direction common to both (twin axis) with the angular rotation typically 180°, and (3) inversion about a point (twin centre). An instance of
     <xref articleid="73957">
      twinning
     </xref>
     is defined by a twin law that specifies the presence of a plane, an axis, or a centre of twinning. If a twin has three or more parts, it is referred to as a multiple, or repeated, twin.
    </p>
   </h3>
  </h2>
  <h2 id="h80359">
   <title>
    Internal structure
   </title>
   <h3 id="h80360">
    <title>
     Examining crystal structures
    </title>
    <p>
     <assembly id="a138659" url="/assembly/view/138659">
      <media mediaid="2610" type="image" url="/10/2610-004-45F7DEBD.jpg"/>
      <caption>
       A sample of wulfenite, a mineral displaying good crystal form, from Mexico.
      </caption>
      <credit>
       Courtesy of Joseph and Helen Guetterman collection; photograph John H. Gerard/Encyclopædia Britannica, Inc.
      </credit>
     </assembly>
     <assembly id="a138662" url="/assembly/view/138662">
      <media mediaid="2615" type="image" url="/15/2615-004-C1F9A18E.jpg"/>
      <caption>
       A sample of rose quartz, a mineral displaying good crystal form, from Minas Gerais state, Braz.
      </caption>
      <credit>
       Courtesy of the Field Museum of Natural History, Chicago, photograph, John H. Gerard/Encyclopædia Britannica, Inc.
      </credit>
     </assembly>
     <assembly id="a138663" url="/assembly/view/138663">
      <media mediaid="2617" type="image" url="/17/2617-004-1ABCDD82.jpg"/>
      <caption>
       A sample of amazonite, a greenish blue variety of microcline feldspar, with smoky (dark gray) quartz. Microcline feldspar is an example of a mineral that displays good crystal form.
      </caption>
      <credit>
       Courtesy of the Harvard Collection; photograph, Benjamin M. Shaub
      </credit>
     </assembly>
     <assemblyref assemblyid="a138659"/>
     <assemblyref assemblyid="a138662"/>
     <assemblyref assemblyid="a138663"/>
     The external morphology of a mineral is an expression of the fundamental internal architecture of a crystalline substance—i.e., its crystal structure. The
     <xref articleid="110297">
      crystal
     </xref>
     structure is the three-dimensional, regular (or ordered) arrangement of chemical units (
     <xref articleid="110411">
      atoms
     </xref>
     ,
     <xref articleid="42688">
      ions
     </xref>
     , and
     <xref articleid="7647">
      anionic
     </xref>
     groups in inorganic materials;
     <xref articleid="53247">
      molecules
     </xref>
     in organic substances); these chemical units (referred to here as motifs) are repeated by various translational and symmetry operations (
     <e type="italic">
      see below
     </e>
     ). The morphology of crystals can be studied with the unaided eye in large well-developed crystals and has been historically examined in considerable detail by optical measurements of smaller well-formed crystals through the use of optical goniometers (instruments that measure the angles between crystal faces). The internal structure of crystalline materials, however, is revealed by a combination of
     <xref articleid="77657">
      X-ray
     </xref>
     , neutron, and
     <xref articleid="32321">
      electron diffraction
     </xref>
     techniques, supplemented by a variety of
     <xref articleid="110407">
      spectroscopic
     </xref>
     methods, including infrared, optical,
     <xref articleid="53926">
      Mössbauer
     </xref>
     , and resonance techniques. These methods, used singly or in combination, provide a quantitative three-dimensional reconstruction of the location of the
     <xref articleid="110411">
      atoms
     </xref>
     (or
     <xref articleid="42688">
      ions
     </xref>
     ), the
     <xref articleid="110108">
      chemical bond
     </xref>
     types and their positions, and the overall internal symmetry of the structure. The repeat distances in most inorganic structures and many of the atomic and ionic motif sizes are on the order of 1 to 10
     <xref articleid="7606">
      angstroms
     </xref>
     (Å; 1 Å is equivalent to 10
     <sup>
      −8
     </sup>
     cm or 3.94 × 10
     <sup>
      −9
     </sup>
     inch) or 10 to 100 nanometres (nm; 1 nm is equivalent to 10
     <sup>
      −7
     </sup>
     cm or 10 Å).
    </p>
   </h3>
   <h3 id="h80361">
    <title>
     Space groups
    </title>
    <p>
     Symmetry elements that are observable in the external morphology of crystals, such as rotation and rotoinversion axes, mirror planes, and a centre of symmetry, also are present in their internal atomic structure. In addition to these symmetry elements, there are translations and symmetry operations combined with translations. (Translation is the operation in which a motif is repeated in a linear pattern at intervals that are equal to the translation distance [commonly on the 1 to 10 Å level].) Two examples of translational symmetry elements are screw axes (combining rotation and translation) and glide planes (combining mirroring and translation). The internal translation distances are exceedingly small and can be seen directly only by very high-magnification electron beam techniques, as used in a transmission
     <xref articleid="32323">
      electron microscope
     </xref>
     , at magnifications of about 600,000×.
    </p>
    <p>
     When all possible combinations of translational elements compatible with the 32 crystal classes (also known as point groups) are considered, one arrives at 230 possible ways in which translations, translational symmetry elements (screw axes and glide planes), and translation-free symmetry elements (rotation and rotoinversion axes and mirror planes) can be combined. These translation and symmetry groupings are known as the 230 space groups, representing the various ways in which motifs can be arranged in an ordered three-dimensional array. The symbolic representation of space groups is closely related to that of the Hermann-Mauguin notation of point groups. A detailed discussion of space groups, their derivation, and notation is beyond the scope of this article. For more specific information, consult the books on
     <xref articleid="52833">
      mineralogy
     </xref>
     cited in the
     <xref articleid="109684">
      Bibliography
     </xref>
     .
    </p>
   </h3>
   <h3 id="h80362">
    <title>
     Illustrating crystal structures
    </title>
    <p>
     <assembly id="a2415" url="/assembly/view/2415">
      <title>
       silicon-oxygen tetrahedrons
      </title>
      <media mediaid="2619" type="image" url="/19/2619-004-8A11194A.jpg"/>
      <caption>
       Single sheet displaying the arrangement of the silicon-oxygen tetrahedrons in the structure of a high-temperature form of SiO
       <sub>
        2
       </sub>
       known as tridymite.
      </caption>
      <credit>
       Encyclopædia Britannica, Inc.
      </credit>
     </assembly>
     <assemblyref assemblyid="a2415"/>
     The external morphology of three-dimensional arrangement of crystal structures may be presented on a two-dimensional page or within a
     <xref articleid="1627">
      computer simulation
     </xref>
     . Another common method of illustration involves projecting the crystal structure onto a planar surface. The high-temperature form of
     <xref articleid="67764">
      silicon
     </xref>
     dioxide (SiO
     <sub>
      2
     </sub>
     ) known as tridymite may be represented this way; however, the structural motif units in this case are SiO
     <sub>
      4
     </sub>
     tetrahedrons composed of a silicon atom surrounded by four
     <xref articleid="57841">
      oxygen
     </xref>
     atoms. To further aid the visualization of complex crystal structures within the physical world, three-dimensional physical
     <xref articleid="51377">
      models
     </xref>
     of such structures can be built or obtained commercially. Models of this sort reproduce the internal atomic arrangement on an enormously enlarged scale (e.g., one angstrom might be represented by one centimetre).
    </p>
   </h3>
  </h2>
  <h2 id="h80363">
   <title>
    Polymorphism
   </title>
   <p>
    Polymorphism is the ability of a specific chemical composition to crystallize in more than one form. This generally occurs as a response to changes in
    <xref articleid="71632">
     temperature
    </xref>
    or
    <xref articleid="61303">
     pressure
    </xref>
    or both. The different structures of such a chemical substance are called polymorphic forms, or polymorphs. For example, the
    <xref articleid="110602">
     element
    </xref>
    <xref articleid="20244">
     carbon
    </xref>
    (C) occurs in nature in two different polymorphic forms, depending on the external (pressure and temperature) conditions. These forms are
    <xref articleid="37755">
     graphite
    </xref>
    , with a hexagonal structure, and
    <xref articleid="30264">
     diamond
    </xref>
    , with an isometric structure. The composition FeS
    <sub>
     2
    </sub>
    occurs most commonly as
    <xref articleid="62054">
     pyrite
    </xref>
    , with an isometric structure, but it is also found as
    <xref articleid="50775">
     marcasite
    </xref>
    , which has an orthorhombic internal arrangement. The composition SiO
    <sub>
     2
    </sub>
    is found in a large number of polymorphs, among them
    <xref articleid="62182">
     quartz
    </xref>
    ,
    <xref articleid="73364">
     tridymite
    </xref>
    ,
    <xref articleid="27922">
     cristobalite
    </xref>
    ,
    <xref articleid="24638">
     coesite
    </xref>
    , and
    <xref articleid="69741">
     stishovite
    </xref>
    . The stability field (conditions under which a mineral is stable) of these SiO
    <sub>
     2
    </sub>
    polymorphs can be expressed in a stability diagram, with the external parameters of temperature and pressure as the two axes. In the general quartz field, there is additional polymorphism leading to the notation of high quartz and low quartz, each form having a slightly different internal structure. Cristobalite and tridymite are the high-temperature forms of SiO
    <sub>
     2
    </sub>
    , and indeed these SiO
    <sub>
     2
    </sub>
    polymorphs occur in high-temperature
    <xref articleid="47378">
     lava
    </xref>
    flows. The high-pressure forms of SiO
    <sub>
     2
    </sub>
    are coesite and stishovite, and these can be found in
    <xref articleid="52320">
     meteorite craters
    </xref>
    , formed as a result of high explosive pressures upon quartz-rich
    <xref articleid="65483">
     sandstones
    </xref>
    , and in very deep-seated rock formations, as from Earth’s upper
    <xref articleid="95973">
     mantle
    </xref>
    or very deep in
    <xref articleid="70092">
     subduction zones
    </xref>
    .
   </p>
  </h2>
  <h2 id="h80364">
   <title>
    Chemical composition
   </title>
   <p>
    The chemical composition of a mineral is of fundamental importance because its properties greatly depend on it. Such properties, however, are determined not only by the chemical composition but also by the geometry of the constituent atoms and ions and by the nature of the electrical forces that bind them. Thus, for a complete understanding of minerals, their internal structure, chemistry, and bond types must be considered.
   </p>
   <p>
    Various analytical techniques may be employed to obtain the chemical composition of a mineral. Quantitative chemical analyses mainly use so-called wet analytical methods (e.g., dissolution in acid, flame tests, and other classic techniques of bench chemistry that rely on observation), in which the mineral
    <xref articleid="342976">
     sample
    </xref>
    is first dissolved. Various
    <xref articleid="110804">
     compounds
    </xref>
    are then precipitated from the solution, which are weighed to obtain a
    <xref articleid="37791">
     gravimetric analysis
    </xref>
    . A number of analytical procedures have been introduced that provide faster but somewhat less accurate results. Most analyses use instrumental methods such as optical emission, X-ray
    <xref articleid="472350">
     fluorescence
    </xref>
    , atomic absorption
    <xref articleid="110407">
     spectroscopy
    </xref>
    , and electron microprobe analysis. Relatively well-established error ranges have been documented for these methods, and samples must be prepared in a specific manner for each technique. A distinct advantage of wet analytical procedures is that they make it possible to determine quantitatively the
    <xref articleid="110112">
     oxidation
    </xref>
    states of positively charged atoms, called
    <xref articleid="21830">
     cations
    </xref>
    (e.g., Fe
    <sup>
     2+
    </sup>
    versus Fe
    <sup>
     3+
    </sup>
    ), and to ascertain the amount of
    <xref articleid="76210">
     water
    </xref>
    in hydrous minerals. It is more difficult to provide this type of information with instrumental techniques.
   </p>
   <p>
    To ensure an accurate
    <xref articleid="110403">
     chemical analysis
    </xref>
    , the selected sample, which might include several minerals, is often made into a thin section (a section of rock less than 1 mm thick cemented for study between clear glass plates). To reduce the effect of the impurities, an instrumental technique, such as electron microprobe analysis, is commonly employed. In this method,
    <xref articleid="62158">
     quantitative analysis
    </xref>
    in situ may be performed on mineral grains only 1 micrometre (10
    <sup>
     −4
    </sup>
    centimetre) in diameter.
   </p>
  </h2>
  <h2 id="h80365">
   <title>
    Mineral formulas
   </title>
   <p>
    <assembly id="a223116" url="/assembly/view/223116">
     <title>
      sphalerite
     </title>
     <media mediaid="176095" type="image" url="/95/176095-004-D5BFAAF1.jpg"/>
     <caption>
      Sphalerite, a mineral that is the principal ore of zinc.
     </caption>
     <credit>
      AdstockRF
     </credit>
    </assembly>
    <assemblyref assemblyid="a223116"/>
    <xref articleid="110602">
     Elements
    </xref>
    may exist in the native (uncombined) state, in which case their
    <xref articleid="22779">
     formulas
    </xref>
    are simply their chemical symbols:
    <xref articleid="37211">
     gold
    </xref>
    (Au),
    <xref articleid="20244">
     carbon
    </xref>
    (C) in its polymorphic form of
    <xref articleid="30264">
     diamond
    </xref>
    , and
    <xref articleid="70248">
     sulfur
    </xref>
    (S) are common examples. Most minerals, however, occur as compounds consisting of two or more elements; their formulas are obtained from quantitative chemical analyses and indicate the relative proportions of the constituent elements. The formula of
    <xref articleid="69096">
     sphalerite
    </xref>
    , ZnS, reflects a one-to-one ratio between atoms of
    <xref articleid="78379">
     zinc
    </xref>
    and those of sulfur. In bornite (Cu
    <sub>
     5
    </sub>
    FeS
    <sub>
     4
    </sub>
    ), there are five atoms of
    <xref articleid="26194">
     copper
    </xref>
    (Cu), one atom of
    <xref articleid="42794">
     iron
    </xref>
    (Fe), and four atoms of sulfur. There exist relatively few minerals with constant composition; notable examples include quartz (SiO
    <sub>
     2
    </sub>
    ) and
    <xref articleid="46563">
     kyanite
    </xref>
    (Al
    <sub>
     2
    </sub>
    SiO
    <sub>
     5
    </sub>
    ). Minerals of this sort are termed pure substances. Most minerals display considerable variation in the ions that occupy specific atomic sites within their structure. For example, the iron content of
    <xref articleid="63459">
     rhodochrosite
    </xref>
    (MnCO
    <sub>
     3
    </sub>
    ) may vary over a wide range. As ferrous iron (Fe
    <sup>
     2+
    </sup>
    ) substitutes for
    <xref articleid="50515">
     manganese
    </xref>
    cations (Mn
    <sup>
     2+
    </sup>
    ) in the rhodochrosite structure, the formula for the mineral might be given in more general terms—namely, (Mn, Fe)CO
    <sub>
     3
    </sub>
    . The amounts of manganese and iron are variable, but the ratio of the cation to the negatively charged anionic group remains fixed at one Mn
    <sup>
     2+
    </sup>
    or Fe
    <sup>
     2+
    </sup>
    atom to one CO
    <sub>
     3
    </sub>
    group.
   </p>
  </h2>
  <h2 id="h80366">
   <title>
    Compositional variation
   </title>
   <p>
    As stated above, most minerals exhibit a considerable range in chemical composition. Such variation results from the replacement of one ion or ionic group by another in a particular structure. This phenomenon is termed ionic substitution, or
    <xref articleid="68593">
     solid solution
    </xref>
    . Three types of solid solution are possible, and these may be described in terms of their corresponding mechanisms—namely, substitutional, interstitial, and omission.
   </p>
   <p>
    Substitutional solid solution is the most common variety. For example, as described above, in the
    <xref articleid="20260">
     carbonate mineral
    </xref>
    rhodochrosite (MnCO
    <sub>
     3
    </sub>
    ), Fe
    <sup>
     2+
    </sup>
    may substitute for Mn
    <sup>
     2+
    </sup>
    in its atomic site in the structure.
   </p>
   <p>
    The degree of substitution may be influenced by various factors, with the size of the
    <xref articleid="42688">
     ion
    </xref>
    being the most important. Ions of two different elements can freely replace one another only if their ionic radii differ by approximately 15 percent or less. Limited substitution can occur if the radii differ by 15 to 30 percent, and a difference of more than 30 percent makes substitution unlikely. These limits, calculated from empirical data, are only approximate.
   </p>
   <p>
    The temperature at which crystals grow also plays a significant role in determining the extent of ionic substitution. The higher the temperature, the more extensive is the thermal disorder in the
    <xref articleid="110297">
     crystal
    </xref>
    structure and the less exacting are the spatial requirements. As a result, ionic substitution that could not have occurred in crystals grown at low temperatures may be present in those grown at higher ones. The high-temperature form of KAlSi
    <sub>
     3
    </sub>
    O
    <sub>
     8
    </sub>
    (
    <xref articleid="65519">
     sanidine
    </xref>
    ), for example, can accommodate more
    <xref articleid="68494">
     sodium
    </xref>
    (Na) in place of
    <xref articleid="61048">
     potassium
    </xref>
    (K) than can
    <xref articleid="52498">
     microcline
    </xref>
    , its low-temperature counterpart.
   </p>
   <p>
    An additional factor affecting ionic substitution is the maintenance of a balance between the positive and negative charges in the structure. Replacement of a monovalent ion (e.g., Na
    <sup>
     +
    </sup>
    , a
    <xref articleid="68494">
     sodium
    </xref>
    <xref articleid="21830">
     cation
    </xref>
    ) by a divalent ion (e.g., Ca
    <sup>
     2+
    </sup>
    , a
    <xref articleid="18627">
     calcium
    </xref>
    cation) requires further substitutions to keep the structure electrically neutral.
   </p>
   <p>
    Simple cationic or anionic substitutions are the most basic types of substitutional solid solution. A simple cationic substitution can be represented in a compound of the general form
    <e type="italic">
     A
    </e>
    <sup>
     +
    </sup>
    <e type="italic">
     X
    </e>
    <sup>
     −
    </sup>
    in which cation
    <e type="italic">
     B
    </e>
    <sup>
     +
    </sup>
    replaces in part or in total cation
    <e type="italic">
     A
    </e>
    <sup>
     +
    </sup>
    . Both cations in this example have the same
    <xref articleid="74681">
     valence
    </xref>
    (+1), as in the substitution of K
    <sup>
     +
    </sup>
    (potassium ions) for Na
    <sup>
     +
    </sup>
    (sodium ions) in the NaCl (
    <xref articleid="68495">
     sodium chloride
    </xref>
    ) structure. Similarly, the substitution of
    <xref articleid="7647">
     anion
    </xref>
    <e type="italic">
     X
    </e>
    <sup>
     −
    </sup>
    by
    <e type="italic">
     Y
    </e>
    <sup>
     −
    </sup>
    in an
    <e type="italic">
     A
    </e>
    <sup>
     +
    </sup>
    <e type="italic">
     X
    </e>
    <sup>
     −
    </sup>
    compound represents a simple anionic substitution; this is exemplified by the replacement of Cl
    <sup>
     −
    </sup>
    (
    <xref articleid="82243">
     chlorine
    </xref>
    ions) with Br
    <sup>
     −
    </sup>
    (
    <xref articleid="16596">
     bromine
    </xref>
    ions) in the structure of KCl (potassium chloride). A complete solid-solution series involves the substitution in one or more atomic sites of one element for another that ranges over all possible compositions and is defined in terms of two end-members. For example, the two end-members of
    <xref articleid="109690">
     olivine
    </xref>
    [(Mg, Fe)
    <sub>
     2
    </sub>
    SiO
    <sub>
     4
    </sub>
    ], forsterite (Mg
    <sub>
     2
    </sub>
    SiO
    <sub>
     4
    </sub>
    ) and fayalite (Fe
    <sub>
     2
    </sub>
    SiO
    <sub>
     4
    </sub>
    ), define a complete solid-solution series (called the
    <xref articleid="34926">
     forsterite-fayalite series
    </xref>
    ) in which
    <xref articleid="50015">
     magnesium
    </xref>
    cations (Mg
    <sup>
     2+
    </sup>
    ) are replaced partially or totally by Fe
    <sup>
     2+
    </sup>
    .
   </p>
   <p>
    In some instances, a cation
    <e type="italic">
     B
    </e>
    <sup>
     3+
    </sup>
    may replace some
    <e type="italic">
     A
    </e>
    <sup>
     2+
    </sup>
    of compound
    <e type="italic">
     A
    </e>
    <sup>
     2+
    </sup>
    <e type="italic">
     X
    </e>
    <sup>
     2−
    </sup>
    . So that the compound will remain neutral, an equal amount of
    <e type="italic">
     A
    </e>
    <sup>
     2+
    </sup>
    must concurrently be replaced by a third cation,
    <e type="italic">
     C
    </e>
    <sup>
     +
    </sup>
    . This is given in equation form as 2
    <e type="italic">
     A
    </e>
    <sup>
     2+
    </sup>
    ←→
    <e type="italic">
     B
    </e>
    <sup>
     3+
    </sup>
    +
    <e type="italic">
     C
    </e>
    <sup>
     +
    </sup>
    ; the positive charge on each side is the same. Substitutions such as this are termed coupled substitutions. The
    <xref articleid="60278">
     plagioclase
    </xref>
    <xref articleid="109684">
     feldspar
    </xref>
    series exhibits complete solid solution, in the form of coupled substitutions, between its two end-members,
    <xref articleid="5461">
     albite
    </xref>
    (NaAlSi
    <sub>
     3
    </sub>
    O
    <sub>
     8
    </sub>
    ) and
    <xref articleid="7713">
     anorthite
    </xref>
    (CaAl
    <sub>
     2
    </sub>
    Si
    <sub>
     2
    </sub>
    O
    <sub>
     8
    </sub>
    ). Every atomic substitution of Na
    <sup>
     +
    </sup>
    by Ca
    <sup>
     2+
    </sup>
    is accompanied by the replacement of a
    <xref articleid="67764">
     silicon
    </xref>
    cation (Si
    <sup>
     4+
    </sup>
    ) by an
    <xref articleid="5954">
     aluminum
    </xref>
    cation (Al
    <sup>
     3+
    </sup>
    ), thereby maintaining electrical neutrality: Na
    <sup>
     +
    </sup>
    + Si
    <sup>
     4+
    </sup>
    ←→ Ca
    <sup>
     2+
    </sup>
    + Al
    <sup>
     3+
    </sup>
    .
   </p>
   <p>
    The second major type of ionic substitution is interstitial solid solution, or interstitial substitution. It takes place when atoms, ions, or
    <xref articleid="53247">
     molecules
    </xref>
    fill the interstices (voids) found between the atoms, ions, or ionic groups of a crystal structure. The interstices may take the form of channel-like cavities in certain crystals, such as the ring silicate
    <xref articleid="78916">
     beryl
    </xref>
    (Be
    <sub>
     3
    </sub>
    Al
    <sub>
     2
    </sub>
    Si
    <sub>
     6
    </sub>
    O
    <sub>
     18
    </sub>
    ).
    <xref articleid="61048">
     Potassium
    </xref>
    ,
    <xref articleid="64322">
     rubidium
    </xref>
    (Rb),
    <xref articleid="22171">
     cesium
    </xref>
    (Cs), and
    <xref articleid="76210">
     water
    </xref>
    , as well as
    <xref articleid="1713">
     helium
    </xref>
    (He), are some of the large ions and
    <xref articleid="110302">
     gases
    </xref>
    found in the tubular voids of beryl.
   </p>
   <p>
    The least common type of solid solution is omission solid solution, in which a crystal contains one or more atomic sites that are not completely filled. The best-known example is exhibited by
    <xref articleid="62069">
     pyrrhotite
    </xref>
    (Fe
    <sub>
     1 −
     <e type="italic">
      x
     </e>
    </sub>
    S). In this mineral, each iron atom is surrounded by six neighbouring sulfur atoms. If every iron site in pyrrhotite were occupied by ferrous iron, its formula would be FeS. There are, however, varying percentages of vacancy in the iron site, so that the formula is given as Fe
    <sub>
     6
    </sub>
    S
    <sub>
     7
    </sub>
    through Fe
    <sub>
     11
    </sub>
    S
    <sub>
     12
    </sub>
    , the latter being very near to pure FeS. The formula for pyrrhotite is normally written as Fe
    <sub>
     1 −
     <e type="italic">
      x
     </e>
    </sub>
    S, with
    <e type="italic">
     x
    </e>
    ranging from 0 to 0.2. It is one of the minerals referred to as a defect structure, because it has a structural site that is not completely occupied.
   </p>
  </h2>
  <h2 id="h80367">
   <title>
    Chemical bonding
   </title>
   <p>
    Electrical forces are responsible for the
    <xref articleid="110108">
     chemical bonding
    </xref>
    of atoms, ions, and ionic groups that constitute crystalline solids. The physical and chemical properties of minerals are attributable for the most part to the types and strengths of these binding forces;
    <xref articleid="472487">
     hardness
    </xref>
    ,
    <xref articleid="24289">
     cleavage
    </xref>
    , fusibility, electrical and thermal
    <xref articleid="628185">
     conductivity
    </xref>
    , and the coefficient of
    <xref articleid="72069">
     thermal expansion
    </xref>
    are examples of such properties. On the whole, the hardness and melting point of a crystal increase proportionally with the strength of the bond, while its coefficient of thermal expansion decreases. The extremely strong forces that link the carbon atoms of diamond, for instance, are responsible for its distinct hardness.
    <xref articleid="59245">
     Periclase
    </xref>
    (MgO) and
    <xref articleid="38903">
     halite
    </xref>
    (NaCl) have similar structures; however, periclase has a melting point of 2,800 °C (5,072 °F) whereas halite melts at 801 °C (1,474 °F). This discrepancy reflects the difference in the bond strength of the two minerals: since the atoms of periclase are joined by a stronger electrical force, a greater amount of
    <xref articleid="39732">
     heat
    </xref>
    is needed to separate them.
   </p>
   <p>
    The electrical forces, called chemical bonds, can be divided into five types:
    <xref articleid="42702">
     ionic
    </xref>
    ,
    <xref articleid="26644">
     covalent
    </xref>
    ,
    <xref articleid="52274">
     metallic
    </xref>
    ,
    <xref articleid="74766">
     van der Waals
    </xref>
    , and
    <xref articleid="472561">
     hydrogen bonds
    </xref>
    . Classification in this manner is largely one of expediency; the chemical bonds in a given mineral may in fact possess characteristics of more than one bond type. For example, the forces that link the
    <xref articleid="67764">
     silicon
    </xref>
    and
    <xref articleid="57841">
     oxygen
    </xref>
    atoms in
    <xref articleid="62182">
     quartz
    </xref>
    exhibit in nearly equal amount the characteristics of both ionic and covalent bonds. As stated above, the electrical interaction between the atoms of a crystal determine its physical and chemical properties. Thus, classifying minerals according to their electrical forces will cause those species with similar properties to be grouped together. This fact justifies classification by bond type.
   </p>
   <h3 id="h80368">
    <title>
     Ionic bonds
    </title>
    <p>
     <assembly id="a148656" url="/assembly/view/148656">
      <title>
       crystal bonding
      </title>
      <media mediaid="105672" type="image" url="/72/105672-004-2E90DA7F.jpg"/>
      <caption>
       Different types of bonding in crystals.
      </caption>
      <credit>
       Encyclopædia Britannica, Inc.
      </credit>
     </assembly>
     <assembly id="a92139" url="/assembly/view/92139">
      <title>
       ionic bond: sodium chloride, or table salt
      </title>
      <media mediaid="96905" type="image" url="/05/96905-004-E8903B97.jpg"/>
      <caption>
       Ionic bonding in sodium chloride. An atom of sodium (Na) donates one of its electrons to an atom of chlorine (Cl) in a chemical reaction, and the resulting positive ion (Na
       <sup>
        +
       </sup>
       ) and negative ion (Cl
       <sup>
        −
       </sup>
       ) form a stable ionic compound (sodium chloride; common table salt) based on this ionic bond.
      </caption>
      <credit>
       Encyclopædia Britannica, Inc.
      </credit>
     </assembly>
     <assemblyref assemblyid="a148656"/>
     <assemblyref assemblyid="a92139"/>
     Atoms have a tendency to gain or lose electrons so that their outer
     <xref articleid="57287">
      orbitals
     </xref>
     become stable; this is normally accomplished by these orbitals being filled with the maximum allowed number of
     <xref articleid="74682">
      valence electrons.
     </xref>
     Metallic sodium, for example, has one valence electron in its outer orbital; it becomes ionized by readily losing this electron and exists as the cation Na
     <sup>
      +
     </sup>
     . Conversely, chlorine gains an electron to complete its outer orbital, thereby forming the anion Cl
     <sup>
      −
     </sup>
     . In the mineral halite, NaCl (common, or rock, salt), the chemical bonding that holds the Na
     <sup>
      +
     </sup>
     and Cl
     <sup>
      −
     </sup>
     ions together is the attraction between the two opposite charges. This bonding mechanism is referred to as ionic, or electrovalent (
     <e type="italic">
      see also
     </e>
     <xref articleid="42702">
      ionic bond
     </xref>
     ).
    </p>
    <p>
     Ionically bonded crystals typically display moderate hardness and specific gravity, rather high melting points, and poor thermal and electrical conductivity. The electrostatic charge of an ion is evenly distributed over its surface, and so a cation tends to become surrounded with the maximum number of anions that can be arranged around it. Since ionic bonding is nondirectional, crystals bonded in this manner normally display high symmetry.
    </p>
   </h3>
   <h3 id="h80369">
    <title>
     Covalent bonds
    </title>
    <p>
     <assembly id="a92140" url="/assembly/view/92140">
      <title>
       polar covalent bond
      </title>
      <media mediaid="96904" type="image" url="/04/96904-004-98113EF2.jpg"/>
      <caption>
       In polar covalent bonds, such as that between hydrogen and oxygen atoms, the electrons are not transferred from one atom to the other as they are in an ionic bond. Instead, some outer electrons merely spend more time in the vicinity of the other atom. The effect of this orbital distortion is to induce regional net charges that hold the atoms together, such as in water molecules.
      </caption>
      <credit>
       Encyclopædia Britannica, Inc.
      </credit>
     </assembly>
     <assemblyref assemblyid="a92140"/>
     In the discussion of the ionic bond, it was noted that chlorine readily gains an electron to achieve a stable electron configuration. An incomplete outer orbital places a chlorine atom in a highly reactive state, so it attempts to combine with nearly any atom in its proximity. Because its closest neighbour is usually another chlorine atom, the two may bond together by sharing one pair of electrons. As a result of this extremely strong bond, each chlorine atom enters a stable state.
    </p>
    <p>
     The electron-sharing, or
     <xref articleid="26644">
      covalent
     </xref>
     , bond is the strongest of all chemical bond types. Minerals bonded in this manner display general insolubility, great stability, and a high melting point. Crystals of covalently bonded minerals tend to exhibit lower symmetry than their ionic counterparts because the covalent bond is highly directional, localized in the vicinity of the shared electrons.
    </p>
    <p>
     The Cl
     <sub>
      2
     </sub>
     <xref articleid="53247">
      molecules
     </xref>
     formed by linking two neighbouring chlorine atoms are stable and do not combine with other molecules. Atoms of some elements, however, have more than one electron in the outer orbital and thus may bond to several neighbouring atoms to form groups, which in turn may join together in larger combinations.
     <xref articleid="20244">
      Carbon
     </xref>
     , in the polymorphic form of
     <xref articleid="30264">
      diamond
     </xref>
     , is a good example of this type of covalent bonding. There are four valence electrons in a carbon atom, so that each atom bonds with four others in a stable tetrahedral configuration. A continuous network is formed by the linkage of every carbon atom in this manner. The rigid diamond structure results from the strong localization of the bond energy in the vicinity of the shared electrons; this makes diamond the hardest of all natural substances. Diamond does not conduct
     <xref articleid="106019">
      electricity
     </xref>
     , because all the valence electrons of its constituent atoms are shared to form bonds and therefore are not mobile.
    </p>
   </h3>
   <h3 id="h80370">
    <title>
     Metallic bonds
    </title>
    <p>
     Bonding in metals is distinct from that in their
     <xref articleid="65127">
      salts
     </xref>
     , as reflected in the significant differences between the properties of the two groups. In contrast to salts, metals display high plasticity, tenacity, ductility, and conductivity. Many are characterized by lower hardness and have higher melting and boiling points than, for example, covalently bonded materials. All these properties result from a
     <xref articleid="52274">
      metallic bonding
     </xref>
     mechanism that can be envisioned as a collection of positively charged ions immersed in a cloud of valence electrons. The attraction between the cations and the electrons holds a crystal together. The electrons are not bound to any particular cation and are thus free to move throughout the structure. In fact, in the metals
     <xref articleid="68494">
      sodium
     </xref>
     ,
     <xref articleid="22171">
      cesium
     </xref>
     , rubidium, and potassium, the radiant energy of light can cause electrons to be removed from their surfaces entirely. (This result is known as the photoelectric effect.) Electron mobility is responsible for the ability of metals to conduct
     <xref articleid="39732">
      heat
     </xref>
     and
     <xref articleid="106019">
      electricity
     </xref>
     . The native metals are the only minerals to exhibit pure metallic bonding.
    </p>
   </h3>
   <h3 id="h80371">
    <title>
     Van der Waals bonds
    </title>
    <p>
     Neutral molecules may be held together by a weak electric force known as the
     <xref articleid="74766">
      van der Waals bond
     </xref>
     . It results from the distortion of a
     <xref articleid="53247">
      molecule
     </xref>
     so that a small positive charge develops on one end and a corresponding negative charge develops on the other. A similar effect is induced in neighbouring molecules, and this dipole effect propagates throughout the entire structure. An attractive force is then formed between oppositely charged ends of the dipoles. Van der Waals bonding is common in
     <xref articleid="110302">
      gases
     </xref>
     and organic
     <xref articleid="110301">
      liquids
     </xref>
     and
     <xref articleid="68592">
      solids
     </xref>
     , but it is rare in minerals. Its presence in a mineral defines a weak area with good cleavage and low hardness. In
     <xref articleid="37755">
      graphite
     </xref>
     , carbon atoms lie in covalently bonded sheets with van der Waals forces acting between the layers.
    </p>
   </h3>
   <h3 id="h80372">
    <title>
     Hydrogen bonds
    </title>
    <p>
     In addition to the four major bond types described above, there is an interaction called
     <xref articleid="472561">
      hydrogen bonding
     </xref>
     . This takes place when a hydrogen atom, bonded to an electronegative atom such as
     <xref articleid="57841">
      oxygen
     </xref>
     ,
     <xref articleid="34677">
      fluorine
     </xref>
     , or
     <xref articleid="55947">
      nitrogen
     </xref>
     , is also attracted to the negative end of a neighbouring molecule. A strong dipole-dipole interaction is produced, forming a bond between the two molecules. Hydrogen bonding is common in hydroxides and in many of the layer
     <xref articleid="67760">
      silicates
     </xref>
     —e.g.,
     <xref articleid="109689">
      micas
     </xref>
     and
     <xref articleid="109692">
      clay minerals
     </xref>
     .
    </p>
   </h3>
  </h2>
  <h2 id="h80373">
   <title>
    Physical properties
   </title>
   <p>
    The physical properties of minerals are the direct result of the structural and chemical characteristics of the minerals. Some properties can be determined by inspection of a hand specimen or by relatively simple tests on such a specimen. Others, such as those determined by optical and
    <xref articleid="77657">
     X-ray diffraction
    </xref>
    techniques, require special and often sophisticated equipment and may involve elaborate sample preparation. In the discussion that follows, emphasis is placed on those properties that can be most easily evaluated with only simple tests.
   </p>
   <h3 id="h80374">
    <title>
     Crystal habit and crystal aggregation
    </title>
    <p>
     <assembly id="a2489" url="/assembly/view/2489">
      <title>
       common crystals
      </title>
      <media mediaid="2624" type="image" url="/24/2624-004-64DE7457.jpg"/>
      <caption>
       Common crystal aggregations and habits.
      </caption>
      <credit>
       Encyclopædia Britannica, Inc.
      </credit>
     </assembly>
     <assemblyref assemblyid="a2489"/>
     The external shape (habit) of well-developed
     <xref articleid="110297">
      crystals
     </xref>
     can be visually studied and classified according to the various crystal systems that span the 32 crystal classes. The majority of crystal occurrences, however, are not part of well-formed single crystals but are found as crystals grown together in aggregates. Examples of some descriptive terms for such aggregations are given here: granular, an intergrowth of mineral grains of approximately the same size; lamellar, flat, platelike individuals arranged in layers; bladed, elongated crystals flattened like a knife blade; fibrous, an aggregate of slender fibres, parallel or radiating; acicular, slender, needlelike crystals; radiating, individuals forming starlike or circular groups; globular, radiating individuals forming small spherical or hemispherical groups; dendritic, in slender divergent branches, somewhat plantlike; mammillary, large smoothly rounded, masses resembling mammae, formed by radiating crystals; botryoidal, globular forms resembling a bunch of grapes; colloform, spherical forms composed of radiating individuals without regard to size (this includes botryoidal, reniform, and mammillary forms); stalactitic, pendant cylinders or cones resembling icicles; concentric, roughly spherical layers arranged about a common centre, as in agate and in geodes; geode, a partially filled rock cavity lined by mineral material (geodes may be banded as in agate owing to successive depositions of material, and the inner surface is often covered with projecting crystals); and oolitic, an assemblage consisting of small
     <xref articleid="473370">
      spheres
     </xref>
     .
    </p>
   </h3>
   <h3 id="h80375">
    <title>
     Cleavage and fracture
    </title>
    <p>
     <assembly id="a38141" url="/assembly/view/38141">
      <title>
       augite
      </title>
      <media mediaid="59721" type="image" url="/21/59721-004-A4502572.jpg"/>
      <caption>
       Photomicrograph of various pyroxene minerals in thin sections (illuminated with polarized light). An augite phenocryst (large individual gray crystal) appears in basalt lava, showing characteristic basal octagonal form and square-segmentation cleavage.
      </caption>
      <credit>
       Courtesy of G. Malcolm Brown
      </credit>
     </assembly>
     <assemblyref assemblyid="a38141"/>
     Both these properties represent the reaction of a mineral to an external force.
     <xref articleid="24289">
      Cleavage
     </xref>
     is breakage along planar surfaces, which are parallel to possible external faces on the crystal. It results from the tendency of some minerals to split in certain directions that are structurally weaker than others. Some crystals exhibit well-developed cleavage, as seen by the planar cleavage in mica; perfect cleavage of this sort is characterized by smooth, shiny surfaces. In other minerals, such as
     <xref articleid="62182">
      quartz
     </xref>
     , cleavage is absent. Quality and direction are the general characteristics used to describe cleavage. Quality is expressed as perfect, good, fair, and so forth; cleavage directions of a crystal are consistent with its overall symmetry.
    </p>
    <p>
     Some crystals do not usually break in any particular direction, reflecting roughly equal bond strengths throughout the crystal structure. Breakage in such minerals is known as
     <xref articleid="35085">
      fracture
     </xref>
     . The term
     <e type="italic">
      conchoidal
     </e>
     is used to describe fracture with smooth, curved surfaces that resemble the interior of a
     <xref articleid="66490">
      seashell
     </xref>
     ; it is commonly observed in quartz and
     <xref articleid="36988">
      glass
     </xref>
     . Splintery fracture is breakage into elongated fragments like splinters of
     <xref articleid="110435">
      wood
     </xref>
     , while hackly fracture is breakage along jagged surfaces.
    </p>
   </h3>
   <h3 id="h80376">
    <title>
     Lustre
    </title>
    <p>
     <assembly id="a164776" url="/assembly/view/164776">
      <title>
       galena
      </title>
      <media mediaid="154500" type="image" url="/00/154500-004-780E9EAF.jpg"/>
      <caption>
       Galena is the most common mineral that contains lead.
      </caption>
      <credit>
       © Jiri Vaclavek/Dreamstime.com
      </credit>
     </assembly>
     <assemblyref assemblyid="a164776"/>
     The term
     <xref articleid="49422">
      <e type="italic">
       lustre
      </e>
     </xref>
     refers to the general appearance of a mineral surface in reflected
     <xref articleid="110443">
      light
     </xref>
     . The main types of lustre, metallic and nonmetallic, are distinguished easily by the human eye after some practice, but the difference between them cannot be quantified and is rather difficult to describe. Metallic refers to the lustre of an untarnished metallic surface such as gold,
     <xref articleid="67807">
      silver
     </xref>
     , copper, or
     <xref articleid="110660">
      steel
     </xref>
     . These materials are opaque to light; none passes through even at thin edges.
     <xref articleid="62054">
      Pyrite
     </xref>
     (FeS
     <sub>
      2
     </sub>
     ),
     <xref articleid="22271">
      chalcopyrite
     </xref>
     (CuFeS
     <sub>
      2
     </sub>
     ), and
     <xref articleid="35857">
      galena
     </xref>
     (PbS) are common minerals that have metallic lustre. Nonmetallic lustre is generally exhibited by light-coloured minerals that transmit light, either through thick portions or at least through their edges. The following terms are used to distinguish the lustre of nonmetallic minerals: vitreous, having the lustre of a piece of broken glass (this is commonly seen in quartz and many other nonmetallic minerals); resinous, having the lustre of a piece of resin (this is common in
     <xref articleid="69096">
      sphalerite
     </xref>
     [ZnS]); pearly, having the lustre of mother-of-pearl (i.e., an iridescent pearl-like lustre characteristic of mineral surfaces that are parallel to well-developed cleavage planes; the cleavage surface of
     <xref articleid="71035">
      talc
     </xref>
     [Mg
     <sub>
      3
     </sub>
     Si
     <sub>
      4
     </sub>
     O
     <sub>
      10
     </sub>
     (OH)
     <sub>
      2
     </sub>
     ] may show pearly lustre); greasy, having the appearance of being covered with a thin layer of
     <xref articleid="56871">
      oil
     </xref>
     (such lustre results from the scattering of light by a microscopically rough surface; some
     <xref articleid="55291">
      nepheline
     </xref>
     [(Na, K)AlSiO
     <sub>
      4
     </sub>
     ] and milky quartz may exhibit this); silky, descriptive of the lustre of a skein of
     <xref articleid="67774">
      silk
     </xref>
     or a piece of
     <xref articleid="65848">
      satin
     </xref>
     and characteristic of some minerals in fibrous aggregates (examples are fibrous
     <xref articleid="38660">
      gypsum
     </xref>
     [CaSO
     <sub>
      4
     </sub>
     ∙ 2H
     <sub>
      2
     </sub>
     O], known as satin spar, and
     <xref articleid="82482">
      chrysotile asbestos
     </xref>
     [Mg
     <sub>
      3
     </sub>
     Si
     <sub>
      2
     </sub>
     O
     <sub>
      5
     </sub>
     (OH)
     <sub>
      4
     </sub>
     ]); and adamantine, having the brilliant lustre of diamond, exhibited by minerals with a high
     <xref articleid="63034">
      refractive index
     </xref>
     comparable to diamond and which as such
     <xref articleid="63033">
      refract
     </xref>
     light as strongly as the latter (examples are
     <xref articleid="22157">
      cerussite
     </xref>
     [PbCO
     <sub>
      3
     </sub>
     ] and
     <xref articleid="7573">
      anglesite
     </xref>
     [PbSO
     <sub>
      4
     </sub>
     ]).
    </p>
   </h3>
   <h3 id="h80377">
    <title>
     Colour
    </title>
    <p>
     <assembly id="a145740" url="/assembly/view/145740">
      <title>
       aquamarine
      </title>
      <media mediaid="140861" type="image" url="/61/140861-004-41BD9BB4.jpg"/>
      <caption>
       Single crystal of aquamarine in matrix.
      </caption>
      <credit>
       © Stephan Pietzko/Dreamstime.com
      </credit>
     </assembly>
     <assemblyref assemblyid="a145740"/>
     Minerals occur in a great variety of colours. Because colour varies not only from one mineral to another but also within the same mineral (or mineral group), the observer must learn in which minerals it is a constant property and can thus be relied on as a distinguishing criterion. Most minerals that have a metallic lustre vary little in colour, but nonmetallic minerals can demonstrate wide variance. Although the colour of a freshly broken surface of a metallic mineral is often highly diagnostic, this same mineral may become tarnished with time. Such a tarnish may dull minerals such as galena (PbS), which has a bright bluish lead-gray colour on a fresh surface but may become dull upon long exposure to air.
     <xref articleid="80767">
      Bornite
     </xref>
     (Cu
     <sub>
      5
     </sub>
     FeS
     <sub>
      4
     </sub>
     ), which on a freshly broken surface has a brownish bronze colour, may be so highly tarnished on an older surface that it shows variegated purples and blues; hence, it is called
     <xref articleid="58859">
      peacock
     </xref>
     ore. In other words, in the identification of minerals with a metallic lustre, it is important for the observer to have a freshly broken surface for accurate determination of colour.
    </p>
    <p>
     A few minerals with nonmetallic lustre display a constant colour that can be used as a truly diagnostic property. Examples are malachite, which is green;
     <xref articleid="11566">
      azurite
     </xref>
     , which is blue;
     <xref articleid="63462">
      rhodonite
     </xref>
     , which is pink;
     <xref articleid="73885">
      turquoise
     </xref>
     , which gives its name to the colour turquoise, a greenish blue to blue-green; and sulfur, which is yellow. Many nonmetallic minerals have a relatively narrow range of colours, although some have an unusually wide range. Members of the
     <xref articleid="60278">
      plagioclase
     </xref>
     <xref articleid="109684">
      feldspar
     </xref>
     series range from almost pure white in albite through light gray to darker gray toward the
     <xref articleid="7713">
      anorthite
     </xref>
     end-member. Most common
     <xref articleid="109691">
      garnets
     </xref>
     show various shades of red to red-brown to brown. Members of the monoclinic
     <xref articleid="109687">
      pyroxene
     </xref>
     group range from almost white in pure
     <xref articleid="30558">
      diopside
     </xref>
     to light green in diopside containing a small amount of
     <xref articleid="42794">
      iron
     </xref>
     as a substitute for
     <xref articleid="50015">
      magnesium
     </xref>
     in the structure through dark green in
     <xref articleid="39789">
      hedenbergite
     </xref>
     to almost black in many
     <xref articleid="11240">
      augites
     </xref>
     . Members of the
     <xref articleid="57495">
      orthopyroxene
     </xref>
     series (
     <xref articleid="32702">
      enstatite
     </xref>
     to orthoferrosilite) range from light beige to darker brown. On the other hand,
     <xref articleid="73060">
      tourmaline
     </xref>
     may show many colours (red, blue, green, brown, and black) as well as distinct colour zonation, from colourless through pink to green, within a single crystal. Similarly, numerous gem minerals such as
     <xref articleid="26446">
      corundum
     </xref>
     , beryl, and quartz occur in many colours; the
     <xref articleid="36349">
      gemstones
     </xref>
     cut from them are given varietal names. In short, in nonmetallic minerals of various kinds, colour is a helpful, though not a truly diagnostic (and therefore unique), property.
    </p>
   </h3>
   <h3 id="h80378">
    <title>
     Hardness
    </title>
    <p>
     Hardness (H) is the resistance of a mineral to scratching. It is a property by which minerals may be described relative to a standard scale of 10 minerals known as the
     <xref articleid="53205">
      Mohs scale of hardness
     </xref>
     . The degree of hardness is determined by observing the comparative ease or difficulty with which one mineral is scratched by another or by a steel tool. For measuring the hardness of a mineral, several common objects that can be used for scratching are helpful, such as a fingernail, a copper coin, a steel pocketknife, glass plate or window glass, the steel of a needle, and a streak plate (an unglazed black or white porcelain surface).
    </p>
    <p>
     Because there is a general link between hardness and chemical composition, these generalizations can be made:
    </p>
    <p>
     1. Most hydrous minerals are relatively soft (H &lt; 5).
    </p>
    <p>
     2.
     <xref articleid="38891">
      Halides
     </xref>
     ,
     <xref articleid="20260">
      carbonates
     </xref>
     ,
     <xref articleid="70236">
      sulfates
     </xref>
     , and
     <xref articleid="59775">
      phosphates
     </xref>
     also are relatively soft (H &lt; 5.5).
    </p>
    <p>
     3. Most
     <xref articleid="70240">
      sulfides
     </xref>
     are relatively soft (H &lt; 5), with
     <xref articleid="50775">
      marcasite
     </xref>
     and
     <xref articleid="62054">
      pyrite
     </xref>
     being examples of exceptions (H &lt; 6 to 6.5).
    </p>
    <p>
     4. Most anhydrous
     <xref articleid="57834">
      oxides
     </xref>
     and
     <xref articleid="67760">
      silicates
     </xref>
     are hard (H &gt; 5.5).
    </p>
    <p>
     Because hardness is a highly diagnostic property in mineral identification, most determinative tables use relative hardness as a sorting parameter.
    </p>
   </h3>
   <h3 id="h80379">
    <title>
     Tenacity
    </title>
    <p>
     <assembly id="a121956" url="/assembly/view/121956">
      <title>
       gold leaf
      </title>
      <media mediaid="127178" type="image" url="/78/127178-004-8ADC7930.jpg"/>
      <caption>
       Burnishing gold leaf.
      </caption>
      <credit>
       Juangonzalez64
      </credit>
     </assembly>
     <assemblyref assemblyid="a121956"/>
     Several mineral properties that depend on the cohesive force between
     <xref articleid="110411">
      atoms
     </xref>
     (and
     <xref articleid="42688">
      ions
     </xref>
     ) in mineral structures are grouped under tenacity. A mineral’s tenacity can be described by the following terms: malleable, capable of being flattened under the blows of a hammer into thin sheets without breaking or crumbling into fragments (most of the native elements show various degrees of malleability, but particularly gold, silver, and copper); sectile, capable of being severed by the smooth cut of a knife (copper, silver, and gold are sectile); ductile, capable of being drawn into the form of a
     <xref articleid="77246">
      wire
     </xref>
     (
     <xref articleid="37211">
      gold
     </xref>
     ,
     <xref articleid="67807">
      silver
     </xref>
     , and
     <xref articleid="26194">
      copper
     </xref>
     exhibit this property); flexible, bending easily and staying bent after the pressure is removed (
     <xref articleid="71035">
      talc
     </xref>
     is flexible); brittle, showing little or no resistance to breakage, and as such separating into fragments under the blow of a hammer or when cut by a knife (most silicate minerals are brittle); and elastic, capable of being bent or pulled out of shape but returning to the original form when relieved (
     <xref articleid="109689">
      mica
     </xref>
     is elastic).
    </p>
   </h3>
   <h3 id="h80380">
    <title>
     Specific gravity
    </title>
    <p>
     <xref articleid="69028">
      Specific gravity
     </xref>
     (G) is defined as the ratio between the weight of a substance and the weight of an equal volume of water at 4 °C (39 °F). Thus a mineral with a specific gravity of 2 weighs twice as much as the same volume of
     <xref articleid="76210">
      water
     </xref>
     . Since it is a ratio, specific gravity has no units.
    </p>
    <p>
     The specific gravity of a mineral depends on the
     <xref articleid="10135">
      atomic weights
     </xref>
     of all its constituent elements and the manner in which the atoms (and ions) are packed together. In mineral series whose species have essentially identical structures, those composed of elements with higher atomic weight have higher specific gravities. If two minerals (as in the two polymorphs of carbon, namely
     <xref articleid="37755">
      graphite
     </xref>
     and diamond) have the same chemical composition, the difference in specific gravity reflects variation in internal packing of the atoms or ions (diamond, with a G of 3.51, has a more densely packed structure than graphite, with a G of 2.23).
    </p>
    <p>
     Measurement of the specific gravity of a mineral specimen requires the use of a special apparatus. An estimate of the value, however, can be obtained by simply testing how heavy a specimen feels. Most people, from everyday experience, have developed a sense of relative weights for even such objects as nonmetallic and metallic minerals. For example,
     <xref articleid="80702">
      borax
     </xref>
     (G = 1.7) seems light for a nonmetallic mineral, whereas
     <xref articleid="7573">
      anglesite
     </xref>
     (G = 6.4) feels heavy. Average specific gravity reflects what a nonmetallic or metallic mineral of a given size should weigh. The average specific gravity for nonmetallic minerals falls between 2.65 and 2.75, which is seen in the range of values for quartz (G = 2.65), feldspar (G = 2.60 to 2.75), and
     <xref articleid="109693">
      calcite
     </xref>
     (G = 2.72). For metallic minerals, graphite (G = 2.23) feels light, while silver (G = 10.5) seems heavy. The average specific gravity for metallic minerals is approximately 5.0, the value for pyrite. With practice using specimens of known specific gravity, a person can develop the ability to distinguish between minerals that have comparatively small differences in specific gravity by merely lifting them.
    </p>
    <p>
     Although an approximate assessment of specific gravity can be obtained by the hefting of a hand specimen of a specific monomineral, an accurate measurement can only be achieved by using a specific gravity balance. An example of such an instrument is the
     <xref articleid="43909">
      Jolly balance
     </xref>
     , which provides numerical values for a small mineral specimen (or fragment) in air as well as in water. Such accurate measurements are highly diagnostic and can greatly aid in the identification of an unknown mineral sample.
    </p>
   </h3>
   <h3 id="h80381">
    <title>
     Magnetism
    </title>
    <p>
     Only two minerals exhibit readily observed
     <xref articleid="106020">
      magnetism
     </xref>
     :
     <xref articleid="50036">
      magnetite
     </xref>
     (Fe
     <sub>
      3
     </sub>
     O
     <sub>
      4
     </sub>
     ), which is strongly attracted to a hand magnet, and
     <xref articleid="62069">
      pyrrhotite
     </xref>
     (Fe
     <sub>
      1 −
      <e type="italic">
       x
      </e>
     </sub>
     S), which typically shows a weaker magnetic reaction.
     <xref articleid="34114">
      Ferromagnetic
     </xref>
     is a term that refers to materials that exhibit strong magnetic attraction when subjected to a
     <xref articleid="50022">
      magnetic field
     </xref>
     . Materials that show only a weak magnetic response in a strong applied magnetic field are known as
     <xref articleid="58400">
      paramagnetic
     </xref>
     . Those materials that are repelled by an applied
     <xref articleid="50023">
      magnetic force
     </xref>
     are known as
     <xref articleid="30261">
      diamagnetic
     </xref>
     . Because minerals display a wide range of slightly different magnetic properties, they can be separated from each other by an
     <xref articleid="32309">
      electromagnet
     </xref>
     . Such magnetic separation is a common procedure both in the laboratory and on a commercial scale.
    </p>
   </h3>
   <h3 id="h80382">
    <title>
     Fluorescence
    </title>
    <p>
     <assembly id="a38254" url="/assembly/view/38254">
      <title>
       franklinite and willemite
      </title>
      <media mediaid="59735" type="image" url="/35/59735-004-0FCB3F48.jpg"/>
      <caption>
       In ordinary light, the willemite grains and veins of this specimen are brownish gold and the franklinite grains are dark brown.
      </caption>
      <credit>
       Benjamin M. Shaub
      </credit>
     </assembly>
     <assemblyref assemblyid="a38254"/>
     Some minerals, when exposed to
     <xref articleid="74181">
      ultraviolet light
     </xref>
     , will emit visible light during irradiation; this is known as
     <xref articleid="472350">
      fluorescence
     </xref>
     . Some minerals fluoresce only in shortwave ultraviolet light, others only in longwave
     <xref articleid="74181">
      ultraviolet light
     </xref>
     , and still others in either situation. Both the colour and intensity of the emitted light vary significantly with the
     <xref articleid="76325">
      wavelengths
     </xref>
     of ultraviolet light. Due to the unpredictable nature of fluorescence, some specimens of a mineral manifest it, while other seemingly similar specimens, even those from the same geographic area, do not. Some minerals that may exhibit fluorescence are
     <xref articleid="34679">
      fluorite
     </xref>
     ,
     <xref articleid="66096">
      scheelite
     </xref>
     ,
     <xref articleid="109693">
      calcite
     </xref>
     ,
     <xref articleid="66034">
      scapolite
     </xref>
     ,
     <xref articleid="77022">
      willemite
     </xref>
     , and
     <xref articleid="11385">
      autunite
     </xref>
     . Specimens of willemite and calcite from the Franklin district of New Jersey in the United States may show brilliant fluorescent colours.
    </p>
   </h3>
   <h3 id="h80383">
    <title>
     Solubility in hydrochloric acid
    </title>
    <p>
     The positive identification of carbonate minerals is aided greatly by the fact that the carbon-oxygen bond of the CO
     <sub>
      3
     </sub>
     group in carbonates becomes unstable and breaks down in the presence of
     <xref articleid="41731">
      hydrogen ions
     </xref>
     (H
     <sup>
      +
     </sup>
     ) available in
     <xref articleid="3543">
      acids
     </xref>
     . This is expressed by the reaction 2H
     <sup>
      +
     </sup>
     + CO
     <fraction>
      <num>
       2−
      </num>
      <den>
       3
      </den>
     </fraction>
     → H
     <sub>
      2
     </sub>
     O + CO
     <sub>
      2
     </sub>
     , which is the basis for the so-called fizz test with dilute
     <xref articleid="41724">
      hydrochloric acid
     </xref>
     (HCl).
     <xref articleid="109693">
      Calcite
     </xref>
     ,
     <xref articleid="9174">
      aragonite
     </xref>
     ,
     <xref articleid="77285">
      witherite
     </xref>
     , and
     <xref articleid="69993">
      strontianite
     </xref>
     , as well as copper carbonates, show bubbling, or effervescence, when a drop of dilute hydrochloric acid is placed on the mineral. This “fizz” is due to the release of
     <xref articleid="20249">
      carbon dioxide
     </xref>
     (CO
     <sub>
      2
     </sub>
     ). Other carbonates such as
     <xref articleid="109694">
      dolomite
     </xref>
     ,
     <xref articleid="63459">
      rhodochrosite
     </xref>
     ,
     <xref articleid="50014">
      magnesite
     </xref>
     , and
     <xref articleid="67639">
      siderite
     </xref>
     will show slow effervescence when acid is applied to powdered minerals or moderate effervescence only in hot hydrochloric acid.
    </p>
   </h3>
   <h3 id="h80384">
    <title>
     Radioactivity
    </title>
    <p>
     Minerals containing
     <xref articleid="74425">
      uranium
     </xref>
     (U) and
     <xref articleid="72236">
      thorium
     </xref>
     (Th) continually undergo decay reactions in which radioactive
     <xref articleid="110412">
      isotopes
     </xref>
     of uranium and thorium form various daughter elements and also release energy in the form of
     <xref articleid="5891">
      alpha
     </xref>
     and
     <xref articleid="78955">
      beta particles
     </xref>
     and
     <xref articleid="35974">
      gamma radiation
     </xref>
     . The
     <xref articleid="109464">
      radiation
     </xref>
     produced can be measured in the laboratory or in the field using a
     <xref articleid="36306">
      Geiger counter
     </xref>
     or a scintillation counter. A radiation counter therefore is helpful in identifying uranium- and thorium-containing minerals, such as
     <xref articleid="74424">
      uraninite
     </xref>
     ,
     <xref articleid="60207">
      pitchblende
     </xref>
     ,
     <xref articleid="72233">
      thorianite
     </xref>
     , and
     <xref articleid="11385">
      autunite
     </xref>
     . Several rock-forming minerals contain enough radioactive elements to permit the determination of the time elapsed since the radioactive material was incorporated into the mineral (
     <e type="italic">
      see also
     </e>
     <xref articleid="117438" refid="h69756">
      dating: Principles of isotopic dating
     </xref>
     ).
    </p>
   </h3>
  </h2>
 </h1>
 <h1 id="h80385">
  <title>
   Classification of minerals
  </title>
  <p>
   Since the middle of the 19th century, minerals have been classified on the basis of their chemical composition. Under this scheme, they are divided into classes according to their dominant
   <xref articleid="7647">
    anion
   </xref>
   or anionic group (e.g.,
   <xref articleid="38891">
    halides
   </xref>
   ,
   <xref articleid="57833">
    oxides
   </xref>
   , and
   <xref articleid="70239">
    sulfides
   </xref>
   ). Several reasons justify use of this criterion as the distinguishing factor at the highest level of mineral classification. First, the similarities in properties of minerals with identical anionic groups are generally more pronounced than those with the same dominant
   <xref articleid="21830">
    cation
   </xref>
   . For example,
   <xref articleid="20258">
    carbonates
   </xref>
   have stronger resemblance to one another than do copper minerals. Secondly, minerals that have identical dominant anions are likely to be found in the same or similar geologic environments. Therefore, sulfides tend to occur together in vein or replacement deposits, while silicate-bearing rocks make up much of
   <xref articleid="110147">
    Earth’s
   </xref>
   <xref articleid="95973">
    crust
   </xref>
   . Third, current chemical practice employs a nomenclature and classification scheme for
   <xref articleid="42474">
    inorganic compounds
   </xref>
   based on similar principles.
  </p>
  <p>
   Investigators have found, however, that chemical composition alone is insufficient for classifying minerals. Determination of internal structures, accomplished through the use of
   <xref articleid="77656">
    X rays
   </xref>
   , allows a more complete appreciation of the nature of minerals. Chemical composition and internal structure together constitute the essence of a mineral and determine its physical properties; thus, classification should rely on both. Crystallochemical principles—i.e., those relating to both chemical composition and
   <xref articleid="110297">
    crystal
   </xref>
   structure—were first applied by the British physicist
   <xref articleid="16144">
    W. Lawrence Bragg
   </xref>
   and the Norwegian mineralogist
   <xref articleid="37278">
    Victor Moritz Goldschmidt
   </xref>
   in the study of
   <xref articleid="67760">
    silicate minerals
   </xref>
   . The silicate group was subdivided in part on the basis of composition but mainly according to internal structure. Based on the topology of the SiO
   <sub>
    4
   </sub>
   tetrahedrons, the subclasses include framework, chain, and sheet silicates, among others. Such mineral classifications are logical and well-defined.
  </p>
  <p>
   The broadest divisions of the classification used in the present discussion are (1)
   <xref articleid="55032">
    native elements
   </xref>
   , (2)
   <xref articleid="70240">
    sulfides
   </xref>
   , (3)
   <xref articleid="70246">
    sulfosalts
   </xref>
   , (4)
   <xref articleid="57834">
    oxides
   </xref>
   and
   <xref articleid="41756">
    hydroxides
   </xref>
   , (5)
   <xref articleid="38891">
    halides
   </xref>
   , (6)
   <xref articleid="20258">
    carbonates
   </xref>
   , (7)
   <xref articleid="55937">
    nitrates
   </xref>
   , (8)
   <xref articleid="80701">
    borates
   </xref>
   , (9)
   <xref articleid="70236">
    sulfates
   </xref>
   , (10)
   <xref articleid="59775">
    phosphates
   </xref>
   , and (11)
   <xref articleid="67760">
    silicates
   </xref>
   .
  </p>
  <h2 id="h80386">
   <title>
    Native elements
   </title>
   <p>
    Apart from the free
    <xref articleid="110302">
     gases
    </xref>
    in Earth’s
    <xref articleid="126202">
     atmosphere
    </xref>
    , some 20
    <xref articleid="110602">
     elements
    </xref>
    occur in nature in a pure (i.e., uncombined) or nearly pure form. Known as the native elements, they are partitioned into three families:
    <xref articleid="52266">
     metals
    </xref>
    , semimetals, and
    <xref articleid="56073">
     nonmetals
    </xref>
    . The most common native metals, which are characterized by simple crystal structures, make up three groups: the
    <xref articleid="37211">
     gold
    </xref>
    group, consisting of gold,
    <xref articleid="67807">
     silver
    </xref>
    ,
    <xref articleid="26194">
     copper
    </xref>
    , and
    <xref articleid="47492">
     lead
    </xref>
    ; the
    <xref articleid="110679">
     platinum group
    </xref>
    , composed of
    <xref articleid="60356">
     platinum
    </xref>
    ,
    <xref articleid="58119">
     palladium
    </xref>
    ,
    <xref articleid="42767">
     iridium
    </xref>
    , and
    <xref articleid="57557">
     osmium
    </xref>
    ; and the
    <xref articleid="42794">
     iron
    </xref>
    group, containing iron and
    <xref articleid="101852">
     nickel-iron
    </xref>
    .
    <xref articleid="52102">
     Mercury
    </xref>
    ,
    <xref articleid="71207">
     tantalum
    </xref>
    ,
    <xref articleid="72547">
     tin
    </xref>
    , and
    <xref articleid="78379">
     zinc
    </xref>
    are other metals that have been found in the native state. The native semimetals are divided into two isostructural groups (those whose members share a common structure type): (1)
    <xref articleid="7843">
     antimony
    </xref>
    ,
    <xref articleid="9638">
     arsenic
    </xref>
    , and
    <xref articleid="80309">
     bismuth
    </xref>
    , with the latter two being more common in nature, and (2) the rather uncommon
    <xref articleid="66662">
     selenium
    </xref>
    and
    <xref articleid="71610">
     tellurium
    </xref>
    .
    <xref articleid="20244">
     Carbon
    </xref>
    , in the form of
    <xref articleid="30264">
     diamond
    </xref>
    and
    <xref articleid="37755">
     graphite
    </xref>
    , and
    <xref articleid="70248">
     sulfur
    </xref>
    are the most important native nonmetals.
   </p>
   <h3 id="h80387">
    <title>
     Metals
    </title>
    <p>
     <assembly id="a127956" url="/assembly/view/127956">
      <title>
       ore
      </title>
      <media mediaid="131295" type="image" url="/95/131295-004-F9D28257.jpg"/>
      <caption>
       A sample of gold ore.
      </caption>
      <credit>
       U.S. Geological Survey
      </credit>
     </assembly>
     <assemblyref assemblyid="a127956"/>
     Gold, silver, and copper are members of the same group (column) in the
     <xref articleid="110603">
      periodic table of elements
     </xref>
     and therefore have similar chemical properties. In the uncombined state, their atoms are joined by the fairly weak
     <xref articleid="52274">
      metallic bond
     </xref>
     . These minerals share a common structure type, and their
     <xref articleid="110411">
      atoms
     </xref>
     are positioned in a simple cubic closest-packed arrangement. Gold and silver both have an atomic radius of 1.44
     <xref articleid="7606">
      angstroms
     </xref>
     (Å), or 1.44 × 10
     <sup>
      – 7
     </sup>
     millimetre, which enables complete solid solution to take place between them. The radius of copper is significantly smaller (1.28 Å), and as such copper substitutes only to a limited extent in gold and silver. Likewise, native copper contains only trace amounts of gold and silver in its structure.
    </p>
    <p>
     Because of their similar crystal structure, the members of the gold group display similar physical properties. All are rather soft,
     <xref articleid="472235">
      ductile
     </xref>
     (capable of being drawn into
     <xref articleid="77246">
      wire
     </xref>
     ), malleable (capable of being shaped by a
     <xref articleid="39056">
      hammer
     </xref>
     or rollers), and sectile (capable of being cut smoothly by a
     <xref articleid="45787">
      knife
     </xref>
     or other instrument); gold, silver, and copper serve as excellent conductors of
     <xref articleid="106019">
      electricity
     </xref>
     and heat and exhibit metallic
     <xref articleid="49422">
      lustre
     </xref>
     and hackly fracture (a type of fracture characterized by sharp jagged surfaces). These properties are attributable to their metallic bonding. The gold-group minerals crystallize in the isometric system and have high densities as a consequence of cubic closest packing.
    </p>
    <p>
     In addition to the elements listed above, the platinum group also includes rare mineral alloys such as
     <xref articleid="42768">
      iridosmine
     </xref>
     . The members of this group are harder than the metals of the gold group and also have higher
     <xref articleid="51921">
      melting points
     </xref>
     .
    </p>
    <p>
     <assembly id="a2416" url="/assembly/view/2416">
      <media mediaid="2627" type="image" url="/27/2627-004-3598848A.jpg"/>
      <caption>
       Figure 9:
       <e type="italic">
        Structures of some native elements.
       </e>
       (A) Close-packed model of simple cubic packing of equal spheres, as shown by iron. Each sphere is surrounded by eight closest neighbours. (B) Close-packed model of the structure of arsenic and antimony. Flat areas represent overlap between adjoining atoms. (C) Partial representation of the structure of diamond. (D) The structure of graphite with sheets perpendicular to the
       <e type="italic">
        c
       </e>
       axis.
      </caption>
      <credit>
       Encyclopædia Britannica, Inc.
      </credit>
     </assembly>
     <assemblyref assemblyid="a2416"/>
     The iron-group metals are isometric and have a simple cubic packed structure. Its members include pure iron, which is rarely found on the surface of Earth, and two species of nickel-iron (
     <xref articleid="44447">
      kamacite
     </xref>
     and
     <xref articleid="342903">
      taenite
     </xref>
     ), which have been identified as common constituents of
     <xref articleid="110159">
      meteorites
     </xref>
     . Native iron has been found in
     <xref articleid="13572">
      basalts
     </xref>
     of Disko Island, Greenland and nickel-iron in Josephine and Jackson counties, Oregon. The atomic radii of iron and nickel are both approximately 1.24 Å, and so nickel is a frequent substitute for iron. Earth’s core is thought to be composed largely of such iron-nickel alloys.
    </p>
   </h3>
   <h3 id="h80388">
    <title>
     Semimetals
    </title>
    <p>
     <assembly id="a4290" url="/assembly/view/4290">
      <title>
       arsenic
      </title>
      <media mediaid="13361" type="image" url="/61/13361-004-7F27B853.jpg"/>
      <caption>
       Arsenic (gray) with realgar (red) and orpiment (yellow)
      </caption>
      <credit>
       Courtesy of the Joseph and Helen Guetterman collection; photograph, John H. Gerard/Encyclopædia Britannica, Inc.
      </credit>
     </assembly>
     <assemblyref assemblyid="a4290"/>
     The semimetals antimony, arsenic, and bismuth have a structure type distinct from the simple-packed spheres of the metals. In these semimetals, each atom is positioned closer to three of its neighbouring atoms than to the rest. The structure of antimony and arsenic is composed of spheres that intersect along flat circular areas.
    </p>
    <p>
     The
     <xref articleid="26644">
      covalent
     </xref>
     character of the bonds joining the four closest atoms is linked to the
     <xref articleid="32331">
      electronegative
     </xref>
     nature of the semimetals, reflected by their position in the periodic table. Members of this group are fairly brittle, and they do not conduct
     <xref articleid="39732">
      heat
     </xref>
     and electricity nearly as well as the native metals. The bond type suggested by these properties is intermediate between metallic and covalent; it is consequently stronger and more directional than pure metallic bonding, resulting in crystals of lower
     <xref articleid="70723">
      symmetry
     </xref>
     .
    </p>
   </h3>
   <h3 id="h80389">
    <title>
     Nonmetals
    </title>
    <p>
     <assembly id="a5964" url="/assembly/view/5964">
      <title>
       Hope diamond
      </title>
      <media mediaid="10938" type="image" url="/38/10938-004-077FABA2.jpg"/>
      <caption>
       The Hope diamond; in the Smithsonian Institution, Washington, D.C.
      </caption>
      <credit>
       Lee Boltin
      </credit>
     </assembly>
     <assemblyref assemblyid="a5964"/>
     The native nonmetals diamond,
     <xref articleid="2185">
      fullerene
     </xref>
     , graphite, and sulfur are structurally distinct from the metals and semimetals. The structure of sulfur (atomic radius = 1.04 Å), usually orthorhombic in form, may contain limited solid solution by selenium (atomic radius = 1.16 Å).
    </p>
    <p>
     The
     <xref articleid="60704">
      polymorphs
     </xref>
     of carbon—graphite, fullerene, and diamond—display dissimilar structures, resulting in their differences in
     <xref articleid="472487">
      hardness
     </xref>
     and
     <xref articleid="69028">
      specific gravity
     </xref>
     . In diamond, each carbon atom is bonded covalently in a tetrahedral arrangement, producing a strongly bonded and exceedingly close-knit but not closest-packed structure. The carbon atoms of graphite, however, are arranged in six-membered rings in which each atom is surrounded by three close-by neighbours located at the vertices of an equilateral triangle. The rings are linked to form sheets, called
     <xref articleid="490133">
      graphene
     </xref>
     , that are separated by a distance exceeding one atomic diameter.
     <xref articleid="74766">
      Van der Waals forces
     </xref>
     act perpendicular to the sheets, offering a weak bond, which, in combination with the wide spacing, leads to perfect basal
     <xref articleid="24289">
      cleavage
     </xref>
     and easy gliding along the sheets. Fullerenes are found in meta-
     <xref articleid="7787">
      anthracite
     </xref>
     , in
     <xref articleid="35622">
      fulgurites
     </xref>
     , and in
     <xref articleid="24268">
      clays
     </xref>
     from the
     <xref articleid="474319">
      Cretaceous-Tertiary
     </xref>
     boundary in New Zealand, Spain, and Turkmenistan as well as in organic-rich layers near the Sudbury
     <xref articleid="55747">
      nickel
     </xref>
     mine of Canada.
    </p>
   </h3>
  </h2>
  <h2 id="h80390">
   <title>
    Sulfides
   </title>
   <p>
    This important class includes most of the
    <xref articleid="57321">
     ore
    </xref>
    minerals. The similar but rarer sulfarsenides are grouped here as well. Sulfide minerals consist of one or more metals combined with sulfur; sulfarsenides contain arsenic replacing some of the sulfur.
   </p>
   <p>
    Sulfides are generally opaque and exhibit distinguishing colours and streaks. (
    <xref articleid="69938">
     Streak
    </xref>
    is the colour of a mineral’s powder.) The nonopaque varieties (e.g.,
    <xref articleid="82674">
     cinnabar
    </xref>
    ,
    <xref articleid="62871">
     realgar
    </xref>
    , and
    <xref articleid="57455">
     orpiment
    </xref>
    ) possess high refractive indices, transmitting light only on the thin edges of a specimen.
   </p>
   <p>
    <assemblyref assemblyid="a2405"/>
    <assemblyref assemblyid="a2406"/>
    Few broad generalizations can be made about the structures of sulfides, although these minerals can be classified into smaller groups according to similarities in structure.
    <xref articleid="42702">
     Ionic
    </xref>
    and
    <xref articleid="26644">
     covalent bonding
    </xref>
    are found in many sulfides, while metallic bonding is apparent in others as evidenced by their metal properties. The simplest and most symmetric sulfide structure is based on the architecture of the
    <xref articleid="68495">
     sodium chloride
    </xref>
    structure. A common sulfide mineral that crystallizes in this manner is the
    <xref articleid="57321">
     ore
    </xref>
    mineral of lead,
    <xref articleid="35857">
     galena
    </xref>
    . Its highly symmetric form consists of cubes modified by octahedral faces at their corners. The structure of the common sulfide
    <xref articleid="62054">
     pyrite
    </xref>
    (FeS
    <sub>
     2
    </sub>
    ) also is modeled after the sodium chloride type; a disulfide grouping is located in a position of coordination with six surrounding ferrous iron atoms. The high symmetry of this structure is reflected in the external morphology of pyrite. In another sulfide structure,
    <xref articleid="69096">
     sphalerite
    </xref>
    (ZnS), each zinc atom is surrounded by four sulfur atoms in a tetrahedral coordinating arrangement. In a derivative of this structure type, the
    <xref articleid="22271">
     chalcopyrite
    </xref>
    (CuFeS
    <sub>
     2
    </sub>
    ) structure, copper and iron ions can be thought of as having been regularly substituted in the zinc positions of the original sphalerite atomic arrangement.
   </p>
   <p>
    <xref articleid="9643">
     Arsenopyrite
    </xref>
    (FeAsS) is a common sulfarsenide that occurs in many ore deposits. It is the chief source of the element arsenic.
   </p>
  </h2>
  <h2 id="h80391">
   <title>
    Sulfosalts
   </title>
   <p>
    There are approximately 100 species constituting the rather large and very diverse
    <xref articleid="70246">
     sulfosalt
    </xref>
    class of minerals. The sulfosalts differ notably from the sulfides and sulfarsenides with regard to the role of semimetals, such as arsenic (As) and antimony (Sb), in their structures. In the sulfarsenides, the semimetals substitute for some of the sulfur in the structure, while in the sulfosalts they are found instead in the metal site. For example, in the sulfarsenide arsenopyrite (FeAsS), the arsenic replaces sulfur in a marcasite- (FeS
    <sub>
     2
    </sub>
    -) type structure. In contrast, the sulfosalt
    <xref articleid="32580">
     enargite
    </xref>
    (Cu
    <sub>
     3
    </sub>
    AsS
    <sub>
     4
    </sub>
    ) contains arsenic in the metal position, coordinated to four sulfur atoms. A sulfosalt such as Cu
    <sub>
     3
    </sub>
    AsS
    <sub>
     4
    </sub>
    may also be thought of as a double sulfide, 3Cu
    <sub>
     2
    </sub>
    S ∙ As
    <sub>
     2
    </sub>
    S
    <sub>
     5
    </sub>
    .
   </p>
  </h2>
  <h2 id="h80392">
   <title>
    Oxides and hydroxides
   </title>
   <p>
    These classes consist of oxygen-bearing minerals; the
    <xref articleid="57834">
     oxides
    </xref>
    combine
    <xref articleid="57841">
     oxygen
    </xref>
    with one or more metals, while the
    <xref articleid="41756">
     hydroxides
    </xref>
    are characterized by hydroxyl (OH)
    <sup>
     –
    </sup>
    groups.
   </p>
   <p>
    The oxides are further divided into two main types: simple and multiple. Simple oxides contain a single metal combined with oxygen in one of several possible metal:oxygen ratios (X:O): XO, X
    <sub>
     2
    </sub>
    O, X
    <sub>
     2
    </sub>
    O
    <sub>
     3
    </sub>
    , etc. Ice, H
    <sub>
     2
    </sub>
    O, is a simple oxide of the X
    <sub>
     2
    </sub>
    O type that incorporates hydrogen as the cation. Although SiO
    <sub>
     2
    </sub>
    (quartz and its polymorphs) is the most commonly occurring oxide, it is discussed below in the section on silicates because its structure more closely resembles that of other silicon-oxygen compounds. Two nonequivalent metal sites (X and Y) characterize multiple oxides, which have the form XY
    <sub>
     2
    </sub>
    O
    <sub>
     4
    </sub>
    .
   </p>
   <p>
    Unlike the minerals of the sulfide class, which exhibit ionic, covalent, and metallic bonding, oxide minerals generally display strong ionic bonding. They are relatively hard, dense, and refractory.
   </p>
   <p>
    Oxides generally occur in small amounts in igneous and metamorphic rocks and also as preexisting grains in
    <xref articleid="109697">
     sedimentary rocks
    </xref>
    . Several oxides have great economic value, including the principal ores of
    <xref articleid="42794">
     iron
    </xref>
    (
    <xref articleid="39951">
     hematite
    </xref>
    and
    <xref articleid="50036">
     magnetite
    </xref>
    ),
    <xref articleid="82451">
     chromium
    </xref>
    (
    <xref articleid="82450">
     chromite
    </xref>
    ),
    <xref articleid="50515">
     manganese
    </xref>
    (
    <xref articleid="62060">
     pyrolusite
    </xref>
    , as well as the hydroxides,
    <xref articleid="50518">
     manganite
    </xref>
    and
    <xref articleid="61702">
     romanechite
    </xref>
    ), tin (
    <xref articleid="20664">
     cassiterite
    </xref>
    ), and
    <xref articleid="74425">
     uranium
    </xref>
    (
    <xref articleid="74424">
     uraninite
    </xref>
    ).
   </p>
   <p>
    Members of the hematite group are of the X
    <sub>
     2
    </sub>
    O
    <sub>
     3
    </sub>
    type and have structures based on hexagonal closest packing of the oxygen atoms with octahedrally coordinated (surrounded by and bonded to six atoms) cations between them.
    <xref articleid="26446">
     Corundum
    </xref>
    and hematite share a common hexagonal architecture. In the
    <xref articleid="42150">
     ilmenite
    </xref>
    structure, iron and
    <xref articleid="72643">
     titanium
    </xref>
    occupy alternate Fe-O and Ti-O layers.
   </p>
   <p>
    The XO
    <sub>
     2
    </sub>
    -type oxides are divided into two groups. The first structure type, exemplified by rutile, contains cations in octahedral coordination with oxygen. The second resembles
    <xref articleid="34679">
     fluorite
    </xref>
    (CaF
    <sub>
     2
    </sub>
    ); each oxygen is bonded to four cations located at the corners of a fairly regular tetrahedron, and each cation lies within a cube at whose corners are eight oxygen atoms. This latter structure is exhibited by uranium,
    <xref articleid="72236">
     thorium
    </xref>
    , and
    <xref articleid="22144">
     cerium
    </xref>
    oxides, whose considerable importance arises from their roles in nuclear chemistry.
   </p>
   <p>
    <assembly id="a2418" url="/assembly/view/2418">
     <media mediaid="2630" type="image" url="/30/2630-004-BD5B848A.jpg"/>
     <caption>
      Figure 10: An oxygen layer in the spinel (MgAl
      <sub>
       2
      </sub>
      O
      <sub>
       4
      </sub>
      ) structure. The large circles represent oxygen in approximate cubic closest packing; the cation layers on each side of the oxygen layer are also shown.
     </caption>
     <credit>
      Encyclopædia Britannica, Inc.
     </credit>
    </assembly>
    <assemblyref assemblyid="a2418"/>
    The spinel-group minerals have type XY
    <sub>
     2
    </sub>
    O
    <sub>
     4
    </sub>
    and contain oxygen atoms in approximate cubic closest packing. The cations located within the oxygen framework are octahedrally (sixfold) and tetrahedrally (fourfold) coordinated with oxygen.
   </p>
   <p>
    The (OH)
    <sup>
     –
    </sup>
    group of the hydroxides generally results in structures with lower bond strengths than in the oxide minerals. The hydroxide minerals tend to be less dense than the oxides and also are not as hard. All hydroxides form at low temperatures and are found predominantly as
    <xref articleid="76370">
     weathering
    </xref>
    products, as, for example, from alteration in
    <xref articleid="41753">
     hydrothermal veins
    </xref>
    . Some common hydroxides are
    <xref articleid="16746">
     brucite
    </xref>
    [Mg(OH)
    <sub>
     2
    </sub>
    ],
    <xref articleid="50518">
     manganite
    </xref>
    [MnO ∙ OH],
    <xref articleid="30292">
     diaspore
    </xref>
    [α-AlO ∙ OH], and goethite [α-FeO ∙ OH]. The ore of
    <xref articleid="5954">
     aluminum
    </xref>
    ,
    <xref articleid="13828">
     bauxite
    </xref>
    , consists of a mixture of diaspore,
    <xref articleid="80378">
     boehmite
    </xref>
    (γ-AlO ∙ OH—a polymorph of diaspore), and gibbsite [Al(OH)
    <sub>
     3
    </sub>
    ], plus iron oxides.
    <xref articleid="37194">
     Goethite
    </xref>
    is a common alteration product of iron-rich occurrences and is an iron ore in some localities.
   </p>
  </h2>
  <h2 id="h80393">
   <title>
    Halides
   </title>
   <p>
    Members of this class are distinguished by the large-sized
    <xref articleid="7647">
     anions
    </xref>
    of the
    <xref articleid="110612">
     halogens
    </xref>
    <xref articleid="82243">
     chlorine
    </xref>
    ,
    <xref articleid="16596">
     bromine
    </xref>
    ,
    <xref articleid="42681">
     iodine
    </xref>
    , and
    <xref articleid="34677">
     fluorine
    </xref>
    . The ions carry an
    <xref articleid="32271">
     electric charge
    </xref>
    of negative one and easily become distorted in the presence of strongly charged bodies. When associated with rather large, weakly polarizing
    <xref articleid="21830">
     cations
    </xref>
    of low charge, such as those of the
    <xref articleid="110605">
     alkali metals
    </xref>
    , both anions and cations take the form of nearly perfect spheres. Structures composed of these
    <xref articleid="473370">
     spheres
    </xref>
    exhibit the highest possible
    <xref articleid="70723">
     symmetry
    </xref>
    .
   </p>
   <p>
    Pure ionic bonding is exemplified best in the isometric halides, for each spherical
    <xref articleid="42688">
     ion
    </xref>
    distributes its weak electrostatic charge over its entire surface. These halides manifest relatively low hardness and moderate-to-high
    <xref articleid="51921">
     melting points
    </xref>
    . In the solid state they are poor thermal and electric conductors, but when molten they conduct
    <xref articleid="106019">
     electricity
    </xref>
    well.
   </p>
   <p>
    Halogen ions may also combine with smaller, more strongly polarizing cations than the alkali metal ions. Lower symmetry and a higher degree of covalent bonding prevail in these structures.
    <xref articleid="76210">
     Water
    </xref>
    and hydroxyl ions may enter the structure, as in
    <xref articleid="10026">
     atacamite
    </xref>
    [Cu
    <sub>
     2
    </sub>
    Cl(OH)
    <sub>
     3
    </sub>
    ].
   </p>
   <p>
    <assembly id="a2420" url="/assembly/view/2420">
     <media mediaid="2633" type="image" url="/33/2633-004-B7FFC2D1.jpg"/>
     <caption>
      Figure 11: (A) The structure of halite, NaCl. (B) The structure of fluorite, CaF
      <sub>
       2
      </sub>
      .
     </caption>
     <credit>
      Encyclopædia Britannica, Inc.
     </credit>
    </assembly>
    <assemblyref assemblyid="a2420"/>
    The halides consist of about 80 chemically related minerals with diverse structures and widely varied origins. The most common are
    <xref articleid="38903">
     halite
    </xref>
    (NaCl),
    <xref articleid="70712">
     sylvite
    </xref>
    (KCl), chlorargyrite (AgCl),
    <xref articleid="28073">
     cryolite
    </xref>
    (Na
    <sub>
     3
    </sub>
    AlF
    <sub>
     6
    </sub>
    ), fluorite (CaF
    <sub>
     2
    </sub>
    ), and atacamite. No
    <xref articleid="53247">
     molecules
    </xref>
    are present among the arrangement of the ions in halite, a naturally occurring form of sodium chloride. Each cation and anion is in octahedral coordination with its six closest neighbours. The NaCl structure is found in the crystals of many XZ-type halides, including sylvite (KCl) and chlorargyrite (AgCl). Some sulfides and oxides of XZ type crystallize in this structure type as well—for example, galena (PbS), alabandite (MnS), and
    <xref articleid="59245">
     periclase
    </xref>
    (MgO).
   </p>
   <p>
    Several XZ
    <sub>
     2
    </sub>
    halides have the same structure as fluorite (CaF
    <sub>
     2
    </sub>
    ). In
    <xref articleid="34679">
     fluorite
    </xref>
    ,
    <xref articleid="18627">
     calcium
    </xref>
    cations are positioned at the corners and face centres of cubic unit cells. (A unit cell is the smallest group of atoms, ions, or molecules from which the entire crystal structure can be generated by its repetition.) Each
    <xref articleid="34677">
     fluorine
    </xref>
    anion is in tetrahedral coordination with four calcium ions, while each calcium cation is in eightfold coordination with eight fluorine ions that form the corners of a cube around it.
    <xref articleid="74424">
     Uraninite
    </xref>
    (UO
    <sub>
     2
    </sub>
    ) and
    <xref articleid="72233">
     thorianite
    </xref>
    (ThO
    <sub>
     2
    </sub>
    ) are two examples of the several oxides that have a fluorite-type structure.
   </p>
  </h2>
  <h2 id="h80394">
   <title>
    Carbonates
   </title>
   <p>
    The
    <xref articleid="20260">
     carbonate minerals
    </xref>
    contain the anionic complex (CO
    <sub>
     3
    </sub>
    )
    <sup>
     2–
    </sup>
    , which is triangular in its coordination—i.e., with a carbon atom at the centre and an oxygen atom at each of the corners of an equilateral triangle. These anionic groups are strongly bonded individual units and do not share oxygen atoms with one another. The triangular carbonate groups are the basic building units of all carbonate minerals and are largely responsible for the properties particular to the class.
   </p>
   <p>
    Carbonates are frequently identified using the effervescence test with
    <xref articleid="3543">
     acid
    </xref>
    . The reaction that results in the characteristic fizz, 2H
    <sup>
     +
    </sup>
    + CO
    <fraction>
     <num>
      2
     </num>
     <den>
      3
     </den>
    </fraction>
    → H
    <sub>
     2
    </sub>
    O + CO
    <sub>
     2
    </sub>
    , makes use of the fact that the carbon-oxygen bonds of the CO
    <sub>
     3
    </sub>
    groups are not quite as strong as the corresponding carbon-oxygen bonds in
    <xref articleid="20249">
     carbon dioxide
    </xref>
    .
   </p>
   <p>
    The common anhydrous (water-free) carbonates are divided into three groups that differ in structure type:
    <xref articleid="109693">
     calcite
    </xref>
    ,
    <xref articleid="9174">
     aragonite
    </xref>
    , and
    <xref articleid="109694">
     dolomite
    </xref>
    . The copper carbonates
    <xref articleid="11566">
     azurite
    </xref>
    and
    <xref articleid="50256">
     malachite
    </xref>
    are the only notable hydrous varieties.
   </p>
   <p>
    The members of the calcite group share a common structure type. It can be considered as a derivative of the NaCl structure in which the carbonate (CO
    <sub>
     3
    </sub>
    ) groups substitute for the chlorine ions and calcium cations replace the sodium cations. As a result of the triangular shape of the CO
    <sub>
     3
    </sub>
    groups, the structure is rhombohedral instead of
    <xref articleid="42957">
     isometric
    </xref>
    as in NaCl. The CO
    <sub>
     3
    </sub>
    groups are in planes perpendicular to the threefold c-axis, and the calcium ions occupy alternate planes and are bonded to six oxygen atoms of the CO
    <sub>
     3
    </sub>
    groups.
   </p>
   <p>
    Members of the calcite group exhibit perfect rhombohedral cleavage. The composition CaCO
    <sub>
     3
    </sub>
    most commonly occurs in two different polymorphs: rhombohedral calcite with calcium surrounded by six closest oxygen atoms and
    <xref articleid="57496">
     orthorhombic
    </xref>
    aragonite with calcium surrounded by nine closest oxygen atoms.
   </p>
   <p>
    When CO
    <sub>
     3
    </sub>
    groups are combined with large divalent cations (generally with ionic radii greater than 1.0 Å), orthorhombic structures result. This is known as the aragonite structure type. Members of this group include those with large cations: BaCO
    <sub>
     3
    </sub>
    , SrCO
    <sub>
     3
    </sub>
    , and PbCO
    <sub>
     3
    </sub>
    . Each cation is surrounded by nine closest oxygen atoms.
   </p>
   <p>
    The aragonite group displays more limited solid solution than the calcite group. The type of cation present in aragonite minerals is largely responsible for the differences in physical properties among the members of the group.
    <xref articleid="69028">
     Specific gravity
    </xref>
    , for example, is roughly proportional to the
    <xref articleid="10135">
     atomic weight
    </xref>
    of the
    <xref articleid="52266">
     metal
    </xref>
    ions.
   </p>
   <p>
    Dolomite [CaMg(CO
    <sub>
     3
    </sub>
    )
    <sub>
     2
    </sub>
    ],
    <xref articleid="46525">
     kutnohorite
    </xref>
    [CaMn(CO
    <sub>
     3
    </sub>
    )
    <sub>
     2
    </sub>
    ], and ankerite [CaFe(CO
    <sub>
     3
    </sub>
    )
    <sub>
     2
    </sub>
    ] are three isostructural members of the dolomite group. The dolomite structure can be considered as a calcite-type structure in which
    <xref articleid="50015">
     magnesium
    </xref>
    and calcium cations occupy the metal sites in alternate layers. The
    <xref articleid="18627">
     calcium
    </xref>
    (Ca
    <sup>
     2+
    </sup>
    ) and magnesium (Mg
    <sup>
     2+
    </sup>
    ) ions differ in size by 33 percent, and this produces cation ordering with the two cations occupying specific and separate levels in the structure. Dolomite has a calcium-to-magnesium ratio of approximately 1:1, which gives it a composition intermediate between CaCO
    <sub>
     3
    </sub>
    and MgCO
    <sub>
     3
    </sub>
    .
   </p>
  </h2>
  <h2 id="h80395">
   <title>
    Nitrates
   </title>
   <p>
    The
    <xref articleid="55937">
     nitrates
    </xref>
    are characterized by their triangular (NO
    <sub>
     3
    </sub>
    )
    <sup>
     –
    </sup>
    groups that resemble the (CO
    <sub>
     3
    </sub>
    )
    <sup>
     2–
    </sup>
    groups of the carbonates, making the two mineral classes similar in structure. The nitrogen cation (N
    <sup>
     5+
    </sup>
    ) carries a high charge and is strongly polarizing like the carbon cation (C
    <sup>
     4+
    </sup>
    ) of the CO
    <sub>
     3
    </sub>
    group. A tightly knit triangular complex is created by the three nitrogen-oxygen bonds of the NO
    <sub>
     3
    </sub>
    group; these bonds are stronger than all others in the crystal. Because the nitrogen-oxygen bond has greater strength than the corresponding carbon-oxygen bond in carbonates, nitrates decompose less readily in the presence of acids.
   </p>
   <p>
    Nitrate structures analogous to those of the calcite group result when NO
    <sub>
     3
    </sub>
    combines in a 1:1 ratio with monovalent cations whose radii can accommodate six closest oxygen neighbours. For example, nitratite (NaNO
    <sub>
     3
    </sub>
    ), also called soda nitre, and calcite exhibit the same structure, crystallography, and cleavage. The two minerals differ in that nitratite is softer and melts at a lower temperature owing to its lesser charge; also, sodium has a lower atomic weight than calcium, causing nitratite to have a lower specific gravity as well. Similarly, nitre (KNO
    <sub>
     3
    </sub>
    ), also known as
    <xref articleid="65150">
     saltpetre
    </xref>
    , is an analogue of
    <xref articleid="9174">
     aragonite
    </xref>
    . These are two examples of only seven known naturally occurring nitrates.
   </p>
  </h2>
  <h2 id="h80396">
   <title>
    Borates
   </title>
   <p>
    <assembly id="a2490" url="/assembly/view/2490">
     <media mediaid="2636" type="image" url="/36/2636-004-73D4667D.jpg"/>
     <caption>
      Figure 12: Various possible linkages of (A) BO
      <sub>
       3
      </sub>
      triangles to form (B,C) multiple groups and (D) chains in borates. Complex (E) triangle and (F) quadrangle groups are also shown. The group depicted in (F) occurs in borax.
     </caption>
     <credit>
      Encyclopædia Britannica, Inc.
     </credit>
    </assembly>
    <assemblyref assemblyid="a2490"/>
    Minerals of the borate class contain
    <xref articleid="80773">
     boron
    </xref>
    -oxygen groups that can link together, in a phenomenon known as
    <xref articleid="60701">
     polymerization
    </xref>
    , to form chains, sheets, and isolated multiple groups. The silicon-oxygen (SiO
    <sub>
     4
    </sub>
    ) tetrahedrons of the silicates polymerize in a manner similar to the (BO
    <sub>
     3
    </sub>
    )
    <sup>
     3–
    </sup>
    triangular groups of the borates. (For further information on such structures,
    <e type="italic">
     see below
    </e>
    <xref articleid="109683" refid="h80399">
     Silicates
    </xref>
    ). A single oxygen atom is shared between two boron cations (B
    <sup>
     3+
    </sup>
    ), thereby linking the BO
    <sub>
     3
    </sub>
    groups into extended units such as double triangles, triple rings, sheets, and chains. The oxygen atom is able to accommodate two boron atoms because the small boron cation has a bond strength to each oxygen that is exactly one-half the bond
    <xref articleid="32627">
     energy
    </xref>
    of the oxygen ion.
   </p>
   <p>
    Although boron is usually found in triangular coordination with three oxygens, it also occurs in fourfold coordination in tetrahedral groups. In addition, boron may exist as part of complex anionic groups such as [B
    <sub>
     3
    </sub>
    O
    <sub>
     3
    </sub>
    (OH)
    <sub>
     3
    </sub>
    ]
    <sup>
     2–
    </sup>
    , consisting of one triangle and two tetrahedrons. Complex infinite chains of tetrahedrons and triangles are found in the structure of
    <xref articleid="24729">
     colemanite
    </xref>
    [CaB
    <sub>
     3
    </sub>
    O
    <sub>
     4
    </sub>
    (OH)
    <sub>
     3
    </sub>
    ∙ H
    <sub>
     2
    </sub>
    O]; a complex ion composed of two tetrahedrons and two triangles, [B
    <sub>
     4
    </sub>
    O
    <sub>
     5
    </sub>
    (OH)
    <sub>
     4
    </sub>
    ]
    <sup>
     2–
    </sup>
    , is present in
    <xref articleid="80702">
     borax
    </xref>
    [Na
    <sub>
     2
    </sub>
    B
    <sub>
     4
    </sub>
    O
    <sub>
     5
    </sub>
    (OH)
    <sub>
     4
    </sub>
    ∙ 8H
    <sub>
     2
    </sub>
    O].
   </p>
  </h2>
  <h2 id="h80397">
   <title>
    Sulfates
   </title>
   <p>
    This class is composed of a large number of minerals, but relatively few are common. All contain anionic (SO
    <sub>
     4
    </sub>
    )
    <sup>
     2–
    </sup>
    groups in their structures. These anionic complexes are formed through the tight bonding of a central S
    <sup>
     6+
    </sup>
    ion to four neighbouring oxygen atoms in a tetrahedral arrangement around the sulfur. This closely knit group is incapable of sharing any of its oxygen atoms with other SO
    <sub>
     4
    </sub>
    groups; as such, the tetrahedrons occur as individual, unlinked groups in
    <xref articleid="70236">
     sulfate mineral
    </xref>
    structures.
   </p>
   <p>
    Members of the barite group constitute the most important and common anhydrous sulfates. They have orthorhombic symmetry with large divalent cations bonded to the sulfate ion. In
    <xref articleid="13369">
     barite
    </xref>
    (BaSO
    <sub>
     4
    </sub>
    ), each barium ion is surrounded by 12 closest oxygen ions belonging to seven distinct SO
    <sub>
     4
    </sub>
    groups.
    <xref articleid="7625">
     Anhydrite
    </xref>
    (CaSO
    <sub>
     4
    </sub>
    ) exhibits a structure very different from that of barite since the ionic radius of Ca
    <sup>
     2+
    </sup>
    is considerably smaller than Ba
    <sup>
     2+
    </sup>
    . Each calcium cation can only fit eight oxygen atoms around it from neighbouring SO
    <sub>
     4
    </sub>
    groups.
    <xref articleid="38660">
     Gypsum
    </xref>
    (CaSO
    <sub>
     4
    </sub>
    ∙ 2H
    <sub>
     2
    </sub>
    O) is the most important and abundant hydrous sulfate.
   </p>
  </h2>
  <h2 id="h80398">
   <title>
    Phosphates
   </title>
   <p>
    Although this mineral class is large (with almost 700 known species), most of its members are quite rare.
    <xref articleid="7981">
     Apatite
    </xref>
    [Ca
    <sub>
     5
    </sub>
    (PO
    <sub>
     4
    </sub>
    )
    <sub>
     3
    </sub>
    (F, Cl, OH)], however, is one of the most important and abundant
    <xref articleid="59775">
     phosphates
    </xref>
    . The members of this group are characterized by tetrahedral anionic (PO
    <sub>
     4
    </sub>
    )
    <sup>
     3–
    </sup>
    complexes, which are analogous to the (SO
    <sub>
     4
    </sub>
    )
    <sup>
     2–
    </sup>
    groups of the sulfates. The phosphorus ion, with a valence of positive five, is only slightly larger than the sulfur ion, which carries a positive six charge.
    <xref articleid="9637">
     Arsenates
    </xref>
    and
    <xref articleid="74780">
     vanadates
    </xref>
    are similar to phosphates.
   </p>
  </h2>
  <h2 id="h80399">
   <title>
    Silicates
   </title>
   <p>
    The
    <xref articleid="67760">
     silicates
    </xref>
    , owing to their abundance on Earth, constitute the most important mineral class. Approximately 25 percent of all known minerals and 40 percent of the most common ones are silicates; the
    <xref articleid="109696">
     igneous rocks
    </xref>
    that make up more than 90 percent of Earth’s crust are composed of virtually all silicates.
   </p>
   <p>
    <assembly id="a2491" url="/assembly/view/2491">
     <media mediaid="2639" type="image" url="/39/2639-004-EAB5751A.jpg"/>
     <caption>
      Figure 13: Two views of a closest-packed representation of the silicon-oxygen tetrahedron.
     </caption>
     <credit>
      Encyclopædia Britannica, Inc.
     </credit>
    </assembly>
    <assemblyref assemblyid="a2491"/>
    The fundamental unit in all silicate structures is the silicon-oxygen (SiO
    <sub>
     4
    </sub>
    )
    <sup>
     4–
    </sup>
    tetrahedron. It is composed of a central silicon cation (Si
    <sup>
     4+
    </sup>
    ) bonded to four oxygen atoms that are located at the corners of a regular tetrahedron. The terrestrial crust is held together by the strong silicon-oxygen bonds of these tetrahedrons. Approximately 50 percent ionic and 50 percent covalent, the bonds develop from the attraction of oppositely charged ions as well as the sharing of their electrons.
   </p>
   <p>
    The positive charge (+4) of each silicon cation is satisfied by its four bonds to oxygen atoms. Each oxygen ion (O
    <sup>
     2–
    </sup>
    ), however, contributes only one-half of its total bonding energy to a silicon-oxygen bond, so it is capable of also bonding to the silicon cation of another tetrahedron. The SiO
    <sub>
     4
    </sub>
    tetrahedrons thereby become linked by shared oxygen atoms; this is referred to as polymerization. The degree and manner of polymerization are the bases for the variety present in silicate structures.
   </p>
   <p>
    <assembly id="a2492" url="/assembly/view/2492">
     <media mediaid="2642" type="image" url="/42/2642-004-AFB59401.jpg"/>
     <caption>
      Figure 14: Various structural linkage schemes in silicates.
     </caption>
     <credit>
      Encyclopædia Britannica, Inc.
     </credit>
    </assembly>
    <assemblyref assemblyid="a2492"/>
    The silicates can be divided into groups according to structural configuration, which arises from the sharing of one, two, three, or all oxygen ions of a tetrahedron.
    <xref articleid="104643">
     Nesosilicates
    </xref>
    have isolated groups of SiO
    <sub>
     4
    </sub>
    , while
    <xref articleid="68764">
     sorosilicates
    </xref>
    contain pairs of SiO
    <sub>
     4
    </sub>
    tetrahedrons linked into Si
    <sub>
     2
    </sub>
    O
    <sub>
     7
    </sub>
    groups. Ring silicates, also known as
    <xref articleid="28384">
     cyclosilicates
    </xref>
    , are closed, ringlike silicates; the sixfold variety has composition Si
    <sub>
     6
    </sub>
    O
    <sub>
     18
    </sub>
    . Silicates that are composed of infinite chains of tetrahedrons are called inosilicates; single chains have a unit composition of SiO
    <sub>
     3
    </sub>
    or Si
    <sub>
     2
    </sub>
    O
    <sub>
     6
    </sub>
    , whereas double chains contain a silicon to oxygen ratio of 4:11.
    <xref articleid="59858">
     Phyllosilicates
    </xref>
    , or sheet silicates, are formed when three oxygen atoms are shared with adjoining tetrahedrons. The resulting infinite flat sheets have unit composition Si
    <sub>
     2
    </sub>
    O
    <sub>
     5
    </sub>
    . In structures where tetrahedrons share all their oxygen ions, an infinite three-dimensional network is created with an SiO
    <sub>
     2
    </sub>
    unit composition. Minerals of this type are called framework silicates or
    <xref articleid="104899">
     tectosilicates
    </xref>
    .
   </p>
   <p>
    As a major constituent of Earth’s crust,
    <xref articleid="5954">
     aluminum
    </xref>
    follows only
    <xref articleid="57841">
     oxygen
    </xref>
    and
    <xref articleid="67764">
     silicon
    </xref>
    in importance. The radius of aluminum, slightly larger than that of silicon, lies close to the upper bound for allowable fourfold coordination in crystals. As a result, aluminum can be surrounded with four oxygen atoms arranged tetrahedrally, but it can also occur in sixfold coordination with oxygen. The ability to maintain two roles within the silicate structure makes aluminum a unique constituent of these minerals. The tetrahedral AlO
    <sub>
     4
    </sub>
    groups are approximately equal in size to SiO
    <sub>
     4
    </sub>
    groups and therefore can become incorporated into the silicate polymerization scheme. Aluminum in sixfold coordination may form ionic bonds with the SiO
    <sub>
     4
    </sub>
    tetrahedrons. Thus, aluminum may occupy tetrahedral sites as a replacement for silicon and octahedral sites in solid
    <xref articleid="68634">
     solution
    </xref>
    with elements such as magnesium and ferrous iron.
   </p>
   <p>
    Several ions may be present in silicate structures in octahedral coordination with oxygen: Mg
    <sup>
     2+
    </sup>
    , Fe
    <sup>
     2+
    </sup>
    , Fe
    <sup>
     3+
    </sup>
    , Mn
    <sup>
     2+
    </sup>
    , Al
    <sup>
     3+
    </sup>
    , and Ti
    <sup>
     4+
    </sup>
    . All cations have approximately the same dimensions and thus are found in equivalent atomic sites, even though their charges range from positive two to positive four. Solid solution involving
    <xref articleid="42688">
     ions
    </xref>
    of different charge is accomplished through coupled substitutions, thereby maintaining neutrality of the structures.
   </p>
   <h3 id="h80400">
    <title>
     Nesosilicates
    </title>
    <p>
     The silicon-oxygen tetrahedrons of the nesosilicates are not polymerized; they are linked to one another only by ionic bonds of the interstitial cations. As a result of the isolation of the tetrahedral groups, the crystal habits of these minerals are typically equidimensional so that prominent cleavage directions are not present. The size and charge of the interstitial cations largely determine the structural form of the nesosilicates. The relatively high
     <xref articleid="69028">
      specific gravity
     </xref>
     and
     <xref articleid="472487">
      hardness
     </xref>
     that are characteristic of this group arise from the dense packing of the atoms within the structure. Substitution of aluminum for silicon is normally quite low.
    </p>
   </h3>
   <h3 id="h80401">
    <title>
     Sorosilicates
    </title>
    <p>
     These minerals contain sets of two SiO
     <sub>
      4
     </sub>
     tetrahedrons joined by one shared apical oxygen. A silicon-to-oxygen ratio of 2:7 is consequently present in their structures. More than 70 minerals belong to the sorosilicate group, although most are rare. Only the members of the
     <xref articleid="32794">
      epidote
     </xref>
     group and
     <xref articleid="75196">
      vesuvianite
     </xref>
     are common. Both independent (SiO
     <sub>
      4
     </sub>
     )
     <sup>
      4–
     </sup>
     and double (Si
     <sub>
      2
     </sub>
     O
     <sub>
      7
     </sub>
     )
     <sup>
      6–
     </sup>
     groups are incorporated into the epidote structure, as is reflected in its formula: Ca
     <sub>
      2
     </sub>
     (Al, Fe)Al
     <sub>
      2
     </sub>
     O(SiO
     <sub>
      4
     </sub>
     )(Si
     <sub>
      2
     </sub>
     O
     <sub>
      7
     </sub>
     )(OH).
    </p>
   </h3>
   <h3 id="h80402">
    <title>
     Cyclosilicates
    </title>
    <p>
     Silicon-oxygen tetrahedrons are linked into rings in cyclosilicate structures, which have an overall Si:O ratio of 1:3. There are three closed cyclic configurations with the following formulas: Si
     <sub>
      3
     </sub>
     O
     <sub>
      9
     </sub>
     , Si
     <sub>
      4
     </sub>
     O
     <sub>
      12
     </sub>
     , and Si
     <sub>
      6
     </sub>
     O
     <sub>
      18
     </sub>
     . The rare titanosilicate benitoite (BaTiSi
     <sub>
      3
     </sub>
     O
     <sub>
      9
     </sub>
     ) is the only mineral that is built with the simple Si
     <sub>
      3
     </sub>
     O
     <sub>
      9
     </sub>
     ring.
     <xref articleid="11478">
      Axinite
     </xref>
     [(Ca, Fe, Mn)
     <sub>
      3
     </sub>
     Al
     <sub>
      2
     </sub>
     (BO
     <sub>
      3
     </sub>
     )(Si
     <sub>
      4
     </sub>
     O
     <sub>
      12
     </sub>
     )(OH)] contains Si
     <sub>
      4
     </sub>
     O
     <sub>
      12
     </sub>
     rings, along with BO
     <sub>
      3
     </sub>
     triangles and OH groups. The two common and important cyclosilicates,
     <xref articleid="78916">
      beryl
     </xref>
     (Be
     <sub>
      3
     </sub>
     Al
     <sub>
      2
     </sub>
     Si
     <sub>
      6
     </sub>
     O
     <sub>
      18
     </sub>
     ) and
     <xref articleid="73060">
      tourmaline
     </xref>
     (which has an extremely complex formula), are based on the Si
     <sub>
      6
     </sub>
     O
     <sub>
      18
     </sub>
     ring.
    </p>
   </h3>
   <h3 id="h80403">
    <title>
     Inosilicates
    </title>
    <p>
     This class is characterized by its one-dimensional chains and bands created by the linkage of SiO
     <sub>
      4
     </sub>
     tetrahedrons. Single chains may be formed by the sharing of two oxygen atoms from each tetrahedron, resulting in a structure with an Si:O ratio of 1:3. Two such chains that are aligned side by side with alternate tetrahedrons sharing an additional oxygen atom form bands of double chains. These structures have an Si:O ratio of 4:11. There are a number of silicate minerals, pyroxenoids, which have a similar Si:O ratio as pyroxene, but with structures that are not identical as the chains of
     <xref articleid="67764">
      silicon
     </xref>
     tetrahedra do not infinitely repeat. Two significant rock-forming mineral families display these structure types: the single-chain
     <xref articleid="109687">
      pyroxenes
     </xref>
     and the double-chain
     <xref articleid="109686">
      amphiboles
     </xref>
     .
    </p>
    <p>
     The amphiboles and pyroxenes share the same cations and have many similar crystallographic, chemical, and physical properties: the colour, lustre, and hardness of analogous species are alike. A distinguishing factor between the two groups, the presence of the hydroxyl radical in the amphiboles, generally gives the double-chain members lower specific gravities and refractive indices than their single-chain analogues. Their crystal habits also are different: amphiboles exhibit needlelike or fibrous crystals, while pyroxenes take the form of stubby
     <xref articleid="61433">
      prisms
     </xref>
     . In addition, the different chain structures of the two groups result in different cleavage angles.
    </p>
    <p>
     Pyroxenes occur in high-temperature igneous and metamorphic rocks. They crystallize at higher temperatures than their amphibole counterparts. A pyroxene formed early in the cooling of an igneous melt or in a metamorphic fluid may later combine with water at a lower temperature to form amphibole.
    </p>
   </h3>
   <h3 id="h80404">
    <title>
     Phyllosilicates
    </title>
    <p>
     These minerals display a two-dimensional framework of infinite sheets of SiO
     <sub>
      4
     </sub>
     tetrahedrons. An Si:O ratio of 2:5 results from the sharing of three oxygen atoms in each tetrahedron. Sixfold symmetry is exhibited in undistorted sheets. The silicate sheet framework is largely responsible for the following properties of the phyllosilicates: platy or flaky habit, single pronounced cleavage, low specific gravity, softness, and possible flexibility and elasticity of cleavage layers. Most minerals of this group contain hydroxyls positioned in the middle of the sixfold rings of tetrahedrons.
    </p>
    <p>
     Many soil constituents, produced through
     <xref articleid="109695">
      rock
     </xref>
     <xref articleid="76370">
      weathering
     </xref>
     , possess a sheet structure. Phyllosilicate properties contribute greatly to the ability of
     <xref articleid="109555">
      soils
     </xref>
     to release and retain
     <xref articleid="108554">
      plant
     </xref>
     food, to reserve water from wet to dry
     <xref articleid="66491">
      seasons
     </xref>
     , and to accommodate organisms and atmospheric
     <xref articleid="110302">
      gases
     </xref>
     .
    </p>
   </h3>
   <h3 id="h80405">
    <title>
     Tectosilicates
    </title>
    <p>
     Almost 75 percent of Earth’s crust is composed of minerals with the three-dimensional framework of the tectosilicates. All oxygen atoms of the SiO
     <sub>
      4
     </sub>
     tetrahedrons of members of this class are shared with nearby tetrahedrons, creating a strongly bound structure with an Si:O ratio of 1:2. Other than the
     <xref articleid="78326">
      zeolite
     </xref>
     group, which can accommodate water owing to the open nature of its structure, all members listed in the table are anhydrous.
    </p>
   </h3>
  </h2>
 </h1>
 <h1 id="h80406">
  <title>
   Mineral associations and phase equilibrium
  </title>
  <p>
   The preceding sections provided an overview of major mineral groups but did not treat minerals as part of assemblages in
   <xref articleid="109695">
    rock
   </xref>
   types nor discuss the experimental study of minerals and rock occurrences.
   <xref articleid="59514">
    Petrology
   </xref>
   , the scientific study of rocks, is concerned largely with identifying individual minerals in rocks, along with their abundance, grain size, and texture, because rocks typically consist of a variety of minerals. Such information is essential to an understanding of the history of any rock.
  </p>
  <p>
   Petrological research requires a strong understanding of the principles of mineralogy and mineral identification and a thorough familiarity with the theoretical and experimental studies of rock origins. The present section focuses on
   <xref articleid="110296">
    phase
   </xref>
   equilibrium, upon which the link between the study of minerals and the study of rocks is largely based.
  </p>
  <p>
   A phase is a homogeneous substance that has a fixed composition and uniform chemical and physical properties. Only a mineral that displays no solid solution may therefore be considered a phase.
   <xref articleid="62182">
    Quartz
   </xref>
   (SiO
   <sub>
    2
   </sub>
   ), for example, is a low-temperature phase in the Si-O
   <sub>
    2
   </sub>
   (SiO
   <sub>
    2
   </sub>
   ) system, and kyanite (Al
   <sub>
    2
   </sub>
   SiO
   <sub>
    5
   </sub>
   ) is a high-pressure phase in the Al
   <sub>
    2
   </sub>
   O
   <sub>
    3
   </sub>
   -SiO
   <sub>
    2
   </sub>
   (Al
   <sub>
    2
   </sub>
   SiO
   <sub>
    5
   </sub>
   ) system. The term phase region is used when a mineral exhibits compositional variation, as in the solid-solution series between
   <xref articleid="34926">
    forsterite and fayalite
   </xref>
   . A phase may exist as a
   <xref articleid="68592">
    solid
   </xref>
   ,
   <xref articleid="110301">
    liquid
   </xref>
   , or
   <xref articleid="110302">
    gas
   </xref>
   : H
   <sub>
    2
   </sub>
   O, for example, occurs in the form of
   <xref articleid="108437">
    ice
   </xref>
   (solid), water (liquid), and
   <xref articleid="69504">
    steam
   </xref>
   (gas).
  </p>
  <p>
   <xref articleid="32843">
    Equilibrium
   </xref>
   refers to the stable coexistence of two or more phases and is established relative to time. If two phases in a mixture of water and ice coexist so that the amount of each is fixed indefinitely, they are said to be in equilibrium. The minerals of some rocks have existed together since their formation for periods of several million years, yet one cannot always ascertain if these rock constituents are in equilibrium or are still undergoing changes.
  </p>
  <p>
   A determining factor of the equilibrium state of minerals is the presence (or absence) of a reaction rim, which is a region separating two or more minerals and consisting of the products of a
   <xref articleid="442482">
    reaction
   </xref>
   between them. The absence of any observable reaction rims between minerals that physically touch each other suggests that they were in equilibrium at the time when the rock formed. Additional chemical data regarding elemental distribution between the minerals is necessary to verify this assumption. In contrast, the presence of megascopically or microscopically visible rims indicates that some minerals were not in equilibrium.
   <xref articleid="109691">
    Garnet
   </xref>
   , for example, may react with coexisting biotite to produce a chlorite rim between them, revealing that the two minerals were not always in equilibrium. An experimental petrologist must assign some period of time after which the absence of further changes between phases will indicate that equilibrium has been reached. The time period is variable, depending on the speed of the reactions involved and in part on the patience of the investigator; it may range from a few hours to several years.
  </p>
  <p>
   Components are the minimum number of independent chemical species that are necessary to describe the compositions of all the phases present in a system. The
   <xref articleid="110804">
    compound
   </xref>
   H
   <sub>
    2
   </sub>
   O is generally used as the sole component defining the H
   <sub>
    2
   </sub>
   O system, although H
   <sub>
    2
   </sub>
   and O
   <sub>
    2
   </sub>
   define the chemical system as well. In examinations of the stability fields of MgSiO
   <sub>
    3
   </sub>
   (
   <xref articleid="32702">
    enstatite
   </xref>
   ), MgSiO
   <sub>
    3
   </sub>
   is normally used as the component rather than the three elements, Mg, Si, and O, or the two oxides, MgO and SiO
   <sub>
    2
   </sub>
   . The three components generally used in the
   <xref articleid="109687">
    pyroxene
   </xref>
   system CaO-MgO-FeO-SiO
   <sub>
    2
   </sub>
   are CaSiO
   <sub>
    3
   </sub>
   -MgSiO
   <sub>
    3
   </sub>
   -FeSiO
   <sub>
    3
   </sub>
   .
  </p>
  <h2 id="h80407">
   <title>
    Assemblage and the phase rule
   </title>
   <p>
    In the early stages of the study of a rock, the constituent minerals of the rock must be identified.
    <xref articleid="57477">
     Orthoclase
    </xref>
    ,
    <xref articleid="5461">
     albite
    </xref>
    , quartz, and
    <xref articleid="79282">
     biotite
    </xref>
    may be found in an igneous granite. By examining the granite’s texture, one may conclude that the four minerals crystallized at approximately the same elevated temperature and that orthoclase-albite-quartz-biotite is its mineral assemblage. The term assemblage is frequently applied to all minerals included in a rock but more appropriately should be used for those minerals that are in equilibrium (and are known more specifically as the equilibrium assemblage). The granite discussed above may display surficial cavities that are lined by several clay minerals and limonite (a hydrous iron oxide). The original high-temperature granite was altered to form the low-temperature
    <xref articleid="109692">
     clay minerals
    </xref>
    and
    <xref articleid="48321">
     limonite
    </xref>
    ; there are consequently two distinct assemblages present in the rock: the high-temperature orthoclase-albite-quartz-biotite assemblage and the low-temperature assemblage of clay minerals and limonite.
   </p>
   <p>
    <xref articleid="109698">
     Metamorphic rocks
    </xref>
    also may contain separate assemblages. A shale that at low temperatures was composed of a
    <xref articleid="66849">
     sericite
    </xref>
    -
    <xref articleid="44637">
     kaolin
    </xref>
    -
    <xref articleid="109694">
     dolomite
    </xref>
    -
    <xref articleid="62182">
     quartz
    </xref>
    -
    <xref articleid="109684">
     feldspar
    </xref>
    assemblage can become metamorphosed at higher temperatures to produce a garnet-
    <xref articleid="67789">
     sillimanite
    </xref>
    -biotite-feldspar assemblage.
   </p>
   <p>
    An assemblage thus consists of minerals that formed under the same or quite comparable conditions of
    <xref articleid="61303">
     pressure
    </xref>
    and
    <xref articleid="71632">
     temperature
    </xref>
    . In practice, minerals that physically touch one another with no reaction rims or alteration products are included in the assemblage. It is likely that the minerals satisfying these conditions are in equilibrium, but additional chemical tests are commonly necessary to define the equilibrium assemblage without ambiguity.
   </p>
   <p>
    Phase systems are governed by a
    <xref articleid="59596">
     phase rule
    </xref>
    , which defines the number of minerals that may coexist in equilibrium: F = C − P + 2, where F is the
    <xref articleid="74850">
     variance
    </xref>
    , or number of degrees of freedom, C is the number of independent components, and P is the number of phases. Applying this rule to a three-phase, three-component system, F is 2. This indicates that two parameters—e.g., pressure and temperature—may be varied independently of one another without altering the number of phases.
   </p>
  </h2>
  <h2 id="h80408">
   <title>
    Phase diagrams
   </title>
   <p>
    <xref articleid="59595">
     Phase (or stability) diagrams
    </xref>
    are used to illustrate the conditions under which certain minerals are stable. They are graphs that show the limiting conditions for solid, liquid, and gaseous phases of a single substance or of a mixture of substances while undergoing changes in pressure and temperature or in some other combination of variables. The following are examples of phase diagrams employed in the study of
    <xref articleid="109696">
     igneous
    </xref>
    ,
    <xref articleid="109698">
     metamorphic
    </xref>
    , and
    <xref articleid="109697">
     sedimentary rocks
    </xref>
    .
   </p>
   <h3 id="h80409">
    <title>
     Use in igneous petrology
    </title>
    <p>
     <assembly id="a2493" url="/assembly/view/2493">
      <media mediaid="2645" type="image" url="/45/2645-004-D5B083C4.jpg"/>
      <caption>
       Figure 15: Melting relations among minerals in the system SiO
       <sub>
        2
       </sub>
       (quartz)–KAlSiO
       <sub>
        4
       </sub>
       (kalsilite)–Mg
       <sub>
        2
       </sub>
       SiO
       <sub>
        4
       </sub>
       (forsterite). Temperatures next to compositions refer to the melting points of those compositions in °C. Protoenstatite, instead of enstatite, is produced in experiments of this type. The compositions of protoenstatite and enstatite are identical, but their structures differ.
      </caption>
      <credit>
       Encyclopædia Britannica, Inc.
      </credit>
     </assembly>
     <assemblyref assemblyid="a2493"/>
     In the field of igneous petrology, the researcher commonly employs a phase equilibrium approach to compare the mineral assemblages found in naturally occurring and synthetic rocks. Much can be learned from studying the
     <xref articleid="72070">
      melting
     </xref>
     of an igneous rock and the reverse process, the crystallization of minerals from a melt (liquid phase). Graphic representations of systems with a liquid phase are called liquidus diagrams. The dashed contours of a liquidus diagram, called isotherms, represent temperatures at which a mineral melts. They define what is known as a liquidus surface. As temperatures decrease, the minerals will crystallize in the manner defined by the arrows on the boundaries separating the different mineral phases. A careful study of the crystalline products formed upon the cooling of melts of specific compositions allows the igneous petrologist to compare such results with minerals observed in natural igneous rocks.
    </p>
   </h3>
   <h3 id="h80410">
    <title>
     Use in metamorphic petrology
    </title>
    <p>
     Pressure-temperature (P-T) phase diagrams are applied in the study of the conditions under which metamorphic rocks originate. They illustrate the equilibrium relationships among various mineral phases in terms of pressure and temperature. The minerals that are separated by a reaction curve may exist in equilibrium at the conditions occurring along lines present within the diagram. For example, the reaction curves for Al
     <sub>
      2
     </sub>
     SiO
     <sub>
      5
     </sub>
     and for
     <xref articleid="54407">
      muscovite
     </xref>
     + quartz ←→
     <xref articleid="61048">
      potassium
     </xref>
     -feldspar + sillimanite + H
     <sub>
      2
     </sub>
     O are significant in metamorphic rocks that have a high aluminum oxide (Al
     <sub>
      2
     </sub>
     O
     <sub>
      3
     </sub>
     ) content as compared to other components (e.g., calcium oxide [CaO], magnesium oxide [MgO], and ferrous oxide [FeO]).
     <xref articleid="67095">
      Shales
     </xref>
     enriched in clay minerals contain a rather large amount of aluminum oxide, and during metamorphism of the shale mineral reactions and recrystallization occur. In their metamorphic form, shales appear as pelitic
     <xref articleid="66136">
      schists
     </xref>
     , and these may include significant amounts of sillimanite, muscovite, and quartz. Such a schist may have equilibrated under a certain set of pressure and temperature conditions.
    </p>
    <p>
     Theoretical calculations are combined with experimental observations to arrive at phase diagrams. In laboratory experiments conducted on the three
     <xref articleid="60704">
      polymorphs
     </xref>
     of Al
     <sub>
      2
     </sub>
     SiO
     <sub>
      5
     </sub>
     , chemicals of high purity are most often used as the starting materials, but extremely pure minerals may be substituted. A specimen of gem-grade
     <xref articleid="46563">
      kyanite
     </xref>
     that does not contain any inclusions may be reacted at high temperatures to form
     <xref articleid="67789">
      sillimanite
     </xref>
     . The placement of the reaction curve between the kyanite and sillimanite fields is determined by the first instance of sillimanite formation from kyanite and also the initial stage of the reverse reaction.
     <xref articleid="77657">
      X-ray powder diffraction
     </xref>
     and optical microscopic techniques are employed to estimate the conditions under which these reactions commence, but the experimental methods are subject to some degree of uncertainty. Therefore, the reaction curves, although commonly drawn as narrow lines, may actually represent wider reaction zones. Also, the naturally occurring system is more complex than the simplified version devised in the laboratory, and so difficulty arises when attempting to relate the two. A P-T diagram serves mainly as a tool in evaluating the conditions of metamorphism, such as pressure and temperature.
    </p>
   </h3>
   <h3 id="h80411">
    <title>
     Use in sedimentary petrology
    </title>
    <p>
     Phase diagrams can also be helpful in the assessment of physical and chemical conditions that prevailed during the deposition of a chemical sedimentary sequence. Atmospheric conditions are characterized by low temperatures and pressures, and under such conditions stability fields of minerals can often conveniently be expressed in terms of Eh (
     <xref articleid="110112">
      oxidation
     </xref>
     potential) and
     <xref articleid="59549">
      pH
     </xref>
     (the negative
     <xref articleid="48759">
      logarithm
     </xref>
     of the hydrogen ion concentration [H
     <sup>
      +
     </sup>
     ]; a pH of 0–7 indicates acidity, a pH of 7–14 indicates basicity, and neutral solutions have a pH of 7).
    </p>
    <p>
     Stability relations for some iron oxides and iron sulfides are often presented at atmospheric conditions, 25 °C (77 °F) and one
     <xref articleid="10118">
      standard atmosphere
     </xref>
     pressure. (One standard atmosphere of pressure equals 760 millimetres, or 29.92 inches, of
     <xref articleid="52102">
      mercury
     </xref>
     .) A high Eh value corresponds to a compound stable under oxidizing conditions, such as
     <xref articleid="39951">
      hematite
     </xref>
     , while a low Eh value indicates a mineral that occurs in reducing environments, such as magnetite.
     <xref articleid="62054">
      Pyrite
     </xref>
     and
     <xref articleid="62069">
      pyrrhotite
     </xref>
     , two sulfide minerals, occur at low Eh values and at pH values of 4–9. Lines separating the fields of an Eh-pH diagram represent conditions under which the two minerals may exist in equilibrium. Hematite and
     <xref articleid="50036">
      magnetite
     </xref>
     , for example, are often found together in iron-bearing sediments. Eh-pH diagrams are valuable in providing information regarding the chemical and physical environments that existed during atmospheric weathering and during chemical sedimentation and
     <xref articleid="30248">
      diagenesis
     </xref>
     of sediments deposited by water at temperatures of 25 to about 100 °C (77 to about 212 °F) and at a pressure of approximately one atmosphere. Τhe coexistence of hematite and magnetite common in Precambrian iron-bearing rocks (those formed from 4.6 billion to 541 million years ago) may enable investigators to estimate variables such as Eh and pH that prevailed in the original ancient sedimentary basin.
    </p>
    <signature>
     Cornelis Klein
    </signature>
   </h3>
  </h2>
 </h1>
 <h1 id="h80412">
  <title>
   Bibliography
  </title>
  <p>
   Standard mineralogical reference works include
   <e type="smallcap">
    W.A. Deer
   </e>
   ,
   <e type="smallcap">
    R.A. Howie
   </e>
   , and
   <e type="smallcap">
    J. Zussman
   </e>
   ,
   <e type="italic">
    Rock-Forming Minerals
   </e>
   , 5 vol., 2nd ed. (2001);
   <e type="smallcap">
    W.A. Deer
   </e>
   ,
   <e type="italic">
    An Introduction to the Rock-Forming Minerals
   </e>
   (2013);
   <e type="smallcap">
    Cornelis Klein
   </e>
   ,
   <e type="italic">
    Manual of Mineral Science (after James D. Dana)
   </e>
   , 23rd ed. (2008);
   <e type="smallcap">
    Annibale Mottana
   </e>
   ,
   <e type="smallcap">
    Rodolfo Crespi
   </e>
   , and
   <e type="smallcap">
    Giuseppe Liborio
   </e>
   ,
   <e type="italic">
    Simon and Schuster’s Guide to Rocks and Minerals
   </e>
   (1987; also published as
   <e type="italic">
    The MacDonald Encyclopedia of Rocks and Minerals
   </e>
   , 1983); and
   <e type="smallcap">
    Malcolm E. Black
   </e>
   ,
   <e type="italic">
    Fleischer’s Glossary of Mineral Species
   </e>
   (2014). Useful texts and monographs include
   <e type="smallcap">
    Harvey Blatt
   </e>
   ,
   <e type="smallcap">
    Robert J. Tracy
   </e>
   , and
   <e type="smallcap">
    Brent E. Owens
   </e>
   ,
   <e type="italic">
    Petrology: Igneous, Sedimentary, and Metamorphic
   </e>
   , 3rd ed. (2006);
   <e type="smallcap">
    Alexander R. McBirney
   </e>
   ,
   <e type="italic">
    Igneous Petrology
   </e>
   , 3rd ed. (2007);
   <e type="smallcap">
    Cornelis Klein
   </e>
   ,
   <e type="italic">
    Minerals and Rocks: Exercises in Crystallography, Mineralogy, and Hand Specimen Petrology
   </e>
   (1994);
   <e type="smallcap">
    Loren A. Raymond
   </e>
   ,
   <e type="italic">
    Petrology: The Study of Igneous, Sedimentary and Metamorphic Rocks
   </e>
   , 2nd ed. (2007); and
   <e type="smallcap">
    Andrew Putnis
   </e>
   ,
   <e type="italic">
    Introduction to Mineral Sciences
   </e>
   (2008). Discussions of minerals as natural resources and industrial commodities can be found in
   <e type="smallcap">
    Mario E. Rossi
   </e>
   and
   <e type="smallcap">
    Clayton V. Deutsch
   </e>
   ,
   <e type="italic">
    Mineral Resource Estimation
   </e>
   (2016); and
   <e type="smallcap">
    Alastair J. Sinclair
   </e>
   and
   <e type="smallcap">
    Garston H. Blackwell
   </e>
   ,
   <e type="italic">
    Applied Mineral Inventory Estimation
   </e>
   (2006). Lists and descriptions of various minerals can be found in
   <e type="smallcap">
    Chris Pellant
   </e>
   ,
   <e type="italic">
    Smithsonian Handbooks: Rocks &amp; Minerals
   </e>
   (2009);
   <e type="smallcap">
    John Farndon
   </e>
   ,
   <e type="italic">
    The Illustrated Guide to Rocks &amp; Minerals: How to Find, Identify and Collect the World’s Most Fascinating Specimens
   </e>
   (2012); and
   <e type="smallcap">
    Ole Johnsen
   </e>
   ,
   <e type="italic">
    Minerals of the World
   </e>
   (2007).
  </p>
  <signature>
   Cornelis Klein
  </signature>
  <signature>
   EB Editors
  </signature>
 </h1>
 <copyright>
  Encyclopædia Britannica
 </copyright>
</article>