<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "syndication_xml.dtd">
<article articleid="109773" articletypeid="1" language="en_us" lastupdate="2021-Jul-01 04:30:44" url="/article/Italic-languages/109773" version="6">
 <title>
  Italic languages
 </title>
 <p>
  <assembly id="a2089" url="/assembly/view/2089">
   <title>
    Italic languages
   </title>
   <media mediaid="2036" type="image" url="/36/2036-004-36C3D810.jpg"/>
   <caption>
    Map showing the approximate extent of the Italic and neighbouring languages about 250
    <e type="smallcap">
     bce
    </e>
    .
   </caption>
   <credit>
    Encyclopædia Britannica, Inc.
   </credit>
  </assembly>
  <e type="bold">
   Italic languages
  </e>
  ,
  <assemblyref assemblyid="a2089"/>
  certain
  <xref articleid="109767">
   Indo-European languages
  </xref>
  that were once spoken in the Apennine Peninsula (modern
  <xref articleid="106448">
   Italy
  </xref>
  ) and in the eastern part of the
  <xref articleid="60492">
   Po
  </xref>
  valley. These include the
  <xref articleid="47296">
   Latin
  </xref>
  ,
  <xref articleid="33625">
   Faliscan
  </xref>
  ,
  <xref articleid="57533">
   Osco-Umbrian
  </xref>
  ,
  <xref articleid="2843">
   South Picene
  </xref>
  , and
  <xref articleid="75017">
   Venetic
  </xref>
  languages, which have in common a considerable number of features that separate them from the other languages of the same area—e.g., from
  <xref articleid="109772">
   Greek
  </xref>
  and
  <xref articleid="109818">
   Etruscan
  </xref>
  . (In a more narrow sense, the term Italic languages excludes Latin and denotes only Osco-Umbrian, South Picene, Faliscan, and Venetic.)
 </p>
 <p>
  For a long time the Italic languages have been considered to be an Indo-European subfamily like
  <xref articleid="109782">
   Celtic
  </xref>
  ,
  <xref articleid="109775">
   Germanic
  </xref>
  , or
  <xref articleid="109784">
   Slavic
  </xref>
  . Today some scholars are inclined to distinguish within the so-called Italic branch at least three independent members of the Indo-European family: Latin (with Faliscan), Osco-Umbrian (with South Picene), and Venetic (if indeed this is an Italic language, as will be assumed in this article). They attribute the similarities—i.e., the unifying phenomena in the division—to a convergence that took place when the speakers of these different idioms were integrated into the “Italic” civilization of the early 1st millennium
  <e type="smallcap">
   bce
  </e>
  . The culture that resulted is known as the “Etruscan koine.”
 </p>
 <h1 id="h74673">
  <title>
   Distribution and origins
  </title>
  <h2 id="h74674">
   <title>
    Languages of the group
   </title>
   <h3 id="h74675">
    <title>
     Latin
    </title>
    <p>
     Latin is the language of
     <xref articleid="47305">
      Latium
     </xref>
     and of
     <xref articleid="109501">
      Rome
     </xref>
     ; its earliest known documents date to the 6th century
     <e type="smallcap">
      bce
     </e>
     . Rich epigraphic evidence and an extensive literature began at the end of the 3rd century
     <e type="smallcap">
      bce
     </e>
     , at the time when Roman Latin was emerging as the predominant language of Italy. By 100
     <e type="smallcap">
      ce
     </e>
     at the latest, Latin had effaced all the other dialects between Sicily and the Alps, with the exception of Greek in the colonies of
     <xref articleid="50004">
      Magna Graecia
     </xref>
     .
    </p>
    <p>
     The other Italic languages—Italic languages in the narrow sense—are known through local and personal names transmitted by Greek and Roman sources, and especially from inscriptions.
    </p>
   </h3>
   <h3 id="h74676">
    <title>
     Oscan
    </title>
    <p>
     Before Latin spread out, Oscan was the most widely spoken group of dialects of the Apennine Peninsula. It was used by the
     <xref articleid="65219">
      Samnites
     </xref>
     in Samnium and
     <xref articleid="19840">
      Campania
     </xref>
     , by the inhabitants of
     <xref articleid="49228">
      Lucania
     </xref>
     and Bruttium, and, with slight variations, by smaller tribes between Latium and the Adriatic coast—the
     <xref articleid="75693">
      Volsci
     </xref>
     ,
     <xref articleid="51124">
      Marsi
     </xref>
     ,
     <xref articleid="57961">
      Paeligni
     </xref>
     ,
     <xref articleid="75188">
      Vestini
     </xref>
     , and
     <xref articleid="51080">
      Marrucini
     </xref>
     . (Those distinct “minor dialects” within the Oscan language continuum are referred to as
     <xref articleid="75694">
      Volscian
     </xref>
     , Marsian, Paelignian, etc., and collectively as
     <xref articleid="64616">
      Sabellic
     </xref>
     , or Sabellian, dialects; this term can also refer more generally to the Italic languages other than Latin and Venetic, roughly comparable to the narrow sense of the term Italic languages.) The legendary
     <xref articleid="64624">
      Sabines
     </xref>
     , who shared the earliest history of Rome, probably also spoke an Oscan dialect. The most important Oscan texts come from Campanian cities, as do the oldest ones (several so-called Paleo-Oscan, or “Pre-Samnite,” vessel inscriptions of the form “I belong to So-and-so,” dating to as early as the mid-6th century
     <e type="smallcap">
      bce
     </e>
     ). The largest text, a treaty between
     <xref articleid="56042">
      Nola
     </xref>
     and Abella from the 2nd century
     <e type="smallcap">
      bce
     </e>
     , is carved on a stone slab, called the Cippus Abellanus. In Bantia, a nearly unknown town of Lucania, the Tabula Bantina is preserved, the most extensive Oscan inscription. It is a bronze tablet with penal laws concerning municipal administration, written in Latin letters during the first half of the 1st century
     <e type="smallcap">
      bce
     </e>
     . The oldest Oscan text of any length is the so-called Agnone Tablet of about 250
     <e type="smallcap">
      bce
     </e>
     (a small bronze tablet found near Fonte Romito, between Agnone and Capracotta), detailing cultic instructions related to the worship of
     <xref articleid="22141">
      Ceres
     </xref>
     and other divinities. The remainder of the Oscan corpus includes diverse material, some of which is of considerable cultural interest (short cultic and sacrificial texts, curse tablets, and several types of municipal inscriptions).
    </p>
   </h3>
   <h3 id="h74677">
    <title>
     Umbrian
    </title>
    <p>
     The Umbrian idiom, closely related to Oscan, is known from a few small inscriptions and from the Tabulae Iguvinae (
     <xref articleid="42077">
      Iguvine Tables
     </xref>
     ), which consist of seven bronze tablets found at
     <xref articleid="38348">
      Gubbio
     </xref>
     (the ancient Iguvium). Constituting one of the largest and most important epigraphic documents of antiquity, the tablets contain ritual regulations of a sacred brotherhood to which a considerable part of the public cults of Iguvium was delegated. The Tabulae Iguvinae were incised, partly in the Umbrian alphabet and partly in Latin letters, within the last three centuries
     <e type="smallcap">
      bce
     </e>
     , but portions of the text itself result from a far more remote
     <xref articleid="477034">
      oral tradition
     </xref>
     .
    </p>
   </h3>
   <h3 id="h74678">
    <title>
     South Picene
    </title>
    <p>
     Approximately two dozen short inscriptions from the southern part of ancient Picenum (most of them found near
     <xref articleid="9795">
      Ascoli Piceno
     </xref>
     and
     <xref articleid="71740">
      Teramo
     </xref>
     ) preserve extremely early remains (6th and 5th centuries
     <e type="smallcap">
      bce
     </e>
     ) of the Italic language now known as South Picene. Formerly referred to as Old Sabellian or Central Adriatic, South Picene shows close affinities to Oscan and Umbrian. (North Picene, known mainly from a 12-line inscription of about 500
     <e type="smallcap">
      bce
     </e>
     on a stele from Novilara, is not an Italic language and may not even be an Indo-European language.)
    </p>
   </h3>
   <h3 id="h74679">
    <title>
     Faliscan
    </title>
    <p>
     <assembly id="a2092" url="/assembly/view/2092">
      <title>
       Faliscan language
      </title>
      <media mediaid="2040" type="image" url="/40/2040-004-62CAB1C2.jpg"/>
      <caption>
       Faliscan inscription on a bowl:
       <e type="italic">
        foied.uino.pipafo.cra.carefo
       </e>
       . (Latin
       <e type="italic">
        Hodie vinum bibam, cras carebo.
       </e>
       ) “Today I shall drink wine, tomorrow I shall have nothing.”
      </caption>
      <credit>
       Encyclopædia Britannica, Inc.
      </credit>
     </assembly>
     <assemblyref assemblyid="a2092"/>
     Faliscan inscriptions appear only in the immediate surroundings of Falerii (the present
     <xref articleid="82768">
      Civita Castellana
     </xref>
     in central Italy), which, except for its dialect, seems to have been a completely
     <xref articleid="33158">
      Etruscan
     </xref>
     city. The Faliscan corpus consists mainly of short sepulchral inscriptions, most of which date to the 4th century
     <e type="smallcap">
      bce
     </e>
     and later. There are, however, several important Archaic Faliscan vessel inscriptions, including some from as early as the 6th century
     <e type="smallcap">
      bce
     </e>
     that show evidence of
     <xref articleid="110446">
      poetic composition
     </xref>
     .
    </p>
   </h3>
   <h3 id="h322316">
    <title>
     Venetic
    </title>
    <p>
     The language represented by inscriptions from the territory of the
     <xref articleid="75011">
      Veneti
     </xref>
     —between the
     <xref articleid="60492">
      Po River
     </xref>
     , the
     <xref articleid="20408">
      Carnic Alps
     </xref>
     , and
     <xref articleid="43006">
      Istria
     </xref>
     —is called Venetic. The majority of discoveries come from sanctuaries at
     <xref articleid="33073">
      Este
     </xref>
     and Làgole di Calalzo. The Venetic inscriptions (of which there are about 300, ranging from the 5th to the 1st century
     <e type="smallcap">
      bce
     </e>
     ) consist almost entirely of brief epitaphs and dedications.
    </p>
   </h3>
   <h3 id="h322317">
    <title>
     Unclassified
    </title>
    <p>
     Several very early texts cannot be ascribed with certainty to any of the individual languages listed above but show linguistic features of a broadly Osco-Umbrian/South Picene type. The most important of these is found on an inscribed flask from Poggio Sommavilla (in Sabine territory), dating from the end of the 7th century
     <e type="smallcap">
      bce
     </e>
     .
    </p>
   </h3>
   <h3 id="h322318">
    <title>
     Writing systems
    </title>
    <p>
     <assembly id="a2090" url="/assembly/view/2090">
      <title>
       Oscan language
      </title>
      <media mediaid="2037" type="image" url="/37/2037-004-2C44F720.jpg"/>
      <caption>
       Oscan inscription from the Cippus Abellanus:
       <e type="italic">
        púst.feíhúís.pús. físnam.am / fret.eíseí.tereí.nep.abel / lanús.nep.núvlanús. pídum /…
       </e>
       [
       <e type="italic">
        ú
       </e>
       represents
       <e type="italic">
        o
       </e>
       ]. (Latin
       <e type="italic">
        Post muros qui fanum circumdant, in eo territorio neque Abellani neque Nolani quicquam
       </e>
       [
       <e type="italic">
        aedificaverint
       </e>
       ].) “Behind the walls which go around the sanctuary, in this area neither the inhabitants of Abella nor the inhabitants of Nola [are allowed to construct] anything.”
      </caption>
      <credit>
       Encyclopædia Britannica, Inc.
      </credit>
     </assembly>
     <assembly id="a2091" url="/assembly/view/2091">
      <title>
       Umbrian language
      </title>
      <media mediaid="2038" type="image" url="/38/2038-004-E20B0EC3.jpg"/>
      <caption>
       Passus in Umbrian from the Iguvine Tables:
       <e type="italic">
        pus veres treplanes tref sif kumiaf feitu / trebe iuvie ukriper fisiu tutaper ikuvina
       </e>
       [
       <e type="italic">
        u
       </e>
       represents
       <e type="italic">
        u
       </e>
       and
       <e type="italic">
        o
       </e>
       ,
       <e type="italic">
        k
       </e>
       represents
       <e type="italic">
        k
       </e>
       and
       <e type="italic">
        g
       </e>
       ]. (Latin
       <e type="italic">
        Post portam Trebulanam tres sues gravidas facito Trebo Iovio pro arce Fisia, pro civitate Iguvina
       </e>
       .) “Behind the Trebulan gate he shall sacrifice three pregnant sows to [the god] Trebus lovius, for the Fisian citadel, for the state of Iguvium.”
      </caption>
      <credit>
       Encyclopædia Britannica, Inc.
      </credit>
     </assembly>
     The scripts used for writing these languages include the
     <xref articleid="37912">
      Greek alphabet
     </xref>
     in Bruttium and Lucania and the
     <xref articleid="47291">
      Latin alphabet
     </xref>
     and various derivations of the
     <xref articleid="33159">
      Etruscan alphabet
     </xref>
     in the other regions. Five “national” or “native” alphabets are distinguished:,
     <assemblyref assemblyid="a2092">
      Faliscan
     </assemblyref>
     ,
     <assemblyref assemblyid="a2090">
      Oscan
     </assemblyref>
     , and
     <assemblyref assemblyid="a2091">
      Umbrian
     </assemblyref>
     .
    </p>
   </h3>
  </h2>
  <h2 id="h74681">
   <title>
    Origins of the Italic languages
   </title>
   <p>
    The Italic languages must have been brought from the original area of the Indo-European languages, perhaps in eastern parts of central Europe, when their speakers crossed the
    <xref articleid="106056">
     Alps
    </xref>
    . This is attested to by a stratum of very old place-names of non-Indo-European origin—e.g., Tarracina (modern
    <xref articleid="71785">
     Terracina
    </xref>
    ),
    <xref articleid="20193">
     Capua
    </xref>
    —that covers not only the Apennine Peninsula but also
    <xref articleid="106266">
     Greece
    </xref>
    and
    <xref articleid="111079">
     Anatolia
    </xref>
    . This stratum is ascribed to a “Mediterranean” language believed to have dominated large parts of the ancient world before the arrival of the Indo-European peoples. Nothing is known about the date, the path, and the circumstances of the above-mentioned immigration, and none of the many attempts to combine archaeological evidence with linguistic prehistory has led to convincing results. Thus, the only resources available for studying the Italic languages are exclusively linguistic methods of comparative philology.
   </p>
  </h2>
 </h1>
 <h1 id="h74682">
  <title>
   Linguistic characteristics
  </title>
  <h2 id="h74683">
   <title>
    Phonology
   </title>
   <p>
    Many of the phonetic processes that make the attested Italic languages differ from the reconstructed Indo-European language seem to have occurred relatively late in time. The only one that can confidently be placed outside of Italy—that is, before the immigration over the Alps—is the change to
    <e type="italic">
     ss
    </e>
    in combinations of
    <e type="italic">
     d
    </e>
    (dental occlusive, or dental stop) +
    <e type="italic">
     t
    </e>
    . This is a feature common to
    <xref articleid="109782">
     Celtic
    </xref>
    ,
    <xref articleid="109775">
     Germanic
    </xref>
    , and the Italic languages. For example,
    <xref articleid="47296">
     Latin
    </xref>
    <e type="italic">
     visus
    </e>
    comes from the older, reconstructed form *
    <e type="italic">
     wissos
    </e>
    ‘seen’; this is cognate with
    <xref articleid="36570">
     High German
    </xref>
    <e type="italic">
     gi-wiss
    </e>
    ‘surely known’ and Old
    <xref articleid="109782" refid="h74854">
     Irish
    </xref>
    <e type="italic">
     ro-fess
    </e>
    ‘is known,’ all of these forms deriving from an Indo-European term *
    <e type="italic">
     wid-to-s
    </e>
    , with
    <e type="italic">
     d
    </e>
    +
    <e type="italic">
     t
    </e>
    . (An asterisk [*] before a word means that it is not attested but reconstructed.)
   </p>
   <p>
    The development of the Indo-European labiovelar stop
    <e type="italic">
     k
     <sup>
      w
     </sup>
    </e>
    is more complex. (A labiovelar stop is a sound pronounced with simultaneous articulation—movement—of the lips and the velum, the soft palate.) From this sound there has resulted a
    <e type="italic">
     qu
    </e>
    in Latin,
    <e type="italic">
     p
    </e>
    in Osco-Umbrian and South Picene,
    <e type="italic">
     c
    </e>
    in Irish, and
    <e type="italic">
     p
    </e>
    in
    <xref articleid="17838">
     Brythonic Celtic
    </xref>
    ; e.g., Latin
    <e type="italic">
     quis
    </e>
    ‘who(ever)’ is cognate with Oscan
    <e type="italic">
     pis
    </e>
    and Umbrian
    <e type="italic">
     pis
    </e>
    (similarly South Picene
    <e type="italic">
     pim
    </e>
    ‘whom[ever]’ or ‘which[ever]’), these forms deriving from Indo-European *
    <e type="italic">
     k
     <sup>
      w
     </sup>
     is
    </e>
    ; and Irish
    <e type="italic">
     cia
    </e>
    is related to
    <xref articleid="76520">
     Welsh
    </xref>
    <e type="italic">
     pwy
    </e>
    , ‘who,’ derived from Indo-European *
    <e type="italic">
     k
     <sup>
      w
     </sup>
     ei
    </e>
    . Some scholars have tried to trace this development back to an Italo-Celtic unity, but the change of Brythonic
    <e type="italic">
     k
     <sup>
      w
     </sup>
    </e>
    to
    <e type="italic">
     p
    </e>
    is surely later than the dropping of the
    <e type="italic">
     p
    </e>
    in Common Celtic. It is sounder, therefore, to assume independent processes in the different languages.
   </p>
   <p>
    Other features developed in Italy itself—e.g., the use of the voiceless dental spirant (
    <xref articleid="35410">
     fricative
    </xref>
    )
    <e type="italic">
     f
    </e>
    that is shared with Etruscan and is lacking in marginal districts of Venetic. In all Italic languages this
    <e type="italic">
     f
    </e>
    sound replaced the Indo-European voiced aspirated sounds (represented as
    <e type="italic">
     bh, dh, g
     <sup>
      w
     </sup>
     h
    </e>
    ) in initial position. Examples of the use of
    <e type="italic">
     f
    </e>
    in Italic are as follows: Latin
    <e type="italic">
     frater
    </e>
    ‘brother’ = Umbrian
    <e type="italic">
     frater
    </e>
    , from Indo-European *
    <e type="italic">
     bhrātēr
    </e>
    ; Latin
    <e type="italic">
     facio
    </e>
    ‘I do, make’ is related to Oscan
    <e type="italic">
     fakiiad
    </e>
    ‘he should do’ and Venetic
    <e type="italic">
     fagsto
    </e>
    ‘he made,’ based on an Indo-European stem *
    <e type="italic">
     dhə-k-
    </e>
    . A more recent common process in Latin and Osco-Umbrian is the use of the full system of five short vowels in initial syllables only; short vowels of noninitial syllables in Latin became less open—e.g.,
    <e type="italic">
     facio
    </e>
    ‘I do, make,’ but
    <e type="italic">
     in-ficio
    </e>
    , the compound of
    <e type="italic">
     in
    </e>
    +
    <e type="italic">
     facio
    </e>
    . In Osco-Umbrian these vowels tend to be lost completely—e.g., Umbrian
    <e type="italic">
     benust
    </e>
    ‘he will have come,’ but Oscan
    <e type="italic">
     cebnust
    </e>
    ‘he will have come near.’ Some differences between Latin and Osco-Umbrian/South Picene probably arose during the last centuries
    <e type="smallcap">
     bce
    </e>
    —e.g., Osco-Umbrian/South Picene
    <e type="italic">
     ō
    </e>
    changed to
    <e type="italic">
     u
    </e>
    (Oscan
    <e type="italic">
     dúnúm
    </e>
    , South Picene
    <e type="italic">
     dúnoí
    </e>
    , Latin
    <e type="italic">
     dōnum
    </e>
    ‘gift’),
    <e type="italic">
     ē
    </e>
    became
    <e type="italic">
     i
    </e>
    (Oscan
    <e type="italic">
     ligud
    </e>
    , Latin
    <e type="italic">
     lēge
    </e>
    ‘law’ in the ablative singular; South Picene
    <e type="italic">
     spolítiú
    </e>
    , Latin
    <e type="italic">
     Spolētium
    </e>
    [name of a town in
    <xref articleid="74203">
     Umbria
    </xref>
    , modern
    <xref articleid="69198">
     Spoleto
    </xref>
    ]), and final
    <e type="italic">
     ā
    </e>
    developed into
    <e type="italic">
     o
    </e>
    (
    <e type="italic">
     viú
    </e>
    [
    <e type="italic">
     ú
    </e>
    in the Oscan national alphabet =
    <e type="italic">
     o
    </e>
    ], Latin
    <e type="italic">
     via
    </e>
    ‘way’). Indo-European voiced aspirated sounds (
    <e type="italic">
     bh, dh, g
     <sup>
      w
     </sup>
     h
    </e>
    ) in internal position probably first became voiced
    <xref articleid="69159">
     spirants
    </xref>
    (e.g., sounds such as
    <e type="italic">
     v
    </e>
    ) in all Italic languages and, later, voiced stops in Latin and Venetic and the voiceless spirant
    <e type="italic">
     f
    </e>
    in Osco-Umbrian, South Picene, and Faliscan. Examples of these changes (for Indo-European
    <e type="italic">
     dh
    </e>
    ) are the voiced
    <xref articleid="69822">
     stop
    </xref>
    <e type="italic">
     b
    </e>
    in Latin
    <e type="italic">
     liberi
    </e>
    ‘(free) children’ and Venetic
    <e type="italic">
     louderobos
    </e>
    ‘children’ (in the dative plural) versus the voiceless spirant
    <e type="italic">
     f
    </e>
    in Oscan
    <e type="italic">
     loufro-
    </e>
    ‘free’ and Faliscan
    <e type="italic">
     loferta
    </e>
    ‘freed woman.’ Examples for Indo-European
    <e type="italic">
     bh
    </e>
    are Oscan
    <e type="italic">
     tfei
    </e>
    , Umbrian
    <e type="italic">
     tefe
    </e>
    , South Picene
    <e type="italic">
     tefeí
    </e>
    versus Latin
    <e type="italic">
     tibi
    </e>
    ‘to/for you.’
   </p>
  </h2>
  <h2 id="h74684">
   <title>
    Morphology
   </title>
   <p>
    In contrast to the phonology, which shows so many correlations among the Italic languages, there are few definite connections between these tongues in their
    <xref articleid="37632">
     grammars
    </xref>
    . A characteristic innovation is the extension of the ablative singular case from
    <e type="italic">
     o-
    </e>
    stems and pronouns, where it occurred originally, to other declension classes: Latin
    <e type="italic">
     praidad
    </e>
    ‘with the plunder,’ later
    <e type="italic">
     praeda, meretod
    </e>
    ‘by merit,’ Oscan
    <e type="italic">
     toutad
    </e>
    ‘by the people,’
    <e type="italic">
     slaagid
    </e>
    ‘of the border,’ South Picene
    <e type="italic">
     arítih
    </e>
    (
    <e type="italic">
     -h
    </e>
    represents earlier
    <e type="italic">
     -d
    </e>
    ) ‘with skill.’ Many of the morphological features common to Osco-Umbrian, South Picene, and Latin are shared by other Indo-European languages; that is, they are not Italic in a specific sense. For example, the
    <e type="italic">
     a-
    </e>
    subjunctive—e.g., Latin
    <e type="italic">
     faciat
    </e>
    ‘may he do’ and Oscan
    <e type="italic">
     fakiiad
    </e>
    —is also Celtic; passive endings in -
    <e type="italic">
     r
    </e>
    —e.g., Oscan
    <e type="italic">
     vincter
    </e>
    and Latin
    <e type="italic">
     vincitur
    </e>
    ‘he is conquered,’ South Picene
    <e type="italic">
     qolofítúr
    </e>
    ‘he honours/supports’ or ‘honour/support is shown to’—are found in
    <xref articleid="109782">
     Celtic
    </xref>
    ,
    <xref articleid="40614">
     Hittite
    </xref>
    , and
    <xref articleid="109781">
     Tocharian
    </xref>
    as well. More important are the discrepancies. For example, the genitive singular of
    <e type="italic">
     o
    </e>
    -stems shows -
    <e type="italic">
     ī
    </e>
    in Latin, Faliscan, and Venetic and in the Celtic languages, but -
    <e type="italic">
     eis
    </e>
    in Osco-Umbrian and South Picene; the nominative plural of the same class is marked by -
    <e type="italic">
     oi
    </e>
    in early Latin, Celtic, and Greek but by -
    <e type="italic">
     ōs
    </e>
    in Osco-Umbrian, South Picene, Germanic,
    <xref articleid="65552">
     Sanskrit
    </xref>
    , and other languages. In addition, the perfect stems of secondary verbs (verbs derived from nouns or from other verbs) are formed by -
    <e type="italic">
     u
    </e>
    - or -
    <e type="italic">
     v
    </e>
    - in Latin, by -
    <e type="italic">
     t
    </e>
    (
    <e type="italic">
     t
    </e>
    )- in Oscan, by -
    <e type="italic">
     s
    </e>
    - in Venetic, and by a variety of formants in Umbrian—e.g., Latin
    <e type="italic">
     donavit
    </e>
    ‘he has given’ = Oscan
    <e type="italic">
     duunated
    </e>
    = Venetic
    <e type="italic">
     donasto
    </e>
    , Umbrian
    <e type="italic">
     combifiansiust
    </e>
    ‘he will have announced’ (with formant
    <e type="italic">
     -nky-
    </e>
    ).
   </p>
  </h2>
  <h2 id="h74685">
   <title>
    Vocabulary
   </title>
   <p>
    Lexical comparison leads to more specific data about the history of the Italic languages. There are linguistic boundaries called isoglosses that may date back to pre-Italic history: e.g., Oscan
    <e type="italic">
     humuns
    </e>
    , Latin
    <e type="italic">
     homines
    </e>
    , and Gothic
    <e type="italic">
     gumans
    </e>
    ‘human beings’ derive from an Indo-European root that meant ‘earth’; and Oscan
    <e type="italic">
     anamúm
    </e>
    ‘mind’ (accusative singular) is directly related to Latin
    <e type="italic">
     animus
    </e>
    ‘mind, soul’ and Irish
    <e type="italic">
     anam
    </e>
    ‘soul,’ these words deriving from an Indo-European root meaning ‘to breathe’ (compare Greek
    <e type="italic">
     anemos
    </e>
    ‘wind’). There are many old differences between Latin on the one hand and Osco-Umbrian (and South Picene) on the other. Latin
    <e type="italic">
     ignis
    </e>
    ‘fire’ = Sanskrit
    <e type="italic">
     agni
    </e>
    , but Umbrian
    <e type="italic">
     pir
    </e>
    ‘fire’ = Greek
    <e type="italic">
     pŷr
    </e>
    = Old English
    <e type="italic">
     fyr
    </e>
    ; Latin
    <e type="italic">
     aqua
    </e>
    ‘water’ = Gothic
    <e type="italic">
     ahwa
    </e>
    , but Umbrian
    <e type="italic">
     utur
    </e>
    ‘water’ = Greek
    <e type="italic">
     hydōr
    </e>
    = Old English
    <e type="italic">
     wæter
    </e>
    ; Latin
    <e type="italic">
     filius, filia
    </e>
    ‘son, daughter,’ but Oscan
    <e type="italic">
     puklu
    </e>
    and South Picene
    <e type="italic">
     puqloh
    </e>
    ‘son’ = Sanskrit
    <e type="italic">
     putra
    </e>
    , and Oscan
    <e type="italic">
     futír
    </e>
    ‘daughter’ = Greek
    <e type="italic">
     thygatēr
    </e>
    = Gothic
    <e type="italic">
     dauhtar
    </e>
    . Adjectives of totality in Latin are
    <e type="italic">
     omnis, cunctus, totus
    </e>
    , in Osco-Umbrian
    <e type="italic">
     sollo-, sevo-, allo-
    </e>
    (cognate to English
    <e type="italic">
     all
    </e>
    ). ‘The people’ or ‘the state’ is expressed in Latin by
    <e type="italic">
     populus
    </e>
    or
    <e type="italic">
     civitas
    </e>
    (the latter literally ‘citizenship,’ based on
    <e type="italic">
     civis
    </e>
    ‘citizen’), but by Oscan
    <e type="italic">
     touto
    </e>
    , Umbrian
    <e type="italic">
     tuta
    </e>
    , South Picene
    <e type="italic">
     toúta
    </e>
    = Irish
    <e type="italic">
     túath
    </e>
    = Gothic
    <e type="italic">
     thiuda
    </e>
    .
   </p>
   <p>
    Certain lexical fields that reflect the acquisition of the Mediterranean culture show an independent terminology. The following forms strongly suggest that Latin and Osco-Umbrian speakers were not in contact with each other when they began to build cities: Latin
    <e type="italic">
     porta
    </e>
    ‘gate,’ Oscan
    <e type="italic">
     veru
    </e>
    ‘gate’; Latin
    <e type="italic">
     arx
    </e>
    ‘citadel,’ Umbrian
    <e type="italic">
     ocar
    </e>
    ‘citadel, castle’; Latin
    <e type="italic">
     moenia
    </e>
    ‘walls, ramparts,’
    <e type="italic">
     murus
    </e>
    ‘wall,’ Oscan
    <e type="italic">
     feíhúss
    </e>
    (accusative plural) ‘walls.’ On the other hand, Latins and Osco-Umbrians adopted the same terms for ‘write’ and ‘read’; Latin
    <e type="italic">
     scribere
    </e>
    ‘to write,’ Oscan
    <e type="italic">
     scriftas
    </e>
    ‘written’; Latin
    <e type="italic">
     legere
    </e>
    ‘to read,’ Paelignian
    <e type="italic">
     lexe
    </e>
    ‘you will read.’ It is known that the Latin and Osco-Umbrian alphabets are derived from the Etruscan alphabet; the spread of these terms can, therefore, be attributed to a period of Etruscan predominance. Etruscan features are obvious in archaic Italic religion; Osco-Umbrians and Veneti adopted even the Etruscan word for ‘god’—
    <e type="italic">
     ais
    </e>
    . Many other religious terms show a close community among Italic peoples; e.g., the Latin forms
    <e type="italic">
     pius
    </e>
    ‘pious, obedient’ and
    <e type="italic">
     piare
    </e>
    ‘to honour with religious rites’ are equivalent to Volscian
    <e type="italic">
     pihom
    </e>
    (neuter singular) and Umbrian
    <e type="italic">
     pihatu
    </e>
    (imperative); Latin
    <e type="italic">
     feriae
    </e>
    ‘religious days’ is related to Oscan
    <e type="italic">
     fiisiais
    </e>
    (ablative plural); and Latin
    <e type="italic">
     sacer
    </e>
    ‘sacred,’
    <e type="italic">
     sacrare
    </e>
    ‘to consecrate, dedicate,’
    <e type="italic">
     sanctus
    </e>
    ‘consecrated’ are cognates with Oscan
    <e type="italic">
     sakrid
    </e>
    (ablative singular),
    <e type="italic">
     sakrafír
    </e>
    (subjunctive passive),
    <e type="italic">
     saahtúm
    </e>
    (neuter singular). These correspondences in religious vocabulary extend to whole phrases, some inherited from Indo-European forms of expression and therefore of very great antiquity: e.g., the Umbrian prayer formula
    <e type="italic">
     ueiro pequo…salua seritu
    </e>
    ‘keep safe men (and) livestock’ is directly comparable to Latin
    <e type="italic">
     pastores pecuaque salva servassis
    </e>
    ‘may you keep safe shepherds and livestock’ (in an ancient Roman prayer), and both are cognate with similar expressions in Vedic
    <xref articleid="65552">
     Sanskrit
    </xref>
    and
    <xref articleid="11429">
     Avestan
    </xref>
    .
   </p>
   <p>
    The
    <xref articleid="33158">
     Etruscan
    </xref>
    supremacy ended with the foundation of local republics in Rome and in other cities of Italy in approximately 500
    <e type="smallcap">
     bce
    </e>
    ; when that occurred, the unifying force of Etruscan culture lost its influence. Early republican terminology developed independently; e.g., Latin
    <e type="italic">
     consul
    </e>
    ‘consul’ but Oscan
    <e type="italic">
     meddíss
    </e>
    designate the first magistrate, to Latin
    <e type="italic">
     senatus
    </e>
    ‘senate’ corresponds Oscan
    <e type="italic">
     kúmparakineís
    </e>
    (genitive singular), and to Latin
    <e type="italic">
     comitia
    </e>
    ‘assembly’ the Oscan forms
    <e type="italic">
     comono
    </e>
    or
    <e type="italic">
     kúmbennieís
    </e>
    . The last period of Italic language history is characterized by an increasing influence of Roman models. For example, Oscan
    <e type="italic">
     ceus
    </e>
    ‘citizen’ is a Latin loanword that stems from a form *
    <e type="italic">
     ceuis
    </e>
    , which existed about 200
    <e type="smallcap">
     bce
    </e>
    and was intermediate between Old Latin
    <e type="italic">
     ceivis
    </e>
    and its later form
    <e type="italic">
     civis
    </e>
    ; Oscan
    <e type="italic">
     aídil
    </e>
    and
    <e type="italic">
     kvaísstur
    </e>
    imitate Latin
    <e type="italic">
     aedilis
    </e>
    and
    <e type="italic">
     quaestor
    </e>
    , terms for offices in the Roman government; and the Veneti adopted the Roman word for ‘freed man,’
    <e type="italic">
     libertus
    </e>
    . In addition, the Oscan Tabula Bantina slavishly copied the juridical style and terminology of the Romans.
   </p>
  </h2>
  <h2 id="h74686">
   <title>
    Poetics
   </title>
   <p>
    Beyond vocabulary, the Italic languages share features of expression that are prominent in formal modes of discourse, such as
    <xref articleid="109489">
     prayers
    </xref>
    ,
    <xref articleid="56615">
     oaths
    </xref>
    and curses, and legal formulations. For many such compositions, the distinction between “prose” and “poetry” is an artificial one: prayers or juridical formulas that otherwise appear to be prose may show elaborate structures dependent on sequences of isosyllabic cola (i.e., phrases with equal numbers of syllables, like lines of verse) or other rhythmic patterns, marked effects arising from
    <xref articleid="7890">
     antithesis
    </xref>
    or synonymy, and a high degree of
    <xref articleid="125150">
     asyndeton
    </xref>
    (i.e., lack of connective words such as
    <e type="italic">
     and
    </e>
    ). Perhaps most striking is the phonetic feature of
    <xref articleid="5821">
     alliteration
    </xref>
    , pervasive throughout early Latin poetry, as well as in formal documents composed in Oscan, Umbrian, and South Picene. For Latin and Umbrian, compare the parallel phrases
    <e type="italic">
     <e type="underline">
      s
     </e>
     alua
     <e type="italic">
      s
     </e>
     eritu
    </e>
    and
    <e type="italic">
     <e type="underline">
      s
     </e>
     alva s
     <e type="underline"/>
     ervassis
    </e>
    in the prayer mentioned above, with the latter preceded by
    <e type="italic">
     <e type="underline">
      p
     </e>
     astores
     <e type="underline">
      p
     </e>
     ecuaque
    </e>
    ; an Oscan curse includes the sequence
    <e type="italic">
     <e type="underline">
      f
     </e>
     akinss,
     <e type="underline">
      f
     </e>
     angvam,
     <e type="underline">
      b
     </e>
     iass,
     <e type="underline">
      b
     </e>
     iítam
    </e>
    ‘(I hand over to the divinity [i.e., I curse] his) deeds, tongue, strength, life’; and note the concluding sequence
    <e type="italic">
     <e type="underline">
      v
     </e>
     iat
     <e type="underline">
      v
     </e>
     epetí
    </e>
    ‘he lies in the tomb’ in the .
   </p>
   <signature>
    J&amp;#x00fc;rgen Untermann
   </signature>
   <signature>
    Brent Vine
   </signature>
  </h2>
 </h1>
 <h1 id="h74687">
  <title>
   Bibliography
  </title>
  <p>
   Detailed surveys of the Italic languages are found in
   <e type="smallcap">
    J.H.W. Penney
   </e>
   , “The Languages of Italy,” in
   <e type="smallcap">
    John Boardman
   </e>
   <e type="italic">
    et al.
   </e>
   (eds.),
   <e type="italic">
    The Cambridge Ancient History
   </e>
   , vol. 4, 2nd ed. (1988), pp. 720–738;
   <e type="smallcap">
    Vittore Pisani
   </e>
   ,
   <e type="italic">
    Le lingue dell’Italia antica oltre il Latino
   </e>
   , 2nd ed., rev. and enlarged (1964);
   <e type="smallcap">
    Giacomo Devoto
   </e>
   ,
   <e type="italic">
    Gli antichi Italici
   </e>
   , 4th ed. (1969), and
   <e type="italic">
    The Languages of Italy
   </e>
   (1978; originally published in Italian, 1974);
   <e type="smallcap">
    Aldo L. Prosdocimi
   </e>
   (ed.),
   <e type="italic">
    Lingue e dialetti dell’Italia antica
   </e>
   (1978), with additions and indices published separately with the same title, ed. by
   <e type="smallcap">
    Anna Marinetti
   </e>
   (1982); and
   <e type="smallcap">
    D. Silvestri
   </e>
   , “Le lingue italiche,” in
   <e type="smallcap">
    Anna Giacalone Ramat
   </e>
   and
   <e type="smallcap">
    Paolo Ramat
   </e>
   (eds.),
   <e type="italic">
    Le lingue indoeuropee
   </e>
   (1993), pp. 349–371. The historical background to the Italic languages is treated by
   <e type="smallcap">
    Massimo Pallottino
   </e>
   ,
   <e type="italic">
    A History of Earliest Italy
   </e>
   (1991; originally published in Italian, 1984).
  </p>
  <p>
   Fundamental works on Osco-Umbrian, most with selected texts, include
   <e type="smallcap">
    Robert von Planta
   </e>
   ,
   <e type="italic">
    Grammatik der oskisch-umbrischen Dialekte
   </e>
   , 2 vol. (1892–97, reissued 1973);
   <e type="smallcap">
    Carl Darling Buck
   </e>
   ,
   <e type="italic">
    A Grammar of Oscan and Umbrian
   </e>
   , new ed. (1928, reprinted 1995);
   <e type="smallcap">
    Gino Bottiglioni
   </e>
   ,
   <e type="italic">
    Manuale dei dialetti italici: Osco, Umbro, e dialetti minori
   </e>
   (1954);
   <e type="smallcap">
    A. Ernout
   </e>
   ,
   <e type="italic">
    Le dialecte ombrien: lexique du vocabulaire des “Tables Eugubines” et des inscriptions
   </e>
   (1961); and
   <e type="smallcap">
    Gerhard Meiser
   </e>
   ,
   <e type="italic">
    Lautgeschichte der umbrischen Sprache
   </e>
   (1986). A detailed treatment of Paelignian, one of the central Oscan “minor dialects,” is
   <e type="smallcap">
    Rafael Jiménez Zamudio
   </e>
   ,
   <e type="italic">
    Estudio del dialecto peligno y su entorno lingüístico
   </e>
   (1986). The most complete edition of Osco-Umbrian and Faliscan texts is
   <e type="smallcap">
    Emil Vetter
   </e>
   ,
   <e type="italic">
    Handbuch der italischen Dialekte
   </e>
   , vol. 1,
   <e type="italic">
    Texte mit Erklärung, Glossen, Wörterverzeichnis
   </e>
   (1953); it is supplemented by
   <e type="smallcap">
    Paolo Poccetti
   </e>
   ,
   <e type="italic">
    Nuovi documenti italici
   </e>
   (1979). Special studies of some of the more important Oscan texts include
   <e type="smallcap">
    Annalisa Franchi De Bellis
   </e>
   ,
   <e type="italic">
    Le iovile capuane
   </e>
   (1981), and
   <e type="italic">
    Il cippo abellano
   </e>
   (1988). The most accurate text of the Iguvine Tables is found in
   <e type="smallcap">
    Aldo L. Prosdocimi
   </e>
   ,
   <e type="italic">
    Le tavole iguvine
   </e>
   , vol. 1 (1984), with introduction and notes in Italian. Special studies of the Iguvine Tables include
   <e type="smallcap">
    James Wilson Poultney
   </e>
   ,
   <e type="italic">
    The Bronze Tables of Iguvium
   </e>
   (1959); and
   <e type="smallcap">
    Giacomo Devoto
   </e>
   (ed.),
   <e type="italic">
    Tabulae Iguvinae
   </e>
   , rev. ed. (1940), in Latin. The authoritative edition of the South Picene texts is
   <e type="smallcap">
    Anna Marinetti
   </e>
   ,
   <e type="italic">
    Le iscrizioni sudpicene
   </e>
   (1985– );
   <e type="smallcap">
    Ignacio-Javier Adiego Lajara
   </e>
   ,
   <e type="italic">
    Protosabelio, osco-umbro, sudpiceno
   </e>
   (1992), in Spanish, is also useful. A grammatical description of Faliscan with many of the texts is provided by
   <e type="smallcap">
    Gabriella Giacomelli
   </e>
   ,
   <e type="italic">
    La lingua falisca
   </e>
   (1963). Similar treatment is given to Venetic in
   <e type="smallcap">
    G.B. Pellegrini
   </e>
   and
   <e type="smallcap">
    Aldo L. Prosdocimi
   </e>
   ,
   <e type="italic">
    La lingua venetica
   </e>
   , 2 vol. (1967);
   <e type="smallcap">
    Michel Lejeune
   </e>
   ,
   <e type="italic">
    Manuel de la langue vénète
   </e>
   (1974); and
   <e type="smallcap">
    Giulia Fogolari
   </e>
   <e type="italic">
    et al., I Veneti antichi: lingua e cultura
   </e>
   (1988). Important studies of onomastic material (so prominent in the Italic language texts) include, for Oscan,
   <e type="smallcap">
    Michel Lejeune
   </e>
   ,
   <e type="italic">
    L’anthroponymie osque
   </e>
   (1976); and for Venetic,
   <e type="smallcap">
    Michel Lejeune
   </e>
   ,
   <e type="italic">
    Ateste à l’heure de la romanisation (étude anthroponymique)
   </e>
   (1978); and
   <e type="smallcap">
    Jürgen Untermann
   </e>
   ,
   <e type="italic">
    Die venetischen Personennamen
   </e>
   , 2 vol. (1961). Questions of ancient Italic poetics are treated in
   <e type="smallcap">
    Calvert Watkins
   </e>
   ,
   <e type="italic">
    How to Kill a Dragon: Aspects of Indo-European Poetics
   </e>
   (1995), especially chapters 10 and 17–20.
  </p>
  <signature>
   J&amp;#x00fc;rgen Untermann
  </signature>
  <signature>
   Brent Vine
  </signature>
 </h1>
 <copyright>
  Encyclopædia Britannica
 </copyright>
</article>