<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "syndication_xml.dtd">
<article articleid="110117" articletypeid="1" language="en_us" lastupdate="2022-Mar-21 15:26:08" url="/article/music/110117" version="15">
 <title>
  music
 </title>
 <p>
  <assembly id="a235853" url="/assembly/view/235853">
   <title>
    music; piano
   </title>
   <media mediaid="149833" type="image" url="/33/149833-004-F2955EF0.jpg"/>
   <caption>
    Playing the piano, hands on the keys.
   </caption>
   <credit>
    © Digital Vision/Thinkstock
   </credit>
  </assembly>
  <e type="bold">
   music
  </e>
  ,
  <assemblyref assemblyid="a235853"/>
  art concerned with combining vocal or instrumental
  <xref articleid="109557">
   sounds
  </xref>
  for beauty of form or emotional expression, usually according to cultural standards of
  <xref articleid="110122">
   rhythm
  </xref>
  ,
  <xref articleid="51910">
   melody
  </xref>
  , and, in most Western music,
  <xref articleid="110125">
   harmony
  </xref>
  . Both the simple
  <xref articleid="390003">
   folk song
  </xref>
  and the complex
  <xref articleid="110137">
   electronic composition
  </xref>
  belong to the same activity, music. Both are humanly engineered; both are conceptual and auditory, and these factors have been present in music of all styles and in all periods of history, throughout the world.
 </p>
 <p>
  Music is an art that, in one guise or another, permeates every human society. Modern music is heard in a bewildering profusion of styles, many of them contemporary, others engendered in past eras. Music is a protean art; it lends itself easily to alliances with words, as in
  <xref articleid="68691">
   song
  </xref>
  , and with physical movement, as in
  <xref articleid="110116">
   dance
  </xref>
  . Throughout history, music has been an important adjunct to
  <xref articleid="109488">
   ritual
  </xref>
  and
  <xref articleid="31140">
   drama
  </xref>
  and has been credited with the capacity to reflect and influence human
  <xref articleid="106029">
   emotion
  </xref>
  . Popular culture has consistently exploited these possibilities, most conspicuously today by means of
  <xref articleid="106101">
   radio
  </xref>
  ,
  <xref articleid="110698">
   film
  </xref>
  ,
  <xref articleid="106102">
   television
  </xref>
  ,
  <xref articleid="54431">
   musical theatre
  </xref>
  , and the
  <xref articleid="1458">
   Internet
  </xref>
  . The implications of the uses of music in
  <xref articleid="61739">
   psychotherapy
  </xref>
  ,
  <xref articleid="36601">
   geriatrics
  </xref>
  , and
  <xref articleid="3817">
   advertising
  </xref>
  testify to a faith in its power to affect
  <xref articleid="110429">
   human behaviour
  </xref>
  . Publications and recordings have effectively internationalized music in its most significant, as well as its most trivial, manifestations. Beyond all this, the teaching of music in primary and secondary schools has now attained virtually worldwide acceptance.
 </p>
 <p>
  <assembly id="a235854" url="/assembly/view/235854">
   <title>
    traditional music
   </title>
   <media mediaid="199157" type="image" url="/57/199157-004-17F58861.jpg"/>
   <caption>
    Afro-Cuban street musicians playing traditional music.
   </caption>
   <credit>
    © Kmiragaya/Dreamstime.com
   </credit>
  </assembly>
  <assemblyref assemblyid="a235854"/>
  But the prevalence of music is nothing new, and its human importance has often been acknowledged. What seems curious is that, despite the universality of the art, no one until recent times has argued for its necessity. The ancient Greek philosopher
  <xref articleid="29904">
   Democritus
  </xref>
  explicitly denied any fundamental need for music: “For it was not necessity that separated it off, but it arose from the existing superfluity.” The view that music and the other arts are mere graces is still widespread, although the growth of psychological understanding of play and other symbolic activities has begun to weaken this tenacious belief.
 </p>
 <p>
  Music is treated in a number of articles. For the history of music in different regions,
  <e type="italic">
   see
  </e>
  <xref articleid="384735">
   African music
  </xref>
  ;
  <xref articleid="387743">
   Oceanic music and dance
  </xref>
  ;
  <xref articleid="108746">
   Western music
  </xref>
  ;
  <xref articleid="106127">
   Central Asian arts: Music
  </xref>
  ;
  <xref articleid="399706">
   Chinese music
  </xref>
  ;
  <xref articleid="399707">
   Japanese music
  </xref>
  ;
  <xref articleid="399708">
   Korean music
  </xref>
  ;
  <xref articleid="106442">
   Islamic arts
  </xref>
  ;
  <xref articleid="437989">
   Native American music
  </xref>
  ;
  <xref articleid="109585">
   South Asian arts: Music
  </xref>
  ; and
  <xref articleid="109586">
   Southeast Asian arts: Music
  </xref>
  .
  <e type="italic">
   See also
  </e>
  <xref articleid="390003">
   folk music
  </xref>
  . Aspects of music are treated in
  <xref articleid="110126">
   counterpoint
  </xref>
  ,
  <xref articleid="110125">
   harmony
  </xref>
  ,
  <xref articleid="110129">
   instrumentation
  </xref>
  ,
  <xref articleid="110124">
   mode
  </xref>
  ,
  <xref articleid="110119">
   music criticism
  </xref>
  ,
  <xref articleid="110128">
   music composition
  </xref>
  ,
  <xref articleid="110118">
   music performance
  </xref>
  ,
  <xref articleid="110130">
   music recording
  </xref>
  ,
  <xref articleid="110120">
   musical sound
  </xref>
  ,
  <xref articleid="110127">
   music notation
  </xref>
  ,
  <xref articleid="110122">
   rhythm
  </xref>
  ,
  <xref articleid="110123">
   scale
  </xref>
  , and
  <xref articleid="110121">
   tuning and temperament
  </xref>
  .
  <e type="italic">
   See also
  </e>
  such articles as
  <xref articleid="15780">
   blues
  </xref>
  ,
  <xref articleid="110132">
   chamber music
  </xref>
  ,
  <xref articleid="110139">
   choral music
  </xref>
  ,
  <xref articleid="110136">
   concerto
  </xref>
  ,
  <xref articleid="110137">
   electronic music
  </xref>
  ,
  <xref articleid="110133">
   fugue
  </xref>
  ,
  <xref articleid="110142">
   jazz
  </xref>
  ,
  <xref articleid="110141">
   opera
  </xref>
  ,
  <xref articleid="63492">
   rhythm and blues
  </xref>
  ,
  <xref articleid="63964">
   rock
  </xref>
  ,
  <xref articleid="110134">
   symphony
  </xref>
  ,
  <xref articleid="110135">
   sonata
  </xref>
  ,
  <xref articleid="110140">
   theatre music
  </xref>
  , and
  <xref articleid="110138">
   vocal music
  </xref>
  . Musical instruments are treated in
  <xref articleid="105993">
   electronic instrument
  </xref>
  ,
  <xref articleid="105991">
   keyboard instrument
  </xref>
  ,
  <xref articleid="105989">
   percussion instrument
  </xref>
  ,
  <xref articleid="105990">
   stringed instrument
  </xref>
  , and
  <xref articleid="105992">
   wind instrument
  </xref>
  , as well as in separate articles on individual instruments, such as
  <xref articleid="24197">
   clarinet
  </xref>
  ,
  <xref articleid="31250">
   drum
  </xref>
  ,
  <xref articleid="38459">
   guitar
  </xref>
  ,
  <xref articleid="44917">
   kayagŭm
  </xref>
  ,
  <xref articleid="59886">
   piano
  </xref>
  ,
  <xref articleid="70836">
   tabla
  </xref>
  , and
  <xref articleid="72060">
   theremin
  </xref>
  .
 </p>
 <h1 id="h64609">
  <title>
   Historical conceptions
  </title>
  <p>
   Music is everywhere to be heard. But what is music? Commentators have spoken of “the relationship of music to the human senses and intellect,” thus affirming a world of human discourse as the necessary setting for the art. A definition of music itself will take longer. As
   <xref articleid="108312">
    Aristotle
   </xref>
   said, “It is not easy to determine the nature of music or why anyone should have a knowledge of it.”
  </p>
  <p>
   <assembly id="a235855" url="/assembly/view/235855">
    <title>
     traditional music
    </title>
    <media mediaid="196867" type="image" url="/67/196867-004-03E2A55D.jpg"/>
    <caption>
     Man playing a traditional Indian musical instrument.
    </caption>
    <credit>
     © Ruslan Kalnitsky/Shutterstock.com
    </credit>
   </assembly>
   <assemblyref assemblyid="a235855"/>
   Early in the 20th century, it was regarded as a commonplace that a musical tone was characterized by the regularity of its vibrations; this uniformity gave it a fixed pitch and distinguished its sounds from “noise.” Although that view may have been supported by traditional music, by the latter half of the 20th century it was recognized as an unacceptable yardstick. Indeed, “noise” itself and silence became elements in composition, and random sounds were used (without prior knowledge of what they would be) by composers, such as the American
   <xref articleid="18542">
    John Cage
   </xref>
   , and others in works having
   <xref articleid="5549">
    aleatory
   </xref>
   (chance) or impromptu features.
   <xref articleid="72858">
    Tone
   </xref>
   , moreover, is only one component in music, others being
   <xref articleid="110122">
    rhythm
   </xref>
   ,
   <xref articleid="72504">
    timbre
   </xref>
   (tone colour), and
   <xref articleid="125699">
    texture
   </xref>
   . Electronic machinery enabled some composers to create works in which the traditional role of the interpreter is abolished and to record, directly on tape or into a digital file, sounds that were formerly beyond human ability to produce, if not to imagine.
  </p>
  <h2 id="h64610">
   <title>
    Early Indian and Chinese conceptions
   </title>
   <p>
    From historical accounts it is clear that the power to move people has always been attributed to music; its ecstatic possibilities have been recognized in all cultures and have usually been admitted in practice under particular conditions, sometimes stringent ones. In India, music has been put into the service of religion from earliest times;
    <xref articleid="74946">
     Vedic hymns
    </xref>
    stand at the beginning of the record. As the art developed over many centuries into a music of profound melodic and rhythmic intricacy, the discipline of a religious text or the guideline of a story determined the structure. In the 21st century the narrator remains central to the performance of much Indian traditional music, and the virtuosity of a skillful singer rivals that of the instrumentalists. There is very little concept of vocal or instrumental idiom in the Western sense. The vertical dimension of chord structure—that is, the effects created by sounding tones simultaneously—is not a part of South Asian classical music; the divisions of an
    <xref articleid="56730">
     octave
    </xref>
    (intervals) are more numerous than in Western music, and the melodic complexity of the music goes far beyond that of its Western counterpart. Moreover, an element of
    <xref articleid="42225">
     improvisation
    </xref>
    is retained that is vital to the success of a performance. The spontaneous imitation carried on between an instrumentalist and narrator, against the insistent rhythmic subtleties of the drums, can be a source of the greatest excitement, which in large measure is because of the faithful adherence to the rigid rules that govern the rendition of
    <xref articleid="62458">
     ragas
    </xref>
    —the ancient melodic patterns of Indian music.
   </p>
   <p>
    <assembly id="a235866" url="/assembly/view/235866">
     <title>
      traditional Chinese music
     </title>
     <media mediaid="160390" type="image" url="/90/160390-004-AB2B1AC0.jpg"/>
     <caption>
      Musician playing a traditional Chinese fiddle, the erhu, at the 2008 Moon Festival.
     </caption>
     <credit>
      © Jose Gil/Shutterstock.com
     </credit>
    </assembly>
    <assemblyref assemblyid="a235866"/>
    Chinese music, like the music of India, has traditionally been an adjunct to ceremony or narrative.
    <xref articleid="109630">
     Confucius
    </xref>
    (551–479
    <e type="smallcap">
     bce
    </e>
    ) assigned an important place to music in the service of a well-ordered moral universe. He saw music and government as reflecting one another and believed that only the superior man who can understand music is equipped to govern. Music, he thought, reveals character through the six emotions that it can portray: sorrow, satisfaction, joy, anger, piety, love. According to Confucius, great music is in harmony with the universe, restoring order to the physical world through that harmony. Music, as a true mirror of character, makes pretense or deception impossible.
   </p>
  </h2>
  <h2 id="h64611">
   <title>
    Ancient Greek ideas
   </title>
   <p>
    <assembly id="a235867" url="/assembly/view/235867">
     <title>
      traditional Greek music
     </title>
     <media mediaid="197128" type="image" url="/28/197128-004-5EDAEF09.jpg"/>
     <caption>
      Dancers in traditional clothing at an Easter celebration in Heraklion on the island of Crete, Greece. Musicians are playing Greek musical instruments, including a Cretan lyra (left) and a bouzouki.
     </caption>
     <credit>
      © Lostafichuk/Dreamstime.com
     </credit>
    </assembly>
    <assemblyref assemblyid="a235867"/>
    Although music was important in the life of ancient Greece, it is not now known how that music actually sounded. Only a few notated fragments have survived, and no key exists for restoring even these. The Greeks were given to theoretical speculation about music; they had a system of notation, and they “practiced music,” as
    <xref articleid="109554">
     Socrates
    </xref>
    himself, in a vision, had been enjoined to do. But the Greek term from which the word
    <e type="italic">
     music
    </e>
    is derived was a generic one, referring to any art or science practiced under the aegis of the
    <xref articleid="54410">
     Muses
    </xref>
    . Music, therefore, as distinct from
    <xref articleid="38648">
     gymnastics
    </xref>
    , was all-encompassing. (Much speculation, however, was clearly directed toward that more-restricted meaning with which we are familiar.) Music was virtually a department of
    <xref articleid="109827">
     mathematics
    </xref>
    for the philosopher
    <xref articleid="62073">
     Pythagoras
    </xref>
    (
    <e type="italic">
     c.
    </e>
    550
    <e type="smallcap">
     bce
    </e>
    ), who was the first musical
    <xref articleid="56499">
     numerologist
    </xref>
    and who laid the foundations for
    <xref articleid="109556">
     acoustics
    </xref>
    . In acoustics, the Greeks discovered the correspondence between the
    <xref articleid="60203">
     pitch
    </xref>
    of a note and the length of a string. But they did not progress to a calculation of pitch on the basis of vibrations, though an attempt was made to connect sounds with underlying motions.
   </p>
   <p>
    <xref articleid="108556">
     Plato
    </xref>
    (428–348/347
    <e type="smallcap">
     bce
    </e>
    ), like Confucius, looked on music as a department of
    <xref articleid="106054">
     ethics
    </xref>
    . And like Confucius he was anxious to regulate the use of particular
    <xref articleid="110124">
     modes
    </xref>
    (i.e., arrangements of notes, like scales) because of their supposed effects on people. Plato was a stern musical disciplinarian; he saw a correspondence between the character of a person and the music that represented him or her. Straightforward simplicity was best. In the
    <e type="italic">
     <e type="italic">
      Laws
     </e>
    </e>
    , Plato declared that rhythmic and melodic complexities were to be avoided because they led to depression and disorder. Music echoes divine harmony; rhythm and melody imitate the movements of heavenly bodies, thus delineating the music of the spheres and reflecting the moral order of the universe. Earthly music, however, is suspect; Plato distrusted its emotional power. Music must therefore be of the right sort; the sensuous qualities of certain modes are dangerous, and a strong censorship must be imposed. Music and gymnastics in the correct balance would constitute the desirable curriculum in education. Plato valued music in its ethically approved forms; his concern was primarily with the effects of music, and he therefore regarded it as a psychosociological phenomenon.
   </p>
   <p>
    Yet Plato, in treating earthly music as a shadow of the ideal, saw a symbolic significance in the art. Aristotle carried forward the concept of the art as imitation, but music could express the universal as well. His idea that works of art could contain a measure of truth in themselves—an idea voiced more explicitly by
    <xref articleid="60438">
     Plotinus
    </xref>
    in the 3rd century
    <e type="smallcap">
     ce
    </e>
    —gave added strength to the symbolic view. Aristotle, following Plato, thought that music has power to mold human character, but he would admit all the modes, recognizing happiness and pleasure as values to both the individual and the state. He advocated a rich musical diet. Aristotle made a distinction between those who have only theoretical knowledge and those who produce music, maintaining that persons who do not perform cannot be good judges of the performances of others.
   </p>
   <p>
    <xref articleid="9453">
     Aristoxenus
    </xref>
    , a pupil of Aristotle, gave considerable credit to human listeners, their importance, and their powers of perception. He denigrated the dominance of mathematical and acoustical considerations. For Aristoxenus, music was emotional and fulfilled a functional role, for which both the hearing and the intellect of the listener were essential. Individual tones were to be understood in their relations to one another and in the context of larger formal units. The
    <xref articleid="108669">
     Epicureans
    </xref>
    and
    <xref articleid="108675">
     Stoics
    </xref>
    adopted a more naturalistic view of music and its function, which they accepted as an adjunct to the good life. They gave more emphasis to sensation than did Plato, but they nevertheless placed music in the service of moderation and virtue. A dissenting 3rd-century voice was that of
    <xref articleid="66998">
     Sextus Empiricus
    </xref>
    , who said that music was an art of tones and rhythms only that meant nothing outside itself.
   </p>
   <p>
    The Platonic influence in musical thought was to be dominant for at least a millennium. Following that period of unquestioned philosophical allegiance, there were times of rededication to Greek concepts, accompanied by reverent and insistent homage (e.g., the group of late 16th-century Florentines, known as the
    <xref articleid="18808">
     Camerata
    </xref>
    , who were instrumental in the development of
    <xref articleid="110141">
     opera
    </xref>
    ). Such returns to simplicity, directness, and the primacy of the word have been made periodically, out of loyalty to Platonic imperatives, however much these “neo” practices may have differed from those of the Greeks themselves.
   </p>
   <p>
    In the 21st century the effects of Greek thought are still strongly evident in the belief that music influences the ethical life; in the idea that music can be explained in terms of some component such as number (that may itself be only a reflection of another, higher source); in the view that music has specific effects and functions that can be appropriately labelled; and in the recurrent observation that music is connected with human emotion. In every historical period there have been defectors from one or more of these views, and there are, of course, differences of emphasis.
   </p>
  </h2>
  <h2 id="h64612">
   <title>
    Music in Christianity
   </title>
   <p>
    <assembly id="a97440" url="/assembly/view/97440">
     <title>
      Preti, Mattia:
      <e type="italic">
       Boethius and Philosophy
      </e>
     </title>
     <media mediaid="95798" type="image" url="/98/95798-004-AD139662.jpg"/>
     <caption>
      <e type="italic">
       Boethius and Philosophy
      </e>
      , oil on canvas, by Mattia Preti, 17th century. 185.4 × 254 cm.
     </caption>
     <credit>
      In a private collection
     </credit>
    </assembly>
    <assemblyref assemblyid="a97440"/>
    Much of the Platonic-Aristotelian teaching, as restated by the Roman philosopher
    <xref articleid="80386">
     Boethius
    </xref>
    (
    <e type="italic">
     c.
    </e>
    480–524), was well suited to the needs of the church; the conservative aspects of that philosophy, with its fear of innovation, were conducive to the maintenance of order. The role of music as accessory to words is nowhere more clearly illustrated than in the history of
    <xref articleid="105945">
     Christianity
    </xref>
    , where the primacy of the text has always been emphasized and sometimes, as in
    <xref articleid="109699">
     Roman Catholic doctrine
    </xref>
    , made an article of faith. In the varieties of
    <xref articleid="60290">
     plainchant
    </xref>
    , melody was used for textual illumination; the configurations of sound took their cue from the words.
    <xref articleid="64804">
     St. Augustine
    </xref>
    (354–430
    <e type="smallcap">
     ce
    </e>
    ), who was attracted by music and valued its utility to religion, was fearful of its sensuous element and anxious that the melody never take precedence over the words. These had been Plato’s concerns also. Still echoing the Greeks, Augustine, whose beliefs were reiterated by
    <xref articleid="108661">
     St. Thomas Aquinas
    </xref>
    (
    <e type="italic">
     c.
    </e>
    1225–74), held the basis of music to be mathematical; music reflects celestial movement and order.
   </p>
   <p>
    <assembly id="a94514" url="/assembly/view/94514">
     <title>
      Martin Luther
     </title>
     <media mediaid="115497" type="image" url="/97/115497-004-850B5BCD.jpg"/>
     <caption>
      Portrait of Martin Luther, oil on panel by Lucas Cranach, 1529; in the Uffizi, Florence.
     </caption>
     <credit>
      Photos.com/Getty Images
     </credit>
    </assembly>
    <assemblyref assemblyid="a94514"/>
    <xref articleid="108504">
     Martin Luther
    </xref>
    (1483–1546) was a musical liberal and reformer. But the uses he envisioned for music, despite his innovations, were in the mainstream of tradition; Luther insisted that music must be simple, direct, accessible, an aid to piety. His assignment of particular qualities to a given mode is reminiscent of Plato and Confucius.
    <xref articleid="106115">
     John Calvin
    </xref>
    (1509–64) took a more cautious and fearful view of music than did Luther, warning against voluptuous, effeminate, or disorderly music and insisting upon the supremacy of the text.
   </p>
  </h2>
  <h2 id="h64613">
   <title>
    17th- and 18th-century Western conceptions
   </title>
   <p>
    In reviewing the accounts of music that have characterized musical and intellectual history, it is clear that the Pythagoreans are reborn from age to age. The German astronomer
    <xref articleid="105767">
     Johannes Kepler
    </xref>
    (1571–1630) perpetuated, in effect, the idea of the harmony of the spheres, attempting to relate music to planetary movement.
    <xref articleid="108563">
     René Descartes
    </xref>
    (1596–1650), too, saw the basis of music as mathematical. He was a faithful Platonist in his prescription of temperate rhythms and simple melodies so that music would not produce imaginative, exciting, and hence immoral, effects. For another philosopher-mathematician, the German
    <xref articleid="47669">
     Gottfried von Leibniz
    </xref>
    (1646–1716), music reflected a universal rhythm and mirrored a reality that was fundamentally mathematical, to be experienced in the mind as a subconscious apprehension of numerical relationships.
   </p>
   <p>
    <assembly id="a95969" url="/assembly/view/95969">
     <title>
      Immanuel Kant
     </title>
     <media mediaid="51029" type="image" url="/29/51029-004-21FCAAB9.jpg"/>
     <caption>
      Immanuel Kant, pencil portrait by Hans Veit Schnorr von Carolsfeld; in the Kupferstichkabinett, Dresden, Germany.
     </caption>
     <credit>
      Marburg—Art Reference Bureau/Art Resource, New York
     </credit>
    </assembly>
    <assemblyref assemblyid="a95969"/>
    <xref articleid="108443">
     Immanuel Kant
    </xref>
    (1724–1804) ranked music as lowest in his hierarchy of the arts. What he distrusted most about music was its wordlessness; he considered it useful for enjoyment but negligible in the service of culture. Allied with poetry, however, it may acquire conceptual value.
    <xref articleid="108411">
     Georg Wilhelm Friedrich Hegel
    </xref>
    (1770–1831) also extolled the discursive faculties, saying that art, though it expresses the divine, must yield to philosophy. He acknowledged the peculiar power of music to express many nuances of the emotions. Like Kant, Hegel preferred
    <xref articleid="110138">
     vocal music
    </xref>
    to instrumental, deprecating wordless music as subjective and indefinite. The essence of music he held to be rhythm, which finds its counterpart in the innermost self. What is original in Hegel’s view is his claim that music, unlike the other arts, has no independent existence in space, is not “objective” in that sense; the fundamental rhythm of music (again an aspect of number) is experienced within the hearer.
   </p>
   <p>
    After the 18th century, speculations upon the intrinsic nature of music became more numerous and profound. The elements necessary for a more comprehensive theory of its function and meaning became discernible. But philosophers whose views have been summarized thus far were not speaking as philosophers of music. Music interested them in terms extrinsic to itself, in its observable effects; in its connections with dance, religious ritual, or festive rites; because of its alliance with words; or for some other extramusical consideration. The only common denominator to be found, aside from the recognition of different types of music, is the acknowledgment of its connection with the emotional life, and here, to be sure, is that problematic power of the art to move. Various extramusical preoccupations are the raison d’être of “contextualist” explanations of music, which are concerned with its relation to the human environment. The history of music itself is largely an account of its adjunctive function in rituals and ceremonies of all kinds—religious, military, courtly—and in musical theatre. The protean character of music that enables it to form such easy alliances with literature and drama (as in folk song, art song, opera, “background” music) and with the dance (ritual, popular entertainment, “social,”
    <xref articleid="11998">
     ballet
    </xref>
    ) appears to confirm the wide range and influence that the Greeks assigned to it.
   </p>
  </h2>
 </h1>
 <h1 id="h64614">
  <title>
   Theories of musical meaning since the 19th century
  </title>
  <p>
   Before the 19th century, musicians themselves seldom were theorists, if theorist is defined as one who explicates meaning. Music theory, when it was something other than the exposition of a prevalent or emerging style, was likely to be a technical manual guiding vocal or instrumental performance, a set of directions for meeting current exigencies in church or theatre practice, or a missive advocating reforms. Prolific masters, such as
   <xref articleid="108452">
    Johann Sebastian Bach
   </xref>
   , produced not learned treatises but monuments of art.
  </p>
  <p>
   <assembly id="a15107" url="/assembly/view/15107">
    <title>
     Richard Wagner
    </title>
    <media mediaid="8788" type="image" url="/88/8788-004-46AF99D9.jpg"/>
    <caption>
     Richard Wagner, drawing by Franz von Lenbach, c. 1870.
    </caption>
    <credit>
     Courtesy of Richard Wagner-Gedenkstatte, Bayreuth, Germany
    </credit>
   </assembly>
   <assemblyref assemblyid="a15107"/>
   The 19th century saw the emergence of composer-critics (
   <xref articleid="76384">
    Carl Maria von Weber
   </xref>
   ,
   <xref articleid="66240">
    Robert Schumann
   </xref>
   ,
   <xref articleid="78815">
    Hector Berlioz
   </xref>
   ,
   <xref articleid="48502">
    Franz Liszt
   </xref>
   ), versatile artists with literary proclivities who were not, to be sure, propounding comprehensive theories or systems of thought.
   <xref articleid="75844">
    Richard Wagner
   </xref>
   , an active theorist, presaged a new species, the composer-author. But he did little to advance music theory. He proposed a unity of music and drama (
   <e type="italic">
    Gesamtkunstwerk
   </e>
   )—a reflection of the
   <xref articleid="61498">
    programmatic
   </xref>
   preoccupations of 19th-century composers—but its multiplicity of musical and extramusical elements only added to the confusion of musical thought. The distinctly musical character of Wagner’s genius, clearly discernible in
   <e type="italic">
    The Ring of the Nibelung
   </e>
   (
   <e type="italic">
    Der Ring des Nibelungen
   </e>
   ), a set of four operas, is in no way explained by his discursive credos.
   <xref articleid="69932">
    Igor Stravinsky
   </xref>
   ,
   <xref articleid="66187">
    Arnold Schoenberg
   </xref>
   , and other composer-authors of the 20th century were somewhat more successful in elucidating their techniques and aims.
  </p>
  <h2 id="h64615">
   <title>
    The concept of dynamism
   </title>
   <p>
    <assembly id="a196865" url="/assembly/view/196865">
     <title>
      Friedrich Nietzsche
     </title>
     <media mediaid="130310" type="image" url="/10/130310-004-BEB71887.jpg"/>
     <caption>
      Friedrich Nietzsche.
     </caption>
     <credit>
      © Photos.com/Jupiterimages
     </credit>
    </assembly>
    <assemblyref assemblyid="a196865"/>
    Ideas of music as a type of symbolism owe much to two German philosophers,
    <xref articleid="66208">
     Arthur Schopenhauer
    </xref>
    (1788–1860) and
    <xref articleid="108765">
     Friedrich Nietzsche
    </xref>
    (1844–1900), who brought to the theory of music a new concept, articulated by each in different ways and in divergent terms but faithful to the same principle—dynamism. Both saw in music an art that is not “spatialized” (hence not “objective”) in the way that other arts are by the very conditions of their manifestation. Music is closer to the inner dynamism of process; there are fewer technical (and no concrete) impediments to immediate apprehension, for an entire dimension of the empirical world has been bypassed.
   </p>
   <p>
    <assembly id="a14147" url="/assembly/view/14147">
     <title>
      Arthur Schopenhauer
     </title>
     <media mediaid="9459" type="image" url="/59/9459-004-DDF12A12.jpg"/>
     <caption>
      Arthur Schopenhauer, 1855.
     </caption>
     <credit>
      Archiv für Kunst und Geschichte, Berlin
     </credit>
    </assembly>
    <assemblyref assemblyid="a14147"/>
    Schopenhauer looked upon Platonic ideas as objectifying will, but music is
   </p>
   <quote>
    <p>
     by no means like the other arts, the copy of the Ideas, but the
     <e type="italic">
      copy of the will itself
     </e>
     . This is why the effect of music is so much more powerful and penetrating than that of the other arts, for they speak only of shadows, but it speaks of the thing itself.
    </p>
   </quote>
   <p>
    In contrast to Kant he accords a special efficacy to music:
   </p>
   <quote>
    <p>
     The effect of music is stronger, quicker, more necessary and infallible. Men have practiced music in all ages without being able to account for this; content to understand it directly, they renounce all claim to an abstract conception of this direct understanding itself.
    </p>
   </quote>
   <p>
    Schopenhauer acknowledged a connection between human feeling and music, which “restores to us all the emotions of our inmost nature, but entirely without reality and far removed from their pain.” Music, which he is presenting an as analogue of the emotional life, is a copy or symbol of the will.
   </p>
   <p>
    Nietzsche posed an
    <xref articleid="124779">
     Apollonian
    </xref>
    -
    <xref articleid="124825">
     Dionysian
    </xref>
    dichotomy, the former representing form and rationality and the latter drunkenness and ecstasy. For Nietzsche, music was the Dionysian art par excellence. In
    <e type="italic">
     The Birth of Tragedy from the Spirit of Music
    </e>
    , Nietzsche anticipated the 20th-century discovery that symbol making (whether in
    <xref articleid="109540">
     dreams
    </xref>
    ,
    <xref articleid="108748">
     myth,
    </xref>
    or
    <xref articleid="389134">
     art
    </xref>
    ) is a necessary and to some extent even automatic human activity. The rich suggestiveness and prescience of his insights embraced the concept of the symbolical analogue—the artistic function of ordering and heightening the ingredients of the actual world—and the polarities of experience symbolized in the Apollonian-Dionysian conflict itself, which Stravinsky also explored. Nietzsche gave short shrift to mathematical aspects of music, and like Schopenhauer he deprecated blatantly programmatic music that abounds in obvious imitations of natural sounds. Discerning a power in music to create myths, he looked upon mere tone painting as the antithesis of its essential character.
   </p>
   <p>
    Efforts of theorists to account for the universal appeal of music and to explain its effects have, since the 19th century, been various, contradictory, and highly controversial. In identifying the chief points of view that have emerged, it must be emphasized that there are no completely isolated categories, and there is usually considerable overlapping; a single spokesman, the 19th-century English
    <xref articleid="61727">
     psychologist
    </xref>
    Edmund Gurney (1847–88), for example, may incorporate
    <xref articleid="108546" refid="h36276">
     formalist
    </xref>
    ,
    <xref articleid="106009" refid="h11705">
     symbolist
    </xref>
    ,
    <xref articleid="106009" refid="h11689">
     expressionist
    </xref>
    , and psychological elements, in varying proportions, to explain the phenomenon of music. Although some disagreements are more apparent than real because of the inherent problems of terminology and definition, diametrically opposing views are also held and tenaciously defended.
   </p>
  </h2>
  <h2 id="h64616">
   <title>
    Referentialists and nonreferentialists
   </title>
   <p>
    <assembly id="a116530" url="/assembly/view/116530">
     <title>
      Eduard Hanslick
     </title>
     <media mediaid="122885" type="image" url="/85/122885-004-F1834996.jpg"/>
     <caption>
      Eduard Hanslick, 1865.
     </caption>
     <credit/>
    </assembly>
    <assemblyref assemblyid="a116530"/>
    Among those who seek and propound theories of musical meaning, the most persistent disagreement is between the referentialists (or heteronomists), who hold that music can and does refer to meanings outside itself, and the nonreferentialists (who are sometimes called formalists or absolutists), who maintain that the art is autonomous and “means itself.” The Austrian critic
    <xref articleid="39176">
     Eduard Hanslick
    </xref>
    , in his
    <e type="italic">
     The Beautiful in Music
    </e>
    (originally in German, 1854), was a strong proponent of music as an art of intrinsic principles and ideas, yet even Hanslick, ardent formalist though he was, struggled with the problem of emotion in music. Hanslick’s views have been classified as a modified heteronomous theory.
   </p>
   <p>
    <assembly id="a55847" url="/assembly/view/55847">
     <title>
      Igor Stravinsky
     </title>
     <media mediaid="61864" type="image" url="/64/61864-004-3B40AFE2.jpg"/>
     <caption>
      Igor Stravinsky, c. 1920.
     </caption>
     <credit>
      G. L. Manuel Freres—Hulton Archive/Getty Images
     </credit>
    </assembly>
    <assemblyref assemblyid="a55847"/>
    One looks in vain for an extremist of either persuasion, referentialist or nonreferentialist. Igor Stravinsky first achieved fame as a composer of
    <xref articleid="11998">
     ballet
    </xref>
    music, and his works throughout his career were rich in extramusical associations. It would be a comfortable simplification to ally referentialism with
    <xref articleid="61498">
     program music
    </xref>
    and nonreferentialism with absolute music. But the problem cannot be resolved by such a choice, if only, first of all, because extramusical referents can vary in complexity from a mere descriptive title to the convolutions of the
    <xref articleid="75844">
     Wagnerian
    </xref>
    <xref articleid="47699">
     leitmotif
    </xref>
    , in which a particular musical phrase is consistently associated with a particular person, place, or thing. Referentialists do not require an explicit program, and nonreferentialists do not necessarily denigrate program music, though they make a point of distinguishing between the extramusical program and the musical meaning. The American musicologist and theorist Leonard Meyer, in his
    <e type="italic">
     Emotion and Meaning in Music
    </e>
    (1956), spoke of “designative” and “embodied” meanings; he recognized both kinds in music but appeared to give equal weight to the extrinsic and intrinsic.
   </p>
   <p>
    If there is intrinsic, or embodied, meaning, one may well ask what meaning is embodied and how it is to be apprehended. An extreme formalist would say that the acoustic pattern itself and nothing more is the sense of music; Hanslick, indeed, said this, though he did not hold consistently to the view. But most nonreferentialists regard music as, in one way or another, emotionally meaningful or expressive. Referentialists, too, find expressive content in music, though this emotional content may be extramusical (even if not explicit) in origin, according to the American theorists John Hospers in
    <e type="italic">
     Meaning and Truth in the Arts
    </e>
    (1946) and Donald Ferguson in
    <e type="italic">
     Music as Metaphor
    </e>
    (1960). Meyer made the observation that while most referentialists are expressionists, not all expressionists are referentialists. He made the useful distinction between absolute expressionists and referential expressionists and identified his own position as “formalist–absolute expressionist.” In acknowledging that music can and does express referential (designative) meanings as well as nonreferential ones, Meyer exhibited an eclectic and certainly permissive view. But he has been criticized for failing to make clear the modus operandi of this referential meaning in music.
   </p>
  </h2>
  <h2 id="h64617">
   <title>
    Intuition and intellect
   </title>
   <p>
    Most theorists agree that music is an auditory phenomenon and that hearing is the beginning of understanding. Beyond this there is little agreement. There is contention especially between proponents of intuition, such as
    <xref articleid="27939">
     Benedetto Croce
    </xref>
    (1866–1952), and champions of intellectual cognition, such as Hospers. Gurney was constrained to postulate a special musical faculty that need not reside exclusively either in the mind or the heart. The main problem for theorists arises from the inveterate tendency to dichotomize thought and feeling.
    <xref articleid="78769">
     Henri Bergson
    </xref>
    (1859–1941) broke with this tradition when he spoke for “an intellectual act of intuition.” In the first half of the 20th century, a reawakened philosophical and artistic concern for the concept of organic unity revealed strong affinities among such disparate works as Gurney’s
    <e type="italic">
     The Power of Sound
    </e>
    (1880), the American philosopher
    <xref articleid="47094">
     Susanne K. Langer
    </xref>
    ’s
    <e type="italic">
     Philosophy in a New Key
    </e>
    (1942) and her later works,
    <xref articleid="30186">
     John Dewey
    </xref>
    ’s classic
    <e type="italic">
     Art as Experience
    </e>
    (1934), and the American composer
    <xref articleid="66900">
     Roger Sessions
    </xref>
    ’s
    <e type="italic">
     The Musical Experience
    </e>
    (1950).
   </p>
   <p>
    It is apparent that music is connected in some way with human emotional life, but the “how” continues to be elusive. Sessions (echoing Aristotle) stated the problem fairly:
   </p>
   <quote>
    <p>
     No one denies that music arouses emotions, nor do most people deny that the values of music are both qualitatively and quantitatively connected with the emotions it arouses. Yet it is not easy to say just what this connection is.
    </p>
   </quote>
   <p>
    It was long fashionable to speak of the “language” of music, or of music as the “language of the emotions,” but, since a precise
    <xref articleid="110293">
     semantics
    </xref>
    is wanting in music, the analogy breaks down. Two or more listeners may derive very different “meanings” from the same piece of music, and, since written and spoken language cannot render these musical “meanings,” whatever they may be, in consistent and commonly recognizable terms, verbal explication often seems to raise more questions than it settles. Philosophical analysts who hold that all meaning is capable of rendition in language therefore pronounce music—unless it can be saved by the referentialists—without meaning, confronting thoughtful listeners, thereby, with a proposition that seems clearly to contradict (and trivialize) their own experiences. The difficulty, of course, is a semantic one and explains why some theorists have substituted such terms as
    <e type="italic">
     import
    </e>
    ,
    <e type="italic">
     significance
    </e>
    ,
    <e type="italic">
     pattern
    </e>
    , or
    <e type="italic">
     gestalt
    </e>
    for
    <e type="italic">
     meaning
    </e>
    . Recognizing an incompatibility between the modalities of nonverbal arts and their treatment by discursive thought, it is hardly surprising that music aestheticians have been few.
   </p>
  </h2>
  <h2 id="h64618">
   <title>
    Symbolist contributions
   </title>
   <p>
    Significant contributions to music theory were made in the mid-20th century by several investigators who may be classified as symbolists, though most of them exhibited formalist, expressionist, and psychological elements as well. Some of the most influential (and controversial) work was done by Langer. Her most adamant critics (such as John Hospers) objected to her use of the term
    <e type="italic">
     symbol
    </e>
    , which, in their lexica, must stand for something definite; she took pains to ascribe this more limited usage to the term
    <e type="italic">
     signal
    </e>
    . The more general use of the term
    <e type="italic">
     symbol
    </e>
    that she endorsed already had a long history, notably in such 19th-century figures as
    <xref articleid="108453">
     Goethe
    </xref>
    ,
    <xref articleid="20374">
     Thomas Carlyle
    </xref>
    , and the French
    <xref articleid="70716">
     Symbolist
    </xref>
    poets. Langer was accused of having somewhat weakened her argument through a vacillating terminology, and she described the musical symbol as “unconsummated” because of its ambiguity. But the validity of her theory did not depend upon the term
    <e type="italic">
     symbol
    </e>
    ; her thought, indeed, had much in common with that of Edmund Gurney, who did not employ the term and whose
    <e type="italic">
     ideal motion
    </e>
    , if substituted for
    <e type="italic">
     symbol
    </e>
    , would remove most of her critics’ objections. Her use of
    <e type="italic">
     symbol
    </e>
    was nevertheless defensible; she construed art as a “symbolic analogue of emotive life,” rendering the “forms of sentient being” into intelligible configurations. She was a naturalist; she saw art as organic in origin, and she echoed the view, long held among symbolists, that artistic form and content compose an indissoluble unity that each art manifests according to its peculiar conditions. The symbolism of music, she contended, is therefore tonal (or, at its broadest, auditory) in character and can be realized only in time; in psychological experience, time assumes an ideal guise. (Painting and sculpture, in their distinctive modalities, embody ideal space.) Langer embraced all the arts in her purview. The American music theorist Gordon Epperson applied her concepts, with modifications, intensively to music in
    <e type="italic">
     The Musical Symbol
    </e>
    (1967).
   </p>
  </h2>
  <h2 id="h64619">
   <title>
    Contextualist theories
   </title>
   <p>
    <assembly id="a181652" url="/assembly/view/181652">
     <title>
      Johann Sebastian Bach
     </title>
     <media mediaid="114461" type="image" url="/61/114461-004-55247C77.jpg"/>
     <caption>
      Johann Sebastian Bach, oil on canvas by Elias Gottlieb (Gottlob) Haussmann, 1746; in the Stadtgeschichtliches Museum Leipzig, Germany.
     </caption>
     <credit>
      Photos.com/Getty Images
     </credit>
    </assembly>
    <assemblyref assemblyid="a181652"/>
    In moving from symbolic to contextualist explanations of music, it is well to note that a source of great confusion, in the former, is the fact that tone painting (with explicit signals that yield, when the code is understood, designative meanings) is widely regarded as musical symbolism. An example of such tone painting is Bach’s introduction of musical notes, corresponding to the letters of his own name, as a theme in the unfinished final fugue of the
    <e type="italic">
     Art of the Fugue
    </e>
    . And surely it may be argued that this qualifies on one level. But the contention that there is an intrinsic symbolism in the musical meaning itself is a claim that referentialists are generally unwilling to honour. Yet many theorists, whose concern is with the sociological or psychological effects of music, are not so much opposed to the idea of inner or profound meaning as indifferent to such meaning per se. Even an absolutist, however, is unable to examine music in isolation from its human environment. Meyer deliberately eschewed logical and philosophical problems of music and made “no attempt to decide whether music is a language or whether musical stimuli are signs or symbols.” (He did not defend the inference that such concerns are irrelevant to meaning.) Musical meaning and communication, he maintained, cannot exist in the absence of the cultural context. The statement is hardly open to dispute; theorists are classified according to their proximity to the referential or nonreferential pole. If referentialists emphasize explicit aims and associations of a particular work (as in varieties of
    <e type="italic">
     Gebrauchsmusik
    </e>
    , or “utility” music, written for specific social or educational purposes), formalists can maintain that there is also an intrinsic, or embodied, meaning to which they attach the greater aesthetic value.
   </p>
   <p>
    Among contextualists, however, a simple referential view is the exception rather than the rule. Any theorists who examine musical perception are studying a complex human activity. They are dealing with the psychology of music, in which certain elements—e.g., music, listener, mode of apprehension, cultural context—are indispensable and in which characteristic processes recur. Specialists will emphasize one element or another: formalists the music itself, sociologists the listeners and their milieu, psychologists the how of perception. Though psychology could survey the whole field, in practice psychologists, according to their persuasions, investigate the perception of measurable acoustic phenomena, the physical-mental effects of musical sound, or—more rarely—the functional role of music in human experience, and pragmatists and analysts alike may leave something out of account. But it remains for the comprehensive theorist, probably one who, like Langer, is equipped to discern relationships among many departments of thought, to construct a valid hierarchical structure of musical meaning in all its ramifications.
   </p>
   <p>
    Deryck Cooke, the British musicologist and the author of
    <e type="italic">
     The Language of Music
    </e>
    (1959), who may be classified as a referential expressionist, offered a sophisticated argument for the notion of music as language. Concepts, however, may not be rendered by this language, only feelings. Cooke reaffirmed the possibility, long disputed by many theorists, that such feelings may be recognized, identified, and even classified. But he confined his investigation to the last few hundred years of the Western tradition.
   </p>
  </h2>
  <h2 id="h64620">
   <title>
    Information theory
   </title>
   <p>
    The French theorist Abraham Moles’s
    <e type="italic">
     Information Theory and Esthetic Perception
    </e>
    (1966) brought the science of
    <xref articleid="106012">
     information theory
    </xref>
    to bear on musical perception, emphasizing that the concept of form is the essential thing; the “sonic message,” whose dimensions vary from one composition to another, is a whole. Information theory thus proved to be a novel ally for organicists. The message, which is subjected to atomistic study of its components, is (thanks to recording) concrete; there is a temporal sonic material, a
    <e type="italic">
     materia musica
    </e>
    . Moles gave reinforcement to the aesthetic theory of distance:
   </p>
   <quote>
    <p>
     The esthetic procedure of isolating sonic objects is analogous to the sculptor’s or decorator’s isolating a marble work against a black velvet draping: This procedure directs attention to it, alone and not as one element among many in a complex framework.
    </p>
   </quote>
   <p>
    Information theory, which Leonard Meyer also discussed, begins its investigations without the help of traditional theory, which it finds to be untenable for its procedures. Musical messages discerned through information theory are not referential, yet Moles chose to describe the measurable elements in the sonic repertoire as symbols: “each definable temporal stage represents a ‘symbol’ analogous to a phoneme in language.” According to Moles, music must, as an art, obey rules; the role of aesthetics is to enumerate universally valid rules, not to perpetuate the arbitrary or merely traditional. He foresaw experimentation with a much richer repertoire of sounds, transcending musical instruments and drawing on whatever sources—certainly electronic ones—are available for realizing the “most general orchestra.” A host of composers set out to fulfill this desideratum. In order to increase the compass of possible sounds, various
    <xref articleid="54429">
     electronic synthesizers
    </xref>
    were constructed. In electronically synthesized music, the medium itself is indistinguishable from its message.
   </p>
   <p>
    The quest for some distillation of musical meaning may be foredoomed to failure. Meanings, intrinsic and extrinsic, abound; meanings of all kinds, moreover, are revealed in and through the social setting. Church, theatre, and broadcasting affect music in characteristic ways. The modern concert is a device whereby formal, autonomous meanings are emphasized; further, the scope and available repertoire of the concert have been enormously increased through recordings, for any suitably equipped room may become, at the turn of a switch, a recital hall.
   </p>
  </h2>
  <h2 id="h64621">
   <title>
    Considerations related to performance practice
   </title>
   <p>
    Listening to music for its own sake, apart from
    <xref articleid="109488">
     ritual
    </xref>
    or storytelling, is a relatively recent historical development. There have always been impromptu song and dance, and performances of music at home, in church, and in theatrical productions have a long history, but there was no public
    <xref articleid="110141">
     opera
    </xref>
    house until 1637, when the first one opened in
    <xref articleid="108773">
     Venice
    </xref>
    . The first public concerts for which admission was charged appeared in
    <xref articleid="108472">
     London
    </xref>
    in 1672. During the next 50 years there were beginnings in Germany and France also, but the modern concert was not a significant feature of musical life until the late 18th century.
   </p>
   <p>
    Of the forms that have characterized distinct periods of music history, it is sufficient to remark here that the chief
    <xref articleid="108746" refid="h15694">
     Renaissance
    </xref>
    forms—
    <xref articleid="51284">
     mass
    </xref>
    ,
    <xref articleid="53945">
     motet
    </xref>
    , the polyphonic
    <xref articleid="22447">
     chanson
    </xref>
    , and
    <xref articleid="49926">
     madrigal
    </xref>
    —were allied to texts that strongly influenced their structure. Instrumental music was for the most part in the service of the voice, though instrumental church compositions, dances, and chansons arranged for
    <xref articleid="57348">
     organ
    </xref>
    were not uncommon. A strong alliance between voices and instruments has continued into the present, with musical theatre, the art song, and religious music. Instrumental music as a separate genre emerged in the 16th century, gaining considerable momentum in the 17th through a variety of idiomatic pieces. Increased attention to technical fluency was accompanied by greater complexity and sophistication in the instruments themselves. In response to stylistic demands for greater resonance and power, the modern forms of the
    <xref articleid="75451">
     violin
    </xref>
    appeared in the late 16th century, only gradually supplanting the earlier
    <xref articleid="75447">
     viols
    </xref>
    . The
    <xref articleid="39325">
     harpsichord
    </xref>
    did not finally yield to the
    <xref articleid="59886">
     pianoforte
    </xref>
    until the 18th century. The once-prevalent idea that early
    <xref articleid="105990">
     stringed
    </xref>
    and
    <xref articleid="105991">
     keyboard
    </xref>
    instruments were primitive precursors of their modern counterparts has been effectually demolished by research in
    <xref articleid="108746" refid="h15688">
     medieval
    </xref>
    and Renaissance music and by dedicated performers, who seek to restore the sounds and spirit of those eras.
   </p>
   <p>
    The development of opera,
    <xref articleid="57280">
     oratorio
    </xref>
    , and the
    <xref articleid="20050">
     cantata
    </xref>
    gave a prominence to vocal music throughout the
    <xref articleid="108746" refid="h15754">
     Baroque
    </xref>
    era (
    <e type="italic">
     c.
    </e>
    1600–1750) that made it equal in importance to instrumental music, with which these forms were closely allied. But instrumental
    <xref articleid="110132">
     chamber
    </xref>
    and independent
    <xref articleid="57295">
     orchestral ensembles
    </xref>
    , as they exist today, also had their beginnings during this period. A highly significant development of the late 18th century was the definitive appearance of the modern
    <xref articleid="110135">
     sonata
    </xref>
    (whether in the form of the solo and duo sonata, piano trio,
    <xref articleid="69972">
     string quartet
    </xref>
    ,
    <xref articleid="110136">
     concerto
    </xref>
    , or
    <xref articleid="110134">
     symphony
    </xref>
    ) with the Viennese classicists
    <xref articleid="39654">
     Haydn
    </xref>
    and
    <xref articleid="108745">
     Mozart
    </xref>
    and, later,
    <xref articleid="109398">
     Beethoven
    </xref>
    .
   </p>
   <p>
    Since a vocal text is likely to be confused with intrinsic musical meaning, or at least to divert attention from a preoccupation with it, it is not surprising that aesthetic theory has followed on the emergence of an autonomous instrumental music requiring greater concentration on the sound itself, its colour and intensity, and the intelligibility (in terms of tonal organization alone) of a composition. Moreover, the very concept of listening as an attentive (and sometimes rigorous), serious, and necessary activity of the music lover gained acceptance only slowly, following the inauguration of public concerts, and is still vigorously resisted. The expectation that the art should provide enjoyment without effort is, indeed, widespread and accounts for much of the opposition to new and demanding idioms. But even for well-disciplined and eager listeners there is the problem of quantity: they must cope as best they can with what Langer has called “the madhouse of too much art.” If more effort is required, more discrimination is also needed. In music education, articulate voices ask that teaching be centred more upon qualitative aspects of the art (“aesthetic education”), less upon music making as an activity. This concern for musical value appears to reflect a more intensive search for meaning, which is not likely to be the exclusive property of a particular style or era, nor is it to be sought in an indiscriminate acceptance or rejection of novelty per se.
   </p>
   <p>
    A pronounced pedagogical interest developed in various genres of popular music, such as
    <xref articleid="63964">
     rock
    </xref>
    ,
    <xref articleid="68792">
     soul
    </xref>
    , and similar idioms with great numbers of followers, especially among the young, whose gigantic festivals generated feelings of religious exaltation. The texts of the songs are highly emotional and deal with a broad range of themes, from political protest to calls for a loud and lively dance party; accompaniments are provided by
    <xref articleid="38459">
     guitars
    </xref>
    , keyboards, and
    <xref articleid="105989">
     percussion
    </xref>
    instruments and are electronically
    <xref articleid="7258">
     amplified
    </xref>
    . Music educators were attracted by the intrinsic structural values of this music, especially its distinctive rhythmic and modal characteristics, its texts, and the qualitative levels that may be distinguished. A music so vital and widespread, moreover, was deemed by many to be worth studying in school. In the mid-20th century the rock music movement emerged as a musical-sociological phenomenon of large proportions. Within a few decades, programs in popular music had been established in many postsecondary institutions, and by the early 21st century musicologists, music theorists, and educators in various disciplines were actively involved in the study of virtually every major genre of popular music across the globe.
   </p>
  </h2>
  <h2 id="h64622">
   <title>
    Music and worldview
   </title>
   <p>
    Again, music proves its protean susceptibilities in the service of disparate worldviews. Among humanist psychologists (such as the Americans
    <xref articleid="5833">
     Gordon Allport
    </xref>
    and
    <xref articleid="51264">
     Abraham Maslow
    </xref>
    ) music may be one among other means toward self-fulfillment, integration, self-actualization; for aesthetic
    <xref articleid="108678">
     existentialists
    </xref>
    (such as the philosopher
    <xref articleid="65811">
     Jean-Paul Sartre
    </xref>
    ) it is yet another crucial department of choice and freedom; for spiritual existentialists (such as the philosophers
    <xref articleid="43410">
     Karl Jaspers
    </xref>
    and
    <xref articleid="17850">
     Martin Buber
    </xref>
    ) it transmits transcendent overtones. For expressionists (such as the composers Schoenberg,
    <xref articleid="46230">
     Ernst Krenek
    </xref>
    , and René Leibowitz) music carries austere, and sometimes doctrinaire, moral imperatives. Theodor Adorno, a composer-philosopher and pupil of
    <xref articleid="78736">
     Alban Berg
    </xref>
    , wrote powerfully of these and spoke for an awareness of dazzling lucidity, but the tone, notwithstanding his humour, was one of obligation. Only the expressionists, among those mentioned here, were committed primarily to music, though Adorno, in particular, considered music and musicians always in interaction with their environments. The aesthetic concept of play is virtually absent, except among such humanists as Maslow. With Sartre, no less a humanist, the tone was one of responsibility. Many educators long held the explicit aim (at least in part because of a misinterpretation of John Dewey) of presenting the content of a discipline as “fun”; the concern for aesthetic education, an area of great interest to Dewey himself, eschewed this trivial view. But play, in the aesthetic sense, follows rules, as
    <xref articleid="106012">
     information theory
    </xref>
    has demonstrated; even controlled aleatory composition observes some limits. And the play may be very serious indeed, as in the important 20th-century atonal style known as
    <xref articleid="73942">
     12-tone technique
    </xref>
    , practiced by the Viennese expressionists and their successors.
   </p>
  </h2>
  <h2 id="h64623">
   <title>
    Tonality and meaning
   </title>
   <p>
    <assembly id="a99693" url="/assembly/view/99693">
     <title>
      Richard Strauss
     </title>
     <media mediaid="99368" type="image" url="/68/99368-004-A501734C.jpg"/>
     <caption>
      Richard Strauss.
     </caption>
     <credit>
      Encyclopædia Britannica, Inc.
     </credit>
    </assembly>
    <assemblyref assemblyid="a99693"/>
    The most troublesome problem not only for the untutored listener but also for the professional musician has been, in much contemporary work, the loss of explicit tonality, and this accounts for the tardy popular response to Schoenberg and his school: the vocabulary is esoteric. Nineteenth-century compositions did, indeed, stretch the tonal system to its outer limits, but it is now clear that Wagner and
    <xref articleid="69931">
     Richard Strauss
    </xref>
    , and even the early Schoenberg, had not broken from it. As for
    <xref articleid="29672">
     Claude Debussy
    </xref>
    , his use of “exoticisms” was filigree upon a secure tonal base. So were such practices as the juxtaposition of keys by Stravinsky. This is not to say that the tonality of the Western world, fecund though it has been, is superior or more natural than other systems.
    <xref articleid="33140">
     Ethnomusicology
    </xref>
    has proved this to be a parochial view, though there are still those who champion harmonic practices based on the physical laws governing overtones—as Western tonality is—as the only “natural” source of development. It should not be irrelevant, however, to inquire if any
    <xref articleid="390003">
     folk music
    </xref>
    exhibits atonal characteristics.
   </p>
   <p>
    Tonality in Western music, though a significant aspect, cannot be considered the crux of musical meaning. The tone rows that are used in the 12-tone compositions of Schoenberg, like major and minor tonality in earlier music, are a technical substratum and must be no more explicit in the finished work than the chemical makeup of pigments in the
    <xref articleid="443963">
     <e type="italic">
      Mona Lisa
     </e>
    </xref>
    . The devices selected may affect the comprehensibility or accessibility of the work, but they are not, per se, the determinants of its worth or quality. Similarly with musical colour, or timbre; the 19th century produced a great profusion of compositions, particularly in the orchestral repertoire (e.g., works by Liszt and Berlioz) that exploited the unique sonorities of instruments; control of volume was, in itself, a rich source of colour. Works with literary or other extramusical associations were excellent vehicles for sonorous effects, but colour, like tonality, must be evaluated in musical context. Most notably, Langer, among other 20th-century aestheticians, regarded words themselves as musical, rather than discursive, ingredients; they are “assimilated” by the song.
   </p>
   <signature>
    Gordon Epperson
   </signature>
   <signature>
    EB Editors
   </signature>
  </h2>
 </h1>
 <h1 id="h64624">
  <title>
   Bibliography
  </title>
  <h2 id="h64625">
   <title>
    Modern theories of musical meaning
   </title>
   <p>
    <e type="smallcap">
     Arthur Schopenhauer
    </e>
    ,
    <e type="italic">
     Die Welt als Wille und Vorstellung
    </e>
    (1883; Eng. trans.,
    <e type="italic">
     The World as Will and Idea
    </e>
    , 1961); and
    <e type="smallcap">
     Friedrich Nietzsche
    </e>
    , “The Birth of Tragedy from the Spirit of Music,” trans. by
    <e type="smallcap">
     Clifton P. Fadiman
    </e>
    in
    <e type="italic">
     The Philosophy of Nietzsche
    </e>
    (1954), are two important expositions.
    <e type="smallcap">
     Eduard Hanslick
    </e>
    ,
    <e type="italic">
     Vom musikalisch Schönen
    </e>
    (1854; Eng. trans.,
    <e type="italic">
     The Beautiful in Music
    </e>
    , 1957), remains the best single exposition of the formalist (or nonreferentialist) position in musical aesthetics.
    <e type="smallcap">
     Edmund Gurney
    </e>
    ,
    <e type="italic">
     The Power of Sound
    </e>
    (1880, reprinted 1966), maintains a similar point of view but with considerably greater amplitude and subtlety. For background of the contemporary symbolist views of musical meaning, see
    <e type="smallcap">
     Alfred North Whitehead
    </e>
    ,
    <e type="italic">
     Symbolism
    </e>
    (1959);
    <e type="smallcap">
     Susanne K. Langer
    </e>
    , “On Significance in Music,” in
    <e type="italic">
     Philosophy in a New Key
    </e>
    , 2nd ed. (1951), and
    <e type="italic">
     Feeling and Form
    </e>
    (1953).
    <e type="smallcap">
     Leonard B. Meyer
    </e>
    has made an important contribution to the aesthetics of music. His interest in the relevance of information theory to music has been evidenced in two articles: “Meaning in Music and Information Theory,”
    <e type="italic">
     Journal of Aesthetics and Art Criticism
    </e>
    , 14:412–424 (1957), and “Some Remarks on Value and Greatness in Music,”
    <e type="italic">
     ibid.
    </e>
    , 17:486–500 (1959), reprinted in his
    <e type="italic">
     Music, The Arts, and Ideas: Patterns and Predictions in Twentieth-Century Culture
    </e>
    (1967).
    <e type="smallcap">
     John Dewey
    </e>
    ,
    <e type="italic">
     Art as Experience
    </e>
    (1934, reprinted 1959); and
    <e type="smallcap">
     Karl Jaspers
    </e>
    ,
    <e type="italic">
     Von der Wahrheit
    </e>
    (1947; Eng. trans.,
    <e type="italic">
     Truth and Symbol
    </e>
    , 1959), have given reinforcement to organic and symbolic theses, respectively.
    <e type="smallcap">
     Peter Le Huray
    </e>
    and
    <e type="smallcap">
     James Day
    </e>
    (eds.),
    <e type="italic">
     Music and Aesthetics in the Eighteenth and Early-Nineteenth Centuries
    </e>
    (1981), expounds theories of musical aesthetics from the pre- and early-Romantic period.
    <e type="smallcap">
     Peter Kivy
    </e>
    ,
    <e type="italic">
     The Corded Shell
    </e>
    (1981), is a study of the emotional expressivity of music.
   </p>
  </h2>
  <h2 id="h64626">
   <title>
    Performance practice, styles, and musical forms
   </title>
   <p>
    The best historical accounts of musical forms, styles, and performance practice are to be found in
    <e type="smallcap">
     Donald J. Grout
    </e>
    ,
    <e type="italic">
     A History of Western Music
    </e>
    (1960);
    <e type="smallcap">
     Gustave Reese
    </e>
    ,
    <e type="italic">
     Music in the Middle Ages
    </e>
    (1940), and
    <e type="italic">
     Music in the Renaissance
    </e>
    , rev. ed. (1959);
    <e type="smallcap">
     Manfred F. Bukofzer
    </e>
    ,
    <e type="italic">
     Music in the Baroque Era
    </e>
    (1947);
    <e type="smallcap">
     Alfred Einstein
    </e>
    ,
    <e type="italic">
     Music in the Romantic Era
    </e>
    (1947); and
    <e type="smallcap">
     William W. Austin
    </e>
    ,
    <e type="italic">
     Music in the 20th Century, from Debussy to Stravinsky
    </e>
    (1966).
    <e type="smallcap">
     Sir Donald Francis Tovey
    </e>
    ,
    <e type="italic">
     The Forms of Music
    </e>
    (1956), contains informative and engaging short pieces.
    <e type="smallcap">
     Robert Schumann
    </e>
    ,
    <e type="italic">
     On Music and Musicians
    </e>
    , ed. by
    <e type="smallcap">
     Konrad Wolff
    </e>
    (Eng. trans. 1947), is an example of the work by a 19th-century precursor of the phenomenon of the present-day composer-authors who have contributed to aesthetic theory by elucidating their own works and commentating on other composers and on the scene in general. See also
    <e type="smallcap">
     Igor Stravinsky
    </e>
    ,
    <e type="italic">
     Poetics of Music in the Form of Six Lessons
    </e>
    (1947);
    <e type="smallcap">
     Paul Hindemith
    </e>
    ,
    <e type="italic">
     A Composer’s World
    </e>
    (1952);
    <e type="smallcap">
     Aaron Copland
    </e>
    ,
    <e type="italic">
     Music and Imagination
    </e>
    (1952). Discussion of music and film may be found in
    <e type="smallcap">
     Lewis Jacobs
    </e>
    (ed.),
    <e type="italic">
     The Emergence of Film Art
    </e>
    (1969). Twelve-tone technique and varieties of serialism deriving from it are treated in
    <e type="smallcap">
     Arnold Schoenberg
    </e>
    ,
    <e type="italic">
     Style and Idea
    </e>
    (1950); and
    <e type="smallcap">
     René Leibowitz
    </e>
    ,
    <e type="italic">
     Schoenberg, et son école
    </e>
    (1947; Eng. trans.,
    <e type="italic">
     Schoenberg and His School
    </e>
    , 1949). Short pieces on electronic music appear often in periodical literature.
    <e type="smallcap">
     Harold C. Schonberg
    </e>
    ,
    <e type="italic">
     Facing the Music
    </e>
    (1981), is a collection of performance-oriented articles. See also
    <e type="smallcap">
     Carol MacClintock
    </e>
    (ed.),
    <e type="italic">
     Readings in the History of Music in Performance
    </e>
    (1979).
   </p>
  </h2>
 </h1>
 <copyright>
  Encyclopædia Britannica
 </copyright>
</article>