<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "syndication_xml.dtd">
<article articleid="110147" articletypeid="1" language="en_us" lastupdate="2021-Oct-27 08:03:33" url="/article/Earth/110147" version="38">
 <title>
  Earth
 </title>
 <p>
  <assembly id="a169506" url="/assembly/view/169506">
   <title>
    Earth
   </title>
   <media mediaid="160325" type="image" url="/25/160325-004-AD594C66.jpg"/>
   <caption>
    A composite image of Earth captured by instruments aboard NASA’s Suomi National Polar-orbiting Partnership satellite, 2012.
   </caption>
   <credit>
    NASA/NOAA/GSFC/Suomi NPP/VIIRS/Norman Kuring
   </credit>
  </assembly>
  <e type="bold">
   Earth
  </e>
  ,
  <assemblyref assemblyid="a169506"/>
  third planet from the
  <xref articleid="110144">
   Sun
  </xref>
  and the fifth largest planet in the
  <xref articleid="110143">
   solar system
  </xref>
  in terms of size and mass. Its single most outstanding feature is that its near-surface
  <xref articleid="32733">
   environments
  </xref>
  are the only places in the
  <xref articleid="74362">
   universe
  </xref>
  known to harbour life. It is designated by the symbol ♁. Earth’s name in
  <xref articleid="109779">
   English
  </xref>
  , the international language of
  <xref articleid="108656">
   astronomy
  </xref>
  , derives from
  <xref articleid="56971">
   Old English
  </xref>
  and Germanic words for
  <e type="italic">
   ground
  </e>
  and
  <e type="italic">
   earth
  </e>
  , and it is the only name for a
  <xref articleid="60298">
   planet
  </xref>
  of the
  <xref articleid="110143">
   solar system
  </xref>
  that does not come from Greco-Roman mythology.
 </p>
 <p>
  Since the Copernican revolution of the 16th century, at which time the Polish astronomer
  <xref articleid="105759">
   Nicolaus Copernicus
  </xref>
  proposed a Sun-centred model of the universe (
  <e type="italic">
   see
  </e>
  <xref articleid="39885">
   heliocentric system
  </xref>
  ), enlightened thinkers have regarded Earth as a planet like the others of the solar system. Concurrent sea voyages provided practical proof that Earth is a globe, just as
  <xref articleid="105766">
   Galileo
  </xref>
  ’s use of his newly invented telescope in the early 17th century soon showed various other planets to be globes as well. It was only after the dawn of the space age, however, when photographs from rockets and orbiting
  <xref articleid="68971">
   spacecraft
  </xref>
  first captured the dramatic curvature of Earth’s
  <xref articleid="41054">
   horizon
  </xref>
  , that the conception of Earth as a roughly spherical planet rather than as a flat entity was verified by direct human observation. Humans first witnessed Earth as a complete orb floating in the inky blackness of space in December 1968 when
  <xref articleid="8019">
   Apollo
  </xref>
  8 carried astronauts around the Moon. Robotic space probes on their way to destinations beyond Earth, such as the
  <xref articleid="35873">
   Galileo
  </xref>
  and the Near Earth Asteroid Rendezvous (NEAR) spacecraft in the 1990s, also looked back with their cameras to provide other unique portraits of the planet.
 </p>
 <p>
  Viewed from another planet in the solar system, Earth would appear bright and bluish in colour. Easiest to see through a large telescope would be its atmospheric features, chiefly the swirling white cloud patterns of midlatitude and
  <xref articleid="343943">
   tropical storms
  </xref>
  , ranged in roughly latitudinal belts around the
  <xref articleid="60298">
   planet
  </xref>
  . The polar regions also would appear a brilliant white, because of the clouds above and the snow and ice below. Beneath the changing patterns of clouds would appear the much darker blue-black oceans, interrupted by occasional tawny patches of
  <xref articleid="117275">
   desert
  </xref>
  lands. The green landscapes that harbour most human life would not be easily seen from space. Not only do they constitute a modest fraction of the land area, which itself is less than one-third of Earth’s surface, but they are often obscured by
  <xref articleid="24441">
   clouds
  </xref>
  . Over the course of the seasons, some changes in the storm patterns and cloud belts on Earth would be observed. Also prominent would be the growth and recession of the winter snowcap across land areas of the Northern Hemisphere.
 </p>
 <p>
  Scientists have applied the full battery of modern instrumentation to studying Earth in ways that have not yet been possible for the other planets; thus, much more is known about its structure and composition. This detailed knowledge, in turn, provides deeper insight into the mechanisms by which planets in general cool down, by which their
  <xref articleid="50022">
   magnetic fields
  </xref>
  are generated, and by which the separation of lighter elements from heavier ones as planets develop their internal structure releases additional energy for geologic processes and alters crustal compositions.
 </p>
 <p>
  Earth’s surface is traditionally subdivided into seven continental masses:
  <xref articleid="108290">
   Africa
  </xref>
  ,
  <xref articleid="109381">
   Antarctica
  </xref>
  ,
  <xref articleid="110518">
   Asia
  </xref>
  ,
  <xref articleid="110544">
   Australia
  </xref>
  ,
  <xref articleid="106055">
   Europe
  </xref>
  ,
  <xref articleid="110716">
   North America
  </xref>
  , and
  <xref articleid="109561">
   South America
  </xref>
  . These continents are surrounded by five major bodies of water: the
  <xref articleid="109839">
   Arctic
  </xref>
  ,
  <xref articleid="109727">
   Atlantic
  </xref>
  ,
  <xref articleid="106295">
   Indian
  </xref>
  ,
  <xref articleid="108644">
   Pacific
  </xref>
  , and
  <xref articleid="7750">
   Southern
  </xref>
  oceans. However, it is convenient to consider separate parts of Earth in terms of concentric, roughly spherical layers. Extending from the interior outward, these are the core, the
  <xref articleid="50643">
   mantle
  </xref>
  , the
  <xref articleid="28060">
   crust
  </xref>
  (including the rocky surface), the
  <xref articleid="106293">
   hydrosphere
  </xref>
  (predominantly the
  <xref articleid="108518">
   oceans
  </xref>
  , which fill in low places in the crust), the
  <xref articleid="126202">
   atmosphere
  </xref>
  (itself divided into spherical zones such as the
  <xref articleid="73507">
   troposphere
  </xref>
  , where weather occurs, and the
  <xref articleid="69919">
   stratosphere
  </xref>
  , where lies the
  <xref articleid="57880">
   ozone layer
  </xref>
  that shields Earth’s surface and its organisms against the
  <xref articleid="110144">
   Sun
  </xref>
  ’s ultraviolet rays), and the
  <xref articleid="50042">
   magnetosphere
  </xref>
  (an enormous region in space where Earth’s magnetic field dominates the behaviour of electrically charged particles coming from the Sun).
 </p>
 <p>
  Knowledge about these divisions is summarized in this astronomically oriented overview. The discussion complements other treatments oriented to the
  <xref articleid="106191">
   Earth sciences
  </xref>
  and life sciences. Earth’s figure and dimensions are discussed in the article
  <xref articleid="36451">
   geodesy
  </xref>
  . Its magnetic field is treated in the article
  <xref articleid="36468">
   geomagnetic field
  </xref>
  . The early evolution of the solid Earth and its atmosphere and oceans is covered in
  <xref articleid="117439">
   geologic history of Earth
  </xref>
  . The geologic and biological development of Earth, including its surface features and the processes by which they are created and modified, are discussed in
  <xref articleid="117437">
   geochronology
  </xref>
  ,
  <xref articleid="111007">
   continental landform
  </xref>
  , and
  <xref articleid="108555">
   plate tectonics
  </xref>
  . The behaviour of the atmosphere and of its tenuous, ionized outer reaches is treated in
  <xref articleid="109848">
   atmosphere
  </xref>
  , while the water cycle and major hydrologic features are described in
  <xref articleid="106293">
   hydrosphere
  </xref>
  ,
  <xref articleid="108518">
   ocean
  </xref>
  , and
  <xref articleid="109500">
   river
  </xref>
  . The solid Earth as a field of study is covered in
  <xref articleid="106192">
   geologic sciences
  </xref>
  , the methods and instruments employed to investigate Earth’s surface and interior are discussed in
  <xref articleid="111024">
   Earth exploration
  </xref>
  , and the history of the study of Earth from antiquity to modern times is surveyed in
  <xref articleid="106191">
   Earth sciences
  </xref>
  . The global ecosystem of living organisms and their life-supporting stratum are detailed in
  <xref articleid="117266">
   biosphere
  </xref>
  .
 </p>
 <h1 id="h54194">
  <title>
   Basic planetary data
  </title>
  <p>
   <assembly id="a159380" url="/assembly/view/159380">
    <title>
     Study Earth’s daily rotation on its axis and yearly revolution around the Sun
    </title>
    <media mediaid="151528" thumburl="/28/151528-049-1FB86498.jpg" type="video" url=""/>
    <caption>
     Earth’s rotation on its axis and its revolution around the Sun.
    </caption>
    <credit>
     Encyclopædia Britannica, Inc.
    </credit>
   </assembly>
   <assembly id="a3473" url="/assembly/view/3473">
    <title>
     Earth
    </title>
    <media mediaid="4280" type="image" url="/80/4280-004-C7086222.jpg"/>
    <caption>
     The planet Earth, as photographed from the Galileo spacecraft during its December 1990 flyby en route to Jupiter. The predominance of water on Earth is apparent, both as ocean and in the form of swirling clouds. The landmass at centre right is Australia, and the bright white patch at the bottom is the South Polar ice cap covering Antarctica.
    </caption>
    <credit>
     NASA/JPL
    </credit>
   </assembly>
   <assemblyref assemblyid="a159380"/>
   <assemblyref assemblyid="a3473"/>
   The mean distance of Earth from the Sun is about 149,600,000 km (92,960,000 miles). The planet orbits the Sun in a path that is presently more nearly a circle (less eccentric) than are the orbits of all but two of the other planets,
   <xref articleid="110146">
    Venus
   </xref>
   and
   <xref articleid="110153">
    Neptune
   </xref>
   . Earth makes one revolution, or one complete orbit of the Sun, in about 365.25 days. The direction of revolution—counterclockwise as viewed down from the north—is in the same sense, or direction, as the rotation of the Sun; Earth’s spin, or rotation about its axis, is also in the same sense, which is called direct or prograde. The rotation period, or length of a sidereal day (
   <e type="italic">
    see
   </e>
   <xref articleid="29551">
    day
   </xref>
   ;
   <xref articleid="67638">
    sidereal time
   </xref>
   )—23 hours, 56 minutes, and 4 seconds—is similar to that of
   <xref articleid="110149">
    Mars
   </xref>
   .
   <xref articleid="110150">
    Jupiter
   </xref>
   and most
   <xref articleid="110155">
    asteroids
   </xref>
   have days less than half as long, while
   <xref articleid="110145">
    Mercury
   </xref>
   and Venus have days more nearly comparable to their orbital periods. The 23.44° tilt, or inclination, of Earth’s axis to its orbital plane, also typical, results in greater heating and more hours of daylight in one hemisphere or the other over the course of a year and so is responsible for the cyclic change of
   <xref articleid="66491">
    seasons
   </xref>
   .
  </p>
  <p>
   <assembly id="a250639" url="/assembly/view/250639">
    <title>
     Earth and the Moon
    </title>
    <media mediaid="209766" type="image" url="/66/209766-004-B5FF7863.jpg"/>
    <caption>
     Image taken by the Galileo spacecraft eight days after its final encounter with Earth and the Moon, 1992. The image was taken from a distance of about 6.2 million km (3.9 million miles).
    </caption>
    <credit>
     NASA
    </credit>
   </assembly>
   <assemblyref assemblyid="a250639"/>
   With an equatorial radius of 6,378 km (3,963 miles), Earth is the largest of the four inner, terrestrial (rocky) planets, but it is considerably smaller than the gas giants of the outer
   <xref articleid="110143">
    solar system
   </xref>
   . Earth has a single natural satellite, the
   <xref articleid="53598">
    Moon
   </xref>
   , which orbits the planet at a mean distance of about 384,400 km (238,900 miles). The Moon is one of the bigger natural satellites in the solar system; only the giant planets have moons comparable or larger in size. Some planetary astronomers consider the Earth-Moon system a double planet, with some similarity in that regard to the dwarf planet
   <xref articleid="110154">
    Pluto
   </xref>
   and its largest moon,
   <xref articleid="22640">
    Charon
   </xref>
   .
  </p>
  <p>
   Earth’s gravitational field (
   <e type="italic">
    see
   </e>
   <xref articleid="106265">
    gravitation
   </xref>
   ) is manifested as the attractive force acting on a free body at rest, causing it to accelerate in the general direction of the centre of the planet. Departures from the spherical shape and the effect of Earth’s rotation cause gravity to vary with latitude over the terrestrial surface. The average gravitational acceleration at sea level is about 980 cm/sec
   <sup>
    2
   </sup>
   (32.2 feet/sec
   <sup>
    2
   </sup>
   ).
  </p>
  <p>
   Earth’s gravity keeps the Moon in its
   <xref articleid="57286">
    orbit
   </xref>
   around the planet and also generates tides in the solid body of the Moon. Such deformations are manifested in the form of slight bulges at the lunar surface, detectable only by sensitive instruments. In turn, the Moon’s mass—relatively large for a natural
   <xref articleid="65844">
    satellite
   </xref>
   —exerts a gravitational force that causes
   <xref articleid="72409">
    tides
   </xref>
   on Earth. The Sun, much more distant but vastly more massive, also raises tides on Earth. (
   <e type="italic">
    See
   </e>
   <xref articleid="110308" refid="h77439">
    celestial mechanics: Tidal evolution
   </xref>
   .) The tides are most apparent as the twice-daily and daily rises and falls of the ocean water, although tidal deformations occur in the solid Earth and in the atmosphere as well (
   <e type="italic">
    see
   </e>
   <xref articleid="72409">
    tide
   </xref>
   ). The movement of the water throughout the ocean basins as a result of the tides (as well as, to a lesser extent, the tidal distortion of the solid Earth) dissipates orbital
   <xref articleid="45490">
    kinetic energy
   </xref>
   as
   <xref articleid="39732">
    heat
   </xref>
   , producing a gradual slowing of Earth’s rotation and a spiraling outward of the Moon’s orbit. Currently this slowing lengthens the
   <xref articleid="29551">
    day
   </xref>
   by a few thousandths of a second per century, but the rate of slowing varies with time as plate tectonics and sea-level changes alter the areas covered by inland
   <xref articleid="13842">
    bays
   </xref>
   and shallow seas. (For additional orbital and physical data,
   <e type="italic">
    see
   </e>
   the .)
  </p>
 </h1>
 <h1 id="h54195">
  <title>
   The atmosphere and hydrosphere
  </title>
  <p>
   The blankets of volatile
   <xref articleid="110302">
    gases
   </xref>
   and
   <xref articleid="110301">
    liquids
   </xref>
   near and above the surface of Earth are, along with
   <xref articleid="68559">
    solar energy
   </xref>
   , of prime importance to the sustenance of life on Earth. They are distributed and recycled throughout the atmosphere and
   <xref articleid="106293">
    hydrosphere
   </xref>
   of the planet.
  </p>
  <h2 id="h54196">
   <title>
    The atmosphere
   </title>
   <p>
    Earth is surrounded by a relatively thin
    <xref articleid="126202">
     atmosphere
    </xref>
    (commonly called
    <xref articleid="5193">
     air
    </xref>
    ) consisting of a mixture of gases, primarily molecular
    <xref articleid="55947">
     nitrogen
    </xref>
    (78 percent) and molecular
    <xref articleid="57841">
     oxygen
    </xref>
    (21 percent). Also present are much smaller amounts of gases such as
    <xref articleid="9382">
     argon
    </xref>
    (nearly 1 percent), water vapour (averaging 1 percent but highly variable in time and location),
    <xref articleid="20249">
     carbon dioxide
    </xref>
    (0.0395 percent [395 parts per million] and presently rising),
    <xref articleid="52328">
     methane
    </xref>
    (0.00018 percent [1.8 parts per million] and presently rising), and others, along with minute
    <xref articleid="68592">
     solid
    </xref>
    and liquid particles in suspension.
   </p>
   <p>
    Because Earth has a weak gravitational field (by virtue of its size) and warm atmospheric
    <xref articleid="71632">
     temperatures
    </xref>
    (due to its proximity to the Sun) compared with the giant
    <xref articleid="60298">
     planets
    </xref>
    , it lacks the most common gases in the universe that they possess:
    <xref articleid="110604">
     hydrogen
    </xref>
    and
    <xref articleid="1713">
     helium
    </xref>
    . Whereas both the
    <xref articleid="110144">
     Sun
    </xref>
    and
    <xref articleid="110150">
     Jupiter
    </xref>
    are composed predominantly of these two elements, they could not be retained long on early Earth and rapidly evaporated into interplanetary space. The high
    <xref articleid="57841">
     oxygen
    </xref>
    content of Earth’s atmosphere is out of the ordinary. Oxygen is a highly reactive gas that, under most planetary conditions, would be combined with other chemicals in the atmosphere, surface, and
    <xref articleid="28060">
     crust
    </xref>
    . It is in fact supplied continuously by biological processes; without life, there would be virtually no free oxygen. The 1.8 parts per million of
    <xref articleid="52328">
     methane
    </xref>
    in the atmosphere is also far out of chemical equilibrium with the atmosphere and crust: it, too, is of biological origin, with the contribution by
    <xref articleid="41467">
     human
    </xref>
    activities far outweighing others.
   </p>
   <p>
    The gases of the atmosphere extend from the surface of Earth to heights of thousands of kilometres, eventually merging with the
    <xref articleid="68567">
     solar wind
    </xref>
    —a stream of charged particles that flows outward from the outermost regions of the Sun. The composition of the atmosphere is more or less constant with height to an altitude of about 100 km (60 miles), with particular exceptions being water vapour and
    <xref articleid="57878">
     ozone
    </xref>
    .
   </p>
   <p>
    The atmosphere is commonly described in terms of distinct layers, or regions. Most of the atmosphere is concentrated in the
    <xref articleid="73507">
     troposphere
    </xref>
    , which extends from the surface to an
    <xref articleid="5936">
     altitude
    </xref>
    of about 10–15 km (6–9 miles), depending on
    <xref articleid="47303">
     latitude
    </xref>
    and season. The behaviour of the gases in this layer is controlled by
    <xref articleid="26084">
     convection
    </xref>
    . This process involves the turbulent, overturning motions resulting from buoyancy of near-surface air that is warmed by the
    <xref articleid="110144">
     Sun
    </xref>
    . Convection maintains a decreasing vertical
    <xref articleid="71632">
     temperature
    </xref>
    gradient—i.e., a temperature decline with altitude—of roughly 6 °C (10.8 °F) per km through the troposphere. At the top of the troposphere, which is called the tropopause, temperatures have fallen to about −80 °C (−112 °F). The
    <xref articleid="73507">
     troposphere
    </xref>
    is the region where nearly all water vapour exists and essentially all
    <xref articleid="76362">
     weather
    </xref>
    occurs.
   </p>
   <p>
    The dry, tenuous
    <xref articleid="69919">
     stratosphere
    </xref>
    lies above the troposphere and extends to an altitude of about 50 km (30 miles). Convective motions are weak or absent in the stratosphere; motions instead tend to be horizontally oriented. The temperature in this layer increases with altitude.
   </p>
   <p>
    In the upper stratospheric regions, absorption of
    <xref articleid="74181">
     ultraviolet light
    </xref>
    from the Sun breaks down molecular oxygen (O
    <sub>
     2
    </sub>
    ); recombination of single oxygen atoms with O
    <sub>
     2
    </sub>
    molecules into
    <xref articleid="57878">
     ozone
    </xref>
    (O
    <sub>
     3
    </sub>
    ) creates the shielding
    <xref articleid="57880">
     ozone layer
    </xref>
    .
   </p>
   <p>
    Above the relatively warm stratopause is the even more tenuous
    <xref articleid="52226">
     mesosphere
    </xref>
    , in which temperatures again decline with altitude to 80–90 km (50–56 miles) above the surface, where the mesopause is defined. The minimum temperature attained there is extremely variable with
    <xref articleid="66491">
     season
    </xref>
    . Temperatures then rise with increasing height through the overlying layer known as the
    <xref articleid="72093">
     thermosphere
    </xref>
    . Also above about 80–90 km there is an increasing fraction of charged, or ionized, particles, which from this altitude upward defines the
    <xref articleid="42708">
     ionosphere
    </xref>
    . Spectacular visible
    <xref articleid="11293">
     auroras
    </xref>
    are generated in this region, particularly along approximately circular zones around the poles, by the interaction of
    <xref articleid="55947">
     nitrogen
    </xref>
    and
    <xref articleid="57841">
     oxygen
    </xref>
    atoms in the atmosphere with episodic bursts of energetic particles originating from the Sun.
   </p>
   <p>
    Earth’s general
    <xref articleid="10119">
     atmospheric circulation
    </xref>
    is driven by the energy of sunlight, which is more abundant in equatorial latitudes. Movement of this heat toward the poles is strongly affected by Earth’s rapid rotation and the associated
    <xref articleid="26305">
     Coriolis force
    </xref>
    at latitudes away from the
    <xref articleid="32837">
     Equator
    </xref>
    (which adds an east-west component to the direction of the
    <xref articleid="77159">
     winds
    </xref>
    ), resulting in multiple cells of circulating air in each hemisphere. Instabilities (
    <xref articleid="59369">
     perturbations
    </xref>
    in the atmospheric flow that grow with time) produce the characteristic high-pressure areas and low-pressure storms of the midlatitudes as well as the fast, eastward-moving
    <xref articleid="43586">
     jet streams
    </xref>
    of the upper troposphere that guide the paths of storms. The
    <xref articleid="108518">
     oceans
    </xref>
    are massive reservoirs of heat that act largely to smooth out variations in Earth’s global temperatures, but their slowly changing currents and temperatures also influence
    <xref articleid="76362">
     weather
    </xref>
    and
    <xref articleid="106248">
     climate
    </xref>
    , as in the El Niño/Southern Oscillation weather phenomenon (
    <e type="italic">
     see
    </e>
    <xref articleid="106248" refid="h53254">
     climate: Circulation, currents, and ocean-atmosphere interaction
    </xref>
    ;
    <xref articleid="106248" refid="h301643">
     climate: El Niño/Southern Oscillation and climatic change
    </xref>
    ).
   </p>
   <p>
    Earth’s atmosphere is not a static feature of the environment. Rather, its composition has evolved over
    <xref articleid="36466">
     geologic time
    </xref>
    in concert with life and is changing more rapidly today in response to human activities. Roughly halfway through the history of Earth, the atmosphere’s unusually high abundance of free oxygen began to develop, through
    <xref articleid="108553">
     photosynthesis
    </xref>
    by cyanobacteria (
    <e type="italic">
     see
    </e>
    <xref articleid="15751">
     blue-green algae
    </xref>
    ) and saturation of natural surface sinks of oxygen (e.g., relatively oxygen-poor minerals and
    <xref articleid="110604">
     hydrogen
    </xref>
    -rich
    <xref articleid="110302">
     gases
    </xref>
    exuded from
    <xref articleid="108777">
     volcanoes
    </xref>
    ). Accumulation of oxygen made it possible for complex cells, which consume oxygen during
    <xref articleid="109831">
     metabolism
    </xref>
    and of which all
    <xref articleid="108554">
     plants
    </xref>
    and
    <xref articleid="110237">
     animals
    </xref>
    are composed, to develop (
    <e type="italic">
     see
    </e>
    <xref articleid="33173">
     eukaryote
    </xref>
    ).
   </p>
   <p>
    Earth’s
    <xref articleid="106248">
     climate
    </xref>
    at any location varies with the seasons, but there are also longer-term variations in global climate. Volcanic explosions, such as the 1991 eruption of
    <xref articleid="60054">
     Mount Pinatubo
    </xref>
    in the Philippines, can inject great quantities of dust particles into the
    <xref articleid="69919">
     stratosphere
    </xref>
    , which remain suspended for years, decreasing atmospheric transparency and resulting in measurable cooling worldwide. Much rarer, giant impacts of
    <xref articleid="110155">
     asteroids
    </xref>
    and
    <xref articleid="110156">
     comets
    </xref>
    can produce even more profound effects, including severe reductions in
    <xref articleid="70375">
     sunlight
    </xref>
    for months or years, such as many scientists believe led to the mass extinction of living species at the end of the
    <xref articleid="117451">
     Cretaceous Period
    </xref>
    , 66 million years ago. (For additional information on the risks posed by cosmic impacts and the chances of their occurrence,
    <e type="italic">
     see
    </e>
    <xref articleid="343051">
     Earth impact hazard
    </xref>
    .) The dominant climate variations observed in the recent geologic record are the
    <xref articleid="41958">
     ice ages
    </xref>
    , which are linked to variations in Earth’s tilt and its orbital geometry with respect to the
    <xref articleid="110144">
     Sun
    </xref>
    .
   </p>
   <p>
    The physics of
    <xref articleid="110604">
     hydrogen
    </xref>
    fusion leads astronomers to conclude that the Sun was 30 percent less luminous during the earliest history of Earth than it is today. Hence, all else being equal, the oceans should have been frozen. Observations of Earth’s planetary neighbours,
    <xref articleid="110149">
     Mars
    </xref>
    and
    <xref articleid="110146">
     Venus
    </xref>
    , and estimates of the
    <xref articleid="110609">
     carbon
    </xref>
    locked in Earth’s crust at present suggest that there was much more
    <xref articleid="20249">
     carbon dioxide
    </xref>
    in Earth’s atmosphere during earlier periods. This would have enhanced warming of the surface via the
    <xref articleid="37976">
     greenhouse effect
    </xref>
    and so allowed the oceans to remain liquid.
   </p>
   <p>
    Today there is 100,000 times more carbon dioxide buried in
    <xref articleid="20260">
     carbonate rocks
    </xref>
    in Earth’s crust than in the atmosphere, in sharp contrast to Venus, whose atmospheric evolution followed a different course. On Earth, the formation of carbonate shells by marine life is the principal mechanism for transforming carbon dioxide to carbonates; abiotic processes involving liquid water also produce
    <xref articleid="20258">
     carbonates
    </xref>
    , albeit more slowly. On Venus, however, life never had the chance to arise and to generate carbonates. Because of the planet’s location in the
    <xref articleid="110143">
     solar system
    </xref>
    , early Venus received 10–20 percent more sunlight than falls on Earth even today, despite the fainter young Sun at the time. Most planetary scientists believe that the elevated surface
    <xref articleid="71632">
     temperature
    </xref>
    that resulted kept water from condensing to a liquid. Instead, it remained in the atmosphere as water vapour, which, like carbon dioxide, is an efficient
    <xref articleid="473968">
     greenhouse gas
    </xref>
    . Together the two gases caused surface temperatures to rise even higher so that massive amounts of water escaped to the stratosphere, where it was dissociated by solar
    <xref articleid="74181">
     ultraviolet radiation
    </xref>
    . With conditions now too hot and dry to permit abiotic carbonate formation, most or all of the planet’s inventory of carbon remained in the atmosphere as carbon dioxide. Models predict that Earth may suffer the same fate in a billion years, when the Sun exceeds its present brightness by 10–20 percent.
   </p>
   <p>
    Between the late 1950s and the end of the 20th century, the amount of carbon dioxide in Earth’s atmosphere increased by more than 15 percent because of the burning of
    <xref articleid="35002">
     fossil fuels
    </xref>
    (e.g.,
    <xref articleid="110442">
     coal
    </xref>
    ,
    <xref articleid="56871">
     oil
    </xref>
    , and
    <xref articleid="110439">
     natural gas
    </xref>
    ) and the destruction of
    <xref articleid="117270">
     tropical rainforests
    </xref>
    , such as that of the
    <xref articleid="109565">
     Amazon River
    </xref>
    basin. Computer models predict that a net doubling of carbon dioxide by the middle of the 21st century could lead to a
    <xref articleid="37044">
     global warming
    </xref>
    of 1.5–4.5 °C (2.7–8.1 °F) averaged over the
    <xref articleid="60298">
     planet
    </xref>
    , which would have profound effects on
    <xref articleid="66445">
     sea level
    </xref>
    and
    <xref articleid="106077">
     agriculture
    </xref>
    . Although this conclusion has been criticized by some on the basis that the warming observed so far has not kept pace with the projection, analyses of ocean temperature data have suggested that much of the warming during the 20th century actually occurred in the oceans themselves—and will eventually appear in the atmosphere.
   </p>
   <p>
    Another present concern regarding the atmosphere is the impact of human activities on the stratospheric
    <xref articleid="57880">
     ozone layer
    </xref>
    . Complex chemical reactions involving traces of man-made
    <xref articleid="82249">
     chlorofluorocarbons
    </xref>
    (CFCs) were found in the mid-1980s to be creating temporary holes in the
    <xref articleid="57880">
     ozone layer
    </xref>
    , particularly over
    <xref articleid="109381">
     Antarctica
    </xref>
    , during polar spring. Yet more disturbing was the discovery of a growing
    <xref articleid="488058">
     depletion of ozone
    </xref>
    over the highly populated temperate latitudes, since the short-
    <xref articleid="76325">
     wavelength
    </xref>
    <xref articleid="74181">
     ultraviolet radiation
    </xref>
    that the ozone layer effectively absorbs has been found to cause skin cancer. International agreements in place to halt the production of the most egregious ozone-destroying CFCs will eventually halt and reverse the depletion, but only by the middle of the 21st century, because of the long residence time of these chemicals in the stratosphere.
   </p>
  </h2>
  <h2 id="h54197">
   <title>
    The hydrosphere
   </title>
   <p>
    <assembly id="a69410" url="/assembly/view/69410">
     <title>
      surface hydrologic cycle
     </title>
     <media mediaid="1473" type="image" url="/73/1473-004-BD6A1807.jpg"/>
     <caption>
      The present-day surface hydrologic cycle, in which water is transferred from the oceans through the atmosphere to the continents and back to the oceans over and beneath the land surface. The values in parentheses following the various forms of water (e.g., ice) refer to volumes in millions of cubic kilometres; those following the processes (e.g., precipitation) refer to their fluxes in millions of cubic kilometres of water per year.
     </caption>
     <credit>
      Encyclopædia Britannica, Inc.
     </credit>
    </assembly>
    <assemblyref assemblyid="a69410"/>
    Earth’s
    <xref articleid="106293">
     hydrosphere
    </xref>
    is a discontinuous layer of water at or near the planet’s surface; it includes all liquid and frozen surface waters,
    <xref articleid="38222">
     groundwater
    </xref>
    held in
    <xref articleid="109555">
     soil
    </xref>
    and
    <xref articleid="109695">
     rock
    </xref>
    , and atmospheric water vapour. Unique within the solar system, the hydrosphere is essential to all life as it is presently understood. Earth has a surface area of roughly 510,066,000 square km (196,938,000 square miles); almost 71 percent of Earth’s surface is covered by saltwater
    <xref articleid="108518">
     oceans
    </xref>
    . The total volume of liquid water on Earth is about 1.39 billion cubic km (332.5 million cubic miles), and it has an average temperature of about 4 °C (39.2 °F), not far above the
    <xref articleid="35313">
     freezing point
    </xref>
    of water. The oceans contain about 97 percent of the planet’s water volume. The remainder occurs as fresh water, three-quarters of which is locked up in the form of
    <xref articleid="108437">
     ice
    </xref>
    at polar latitudes. Most of the remaining fresh water is
    <xref articleid="38222">
     groundwater
    </xref>
    held in soils and rocks; less than 1 percent of it occurs in
    <xref articleid="108459">
     lakes
    </xref>
    and
    <xref articleid="109500">
     rivers
    </xref>
    . In terms of percentage, atmospheric water vapour is negligible, but the transport of water evaporated from the oceans onto land surfaces is an integral part of the
    <xref articleid="41738">
     hydrologic cycle
    </xref>
    that renews and sustains life.
   </p>
   <p>
    The hydrologic cycle involves the transfer of water from the oceans through the atmosphere to the
    <xref articleid="26050">
     continents
    </xref>
    and back to the
    <xref articleid="108518">
     oceans
    </xref>
    over and beneath the land surface. The cycle includes processes such as
    <xref articleid="61233">
     precipitation
    </xref>
    ,
    <xref articleid="472295">
     evaporation
    </xref>
    ,
    <xref articleid="73214">
     transpiration
    </xref>
    , infiltration, percolation, and
    <xref articleid="64427">
     runoff
    </xref>
    . These processes operate throughout the entire
    <xref articleid="106293">
     hydrosphere
    </xref>
    , which extends from about 15 km (9 miles) into the atmosphere to roughly 5 km (3 miles) into the crust.
   </p>
   <p>
    About one-third of the solar energy that reaches Earth’s surface is expended on evaporating ocean water. The resulting atmospheric moisture and
    <xref articleid="41502">
     humidity
    </xref>
    condense into
    <xref articleid="24441">
     clouds
    </xref>
    ,
    <xref articleid="62486">
     rain
    </xref>
    ,
    <xref articleid="68389">
     snow
    </xref>
    , and
    <xref articleid="30180">
     dew
    </xref>
    . Moisture is a crucial factor in determining
    <xref articleid="76362">
     weather
    </xref>
    . It is the driving force behind
    <xref articleid="69834">
     storms
    </xref>
    and is responsible for separating electrical charge, which is the cause of
    <xref articleid="48228">
     lightning
    </xref>
    and thus of natural wildland
    <xref articleid="34321">
     fires
    </xref>
    , which have an important role in some
    <xref articleid="31944">
     ecosystems
    </xref>
    . Moisture wets the
    <xref articleid="472715">
     land
    </xref>
    , replenishes subterranean
    <xref articleid="8129">
     aquifers
    </xref>
    , chemically
    <xref articleid="76370">
     weathers
    </xref>
    the rocks,
    <xref articleid="32940">
     erodes
    </xref>
    the landscape, nourishes life, and fills the rivers, which carry dissolved chemicals and sediments back into the oceans.
   </p>
   <p>
    Water also plays a vital role in the carbon dioxide cycle (a part of the more inclusive
    <xref articleid="20247">
     carbon cycle
    </xref>
    ). Under the action of water and dissolved carbon dioxide,
    <xref articleid="18627">
     calcium
    </xref>
    is weathered from continental rocks and carried to the oceans, where it combines to form calcium carbonates (including shells of marine life). Eventually the carbonates are deposited on the seafloor and are lithified to form
    <xref articleid="48303">
     limestones
    </xref>
    . Some of these carbonate rocks are later dragged deep into Earth’s interior by the global process of plate tectonics (
    <e type="italic">
     see below
    </e>
    <xref articleid="110147" refid="h54198">
     The outer shell
    </xref>
    ) and melted, resulting in a rerelease of carbon dioxide (from
    <xref articleid="108777">
     volcanoes
    </xref>
    , for example) into the atmosphere. Cyclic processing of water, carbon dioxide, and
    <xref articleid="57841">
     oxygen
    </xref>
    through geologic and biological systems on Earth has been fundamental to maintaining the habitability of the planet with time and to shaping the
    <xref articleid="32940">
     erosion
    </xref>
    and weathering of the continents, and it contrasts sharply with the lack of such processes on
    <xref articleid="110146">
     Venus
    </xref>
    . (Evidence of past episodes of liquid water erosion—and possibly limited amounts of such erosion today—has been found on
    <xref articleid="110149">
     Mars
    </xref>
    .)
   </p>
  </h2>
 </h1>
 <h1 id="h54198">
  <title>
   The outer shell
  </title>
  <p>
   <assembly id="a149144" url="/assembly/view/149144">
    <title>
     Earth: surface composition
    </title>
    <media mediaid="102390" type="image" url="/90/102390-004-B95FDDE0.jpg"/>
    <caption>
     Percentage of Earth’s surface devoted to various land and water features.
    </caption>
    <credit>
     Encyclopædia Britannica, Inc.
    </credit>
   </assembly>
   <assemblyref assemblyid="a149144"/>
   Earth’s outermost, rigid, rocky layer is called the
   <xref articleid="28060">
    crust
   </xref>
   . It is composed of low-density, easily melted rocks; the continental crust is predominantly granitic rock (
   <e type="italic">
    see
   </e>
   <xref articleid="37718">
    granite
   </xref>
   ), while composition of the oceanic crust corresponds mainly to that of
   <xref articleid="13572">
    basalt
   </xref>
   and
   <xref articleid="35744">
    gabbro
   </xref>
   . Analyses of
   <xref articleid="66632">
    seismic waves
   </xref>
   , generated by
   <xref articleid="106195">
    earthquakes
   </xref>
   within Earth’s interior, show that the crust extends about 50 km (30 miles) beneath the continents but only 5–10 km (3–6 miles) beneath the ocean floors.
  </p>
  <p>
   At the base of the crust, a sharp change in the observed behaviour of seismic waves marks the interface with the
   <xref articleid="50643">
    mantle
   </xref>
   . The mantle is composed of denser rocks, on which the rocks of the crust float. On geologic timescales, the mantle behaves as a very viscous fluid and responds to stress by flowing. Together the uppermost mantle and the crust act mechanically as a single rigid layer, called the
   <xref articleid="472772">
    lithosphere
   </xref>
   .
  </p>
  <p>
   <assembly id="a69411" url="/assembly/view/69411">
    <title>
     Earth’s principal tectonic plates
    </title>
    <media mediaid="3537" type="image" url="/37/3537-004-C6EE8FD4.jpg"/>
    <caption>
     The principal tectonic plates that make up Earth’s lithosphere. Also located are several dozen hotspots where plumes of hot mantle material are upwelling beneath the plates.
    </caption>
    <credit>
     Encyclopædia Britannica, Inc.
    </credit>
   </assembly>
   <assemblyref assemblyid="a69411"/>
   The lithospheric outer shell of Earth is not one continuous piece but is broken, like a slightly cracked eggshell, into about a dozen major separate rigid blocks, or plates. There are two types of plates, oceanic and continental. An example of an oceanic plate is the Pacific Plate, which extends from the
   <xref articleid="31790">
    East Pacific Rise
   </xref>
   to the
   <xref articleid="29727">
    deep-sea trenches
   </xref>
   bordering the western part of the Pacific basin. A continental plate is exemplified by the North American Plate, which includes
   <xref articleid="110716">
    North America
   </xref>
   as well as the oceanic crust between it and a portion of the
   <xref articleid="52526">
    Mid-Atlantic Ridge
   </xref>
   . The latter is an enormous submarine mountain chain that extends down the axis of the Atlantic basin, passing midway between
   <xref articleid="108290">
    Africa
   </xref>
   and North and
   <xref articleid="109561">
    South America
   </xref>
   .
  </p>
  <p>
   <assembly id="a69412" url="/assembly/view/69412">
    <title>
     production and destruction of Earth’s crust
    </title>
    <media mediaid="3534" type="image" url="/34/3534-004-EAA9832C.jpg"/>
    <caption>
     Production and destruction of Earth’s crust according to the theory of plate tectonics. Oceanic crust is continually generated at divergent plate boundaries (typified by midocean ridges and their rift zones) from upwelling mantle material, and it is consumed in the subduction process at convergent plate boundaries (marked by deep-sea trenches). Areas of convergence are sites of mountain building or of formation of volcanic island arcs. At transform, or strike-slip, boundaries, two plates slide past each other laterally; these areas are often associated with a high frequency of earthquakes.
    </caption>
    <credit>
     Encyclopædia Britannica, Inc.
    </credit>
   </assembly>
   <assemblyref assemblyid="a69412"/>
   The lithospheric plates are about 60 km (35 miles) thick beneath the oceans and 100–200 km (60–120 miles) beneath the continents. (It should be noted that these thicknesses are defined by the mechanical rigidity of the lithospheric material. They do not correspond to the thickness of the crust, which is defined at its base by the discontinuity in seismic wave behaviour, as cited above.) They ride on a weak, perhaps partially molten, layer of the upper mantle called the
   <xref articleid="471801">
    asthenosphere
   </xref>
   . Slow convection currents deep within the mantle generated by radioactive heating of the interior drive lateral movements of the plates (and the continents on top of them) at a rate of several centimetres per year. The plates interact along their margins, and these boundaries are classified into three general types on the basis of the relative motions of the adjacent plates: divergent, convergent, and transform (or strike-slip).
  </p>
  <p>
   In areas of divergence, two plates move away from each other. Buoyant upwelling motions in the mantle force the plates apart at rift zones (such as along the middle of the Atlantic Ocean floor), where magmas from the underlying mantle rise to form new oceanic crustal rocks.
  </p>
  <p>
   Lithospheric plates move toward each other along convergent boundaries. When a continental plate and an oceanic plate come together, the leading edge of the oceanic plate is forced beneath the continental plate and down into the asthenosphere—a process called subduction. Only the thinner, denser slabs of oceanic crust will subduct, however. When two thicker, more buoyant continents come together at convergent zones, they resist subduction and tend to buckle, producing great
   <xref articleid="111009">
    mountain
   </xref>
   ranges. The
   <xref articleid="110521">
    Himalayas
   </xref>
   , along with the adjacent
   <xref articleid="72386">
    Plateau of Tibet
   </xref>
   , were formed during such a continent-continent collision, when
   <xref articleid="111197">
    India
   </xref>
   was carried into the Eurasian Plate by relative motion of the Indian-Australian Plate.
  </p>
  <p>
   At the third type of plate boundary, the transform variety, two plates slide parallel to one another in opposite directions. These areas are often associated with high seismicity, as stresses that build up in the sliding crustal slabs are released at intervals to generate
   <xref articleid="106195">
    earthquakes
   </xref>
   . The
   <xref articleid="65260">
    San Andreas Fault
   </xref>
   in
   <xref articleid="111278">
    California
   </xref>
   is an example of this type of boundary, which is also known as a
   <xref articleid="33830">
    fault
   </xref>
   or fracture zone (
   <e type="italic">
    see
   </e>
   <xref articleid="70105">
    submarine fracture zone
   </xref>
   ).
  </p>
  <p>
   Most of Earth’s active tectonic processes, including nearly all earthquakes, occur near plate margins. Volcanoes form along
   <xref articleid="70092">
    zones of subduction
   </xref>
   , because the
   <xref articleid="475369">
    oceanic crust
   </xref>
   tends to be remelted as it descends into the hot mantle and then rises to the surface as lava. Chains of active, often explosive volcanoes are thus formed in such places as the western Pacific and the west coasts of the Americas. Older mountain ranges, eroded by weathering and runoff, mark zones of earlier plate-margin activity. The oldest, most geologically stable parts of Earth are the central cores of some continents (such as
   <xref articleid="110544">
    Australia
   </xref>
   , parts of Africa, and northern North America). Called
   <xref articleid="26059">
    continental shields
   </xref>
   , they are regions where mountain building, faulting, and other tectonic processes are diminished compared with the activity that occurs at the boundaries between plates. Because of their stability, erosion has had the time to flatten the topography of continental shields. It is also on the shields that geologic evidence of
   <xref articleid="472142">
    crater
   </xref>
   scars from ancient impacts of asteroids and comets is better-preserved. Even there, however, tectonic processes and the action of water have erased many ancient features. In contrast, much of the oceanic crust is substantially younger (tens of millions of years old), and none dates back more than 200 million years.
  </p>
  <p>
   This conceptual framework in which scientists now understand the
   <xref articleid="106075">
    evolution
   </xref>
   of Earth’s
   <xref articleid="472772">
    lithosphere
   </xref>
   —termed
   <xref articleid="108555">
    plate tectonics
   </xref>
   —is almost universally accepted, although many details remain to be worked out. For example, scientists have yet to reach a general agreement as to when the original continental cores formed or how long ago modern plate-tectonic processes began to operate. Certainly the processes of internal convection, segregation of
   <xref articleid="110655">
    minerals
   </xref>
   by partial melting and recrystallization, and basaltic
   <xref articleid="75659">
    volcanism
   </xref>
   were operating more vigorously in the first billion years of Earth’s
   <xref articleid="40600">
    history
   </xref>
   , when the planet’s interior was much hotter than it is today; nevertheless, how the surface landmasses were formed and were dispersed may have been different.
  </p>
  <p>
   <assembly id="a158683" url="/assembly/view/158683">
    <title>
     Watch Earth’s continents move, from 650 million years ago to 250 million years in the future
    </title>
    <media mediaid="151108" thumburl="/08/151108-049-2BE756A1.jpg" type="video" url=""/>
    <caption>
     A time-lapse representation of Earth changing through geologic time, from the late Proterozoic Eon (c. 650 million years ago) to the projected period of Pangea Proxima (c. 250 million years from now).
    </caption>
    <credit>
     Adapted from C.R. Scotese, The University of Texas at Arlington
    </credit>
   </assembly>
   <assemblyref assemblyid="a158683"/>
   Once major continental shields grew, plate tectonics was characterized by the cyclic assembly and breakup of supercontinents created by the amalgamation of many smaller continental cores and
   <xref articleid="42922">
    island arcs
   </xref>
   . Scientists have identified two such cycles in the geologic record. A supercontinent began breaking up about 700 million years ago, in late Precambrian time, into several major
   <xref articleid="26050">
    continents
   </xref>
   , but by about 250 million years ago, near the beginning of the Triassic Period, the continued drifting of these continents resulted in their fusion again into a single supercontinental landmass called
   <xref articleid="58254">
    Pangea
   </xref>
   . Some 70 million years later, Pangea began to fragment, gradually giving rise to today’s continental configuration. The distribution is still asymmetric, with continents predominantly located in the Northern Hemisphere opposite the Pacific basin.
  </p>
  <p>
   Startlingly, of the four terrestrial planets, only Earth shows evidence of long-term, pervasive
   <xref articleid="108555">
    plate tectonics
   </xref>
   . Both
   <xref articleid="110146">
    Venus
   </xref>
   and
   <xref articleid="110149">
    Mars
   </xref>
   exhibit geology dominated by basaltic
   <xref articleid="75659">
    volcanism
   </xref>
   on a largely immovable crust, with only faint hints of possibly limited episodes of horizontal plate motion.
   <xref articleid="110145">
    Mercury
   </xref>
   is intrinsically much denser than the other terrestrial planets, which implies a larger metallic core; its surface is mostly covered with impact craters, but it also shows a global pattern of scarps suggesting shrinkage of the planet, associated perhaps with interior cooling. Apparently essential to the kind of plate tectonics that occurs on Earth are large planetary size (hence, high heat flow and thin crust), which eliminates Mars, and pervasive crustal water to soften the rock, which Venus lost very early in its history. Although Earth is indeed geologically active and hence possesses a youthful surface, Venus’s surface may have been completely renewed by global basaltic volcanism within the past billion years, and small portions of Mars’s surface may have experienced very recent erosion from liquid water or landslides.
  </p>
 </h1>
 <h1 id="h54199">
  <title>
   The interior
  </title>
  <p>
   More than 90 percent of Earth’s mass is composed of
   <xref articleid="42794">
    iron
   </xref>
   ,
   <xref articleid="57841">
    oxygen
   </xref>
   ,
   <xref articleid="67764">
    silicon
   </xref>
   , and
   <xref articleid="50015">
    magnesium
   </xref>
   , elements that can form the crystalline minerals known as
   <xref articleid="67760">
    silicates
   </xref>
   . Nevertheless, in chemical and mineralogical composition, as in physical properties, Earth is far from homogeneous. Apart from the superficial lateral differences near the surface (i.e., in the compositions of the continental and oceanic crusts), Earth’s principal differences vary with distance toward the centre. This is due to increasing
   <xref articleid="71632">
    temperatures
   </xref>
   and pressures and to the original segregation of materials, soon after Earth accreted from the
   <xref articleid="68562">
    solar nebula
   </xref>
   about 4.56 billion years ago, into a metal-rich core, a
   <xref articleid="67760">
    silicate
   </xref>
   -rich mantle, and the more highly refined crustal rocks. Earth is geochemically differentiated to a great extent (
   <e type="italic">
    see below
   </e>
   <xref articleid="110147" refid="h242084">
    Planetary differentiation
   </xref>
   ). Crustal rocks contain several times as much of the rock-forming element
   <xref articleid="5954">
    aluminum
   </xref>
   as does the rest of the solid Earth and many dozens of times as much
   <xref articleid="74425">
    uranium
   </xref>
   . On the other hand, the crust, which accounts for a mere 0.4 percent of Earth’s mass, contains less than 0.1 percent of its iron. Between 85 and 90 percent of Earth’s iron is concentrated in the core.
  </p>
  <p>
   The increasing pressure with depth causes phase changes in crustal rocks at depths between 5 and 50 km (3 and 30 miles), which marks the top of the upper mantle, as mentioned above. This transition area is called the Mohorovic̆ić discontinuity, or Moho. Most basaltic magmas are generated in the upper mantle at depths of hundreds of kilometres. The upper mantle, which is rich in the
   <xref articleid="109690">
    olivine
   </xref>
   ,
   <xref articleid="109687">
    pyroxene
   </xref>
   , and silicate perovskite minerals, shows significant lateral differences in composition. A large fraction of Earth’s interior, from a depth of about 650 km (400 miles) down to 2,900 km (1,800 miles), consists of the lower mantle, which is composed chiefly of magnesium- and iron-bearing silicates, including the high-pressure equivalents of
   <xref articleid="109690">
    olivine
   </xref>
   and
   <xref articleid="109687">
    pyroxene
   </xref>
   .
  </p>
  <p>
   The mantle is not static but rather churns slowly in convective motions, with hotter material rising up and cooler material sinking; through this process, Earth gradually loses its internal
   <xref articleid="39732">
    heat
   </xref>
   . In addition to being the driving force of horizontal plate motion, mantle convection is manifested in the occurrence of temporary superplumes—huge, rising jets of hot, partially molten rock—which may originate from a deep layer near the core-mantle interface. Much larger than ordinary thermal plumes, such as that associated with the Hawaiian island chain in the central Pacific (
   <e type="italic">
    see
   </e>
   <xref articleid="108777" refid="h24477">
    volcano: Intraplate volcanism
   </xref>
   ), superplumes may have had profound effects on Earth’s geologic history and even on its
   <xref articleid="106248">
    climate
   </xref>
   . One outburst of global
   <xref articleid="75659">
    volcanism
   </xref>
   about 66 million years ago, which created the vast flood
   <xref articleid="13572">
    basalt
   </xref>
   deposits known as the
   <xref articleid="29688">
    Deccan
   </xref>
   Traps on the Indian subcontinent (
   <e type="italic">
    see
   </e>
   <xref articleid="111010">
    plateau
   </xref>
   ), may have been associated with a superplume, though this model is far from universally accepted.
  </p>
  <p>
   With a radius of almost 3,500 km (2,200 miles), Earth’s core is about the size of the entire planet
   <xref articleid="110149">
    Mars
   </xref>
   . About one-third of Earth’s mass is contained in the core, most of which is liquid
   <xref articleid="42794">
    iron
   </xref>
   alloyed with nickel and some lighter, cosmically abundant components (e.g., sulfur, oxygen, and, controversially, even
   <xref articleid="110604">
    hydrogen
   </xref>
   ). Its liquid nature is revealed by the failure of shear-type
   <xref articleid="66632">
    seismic waves
   </xref>
   to penetrate the core. A small, central part of the core, however, below a depth of about 5,100 km (3,200 miles), is solid iron. This inner core is itself divided into two layers known only by the polarity differences of the iron
   <xref articleid="110297">
    crystals
   </xref>
   found within them. The polarity of the iron crystals of the innermost layer is oriented in an east-west direction, whereas that of the outermost layer is oriented north-south.
   <xref articleid="71632">
    Temperatures
   </xref>
   in the core are extremely hot, ranging from 4,000–5,000 K (roughly 6,700–8,500 °F; 3,700–4,700 °C) at the outer part of the core to 5,000–7,000 K (8,500–12,100 °F; 4,700–6,700 °C) in the centre, comparable to the surface of the
   <xref articleid="110144">
    Sun
   </xref>
   . Large uncertainties in temperature arise from questions as to which compounds form alloys with iron in the core, and more recent data favour the lower end of the temperature estimates for the inner core. The core’s reservoir of heat may contribute as much as one-fifth of all the internal heat that ultimately flows to the surface of Earth. The basic structure of Earth—
   <xref articleid="28060">
    crust
   </xref>
   ,
   <xref articleid="50643">
    mantle
   </xref>
   , and
   <xref articleid="26280">
    core
   </xref>
   —appears to be replicated on the other terrestrial planets, though with substantial variations in the relative size of each region.
  </p>
 </h1>
 <h1 id="h54200">
  <title>
   The geomagnetic field and magnetosphere
  </title>
  <p>
   Helical fluid motions in Earth’s electrically conducting liquid outer core have an electromagnetic
   <xref articleid="31673">
    dynamo
   </xref>
   effect, giving rise to the
   <xref articleid="36468">
    geomagnetic field
   </xref>
   . The planet’s sizable, hot core, along with its rapid spin, probably accounts for the exceptional strength of the magnetic field of Earth compared with those of the other terrestrial planets. Venus, for example, which has a metallic core that may be similar to Earth’s in size, rotates very slowly and has no detected intrinsic
   <xref articleid="50022">
    magnetic field
   </xref>
   .
   <xref articleid="110145">
    Mercury
   </xref>
   and Mars have only small intrinsic magnetic fields.
  </p>
  <p>
   Earth’s main magnetic field permeates the planet and an enormous volume of space surrounding it. A great teardrop-shaped region of space called the
   <xref articleid="50042">
    magnetosphere
   </xref>
   is formed by the interaction of Earth’s field with the
   <xref articleid="68567">
    solar wind
   </xref>
   . At a distance of about 65,000 km (40,000 miles) outward toward the Sun, the pressure of the solar wind is balanced by the geomagnetic field. This serves as an obstacle to the
   <xref articleid="68567">
    solar wind
   </xref>
   , and the flow of charged particles, or
   <xref articleid="110303">
    plasma
   </xref>
   , is deflected around Earth by the resulting bow shock. The magnetosphere so produced streams out into an elongated magnetotail that stretches several million kilometres downstream from Earth away from the Sun.
  </p>
  <p>
   Plasma particles from the solar wind can leak through the magnetopause, the sunward boundary of the magnetosphere, and populate its interior; charged particles from the Earth’s
   <xref articleid="42708">
    ionosphere
   </xref>
   also enter the
   <xref articleid="50042">
    magnetosphere
   </xref>
   . The magnetotail can store for hours an enormous amount of energy—several billion megajoules, which is roughly equivalent to the yearly electricity production of many smaller countries). This occurs through a process called reconnection, in which the Sun’s magnetic field, dragged into interplanetary space by the solar wind, becomes linked with the magnetic field in Earth’s magnetosphere. The energy is released in dynamic structural reconfigurations of the magnetosphere, called geomagnetic substorms, which often result in the precipitation of energetic particles into the ionosphere, giving rise to fluorescing
   <xref articleid="11293">
    auroral
   </xref>
   displays.
  </p>
  <p>
   Converging magnetic field lines fairly close to Earth can trap highly energetic particles so that they gyrate between the Northern and Southern hemispheres and slowly drift longitudinally around the planet in two concentric doughnut-shaped zones known as the
   <xref articleid="74758">
    Van Allen radiation belts
   </xref>
   . Many of the charged particles trapped in these belts are produced when energetic
   <xref articleid="26471">
    cosmic rays
   </xref>
   strike Earth’s upper atmosphere, producing
   <xref articleid="55406">
    neutrons
   </xref>
   that then decay into
   <xref articleid="32316">
    electrons
   </xref>
   , which are negatively charged, and
   <xref articleid="61626">
    protons
   </xref>
   , which are positively charged. Others come from the solar wind or Earth’s atmosphere. The inner
   <xref articleid="109464">
    radiation
   </xref>
   belt was detected in 1958 by the American physicist
   <xref articleid="74757">
    James Van Allen
   </xref>
   and colleagues, using a Geiger-Müller counter aboard the first U.S.
   <xref articleid="65845">
    satellite
   </xref>
   ,
   <xref articleid="33446">
    Explorer
   </xref>
   1; the outer belt was distinguished by other U.S. and Soviet spacecraft launched the same year. Earth’s magnetosphere has been extensively studied ever since, and space physicists have extended their studies of plasma processes to the vicinities of comets and other planets. (For additional information on the interaction of the Sun and Earth’s charged particles and magnetic fields,
   <e type="italic">
    see
   </e>
   <xref articleid="110303" refid="h51968">
    plasma: Solar-terrestrial forms
   </xref>
   .)
  </p>
  <p>
   An important characteristic of Earth’s magnetic field is polarity reversal. In this process the direction of the dipole component reverses—i.e., the north magnetic pole becomes the south magnetic pole and vice versa. From studying the direction of magnetization of many rocks, geologists know that such reversals occur, without a discernible pattern, at intervals that range from tens of thousands of years to millions of years, though they are still uncertain about the mechanisms responsible. It is likely that during the changeover, which is believed to take a few thousand years, a nondipolar field remains, at a small fraction of the strength of the normal field. In the temporary absence of the dipole component, the solar wind would approach much closer to Earth, allowing particles that are normally deflected by the field or are trapped in its outer portions to reach the surface. The increase in particle radiation could lead to increased rates of genetic damage and thus of mutations or sterility in
   <xref articleid="108554">
    plants
   </xref>
   and
   <xref articleid="110237">
    animals
   </xref>
   , leading to the disappearance of some species. Scientists have looked for evidence of such changes in the
   <xref articleid="101225">
    fossil record
   </xref>
   at times of past field reversals, but the results have been inconclusive.
  </p>
  <signature>
   Clark R. Chapman
  </signature>
  <signature>
   Jonathan I. Lunine
  </signature>
 </h1>
 <h1 id="h242081">
  <title>
   Development of Earth’s structure and composition
  </title>
  <p>
   The origin of Earth in its present form has long been the subject of intellectual interest, but since the mid-20th century scientists have made particularly significant advances both in concepts and in measurements. Analysis of the isotopes in
   <xref articleid="110159">
    meteorites
   </xref>
   and, in particular, of rocks brought back from the
   <xref articleid="53598">
    Moon
   </xref>
   by U.S.
   <xref articleid="8019">
    Apollo
   </xref>
   astronauts have produced some of the major contributions. Other gains have come from geochemical research on terrestrial samples combined with the new understanding of internal processes brought on by the recognition of
   <xref articleid="108555">
    plate tectonics
   </xref>
   , study of the terrestrial planets as a group, and advances in numerical modeling of the physical processes that lead to planetary formation.
  </p>
  <p>
   The starting point in tracing planetary evolution is
   <xref articleid="56459">
    nucleosynthesis
   </xref>
   , the formation of the chemical elements on a cosmic scale. This includes the nuclear processes by which the lightest elements—mostly
   <xref articleid="110604">
    hydrogen
   </xref>
   and
   <xref articleid="1713">
    helium
   </xref>
   —were produced at the explosive birth of the
   <xref articleid="74362">
    universe
   </xref>
   (
   <e type="italic">
    see
   </e>
   <xref articleid="79147">
    big-bang model
   </xref>
   ), 13.8 billion years ago, and the subsequent formation of the heavier elements within stars (
   <e type="italic">
    see
   </e>
   <xref articleid="110602">
    chemical element: Origin of the elements
   </xref>
   ). By analogy with what astronomers presently observe to happen in regions of star formation, it is thought that the
   <xref articleid="110143">
    solar system
   </xref>
   began as a cloud of gas and dust comprising such preexisting elements. Under its own gravitational attraction, the cloud collapsed into a rotating disk of matter, called the
   <xref articleid="68562">
    solar nebula
   </xref>
   . The collapse could have been initiated by a shock wave emanating from a nearby
   <xref articleid="70402">
    supernova
   </xref>
   , a violently exploding star, or by random density fluctuations in the cloud itself. Once sufficiently high pressures and densities were achieved in the compacted nebular core,
   <xref articleid="110415">
    nuclear fusion
   </xref>
   reactions within it could begin, giving birth to a star. The outer part of the rotating disk—the matter not incorporated into the new Sun—became the raw material for the planets and other orbiting bodies of the solar system. The birth of the Sun, which makes up more than 99.9 percent of the mass of the entire solar system, is taken to be the time at which the planets started to form, approximately 4.56 billion years ago.
  </p>
  <h2 id="h242082">
   <title>
    Accretion of the early Earth
   </title>
   <p>
    As the gas making up the solar nebula beyond the Sun cooled with time, mineral grains are thought to have condensed and aggregated to form the earliest meteoritic material. In addition, as is suggested by the finding of anomalous concentrations of
    <xref articleid="110412">
     isotopes
    </xref>
    in a few
    <xref articleid="110159">
     meteorites
    </xref>
    , solid material from outside the solar system, apparently existing prior to the formation of the Sun, was occasionally incorporated into these developing small bodies.
   </p>
   <p>
    The concentrations of isotopes that decay radioactively and of isotopes that are produced by radioactive decay provide scientists the information required to determine when meteorites and the planets formed. For example, the concentrations of
    <xref articleid="64323">
     rubidium-87
    </xref>
    and the strontium-87 into which it decays, or those of samarium-147 and its decay product neodymium-143, indicate that the oldest meteorites formed some 4.56 billion years ago. Other isotope studies demonstrate that Earth formed within, at most, a few tens of millions of years after the birth of the Sun.
   </p>
   <p>
    The most abundant elements in the Sun, hydrogen and helium, are severely lacking in the inner, terrestrial planets but are still abundant constituents of the large, gaseous, outer planets such as
    <xref articleid="110150">
     Jupiter
    </xref>
    and
    <xref articleid="110151">
     Saturn
    </xref>
    . It is thought that only at the distance of Jupiter and beyond—in the colder regions of the solar system, including the zone beyond
    <xref articleid="110153">
     Neptune
    </xref>
    in which comets originated (
    <e type="italic">
     see
    </e>
    <xref articleid="342992">
     Kuiper belt
    </xref>
    ;
    <xref articleid="342991">
     Oort cloud
    </xref>
    )—could the more volatile substances, which also include water,
    <xref articleid="20249">
     carbon dioxide
    </xref>
    , and
    <xref articleid="7200">
     ammonia
    </xref>
    , condense and be retained in appreciable amounts during the formation of the
    <xref articleid="60298">
     planets
    </xref>
    . Nevertheless, when the relative abundances of the less volatile elements are compared for the
    <xref articleid="110144">
     Sun
    </xref>
    , for a class of primitive, largely chemically unaltered meteorites called CI
    <xref articleid="20255">
     carbonaceous chondrites
    </xref>
    (considered by many researchers the most pristine samples of original solar system material), and for the estimated composition of Earth, their values are all in close agreement. This is the basis for the chondritic model, which holds that Earth (and presumably the other terrestrial planets) was essentially built up from bodies made of such meteoritic material. This idea is corroborated by isotopic studies of rocks derived from interior regions of Earth considered to be little changed throughout the planet’s history. Thus, it appears that the composition of Earth is roughly what would be expected given the observed elemental abundances in the Sun and accounting for the loss of the more volatile elements.
   </p>
   <p>
    The dust and grains that condensed out of the cooling nebular
    <xref articleid="110302">
     gas
    </xref>
    aggregated gravitationally to form larger fragments of rock. The chondritic meteorites (
    <e type="italic">
     see
    </e>
    <xref articleid="82322">
     chondrite
    </xref>
    ) observed today are basically just such collections of grains and fragments that were compacted together into larger pieces. Through continued accretion, the smaller pieces formed boulders and asteroid-size bodies (
    <xref articleid="60302">
     planetesimals
    </xref>
    ) and, ultimately, bodies the size of the
    <xref articleid="53598">
     Moon
    </xref>
    and
    <xref articleid="110149">
     Mars
    </xref>
    . The larger the planetesimals grew, the greater their gravitational attraction and the more effectively they swept up additional particles and rock fragments while circling the Sun. Growth slowed when most bodies were lunar- and Mars-size because they were limited in number and hence effectively isolated one from another in their orbits. As Jupiter increased to its giant size, its powerful gravity perturbed these “embryos” of the terrestrial planets, elongating their orbits and allowing their incremental growth to approximately the
    <xref articleid="51285">
     mass
    </xref>
    of Earth to proceed over tens of millions of years.
   </p>
   <p>
    Stony meteorites and iron
    <xref articleid="110159">
     meteorites
    </xref>
    (those composed largely of
    <xref articleid="42794">
     iron
    </xref>
    alloyed with
    <xref articleid="55747">
     nickel
    </xref>
    and
    <xref articleid="70248">
     sulfur
    </xref>
    ) both fall on Earth today, and both types are thought to have been present during the formation of the planetesimals that would accrete to become Earth. In other words, Earth seems to have accreted only after most, if not all, solid matter had already condensed. Thus, a wide range of
    <xref articleid="110655">
     minerals
    </xref>
    was included in the grains, the larger fragments, and even the planetesimals that were accumulated by the growing planet. Apparently, such an aggregation of dense metallic fragments and less dense rocky fragments is not very stable. Calculations based on the measured strengths of rocks indicate that the metallic fragments probably sank downward as Earth grew. Although the planet was relatively cold at this stage—less than 500 K (440 °F; 230 °C)—the rock was weak. This is an important point because it leads to the conclusion that Earth’s metallic core began to form during accretion of the planet and probably before the planet had grown to one-fifth of its present volume.
   </p>
  </h2>
  <h2 id="h242083">
   <title>
    Effects of planetesimal impacts
   </title>
   <p>
    During its accretion, Earth is thought to have been shock-heated by the impacts of meteorite-size bodies and larger planetesimals. For a meteorite
    <xref articleid="24789">
     collision
    </xref>
    , the heating is concentrated near the surface where the impact occurs, which allows the heat to radiate back into space. A planetesimal, however, can penetrate sufficiently deeply on impact to produce heating well beneath the surface. In addition, the debris formed on impact can blanket the planetary surface, which helps to retain heat inside the planet. Some scientists have suggested that, in this way, Earth may have become hot enough to begin melting after growing to less than 15 percent of its final volume.
   </p>
   <p>
    Among the planetesimals striking the forming Earth, at least one is considered to have been comparable in size to
    <xref articleid="110149">
     Mars
    </xref>
    . Although the details are not well understood, there is good evidence that the impact of such a large planetesimal created the
    <xref articleid="110148">
     Moon
    </xref>
    . Among the more persuasive indications is that the relative abundances of many trace elements in rocks from the Moon are close to the values obtained for Earth’s mantle. Unless this is a fortuitous coincidence, it points to the Moon having been derived from the mantle. Computer simulations have shown that a glancing collision of a Mars-size planetary body could have been sufficient to excavate from Earth’s interior the material that would form the Moon. Again, the evidence for such large collisions suggests that Earth was very effectively heated during accretion.
   </p>
   <p>
    It is apparent, then, that many processes contributing to the early development of Earth occurred almost simultaneously, within tens to hundreds of million of years after the
    <xref articleid="110144">
     Sun
    </xref>
    was formed. Meteorites and Earth were formed within this time, and the Moon, which has been dated at more than four billion years in age, apparently was formed in the same time period. Simultaneously, Earth’s
    <xref articleid="26280">
     core
    </xref>
    was accumulating and may have been completely formed during the planet’s growth period. In addition to the possible accretional heating caused by planetesimal impacts, the sinking of metal to form the core released enough gravitational energy to heat the entire planet by 1,000 K (1,800 °F; 1,000 °C) or more. Thus, once core formation began, Earth’s interior became sufficiently hot to convect. Although it is not known whether or in what form
    <xref articleid="108555">
     plate tectonics
    </xref>
    was active at the surface, it seems quite possible that the underlying mantle convection began even before the planet had grown to its final dimensions. Only later in Earth’s development did
    <xref articleid="110413">
     radioactivity
    </xref>
    become an important heat source as well.
   </p>
  </h2>
  <h2 id="h242084">
   <title>
    Planetary differentiation
   </title>
   <p>
    Once hot, Earth’s interior could begin its chemical evolution. For example, outgassing of a fraction of volatile substances that had been trapped in small amounts within the accreting planet probably formed the earliest atmosphere. Outgassing of water to Earth’s surface began before 4.3 billion years ago, a time based on analysis of ancient
    <xref articleid="78403">
     zircons
    </xref>
    that show the effects of alteration by liquid water. In Earth’s deepest interior, chemical reactions between the mantle and the core became possible. Perhaps the most important event for Earth’s surface, however, was the formation of the earliest crust by partial
    <xref articleid="51921">
     melting
    </xref>
    of the interior. This chemical separation by partial melting and outgassing of volatiles is termed differentiation. As the interior differentiated, less-dense liquids rose from the melt toward the surface and crystallized to form crust.
   </p>
   <p>
    Uncertainty exists over when and how the continental crust began to grow, because the record of the first 600 million years has not been found. The oldest known
    <xref articleid="109695">
     rocks
    </xref>
    date to only about 4 billion years. Because these are
    <xref articleid="109698">
     metamorphic rocks
    </xref>
    —i.e., because they were changed by heat and pressure from preexisting crustal rocks at the time of their dated age—it can be inferred that crust was present earlier in Earth’s history. In fact, two tiny grains of
    <xref articleid="78403">
     zircon
    </xref>
    from
    <xref articleid="110544">
     Australia
    </xref>
    have been dated at 4.28 billion and 4.4 billion years, but their relation to the formation of continental crust is uncertain.
   </p>
   <p>
    Although direct evidence is not available, indirect evidence derived from the compositions of rocks indicates that continental crust formed early. Isotopic analyses suggests that the average age of the present continental crust is about 2.5 billion years. Thus, in all probability, repeated partial melting of the upper mantle formed successively more refined,
    <xref articleid="26050">
     continent
    </xref>
    -like crustal rocks starting before 4 billion years ago. Over the first billion years, however, much of the continental crust that was formed appears to have been reincorporated into the mantle—the isotopic data infers that on average about one-third of the continental crust was recycled every billion years. As a result, only a few fragments of crust older than 3.5 billion years remain, virtually none older than 4 billion years.
   </p>
   <p>
    The process of partial melting and formation of crust, especially continental crust, leads to a depletion of certain elements (e.g.,
    <xref articleid="67764">
     silicon
    </xref>
    and aluminum) from the mantle. Undepleted and thus relatively primitive regions still exist, making up about one-third to one-half of the mantle, according to the isotopic models. The distribution of depleted and undepleted regions, however, is uncertain. Although much (perhaps all) of the upper
    <xref articleid="50643">
     mantle
    </xref>
    appears to be depleted, it is not known whether depleted rocks also exist in the lower mantle.
   </p>
   <p>
    What is recognized is that Earth is still differentiating into chemically distinct layers or regions. This is most evident in the processes of plate tectonics that involve ongoing production of crust at divergent plate boundaries such as the midocean ridges. As this material is cycled back down into the mantle at
    <xref articleid="70092">
     subduction zones
    </xref>
    and then upward again, it continues to undergo chemical processing from basaltic to andesitic and eventually to granitic (continental) composition. Thus, chemical and thermal evolution of the interior, intimately connected through mantle
    <xref articleid="26084">
     convection
    </xref>
    , is still vigorously in progress some 4.56 billion years after the formation of the
    <xref articleid="60298">
     planet
    </xref>
    .
   </p>
   <signature>
    Raymond Jeanloz
   </signature>
   <signature>
    Jonathan I. Lunine
   </signature>
  </h2>
 </h1>
 <h1 id="h54201">
  <title>
   Bibliography
  </title>
  <p>
   <e type="smallcap">
    Peter D. Ward
   </e>
   and
   <e type="smallcap">
    Don Brownlee
   </e>
   ,
   <e type="italic">
    Rare Earth: Why Complex Life is Uncommon in the Universe
   </e>
   , 2nd rev. ed. (2003), lays out for general readers a case for the uncommon nature of planet Earth.
   <e type="smallcap">
    Jonathan I. Lunine
   </e>
   ,
   <e type="italic">
    Earth: Evolution of a Habitable World
   </e>
   (1999); and
   <e type="smallcap">
    John J.W. Rogers
   </e>
   ,
   <e type="italic">
    A History of the Earth
   </e>
   (1993), provide comprehensive introductions to Earth from, respectively, planetological and geologic perspectives.
   <e type="smallcap">
    William K. Hartmann
   </e>
   ,
   <e type="italic">
    The History of Earth: An Illustrated Chronicle of an Evolving Planet
   </e>
   (1991), is a lavishly illustrated introduction. A graduate-level text comprising excellent chapters on its subject matter is
   <e type="smallcap">
    Robin M. Canup
   </e>
   and
   <e type="smallcap">
    Kevin Righter
   </e>
   (eds.),
   <e type="italic">
    Origin of the Earth and Moon
   </e>
   (2000). A popular and balanced account of the physical causes of mass extinctions is given in
   <e type="smallcap">
    Charles Frankel
   </e>
   ,
   <e type="italic">
    The End of the Dinosaurs: Chicxulub Crater and Mass Extinctions
   </e>
   (1999; originally published in French, 1996). The periodical
   <e type="italic">
    Scientific American
   </e>
   (monthly) is an excellent and accessible source for the latest thinking on Earth and planetary processes; for example, a good description of plate tectonics is found in
   <e type="smallcap">
    Ian W.D. Dalziel
   </e>
   , “Earth Before Pangea,” 272(1):58–63 (January 1995). The
   <e type="italic">
    State of the World
   </e>
   report (annual), published by the Worldwatch Institute, provides authoritative updates on Earth’s vital signs for the general reader.
  </p>
  <signature>
   Jonathan I. Lunine
  </signature>
 </h1>
 <copyright>
  Encyclopædia Britannica
 </copyright>
</article>