<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "syndication_xml.dtd">
<article articleid="110578" articletypeid="1" language="en_us" lastupdate="2021-Jul-01 04:49:17" url="/article/physiology/110578" version="7">
 <title>
  physiology
 </title>
 <p>
  <assembly id="a225434" url="/assembly/view/225434">
   <title>
    adenosine triphosphate; physiology
   </title>
   <media mediaid="104436" type="image" url="/36/104436-004-3649A115.jpg"/>
   <caption>
    Adenosine triphosphate (ATP) is the power source of many biochemical reactions. It is produced in the cell structures and system listed at the left to energize the important life processes listed on the right. An abbreviated chemical formula of the structure of ATP is also shown. The two high-energy P―O―P bonds are responsible for its power.
   </caption>
   <credit>
    Encyclopædia Britannica, Inc.
   </credit>
  </assembly>
  <e type="bold">
   physiology
  </e>
  ,
  <assemblyref assemblyid="a225434"/>
  study of the functioning of living organisms,
  <xref articleid="110237">
   animal
  </xref>
  or
  <xref articleid="108554">
   plant
  </xref>
  , and of the functioning of their constituent
  <xref articleid="72629">
   tissues
  </xref>
  or
  <xref articleid="106125">
   cells
  </xref>
  .
 </p>
 <p>
  The word
  <e type="italic">
   physiology
  </e>
  was first used by the Greeks around 600
  <e type="smallcap">
   bce
  </e>
  to describe a philosophical inquiry into the nature of things. The use of the term with specific reference to vital activities of healthy humans, which began in the 16th century, also is applicable to many current aspects of physiology. In the 19th century, curiosity, medical necessity, and economic interest stimulated research concerning the physiology of all living organisms. Discoveries of unity of structure and functions common to all living things resulted in the development of the concept of general physiology, in which general principles and concepts applicable to all living things are sought. Since the mid-19th century, therefore, the word
  <e type="italic">
   physiology
  </e>
  has implied the utilization of experimental methods, as well as techniques and concepts of the physical sciences, to investigate causes and mechanisms of the activities of all living things.
 </p>
 <h1 id="h48683">
  <title>
   Historical background
  </title>
  <p>
   The philosophical natural history that comprised the physiology of the Greeks has little in common with modern physiology. Many ideas important in the development of physiology, however, were formulated in the books of the Hippocratic school of medicine (before 350
   <e type="smallcap">
    bce
   </e>
   ), especially the humoral theory of disease—presented by a philosopher,
   <xref articleid="55234">
    Nemesius
   </xref>
   , in the treatise
   <e type="italic">
    De natura hominis
   </e>
   (4th century
   <e type="smallcap">
    ce
   </e>
   ;
   <e type="italic">
    On the Nature of Man
   </e>
   ). Other contributions were made by
   <xref articleid="108312">
    Aristotle
   </xref>
   and
   <xref articleid="35854">
    Galen of Pergamum
   </xref>
   . Significant in the history of physiology was the
   <xref articleid="71588">
    teleology
   </xref>
   of Aristotle, who assumed that every part of the body is formed for a purpose and that function, therefore, can be deduced from structure. The work of Aristotle was the basis for Galen’s
   <e type="italic">
    De usu partium corporis humani
   </e>
   (
   <e type="italic">
    On the Usefulness of the Parts of the Body
   </e>
   ) and a source for many early misconceptions in physiology. The tidal concept of
   <xref articleid="106084">
    blood
   </xref>
   flow, the humoral theory of disease, and Aristotle’s teleology, for example, led Galen into a basic misunderstanding of the movements of blood that was not corrected until English physician
   <xref articleid="106277">
    William Harvey
   </xref>
   ’s work on blood circulation in the 17th century.
  </p>
  <p>
   <assembly id="a188953" url="/assembly/view/188953">
    <title>
     William Harvey: theory of the circulation of blood
    </title>
    <media mediaid="176958" type="image" url="/58/176958-004-F904BD3E.jpg"/>
    <caption>
     Woodcut depicting William Harvey’s theory of the circulation of blood, from his
     <e type="italic">
      Exercitatio Anatomica de Motu Cordis et Sanguinis in Animalibus
     </e>
     (1628).
    </caption>
    <credit>
     National Library of Medicine, Bethesda, Maryland
    </credit>
   </assembly>
   <assemblyref assemblyid="a188953"/>
   The publication in 1628 of Harvey’s
   <e type="italic">
    Exercitatio Anatomica de Motu Cordis et Sanguinis in Animalibus
   </e>
   (
   <e type="italic">
    An Anatomical Dissertation upon the Movement of the Heart and Blood in Animals
   </e>
   ) usually is identified as the beginning of modern experimental physiology. Harvey’s study was based only on anatomical experiments; despite increased knowledge in
   <xref articleid="108654">
    physics
   </xref>
   and
   <xref articleid="108655">
    chemistry
   </xref>
   during the 17th century, physiology remained closely tied to
   <xref articleid="7388">
    anatomy
   </xref>
   and
   <xref articleid="110314">
    medicine
   </xref>
   . In 1747 in Berne, Switzerland,
   <xref articleid="38941">
    Albrecht von Haller
   </xref>
   , eminent as anatomist, physiologist, and botanist, published the first manual for physiology. Between 1757 and 1766 he published eight volumes entitled
   <e type="italic">
    Elementa Physiologiae Corporis Humani
   </e>
   (
   <e type="italic">
    Elements of Human Physiology
   </e>
   ); all were in Latin and characterized his definition of physiology as anatomy in motion. At the end of the 18th century,
   <xref articleid="106472">
    Antoine Lavoisier
   </xref>
   wrote about the physiological problems of respiration and the production of heat by animals in a series of memoirs that still serve as a foundation for understanding these subjects.
  </p>
  <p>
   Physiology as a distinct discipline utilizing chemical, physical, and anatomical methods began to develop in the 19th century.
   <xref articleid="78837">
    Claude Bernard
   </xref>
   in France;
   <xref articleid="54219">
    Johannes Müller
   </xref>
   ,
   <xref articleid="48177">
    Justus von Liebig
   </xref>
   , and
   <xref articleid="49277">
    Carl Ludwig
   </xref>
   in Germany; and
   <xref articleid="35006">
    Sir Michael Foster
   </xref>
   in England may be numbered among the founders of physiology as it now is known. At the beginning of the 19th century, German physiology was under the influence of the romantic school of
   <e type="italic">
    Naturphilosophie
   </e>
   . In France, on the other hand, romantic elements were opposed by rational and skeptical viewpoints. Bernard’s teacher,
   <xref articleid="49982">
    François Magendie
   </xref>
   , the pioneer of experimental physiology, was one of the first men to perform experiments on living animals. Both Müller and Bernard, however, recognized that the results of observations and experiments must be incorporated into a body of scientific knowledge, and that the theories of natural philosophers must be tested by experimentation. Many important ideas in physiology were investigated experimentally by Bernard, who also wrote books on the subject. He recognized
   <xref articleid="106125">
    cells
   </xref>
   as functional units of life and developed the concept of blood and body fluids as the internal environment (
   <e type="italic">
    milieu intérieur
   </e>
   ) in which cells carry out their activities. This concept of physiological regulation of the internal environment occupies an important position in physiology and medicine; Bernard’s work had a profound influence on succeeding generations of physiologists in France, Russia, Italy, England, and the United States.
  </p>
  <p>
   Müller’s interests were anatomical and zoological, whereas Bernard’s were chemical and medical, but both men sought a broad biological viewpoint in physiology rather than one limited to human functions. Although Müller did not perform many experiments, his textbook
   <e type="italic">
    Handbuch der Physiologie des Menschen für Vorlesungen
   </e>
   (1837) and his personal influence determined the course of animal biology in Germany during the 19th century.
  </p>
  <p>
   It has been said that, if Müller provided the enthusiasm and Bernard the ideas for modern physiology, Carl Ludwig provided the methods. During his medical studies at the University of Marburg in Germany, Ludwig applied new ideas and methods of the physical sciences to physiology. In 1847 he invented the kymograph, a cylindrical drum used to record muscular motion, changes in
   <xref articleid="15702">
    blood pressure
   </xref>
   , and other physiological phenomena. He also made significant contributions to the physiology of circulation and
   <xref articleid="74481">
    urine
   </xref>
   secretion. His textbook of physiology, published in two volumes in 1852 and 1856, was the first to stress physical instead of anatomical orientation in physiology. In 1869 at Leipzig, Ludwig founded the Physiological Institute (
   <e type="italic">
    neue physiologische Anstalt
   </e>
   ), which served as a model for research institutes in medical schools worldwide. The chemical approach to physiological problems, developed first in France by Lavoisier, was expanded in Germany by Justus von Liebig, whose books on
   <e type="italic">
    Organic Chemistry and its Applications to Agriculture and Physiology
   </e>
   (1840) and
   <e type="italic">
    Animal Chemistry
   </e>
   (1842) created new areas of study both in medical physiology and agriculture. German schools devoted to the study of physiological chemistry evolved from Liebig’s laboratory at Giessen.
  </p>
  <p>
   The British tradition of physiology is distinct from that of the continental schools. In 1869 Sir Michael Foster became Professor of Practical Physiology at University College in London, where he taught the first laboratory course ever offered as a regular part of instruction in
   <xref articleid="110314">
    medicine
   </xref>
   . The pattern Foster established still is followed in medical schools in Great Britain and the United States. In 1870 Foster transferred his activities to
   <xref articleid="2127">
    Trinity College
   </xref>
   at Cambridge, England, and a postgraduate medical school emerged from his physiology laboratory there. Although Foster did not distinguish himself in research, his laboratory produced many of the leading physiologists of the late 19th century in Great Britain and the United States. In 1877 Foster wrote a major book (
   <e type="italic">
    Textbook of Physiology
   </e>
   ), which passed through seven editions and was translated into German, Italian, and Russian. He also published
   <e type="italic">
    Lectures on the History of Physiology
   </e>
   (1901). In 1876, partly in response to increased opposition in England to experimentation with animals, Foster was instrumental in founding the Physiological Society, the first organization of professional physiologists. In 1878, again due largely to Foster’s activities, the
   <e type="italic">
    Journal of Physiology
   </e>
   , which was the first journal devoted exclusively to the publication of research results in physiology, was initiated.
  </p>
  <p>
   Foster’s teaching methods in physiology and a new evolutionary approach to
   <xref articleid="110584">
    zoology
   </xref>
   were transferred to the United States in 1876 by Henry Newell Martin, a professor of biology at
   <xref articleid="43847">
    Johns Hopkins University
   </xref>
   in Baltimore, Maryland. The American tradition drew also on the continental schools.
   <xref articleid="53024">
    S. Weir Mitchell
   </xref>
   , who studied under Claude Bernard, and Henry P. Bowditch, who worked with Carl Ludwig, joined Martin to organize the American Physiological Society in 1887, and in 1898 the society sponsored publication of the
   <e type="italic">
    American Journal of Physiology
   </e>
   . In 1868 Eduard Pflüger, professor at the Institute of Physiology at Bonn, founded the
   <e type="italic">
    Archiv für die gesammte Physiologie
   </e>
   , which became the most important journal of physiology in Germany.
  </p>
  <p>
   Physiological chemistry followed a course partly independent of physiology. Müller and Liebig provided a stronger relationship between physical and chemical approaches to physiology in Germany than prevailed elsewhere.
   <xref articleid="41036">
    Felix Hoppe-Seyler
   </xref>
   , who founded his
   <e type="italic">
    Zeitschrift für physiologische Chemie
   </e>
   in 1877, gave identity to the chemical approach to physiology. The American tradition in physiological chemistry initially followed that in Germany; in England, however, it developed from a Cambridge laboratory founded in 1898 to complement the physical approach started earlier by Foster.
  </p>
  <p>
   Physiology in the 20th century was a mature science; during a century of growth, physiology became the parent of a number of related disciplines, of which
   <xref articleid="110581">
    biochemistry
   </xref>
   ,
   <xref articleid="110580">
    biophysics
   </xref>
   , general physiology, and
   <xref articleid="53245">
    molecular biology
   </xref>
   are the most vigorous examples. Physiology, however, retains an important position among the functional sciences that are closely related to the field of medicine. Although many research areas, especially in mammalian physiology, have been fully exploited from a classical-
   <xref articleid="57347">
    organ
   </xref>
   and organ-system point of view, comparative studies in physiology may be expected to continue. The solution of the major unsolved problems of physiology will require technical and expensive research by teams of specialized investigators. Unsolved problems include the unravelling of the ultimate bases of the phenomena of life. Research in physiology also is aimed at the integration of the varied activities of cells, tissues, and organs at the level of the intact organism. Both analytical and integrative approaches uncover new problems that also must be solved. In many instances, the solution is of practical value in medicine or helps to improve the understanding of both human beings and other animals.
  </p>
 </h1>
 <h1 id="h48684">
  <title>
   Intradisciplinary work
  </title>
  <p>
   The anatomical and medical origins of physiology still are reflected in university courses and textbooks that concentrate on functional organ systems of animals (e.g., frog, dog, cat, and rat). The trend in physiology, however, is to emphasize function rather than structure. Hence, comprehensive functional specializations such as
   <xref articleid="108508">
    nutrition
   </xref>
   , transport,
   <xref articleid="109831">
    metabolism
   </xref>
   , and information have replaced earlier structural studies of organ systems. This trend can be explained in part by the fact that the analysis of an organ system typically involves studies at the levels of cells and molecules, and functional emphasis accommodates such studies better than the organ-system approach.
  </p>
  <p>
   Early in the 20th century the emphasis on cells as units of function resulted in a view that all physiology is essentially cell physiology and that all teaching therefore should pivot around the properties of cells. In later years successful analyses of cellular mechanisms involving synthesis, control, and inheritance led to similar emphasis at a new and more fundamental level, the molecules that constitute cells. The study of physiology now encompasses molecules, cells, organs, and many types of animals, including humans. The comparisons resulting from such studies not only strengthen human physiology but also generate new problems that extend into
   <xref articleid="106075">
    evolution
   </xref>
   and
   <xref articleid="110583">
    ecology
   </xref>
   . Much of the impetus for comparative physiology resulted from the economic or medical importance to humans of parasites,
   <xref articleid="105953">
    insects
   </xref>
   , and
   <xref articleid="111049">
    fishes
   </xref>
   .
  </p>
  <p>
   Most of the physiology of microorganisms and plants developed independently of animal physiology. The concept of comparative biochemistry provided the foundations for a physiology of microorganisms that extended beyond the parasitic forms that are of medical importance and resulted in recognition of the fundamental roles of microorganisms in the
   <xref articleid="117266">
    biosphere
   </xref>
   . Botanists and agriculturists explore the physiology of higher plants, but fundamental differences in the modes of life of animals and plants leave little common ground above the molecular and cellular levels. In a little-known textbook, Claude Bernard stated that there is only one way to live, only one physiology of all living things. The goal of general physiology is to abstract this single physiology from the physiologies of all types of organisms. Although common or general features usually are found at the cellular and molecular levels of organization, multicellular structures also are studied. Processes that underlie cell function are emphasized in an approach based on analyses in terms of physical and chemical principles.
  </p>
 </h1>
 <h1 id="h48685">
  <title>
   Areas of study
  </title>
  <h2 id="h48686">
   <title>
    Metabolism
   </title>
   <p>
    In the late 19th century the principle of
    <xref articleid="32628">
     conservation of energy
    </xref>
    was derived in part from observations that fermentation and muscle contraction are essentially problems in energetics. Biological energetics began with studies that established the basic equation of respiration as:
    <formula>
     Fuel + oxygen → carbon dioxide + water + heat.
    </formula>
    It was realized that the heat produced in
    <xref articleid="34052">
     fermentation
    </xref>
    and the work performed during muscle contraction must originate in similar processes and that fuel in the equation above is a source of
    <xref articleid="61056">
     potential energy
    </xref>
    . Early in the 20th century, studies of animal calorimetry verified these concepts in humans and other animals. Calorimetry studies showed that the energy produced by the metabolism of foodstuffs in an animal equals that produced by the combustion of these foodstuffs outside the body. After these studies, measurement of the basal metabolic rate (BMR) was used in the
    <xref articleid="106175">
     diagnosis
    </xref>
    of certain diseases, and data relating the composition of foodstuffs to their value as sources of metabolic energy were obtained.
   </p>
   <p>
    <assembly id="a121339" url="/assembly/view/121339">
     <title>
      glycolysis
     </title>
     <media mediaid="116269" type="image" url="/69/116269-004-730AB723.jpg"/>
     <caption>
      The generation of pyruvate through the process of glycolysis is the first step in fermentation.
     </caption>
     <credit>
      Encyclopædia Britannica, Inc.
     </credit>
    </assembly>
    <assemblyref assemblyid="a121339"/>
    Early in the 20th century it was established that measurable amounts of the carbohydrate
    <xref articleid="37099">
     glycogen
    </xref>
    are converted to
    <xref articleid="46770">
     lactic acid
    </xref>
    in frog muscles contracting in the absence of oxygen. This observation and studies of alcoholic fermentation confirmed that the energy for fermentation or muscle contraction depends on a series of reactions now known as
    <xref articleid="472438">
     glycolysis
    </xref>
    . In order to show that the conversion of glycogen to lactic acid could provide the necessary energy for muscular contraction, extremely delicate measurements of the heat produced by contracting muscles were required. As a result of glycolysis studies,
    <xref articleid="3722">
     adenosine triphosphate
    </xref>
    (ATP) was recognized as an important molecule in cellular energy transfer and utilization—e.g., movement, generation of electricity, transport of materials across cell membranes, and production of light by cells. Soon it was discovered that a muscle protein called myosin acts as an
    <xref articleid="32739">
     enzyme
    </xref>
    (organic catalyst) by liberating the energy stored in ATP and that ATP in turn can modify the physical properties of myosin molecules. It was also shown that a muscle fibre has an elaborate and ordered structure, which is based on a precise arrangement of myosin and another muscle protein called
    <xref articleid="3598">
     actin
    </xref>
    .
   </p>
   <p>
    Glycolysis is an anaerobic process (i.e., it does not require oxygen) and may represent one of the oldest mechanisms for cellular energy transfer, since the process could have evolved before there was free oxygen in Earth’s
    <xref articleid="126202">
     atmosphere
    </xref>
    . Most cells, however, derive their energy from a series of reactions involving oxygen and called the
    <xref articleid="73342">
     tricarboxylic acid cycle
    </xref>
    (Krebs cycle, or citric acid cycle). The enzymes for the cycle are part of the structure of a
    <xref articleid="443654">
     mitochondrion
    </xref>
    , which is an elaborate cellular component filled with membranes, generally shaped like a bean. In the course of the oxidation, three molecules of energy-rich ATP are generated for each oxygen
    <xref articleid="110411">
     atom
    </xref>
    used to form a molecule of water. The mitochondrion, therefore, is the cellular site of respiratory combustion first clearly demonstrated in whole animals by Lavoisier.
   </p>
   <p>
    The ultimate source of foodstuffs used by animals is plants. Early 19th-century studies of
    <xref articleid="108553">
     photosynthesis
    </xref>
    were closely related to those of respiration and began with
    <xref articleid="61366">
     Joseph Priestley
    </xref>
    ’s demonstration that plants could restore the air used during respiration or combustion. The most important equations for living things therefore, are mutually inverse. In respiration:
    <formula>
     (CH
     <sub>
      2
     </sub>
     O)
     <sub>
      <e type="italic">
       n
      </e>
     </sub>
     +
     <e type="italic">
      n
     </e>
     O
     <sub>
      2
     </sub>
     →
     <e type="italic">
      n
     </e>
     CO
     <sub>
      2
     </sub>
     +
     <e type="italic">
      n
     </e>
     H
     <sub>
      2
     </sub>
     O + heat.
     <linebreak/>
     carbo-oxygen carbon water
     <linebreak/>
     hydrate dioxide
    </formula>
    In photosynthesis:
    <formula>
     <e type="italic">
      n
     </e>
     CO
     <sub>
      2
     </sub>
     +
     <e type="italic">
      n
     </e>
     H
     <sub>
      2
     </sub>
     O + light → (CH
     <sub>
      2
     </sub>
     O)
     <sub>
      <e type="italic">
       n
      </e>
     </sub>
     +
     <e type="italic">
      n
     </e>
     O
     <sub>
      2
     </sub>
     .
    </formula>
   </p>
   <p>
    In the 1930s, it was shown that photosynthesis involves splitting hydrogen from water and that the oxygen liberated in photosynthesis comes from water. During the light reactions, light energy is captured by a green pigment called
    <xref articleid="82254">
     chlorophyll
    </xref>
    and used to generate reactive hydrogen and ATP that are used during dark reactions in which
    <xref articleid="110799">
     carbohydrates
    </xref>
    and other cell constituents are synthesized.
   </p>
   <p>
    The classical fields of organ-system physiology have a role subsidiary to that of cellular metabolism. Feeding and
    <xref articleid="30427">
     digestion
    </xref>
    , for example, become a means for the enzyme-catalyzed breakdown of organic compounds into relatively small molecules that can be transported readily;
    <xref articleid="108507">
     nutrition
    </xref>
    , therefore, is a way to supply animals with sufficient sources of energy and specific substances that they cannot synthesize. Comparative animal studies, which were of practical importance in the discovery of some vitamins, led also to the general observation that the specific nutrient requirements of animals are consequences of a slow evolutionary deterioration in which synthetic abilities are lost through changes or
    <xref articleid="54492">
     mutations
    </xref>
    in hereditary material.
   </p>
   <p>
    Nutrition and digestion, however, also have been important in obtaining information at the cellular and molecular levels. It was through studies of digestion, for example, that the existence and nature of enzymes were first disclosed clearly. In addition, early recognition of similarities between digestion and fermentation foreshadowed knowledge of the important role of fermentation in cellular metabolism. Finally, the study of
    <xref articleid="110802">
     vitamin
    </xref>
    nutrition was closely integrated with that of cellular oxidation, in which certain vitamins play an essential catalytic role.
   </p>
   <p>
    In intact organisms, the chemical activities of individual cells do not interfere with the functions of the organism. Much of the study of physiology is concerned with the ways by which cells obtain their nutrients and dispose of their waste products. Knowledge of the mechanism of protein synthesis and its connections with inheritance and cellular control mechanisms have initiated new inquiries into functions at all levels (i.e., cells, organs, and organisms).
   </p>
  </h2>
  <h2 id="h48687">
   <title>
    Transport
   </title>
   <p>
    Many important advances in
    <xref articleid="70446">
     surgery
    </xref>
    and medicine have been based on the physiology of circulation, which was first studied in 1628. The measurement of
    <xref articleid="15702">
     blood pressure
    </xref>
    , for example, was introduced on a practicable basis late in the 19th century and has become an important part of medical diagnosis. The physiology of circulation is concerned with the origin of blood pressure in the force of the heartbeat and the regulation of
    <xref articleid="39718">
     heart
    </xref>
    rate, blood pressure, and the flow of blood.
   </p>
   <p>
    Variations in heart rate that led Aristotle to consider the heart as the seat of the
    <xref articleid="106029">
     emotions
    </xref>
    (an idea later proven incorrect) were among the phenomena whose explanation revealed the existence of the
    <xref articleid="11379">
     autonomic nervous system
    </xref>
    . More important to the
    <xref articleid="106243">
     circulatory system
    </xref>
    than variation in heart rate, however, is the ability of the heart to adjust the strength of its beat to meet certain demands of the body.
   </p>
   <p>
    The peripheral control of blood pressure and blood flow depends upon a maze of interacting control mechanisms, the most significant of which are in direct control of the diameter of small arterial branches that enlarge or dilate in response to chemical products formed during metabolism. Increased metabolic activity of tissues such as
    <xref articleid="110701">
     muscles
    </xref>
    or the
    <xref articleid="2491">
     intestine
    </xref>
    , therefore, automatically induces increased blood flow through the dilated vessels. This action, which could result in a fall in blood pressure, is offset by central-reflex controls that constrict arterial branches not dilated as a result of local chemical effects. Certain regions of the
    <xref articleid="106316">
     skin
    </xref>
    and the intestines serve as reservoirs for blood that may be diverted to muscles or the
    <xref articleid="16178">
     brain
    </xref>
    if necessary. Peripheral control may break down if excessive demands are made upon it in hot weather (
    <xref articleid="39744">
     heatstroke
    </xref>
    ), during vigorous exercise after meals (muscle cramp), and after extensive loss of blood or tissue damage (
    <xref articleid="67460">
     shock
    </xref>
    ) or extreme emotion with consequent activation of the autonomic nervous system (emotional shock). A remarkable
    <xref articleid="3688">
     adaptation
    </xref>
    occurs in air-breathing
    <xref articleid="110433">
     vertebrates
    </xref>
    —reptiles, birds, and mammals—which dive for food or protection. During a dive, the flow of blood to all parts of the body except the brain and the heart is reduced substantially. The energy for muscle contraction is provided by the anaerobic process of glycolysis because the oxygen in the blood goes to the brain and heart, which cannot function without a constant supply of oxygen.
   </p>
   <p>
    Comparative studies have disclosed two major patterns in circulatory systems. Among vertebrates and a few
    <xref articleid="42669">
     invertebrates
    </xref>
    —notably annelid worms and cephalopod mollusks—the blood flows entirely in closed channels or vessels, never coming into direct contact with cells and tissues; blood pressure and the
    <xref articleid="74984">
     velocity
    </xref>
    of flow are high and relatively constant, and the volume of blood is small. In many invertebrates—especially arthropods and mollusks other than cephalopods—the blood flows for part of its course in large sinuses or lacunae and comes directly into contact with the tissues. Blood pressure and the velocity of flow are low and variable in these invertebrates, and the large volume of blood is comparable to the total volume of all body fluids in vertebrates.
   </p>
   <p>
    Consideration of the blood as a transport system has centred especially on the transport of
    <xref articleid="57841">
     oxygen
    </xref>
    and
    <xref articleid="20249">
     carbon dioxide
    </xref>
    . The colour of blood changes as it passes through the
    <xref articleid="49375">
     lungs
    </xref>
    : venous blood is dark purple and arterial blood is bright red because of the properties of a blood pigment called
    <xref articleid="39968">
     hemoglobin
    </xref>
    . Knowledge of the complete structure of hemoglobin has enabled scientists to study fundamental questions of
    <xref articleid="111157">
     heredity
    </xref>
    at the molecular level. The development of
    <xref articleid="15696">
     blood banks
    </xref>
    and the techniques involved in
    <xref articleid="15705">
     blood transfusion
    </xref>
    depend on knowledge of the physical, chemical, and biological properties of blood. These properties include a remarkable diversity of hemoglobin, both among individuals and species and also within an individual during development. In many instances variations in
    <xref articleid="110575">
     protein
    </xref>
    composition better adapt a species to its circumstances.
   </p>
   <p>
    Studies of membrane transport at the cellular level are an important part of general physiology. Although quantitative theories of
    <xref articleid="30421">
     diffusion
    </xref>
    and
    <xref articleid="57559">
     osmosis
    </xref>
    that developed around 1900 were applied to cell physiology, a number of phenomena (e.g., movement through membranes of certain
    <xref articleid="42688">
     ions
    </xref>
    and other compounds of biological importance) did not behave according to established physical principles. As a result of studies of osmotic and ionic regulation in freshwater animals, the concept of active transport was formulated. Crucial to the acceptance of this concept were studies with frog skin, which can transport sodium ions against chemical and electrical forces; the transport, specific for sodium ions, is dependent on a continuing input of metabolic energy. Efforts have been directed toward establishing a molecular mechanism that may involve an enzyme found in surface membranes of cells. This enzyme breaks down ATP and releases the energy in the molecule only if sodium and potassium ions are present.
   </p>
  </h2>
  <h2 id="h48688">
   <title>
    Information transfer
   </title>
   <p>
    The physiology of animals differs from that of plants in the rapid response of animals to stimuli. French mathematician and philosopher
    <xref articleid="108563">
     René Descartes
    </xref>
    , responsible for the concept of the
    <xref articleid="63018">
     reflex
    </xref>
    that dominated neurophysiology for most of its history, thought a sensory impulse was “reflected” from the brain to produce a reaction in muscles. Later studies of the effects of ions on nerves suggested that a nerve must be surrounded by a membrane and that a nerve impulse results from a change in the ability of the membrane to allow passage of potassium ions. When it was shown that nerves are made up of thousands of tiny fibres, which are processes that extend from cells located in the brain or spinal cord, the nerve impulse hypothesis was applied to individual nerve fibres rather than to whole nerves. Electronic technology provided the techniques and giant nerve fibres of squids provided the experimental material that enabled two Nobel prize winners for physiology,
    <xref articleid="40679">
     Alan Lloyd Hodgkin
    </xref>
    and
    <xref articleid="41653">
     Andrew Fielding Huxley
    </xref>
    , to extend this hypothesis into a theory of the excitation of nerve cells in which sodium ions and potassium ions play principal roles.
   </p>
   <p>
    <assembly id="a155704" url="/assembly/view/155704">
     <title>
      knee-jerk reflex
     </title>
     <media mediaid="141362" type="image" url="/62/141362-004-BB0AD15A.jpg"/>
     <caption>
      Knee-jerk reflex and motor-neuron connection.
     </caption>
     <credit>
      Encyclopædia Britannica, Inc.
     </credit>
    </assembly>
    <assemblyref assemblyid="a155704"/>
    The reflex concept, however, was not dependent on understanding the molecular basis of excitation, conduction, and transmission. Early in the 20th century the role of interaction of nervous centres in controlling muscle contractions was established. The reflex now is conceived as a unit in which nerve impulses initiated in sensory
    <xref articleid="55388">
     neurons
    </xref>
    or nerve cells are conducted to a centre in the brain or spinal cord. In the centre, impulses initiated in motor neurons are conducted to muscles and induce a reflex response. Two processes can occur in the centre; one is associated with central excitatory states, the other with central inhibitory states. The net effect of any stimulus or group of stimuli, therefore, can be interpreted as an interaction of these opposing states in the centre.
   </p>
   <p>
    <assembly id="a17901" url="/assembly/view/17901">
     <title>
      autonomic nervous system
     </title>
     <media mediaid="8248" type="image" url="/48/8248-004-9927D90E.jpg"/>
     <caption>
      Organization of the autonomic nervous system, showing the key role of acetylcholine in the transmission of nervous impulses.
     </caption>
     <credit>
      Encyclopædia Britannica, Inc.
     </credit>
    </assembly>
    <assemblyref assemblyid="a17901"/>
    After the demonstration that the effects of the
    <xref articleid="74624">
     vagus nerve
    </xref>
    in slowing the heart are mediated by a chemical substance, subsequently identified as
    <xref articleid="3509">
     acetylcholine
    </xref>
    , the concept of chemical transmission of nervous impulses was extended to the central nervous system. Typically, transmission of excitation from cell to cell is accomplished by the liberation of a chemical transmitter from a nerve ending.
   </p>
   <p>
    The reflex concept gave rise to premature attempts to develop a psychology based on reflexes. These attempts (
    <xref articleid="14132">
     behaviourism
    </xref>
    ) were advanced by Russian scientist
    <xref articleid="58811">
     Ivan Pavlov
    </xref>
    ’s discovery of conditioned responses. Originally known as conditioned reflexes, these responses have been found in most animals with central nervous systems. More complex than simple reflexes, their mechanism has not yet been established with certainty.
   </p>
   <p>
    The analysis of sensory functions also extends to the cellular level. Sense organs are diverse in structure and sensitivity to specific stimuli. It may be that the common molecular basis for the differences in sensitivity is a change in permeability of a special region of the membrane surrounding a sensory cell. This change in permeability could allow a nerve fibre to become excited and initiate a nerve impulse. Neurophysiology has borrowed from, and contributed to, the information theory used in communications engineering. The function of sense organs is to gather information both from the environment and the organism. The central nervous system integrates this information and translates it into a program of response involving the entire organism. In addition, the brain can store information previously received (
    <xref articleid="109427">
     memory
    </xref>
    ) and has the ability to initiate actions without obvious external stimulation (spontaneity). Some aspects of memory and integrative function have been modelled in electronic computers; in fact the development of computers was closely connected with the development of ideas about the functions of the central nervous system.
   </p>
   <p>
    The analytical interpretation of central nervous function remains, however, a complex and difficult field, even though recent progress has brought closer together the study of behaviour in terms of nerve function and behavioral models. Considerable effort has been directed to the localization of brain function. Although specific centres for reception of sensory information and integration of motor programs are known, the integrative functions that tie them together, as well as the functions of memory, are not so well established.
   </p>
  </h2>
  <h2 id="h48689">
   <title>
    Regulation
   </title>
   <p>
    <assembly id="a1900" url="/assembly/view/1900">
     <title>
      steroid hormones
     </title>
     <media mediaid="6530" type="image" url="/30/6530-004-798906B4.jpg"/>
     <caption>
      Many important physiological functions of vertebrates are controlled by steroid hormones.
     </caption>
     <credit>
      Encyclopædia Britannica, Inc.
     </credit>
    </assembly>
    <assemblyref assemblyid="a1900"/>
    The concept of internal regulations is attributed to Claude Bernard, who thought of blood as an internal environment in which cells function; according to Bernard, maintenance of the internal environment at a constant level was a major responsibility of all body functions. Bernard showed in studies of the formation and breakdown of
    <xref articleid="37099">
     glycogen
    </xref>
    in the
    <xref articleid="48577">
     liver
    </xref>
    that internal organs can secrete materials into the blood. Other investigators demonstrated such a secretion and used the word
    <xref articleid="110803">
     hormone
    </xref>
    to describe the substance. One classical study concerned control of the secretion of digestive fluids by the
    <xref articleid="58232">
     pancreas
    </xref>
    ; an active substance secretin was purified, as have been a number of similar materials from the digestive tract. The field of
    <xref articleid="32614">
     endocrinology
    </xref>
    now is a major part of physiology.
   </p>
   <p>
    The
    <xref articleid="106033">
     endocrine system
    </xref>
    complements the
    <xref articleid="110703">
     nervous system
    </xref>
    in control and coordination. Hormones, liberated into blood and other body fluids by endocrine glands and transported throughout the body, usually act either on specific target organs or on certain activities of many organs. Nervous coordination most often is concerned with rapid responses of short duration; endocrine coordination, however, usually is involved in slower responses of longer duration. Stationary-state regulation, or
    <xref articleid="40879">
     homeostasis
    </xref>
    , depends on the action of hormones at many points. The hormones
    <xref articleid="42512">
     insulin
    </xref>
    and
    <xref articleid="37079">
     glucagon
    </xref>
    , both formed in specialized endocrine tissue in the pancreas, control the level of sugar in blood.
    <xref articleid="475790">
     Vasopressin
    </xref>
    from the
    <xref articleid="60236">
     pituitary gland
    </xref>
    at the base of the brain and
    <xref articleid="5538">
     aldosterone
    </xref>
    from the
    <xref articleid="3782">
     adrenal glands
    </xref>
    near the kidneys control salt and water balance of the blood. Hormonal regulation, however, is not confined to homeostasis. The cyclic events of the female reproductive cycles in
    <xref articleid="105972">
     mammals
    </xref>
    , for example, are determined by a complex sequence of endocrine interactions involving hormones of the pituitary gland and the
    <xref articleid="57758">
     ovary
    </xref>
    .
   </p>
   <p>
    The pervasive regulatory action of hormones is part of a large system of interactions to which the term
    <e type="italic">
     feedback
    </e>
    generally is applied. Hormones involved in homeostatic regulation, for example, influence their own secretion. The secretion of certain
    <xref articleid="69641">
     steroid hormones
    </xref>
    , which have a significant action on the conversion of amino acids to glycogen, is controlled by another hormone called the
    <xref articleid="3785">
     adrenocorticotropic hormone
    </xref>
    (ACTH), which is formed in the anterior pituitary gland. In turn the secretion of ACTH is controlled by a releasing factor formed in the midbrain and liberated from the stalk of the pituitary gland. ACTH liberation normally is controlled by the concentration of steroids in the blood, so that an increase in steroid concentration inhibits ACTH secretion; this negative feedback, however, may be overcome in certain conditions of intense nervous stimulation.
   </p>
   <p>
    <assembly id="a48973" url="/assembly/view/48973">
     <media mediaid="6524" type="image" url="/24/6524-004-796DF346.jpg"/>
     <caption>
      Neurohormones are released from neurosecretory nerve cells. These nerve cells are considered true endocrine cells because they produce and secrete hormones that enter the circulation to reach their target cells.
     </caption>
     <credit>
      Encyclopædia Britannica, Inc.
     </credit>
    </assembly>
    <assemblyref assemblyid="a48973"/>
    A similar pattern of releasing factors, by which the nervous system interacts with the endocrine system, also is known for other anterior pituitary hormones—e.g., those involved in the reproductive cycle and in responses of the thyroid gland to temperature changes. In addition,
    <xref articleid="55390">
     neurosecretory cells
    </xref>
    —nerve cells specialized for endocrine function—liberate hormones (e.g., vasopressin) that act directly on a specific target. Comparative studies show that neurosecretory cells are important in developmental and regulatory functions of most animals. Discrete endocrine glands, however, occur less frequently; in insects and crustaceans, cycles of growth, molting (shedding of the cuticle), and development are controlled by hormones. The identification of insect hormones may be useful in controlling pests through specific interference with processes of growth and development.
   </p>
   <signature>
    Bradley Titus Scheer
   </signature>
  </h2>
 </h1>
 <h1 id="h48690">
  <title>
   Bibliography
  </title>
  <p>
   An introduction to physiology is
   <e type="smallcap">
    David Le Vay
   </e>
   and
   <e type="smallcap">
    Jennifer Stafford-Brown
   </e>
   ,
   <e type="italic">
    Anatomy &amp; Physiology: A Complete Introduction
   </e>
   (2015). The subject is discussed in depth in
   <e type="smallcap">
    Laurence A. Cole
   </e>
   and
   <e type="smallcap">
    Peter R. Kramer
   </e>
   ,
   <e type="italic">
    Human Physiology, Biochemistry, and Basic Medicine
   </e>
   (2016);
   <e type="smallcap">
    Lauralee Sherwood
   </e>
   ,
   <e type="italic">
    Human Physiology: From Cells to Systems
   </e>
   (2015); and
   <e type="smallcap">
    Gillian Pocock
   </e>
   and
   <e type="smallcap">
    Christopher D. Richards
   </e>
   ,
   <e type="italic">
    Human Physiology: The Basis of Medicine
   </e>
   , 3rd ed. (2006). Unique adaptations of human physiology are discussed in
   <e type="smallcap">
    Hanns-Christian Gunga
   </e>
   ,
   <e type="italic">
    Human Physiology in Extreme Environments
   </e>
   (2015).
  </p>
  <p>
   Books on function in animals include
   <e type="smallcap">
    H.H. Dukes
   </e>
   ,
   <e type="italic">
    Dukes’ Physiology of Domestic Animals
   </e>
   , ed. by
   <e type="smallcap">
    William O. Reece
   </e>
   , 13th ed. (2015);
   <e type="smallcap">
    David Randall
   </e>
   ,
   <e type="smallcap">
    Warren Burggren
   </e>
   , and
   <e type="smallcap">
    Kathleen French
   </e>
   ,
   <e type="italic">
    Eckert Animal Physiology
   </e>
   , 5th ed. (2002); and
   <e type="smallcap">
    Kurt Schmidt-Neilsen
   </e>
   ,
   <e type="italic">
    Animal Physiology: Adaptation and Environment
   </e>
   , 5th ed. (1997). Specialized adaptations of insects are addressed in
   <e type="smallcap">
    Richard E. Lee, Jr.
   </e>
   , and
   <e type="smallcap">
    David L. Denlinger
   </e>
   (eds.),
   <e type="italic">
    Low Temperature Biology of Insects
   </e>
   (2010). Communication between different organisms, often involving chemical signals, is the subject of
   <e type="smallcap">
    William C. Agosta
   </e>
   ,
   <e type="italic">
    Chemical Communication: The Language of Pheromones
   </e>
   (1992). An introduction to plant growth and metabolism is
   <e type="smallcap">
    Hans Mohr
   </e>
   and
   <e type="smallcap">
    Peter Schopfer
   </e>
   (eds.),
   <e type="italic">
    Plant Physiology
   </e>
   (2011). Other aspects of physiology in living organisms are discussed in
   <e type="smallcap">
    J.B. Harborne
   </e>
   ,
   <e type="italic">
    Introduction to Ecological Biochemistry
   </e>
   , 4th ed. (1993).
  </p>
  <p>
   Treatments of the history of physiology are found in
   <e type="smallcap">
    John Farquhar Fulton
   </e>
   and
   <e type="smallcap">
    Leonard G. Wilson
   </e>
   (eds.),
   <e type="italic">
    Selected Readings in the History of Physiology
   </e>
   , 2nd ed. rev. and enlarged (1966), excerpts from classical publications;
   <e type="smallcap">
    James L. Larson
   </e>
   ,
   <e type="italic">
    Interpreting Nature: The Science of Living Form from Linnaeus to Kant
   </e>
   (1994), a discussion of physiological thought in the 18th century; and
   <e type="smallcap">
    W. Bruce Fye
   </e>
   ,
   <e type="italic">
    The Development of American Physiology: Scientific Medicine in the Nineteenth Century
   </e>
   (1987), examining the growth of the discipline in the United States.
   <e type="smallcap">
    Gerald L. Geison
   </e>
   ,
   <e type="italic">
    Michael Foster and the Cambridge School of Physiology: The Scientific Enterprise in Late Victorian Society
   </e>
   (1978), is a classic study of Foster and the creation of modern physiology.
  </p>
  <signature>
   Bradley Titus Scheer
  </signature>
  <signature>
   EB Editors
  </signature>
 </h1>
 <copyright>
  Encyclopædia Britannica
 </copyright>
</article>