<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "syndication_xml.dtd">
<article articleid="11254" articletypeid="1" language="en_us" lastupdate="2021-Jun-30 20:30:09" url="/article/Augustan-History/11254" version="2">
 <title>
  Augustan History
 </title>
 <p>
  <e type="bold">
   Augustan History
  </e>
  , Latin
  <e type="bold">
   Historia Augusta
  </e>
  , a collection of biographies of the Roman emperors (Augusti) from
  <xref articleid="38745">
   Hadrian
  </xref>
  to
  <xref articleid="56497">
   Numerian
  </xref>
  (117–284), an important source for the history of the Roman Empire.
 </p>
 <p>
  The work is incomplete in its surviving form; there are no lives for 244–259. It may originally have begun with one of Hadrian’s predecessors,
  <xref articleid="55323">
   Nerva
  </xref>
  or
  <xref articleid="73159">
   Trajan
  </xref>
  . The name
  <e type="italic">
   Historia Augusta
  </e>
  was invented in 1603 by the great classicist
  <xref articleid="20602">
   Isaac Casaubon
  </xref>
  . Its original title is unknown, and its authorship and date of composition are also matters of argument. The names of six authors of the early 4th century are given in the manuscript itself, but most scholars regard these as spurious and believe that the
  <e type="italic">
   History
  </e>
  was written in the late 4th century by a single person. Its point of view is consciously pagan, and the author may have been trying to counteract the growing dominance of Christianity, perhaps influenced by the paganism of the emperor
  <xref articleid="44116">
   Julian
  </xref>
  (reigned 361–363).
 </p>
 <p>
  The first part of the work, from Hadrian to Caracalla, is thought to be based on reliable sources and is of some historical value; the remaining parts are considered to be generally less reliable, since they contain invented official documents and letters and are marred by anachronisms.
 </p>
 <copyright>
  Encyclopædia Britannica
 </copyright>
</article>