<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "syndication_xml.dtd">
<article articleid="11293" articletypeid="1" language="en_us" lastupdate="2021-Jun-30 20:30:25" url="/article/aurora/11293" version="9">
 <title>
  aurora
 </title>
 <p>
  <assembly id="a75797" url="/assembly/view/75797">
   <title>
    aurora australis
   </title>
   <media mediaid="76812" type="image" url="/12/76812-004-EEA8843E.jpg"/>
   <caption>
    A display of aurora australis, or southern lights, manifesting itself as a glowing loop, in an image of part of Earth’s Southern Hemisphere taken from space by astronauts aboard the U.S. space shuttle orbiter
    <e type="italic">
     Discovery
    </e>
    on May 6, 1991. The mostly greenish blue emission is from ionized oxygen atoms at an altitude of 100–250 km (60–150 miles). The red-tinged spikes at the top of the loop are produced by ionized oxygen atoms at higher altitudes, up to 500 km (300 miles).
   </caption>
   <credit>
    NASA/Johnson Space Center/Earth Sciences and Image Analysis Laboratory
   </credit>
  </assembly>
  <e type="bold">
   aurora
  </e>
  ,
  <assemblyref assemblyid="a75797"/>
  luminous phenomenon of
  <xref articleid="110147">
   Earth
  </xref>
  ’s upper
  <xref articleid="126202">
   atmosphere
  </xref>
  that occurs primarily in high latitudes of both hemispheres; in the Northern Hemisphere auroras are called aurora borealis, aurora polaris, or northern lights, and in the Southern Hemisphere they are called aurora australis or southern lights.
 </p>
 <p>
  A brief treatment of auroras follows. For full treatment,
  <e type="italic">
   see
  </e>
  <xref articleid="42708">
   ionosphere and magnetosphere
  </xref>
  .
 </p>
 <p>
  <assembly id="a73159" url="/assembly/view/73159">
   <title>
    auroral oval
   </title>
   <media mediaid="76810" type="image" url="/10/76810-004-DE63D1C8.jpg"/>
   <caption>
    Earth’s full North Polar auroral oval, in an image taken in ultraviolet light by the U.S. Polar spacecraft over northern Canada, April 6, 1996. In the colour-coded image, which simultaneously shows dayside and nightside auroral activity, the most intense levels of activity are red, and the lowest levels are blue. Polar, launched in February 1996, was designed to further scientists’ understanding of how plasma energy contained in the solar wind interacts with Earth’s magnetosphere.
   </caption>
   <credit>
    NASA
   </credit>
  </assembly>
  <assemblyref assemblyid="a73159"/>
  Auroras are caused by the interaction of energetic particles (
  <xref articleid="32316">
   electrons
  </xref>
  and
  <xref articleid="61626">
   protons
  </xref>
  ) of the
  <xref articleid="68567">
   solar wind
  </xref>
  with
  <xref articleid="110411">
   atoms
  </xref>
  of the upper
  <xref articleid="126202">
   atmosphere
  </xref>
  . Such interaction is confined for the most part to high latitudes in oval-shaped zones that surround
  <xref articleid="110147">
   Earth’s
  </xref>
  <xref articleid="50028">
   magnetic poles
  </xref>
  and maintain a more or less fixed orientation with respect to the
  <xref articleid="110144">
   Sun
  </xref>
  . During periods of low solar activity, the auroral zones shift poleward. During periods of intense solar activity, auroras occasionally extend to the middle latitudes; for example, the aurora borealis has been seen as far south as 40° latitude in the
  <xref articleid="111233">
   United States
  </xref>
  . Auroral emissions typically occur at altitudes of about 100 km (60 miles); however, they may occur anywhere between 80 and 250 km (about 50 to 155 miles) above Earth’s surface.
 </p>
 <p>
  <assembly id="a226140" url="/assembly/view/226140">
   <title>
    Watch the aurora australis, the southern lights, from outer space
   </title>
   <media mediaid="195969" thumburl="/69/195969-049-98809EA3.jpg" type="video" url=""/>
   <caption>
    Watch a time-lapse video of the aurora australis in the Southern Hemisphere.
   </caption>
   <credit>
    NASA
   </credit>
  </assembly>
  <assemblyref assemblyid="a226140"/>
  Auroras take many forms, including luminous curtains, arcs, bands, and patches. The uniform arc is the most stable form of aurora, sometimes persisting for hours without noticeable variation. However, in a great display, other forms appear, commonly undergoing dramatic variation. The lower edges of the arcs and folds are usually much more sharply defined than the upper parts. Greenish rays may cover most of the sky poleward of the magnetic
  <xref articleid="78318">
   zenith
  </xref>
  , ending in an arc that is usually folded and sometimes edged with a lower red border that may ripple like drapery. The display ends with a poleward retreat of the auroral forms, the rays gradually degenerating into diffuse areas of white
  <xref articleid="110443">
   light
  </xref>
  .
 </p>
 <p>
  Auroras receive their
  <xref articleid="32627">
   energy
  </xref>
  from charged particles traveling between the
  <xref articleid="110144">
   Sun
  </xref>
  and
  <xref articleid="110147">
   Earth
  </xref>
  along bundled ropelike magnetic fields.
  <xref articleid="32316">
   Electrons
  </xref>
  and other charged particles, which are released by
  <xref articleid="343049">
   coronal mass ejections
  </xref>
  ,
  <xref articleid="68560">
   solar flares
  </xref>
  , and other emanations from the Sun, are driven outward by the
  <xref articleid="68567">
   solar wind
  </xref>
  . Some electrons are captured by Earth’s magnetic field (
  <e type="italic">
   see
  </e>
  <xref articleid="36468">
   geomagnetic field
  </xref>
  ) and conducted along magnetic
  <xref articleid="34835">
   field lines
  </xref>
  downward toward the magnetic poles. Alfvén waves—which are generated in the dayside and nightside regions of the
  <xref articleid="50042">
   magnetosphere
  </xref>
  and in the region of the magnetosphere called the magnetotail—push these electrons along and accelerate them up to 72.4 million km (45 million miles) per hour. They collide with
  <xref articleid="57841">
   oxygen
  </xref>
  and
  <xref articleid="55947">
   nitrogen
  </xref>
  atoms, knocking away electrons from these atoms to leave
  <xref articleid="42688">
   ions
  </xref>
  in excited states. These ions emit
  <xref articleid="109464">
   radiation
  </xref>
  at various
  <xref articleid="76325">
   wavelengths
  </xref>
  , creating the characteristic colours (red or greenish blue) of the aurora.
 </p>
 <p>
  <assembly id="a17768" url="/assembly/view/17768">
   <title>
    Jupiter’s northern and southern auroras
   </title>
   <media mediaid="21231" type="image" url="/31/21231-004-0639F13E.jpg"/>
   <caption>
    Jupiter’s northern and southern auroras, as observed by the Hubble Space Telescope. The auroras are produced by the interaction of the planet’s powerful magnetic field and particles in its upper atmosphere.
   </caption>
   <credit>
    Photo AURA/STScI/NASA/JPL (NASA photo # PIA01254, STScI-PRC98-04)
   </credit>
  </assembly>
  <assemblyref assemblyid="a17768"/>
  In addition to Earth, other planets in the
  <xref articleid="110143">
   solar system
  </xref>
  that have atmospheres and substantial magnetic fields—i.e.,
  <xref articleid="110150">
   Jupiter
  </xref>
  ,
  <xref articleid="110151">
   Saturn
  </xref>
  ,
  <xref articleid="110152">
   Uranus
  </xref>
  , and
  <xref articleid="110153">
   Neptune
  </xref>
  —display auroral activity on a large scale. Auroras also have been observed on Jupiter’s moon
  <xref articleid="42680">
   Io
  </xref>
  , where they are produced by the interaction of Io’s atmosphere with Jupiter’s powerful magnetic field.
 </p>
 <signature>
  EB Editors
 </signature>
 <copyright>
  Encyclopædia Britannica
 </copyright>
</article>