<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "syndication_xml.dtd">
<article articleid="11292" articletypeid="1" language="en_us" lastupdate="2021-Nov-05 10:27:00" url="/article/Aurora/11292" version="5">
 <title>
  Aurora
 </title>
 <p>
  <assembly id="a160777" url="/assembly/view/160777">
   <title>
    Aurora
   </title>
   <media mediaid="152630" type="image" url="/30/152630-004-FBA42BC1.jpg"/>
   <caption>
    Aurora, Illinois, on the Fox River.
   </caption>
   <credit>
    Cbradshaw
   </credit>
  </assembly>
  <e type="bold">
   Aurora
  </e>
  ,
  <assemblyref assemblyid="a160777"/>
  city, Kane and DuPage counties, northeastern
  <xref articleid="111255">
   Illinois
  </xref>
  , U.S. It lies on the Fox River, about 40 miles (65 km) west of
  <xref articleid="106238">
   Chicago
  </xref>
  . Founded in 1834 by settlers from New York, it was originally known as McCarty’s Mills. A trading point and mill site near a
  <xref articleid="61053">
   Potawatomi
  </xref>
  Indian village, the town was laid out in 1836 and renamed Aurora in 1837. It developed as both a residential and an industrial city largely because of its key position along the Chicago, Burlington and Quincy Railroad. In 1881 Aurora became the first city in Illinois to install electric streetlights.
 </p>
 <p>
  The city’s manufactures include heavy machinery, industrial and electrical equipment, woven cotton fabrics, timing products, rod end and spherical bearings, masonry accessories, and furniture. Casino gambling and the insurance industry also contribute to the economy. Aurora University (originally Mendota Seminary), founded in 1893 at Mendota by the
  <xref articleid="3813">
   Advent Christian Church
  </xref>
  , relocated to Aurora in 1912; its campus includes a centre for Native American culture. Waubonsee Community College, named for a local Potawatomi chief, was established in 1966 in Sugar Grove, a few miles west. The Aurora Historical Society museum, sited in a home built in 1857, includes locally excavated
  <xref articleid="51333">
   mastodon
  </xref>
  bones. Blackberry Farm’s Pioneer Village features an 1840s farm. The
  <xref articleid="34056">
   Fermi National Accelerator Laboratory
  </xref>
  , a physics research facility that once contained the world’s most powerful particle accelerator, is in Batavia, just north of the city. Inc. 1857. Pop. (2010) 197,899; (2020) 180,542.
 </p>
 <copyright>
  Encyclopædia Britannica
 </copyright>
</article>