<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "syndication_xml.dtd">
<article articleid="1177" articletypeid="1" language="en_us" lastupdate="2021-Jun-30 19:55:44" url="/article/Rackham-Arthur/1177" version="7">
 <title>
  Arthur Rackham
 </title>
 <p>
  <assembly id="a148972" url="/assembly/view/148972">
   <title>
    Hansel and Gretel
   </title>
   <media mediaid="130322" type="image" url="/22/130322-004-5C7D3082.jpg"/>
   <caption>
    Hansel and Gretel with the Witch on the doorstep of her cottage, illustration by Arthur Rackham for
    <e type="italic">
     Grimm’s Fairy Tales
    </e>
    , 1909.
   </caption>
   <credit>
    © Photos.com/Jupiterimages
   </credit>
  </assembly>
  <e type="bold">
   Arthur Rackham
  </e>
  ,
  <assemblyref assemblyid="a148972"/>
  (born Sept. 19, 1867, London, Eng.—died Sept. 6, 1939, Limpsfield, Surrey), British artist best known for his illustrations for classic fiction and children’s literature.
 </p>
 <p>
  Reared in London, Rackham enrolled in evening classes at the Lambeth School of Art in 1884 and spent seven years studying there while also working full-time in an insurance office. While a staff artist for a newspaper, the
  <e type="italic">
   Westminster Budget
  </e>
  (1892–96), he also began illustrating books. He became skillful using the new halftone process, and his drawings began to reveal a unique range of imagination. Rackham achieved renown with the publication of a 1900 edition of the
  <xref articleid="38131">
   Grimm brothers
  </xref>
  ’
  <e type="italic">
   Fairy Tales
  </e>
  featuring his illustrations. He illustrated a limited edition of
  <xref articleid="42827">
   Washington Irving
  </xref>
  ’s
  <e type="italic">
   Rip Van Winkle
  </e>
  (1905), which made him known in America as well. In 1908 Rackham was made a full member of the Royal Society of Painters in Watercolours.
 </p>
 <p>
  Inspired by the early 16th-century German artists
  <xref articleid="31569">
   Albrecht Dürer
  </xref>
  and
  <xref articleid="5925">
   Albrecht Altdorfer
  </xref>
  , Rackham produced drawings that are distinctive for their angularity and high detail. His illustrations are also noted for their ability to communicate the spirit of each story. Altogether he illustrated more than 60 books, including works of William Shakespeare, James Barrie, Charles Dickens, Jonathan Swift, Izaak Walton, John Milton, and Edgar Allan Poe, as well as Mother Goose rhymes and several further collections of fairy tales.
 </p>
 <copyright>
  Encyclopædia Britannica
 </copyright>
</article>