<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "syndication_xml.dtd">
<article articleid="125081" articletypeid="1" language="en_us" lastupdate="2021-Jul-01 05:20:56" url="/article/WAVES/125081" version="2">
 <title>
  WAVES
 </title>
 <p>
  <e type="bold">
   WAVES
  </e>
  , acronym of
  <e type="bold">
   Women Accepted for Volunteer Emergency Service
  </e>
  , military unit, established on July 30, 1942, as the U.S. Navy’s corps of female members. During World War II some 100,000 WAVES served in a wide variety of capacities, ranging from performing essential clerical duties to serving as instructors for male pilots-in-training. Initially, they did not serve overseas. Several thousand WAVES also participated in the Korean War. The corps continued its separate existence until 1978.
 </p>
 <p>
  The navy’s policies toward women were in some ways quite progressive. Unlike the army’s female branch, the Women’s Auxiliary Corps (WAC), the WAVES were not an auxiliary and were accorded a status comparable to that of male members of the reserve. However, the navy did come under fire for excluding African-American women from the ranks until the final months of the war, when President Franklin D. Roosevelt ordered racial integration.
 </p>
 <p>
  The first commander of the WAVES was Mildred McAfee, who as a civilian was the president of Wellesley College. Another notable woman who was a member of the WAVES was
  <xref articleid="888">
   Grace Hopper
  </xref>
  , who later attained the rank of rear admiral. Many WAVES were assigned to administrative or other office work, but for a significant number the war provided the opportunity to work at jobs usually open only to men. At least one-third of the WAVES were assigned to naval aviation duties. The navy also actively recruited college-educated women with backgrounds in mathematics, the physical sciences, and engineering. These women carried out complex and precise operations such as calculating bomb trajectories.
 </p>
 <p>
  After the war the status of women’s corps was uncertain. In 1948, however, with the passage of the Women’s Armed Services Integration Act, the WAVES became a permanent component of the navy, and in 1978 separate women’s units of the armed forces were integrated with formerly all-male units.
 </p>
 <copyright>
  Encyclopædia Britannica
 </copyright>
</article>