<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "syndication_xml.dtd">
<article articleid="126053" articletypeid="1" language="en_us" lastupdate="2021-Jul-01 05:24:50" url="/article/Woolsey-Sarah-Chauncey/126053" version="3">
 <title>
  Sarah Chauncey Woolsey
 </title>
 <p>
  <e type="bold">
   Sarah Chauncey Woolsey
  </e>
  , pseudonym
  <e type="bold">
   Susan Coolidge
  </e>
  , (born Jan. 29, 1835, Cleveland, Ohio, U.S.—died April 9, 1905, Newport, R.I.), American children’s author whose vivacious and mischievous heroines presented a popular contrast to the norm of her day.
 </p>
 <p>
  Woolsey displayed a love for reading and writing stories at an early age. In 1855 she moved with her family to New Haven, Connecticut (her uncle,
  <xref articleid="77450">
   Theodore Dwight Woolsey
  </xref>
  , was president of Yale College). During the Civil War she was active in hospital work. In 1870, after her father’s death, the family settled in Newport, Rhode Island. By that time Sarah Woolsey had already published a few magazine articles, and, in part through the influence of her close friend
  <xref articleid="43162">
   Helen Hunt (Jackson)
  </xref>
  , she began to write in earnest.
 </p>
 <p>
  Woolsey’s first book, a collection of stories for girls, appeared as
  <e type="italic">
   The New-Year’s Bargain
  </e>
  under the pseudonym Susan Coolidge in 1871. She used that name thereafter. Her subsequent books include
  <e type="italic">
   What Katy Did
  </e>
  (1872), a novel for girls that was inspired by her own childhood and was the first of a highly popular series;
  <e type="italic">
   Mischief’s Thanksgiving
  </e>
  (1874);
  <e type="italic">
   Eyebright
  </e>
  (1879);
  <e type="italic">
   A Little Country Girl
  </e>
  (1885);
  <e type="italic">
   Just Sixteen
  </e>
  (1889);
  <e type="italic">
   The Barberry Bush
  </e>
  (1893); and
  <e type="italic">
   An Old Convent School in Paris and Other Papers
  </e>
  (1895). The good-natured mischief and high-spirited heroines of Woolsey’s books set them apart from much contemporary literature and helped them retain their popularity for decades.
 </p>
 <p>
  Woolsey also published three volumes of poetry,
  <e type="italic">
   Verses
  </e>
  (1880),
  <e type="italic">
   A Few More Verses
  </e>
  (1889), and
  <e type="italic">
   Last Verses
  </e>
  (published posthumously in 1906); brought out editions of
  <e type="italic">
   The Autobiography and Correspondence of Mrs. Delany
  </e>
  (1879),
  <e type="italic">
   The Diary and Letters of Frances Burney, Mme. d’Arblay
  </e>
  (1880), and
  <e type="italic">
   Letters of Jane Austen
  </e>
  (1892); and translated Théophile Gautier’s
  <e type="italic">
   My Household of Pets
  </e>
  (1882).
 </p>
 <copyright>
  Encyclopædia Britannica
 </copyright>
</article>