<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "syndication_xml.dtd">
<article articleid="16421" articletypeid="1" language="en_us" lastupdate="2022-Aug-24 11:25:06" url="/article/bridge/16421" version="8">
 <title>
  bridge
 </title>
 <p>
  <e type="bold">
   bridge
  </e>
  , card game derived from
  <xref articleid="76789">
   whist
  </xref>
  , through the earlier variants bridge whist and auction bridge. The essential features of all bridge games, as of whist, are that four persons play, two against two as partners; a standard 52-card deck of
  <xref articleid="60380">
   playing cards
  </xref>
  is dealt out one at a time, clockwise around the table, so that each player holds 13 cards; and the object of play is to win tricks, each trick consisting of one card played by each player. Another feature is that one suit may be designated the trump suit (i.e., any card in that suit may take any card of the other suits), but the methods of designating the trump suit (or of determining that a deal will be played without trumps) differ in the various bridge games, as explained below.
 </p>
 <p>
  Since about 1896 bridge whist, auction bridge, and contract bridge have successively been the principal intellectual card games of the English-speaking countries. The third game of the series, contract bridge, spread throughout the world and in some respects constituted a social phenomenon unparalleled in the history of games. In addition to millions of casual players worldwide, there exist numerous national federations affiliated with the World Bridge Federation (WBF), which organizes international tournaments for more-serious competitors. Its largest affiliated member is the American Contract Bridge League (ACBL) with nearly 160,000 members.
 </p>
 <p>
  The arrival of personal computers and the Internet opened up new opportunities for instruction and play. In addition to being a venue for casual play, some Internet sites host tournaments recognized by ACBL and WBF at which participants can earn international master points.
 </p>
 <h1 id="h256375">
  <title>
   The bridge games
  </title>
  <p>
   The first game of the series was originally called, simply, bridge, but it is now called bridge whist to distinguish it from the two later games. Upon its introduction to New York in 1893 and to London in 1894, it almost immediately supplanted whist in the card rooms of men’s clubs, and before 1900 it was the favourite diversion of fashionable mixed gatherings. Bridge whist was itself supplanted with almost equal rapidity by auction bridge, which was introduced in England about 1904 and which became, from 1907 to 1928, the most universally popular card game theretofore known. Auction bridge had at least 15 million adherents when it was supplanted by contract bridge about 1930 and began to die out.
  </p>
  <h2 id="h256376">
   <title>
    Bridge whist
   </title>
   <p>
    In bridge, as in whist, there are four players in two partnerships, each player being dealt 13 cards. But in whist there is always a trump suit, determined by turning up the last card dealt to the dealer, and each player holds and plays his own hand. The principal innovations of bridge whist were: selection of the trump suit by the dealer or the dealer’s partner after they saw their hands; the option of playing at no trump; the exposed dummy (the hand of dealer’s partner), which was played by the dealer; a different method of scoring; and the right to double (the scoring values).
   </p>
   <p>
    In bridge whist, after the cards were dealt, the dealer could make the declaration (name any suit as trump, or decide to play without any trump), or he could transfer this duty to his partner. Before leading, the player on the dealer’s left (eldest hand) could double or could pass that privilege to his partner; and if either doubled, dealer or his partner could redouble, and so the redoubling might continue indefinitely (except that many clubs placed a limit upon the number of redoubles).
   </p>
   <p>
    The player on the dealer’s left then led. Dealer’s partner, called the dummy, placed his entire hand faceup on the table in front of him, and dealer played both his own cards and dummy’s, from each hand in proper turn. Otherwise play was as at whist.
   </p>
   <p>
    The side that won the majority of the tricks scored, for each odd trick (trick over six): if spades were trumps, 2 points; clubs, 4; diamonds, 6; hearts, 8; no trump, 12; these values doubled and redoubled as previously determined. The first side thus to score 30 or more points won game, and a fresh game was begun. The first side to win two games won rubber and received a 100-point bonus. Other bonuses, which did not count toward game, were awarded for a side holding three or more honours (ace, king, queen, jack, and 10) of the trump suit or, at no-trump declarations, three or more aces; for making slams (12 or 13 tricks won); and for chicane (a player’s holding no card of the trump suit).
   </p>
  </h2>
  <h2 id="h256377">
   <title>
    Auction bridge
   </title>
   <p>
    The essential features added by auction bridge were that all four players bid for the right to name the trump suit and that the high bidder or his partner (not necessarily the dealer) became declarer and played the dummy’s hand. In other respects the procedure at auction bridge underwent constant and frequent change.
   </p>
  </h2>
  <h2 id="h256378">
   <title>
    Contract bridge
   </title>
   <p>
    In its mechanics, contract bridge differs from auction bridge only in the scoring. At auction bridge, declarer’s side scores toward game each odd trick that it wins, whether or not it contracted to win such a trick. At contract bridge, the odd tricks won by declarer cannot be scored toward game unless declarer’s side previously contracted to win those tricks. Values of tricks, penalties, and premiums are higher in contract bridge than in auction bridge, and large bonuses are awarded for bidding and making slam contracts.
    <e type="italic">
     See below
    </e>
    <xref articleid="16421" refid="h256383">
     Scoring
    </xref>
    .
   </p>
  </h2>
 </h1>
 <h1 id="h256379">
  <title>
   How to play contract bridge
  </title>
  <p>
   The standard 52-card deck is used. The suits ranking downward in order are spades, hearts, diamonds, clubs; and the cards ranking downward in order are ace, king, queen, jack, 10, 9, 8, 7, 6, 5, 4, 3, 2.
  </p>
  <p>
   There are four players, two against two as partners, who face each other across the table. To determine partners, a pack may be spread facedown for each player to draw a card (not valid are any of the four cards at either end). The players drawing the two highest cards would then play as partners, the highest having choice of seats and cards (when two packs are used) and becoming the first dealer.
  </p>
  <p>
   If five or six wish to play in the same game, the draw establishes precedence: the player lowest in order of precedence sits out until the end of the first rubber, when he replaces the next lowest in the order. If two players draw cards of the same rank, the card of the higher-ranking suit takes precedence over the other.
  </p>
  <h2 id="h256380">
   <title>
    Deal
   </title>
   <p>
    The player at dealer’s left shuffles the cards. Preferably two packs are used so that one may be shuffled while the other is being dealt. Dealer transfers the shuffled pack to his right, where his opponent cuts it into two packets, each containing at least four cards. Dealer completes the cut.
   </p>
   <p>
    The rotation in contract bridge is always from player to player to the left. Dealer deals the cards in rotation, one at a time facedown, the first card to the player at his left and the last card to himself so that each player has 13 cards.
   </p>
  </h2>
  <h2 id="h256381">
   <title>
    Auction
   </title>
   <p>
    The deal completed, each player in rotation beginning with the dealer has a chance to call. A call is a pass, a bid, a double, or a redouble. A pass signifies disinclination to contract to win any number of tricks. A bid contracts to win a specified number of odd tricks with a specified trump or at no trump. Thus, a bid of one heart assumes a contract to win seven tricks with hearts as trumps; a bid of one no trump, seven tricks with no trump suit. The highest possible bid is seven, a contract to win all 13 tricks.
   </p>
   <p>
    Each successive bid must overcall—that is, be higher than—any preceding bid. It must name a greater number of odd tricks, or the same number of odd tricks in a higher-ranking suit, with no trump as highest ranking. Thus, two no trump will overcall a bid of two in any suit but may be overcalled by three clubs or any higher bid.
   </p>
   <p>
    A player may double the last preceding bid if it was made by an opponent and has not previously been doubled. A player may redouble the last preceding bid if it was made by his own side, doubled by an opponent, and not previously redoubled. A bid may be overcalled as usual whether or not it has been doubled or redoubled.
   </p>
   <p>
    Each time a player’s turn comes in rotation, he must make a call, and he may not change that call once it is made. A call out of rotation or a change of call is subject to penalty.
   </p>
   <p>
    The auction continues until any call is followed by three consecutive passes. If there was no bid, the next player in rotation deals. If any bid was made, the highest bid becomes the contract. The suit (if any) named in the contract becomes trump. The contractor who first named that suit (or no trump) becomes declarer, and his opponents become defenders. The auction is ended, and trick play commences.
   </p>
  </h2>
  <h2 id="h256382">
   <title>
    Trick play
   </title>
   <p>
    The object of play is to win tricks. A trick consists of four cards, one played from the hand of each player in rotation. The first card played to a trick is the lead.
   </p>
   <p>
    The defender at declarer’s left leads to the first trick. Declarer’s partner then spreads his hand faceup before him on the table, grouped in suits with the trumps, if any, to his right; this player, and his hand, are the dummy. Declarer plays both his own cards and dummy’s, but each in proper turn.
   </p>
   <p>
    Each player in rotation must follow suit to the card led (play a card of the same suit). A player unable to follow suit may play any card, including a trump, if desired. A trick is won by the highest card of the suit led or by the highest trump, if it contains any. One member of each side gathers in all tricks won by the partnership, turns them facedown, and keeps them separated sufficiently to make their number and sequence apparent. The winner of each trick leads to the next.
   </p>
   <p>
    When all 13 tricks have been played, the result is scored. The next dealer in rotation distributes the cards for a new deal.
   </p>
  </h2>
  <h2 id="h256383">
   <title>
    Scoring
   </title>
   <p>
    Each player is entitled to keep score; it is preferable for one member of each side to keep score. Scores are entered on a score sheet (U.S.) or bridge block (British): scores earned by the scorekeeper’s side (conventionally designated “We”) are to the left of the vertical line, scores earned by the opponents (designated “They”) are to the right; below the horizontal line is the trick score, and above that line is the honour score.
   </p>
   <p>
    Provided declarer’s side has at least fulfilled its contract, it scores bonus points, depending on the contract suit, for each trick over six. Diamonds and clubs score 20 points for each odd trick, spades and hearts score 30 points, and no trump scores 40 points for the first odd trick and 30 points for each additional odd trick.
   </p>
   <p>
    Such of these tricks as were included in the contract go in the trick score; the value of additional tricks (overtricks) goes in the honour score. If the contract was doubled, trick points scored below the line count twice their normal value, while overtricks count 100 each above the line if declarer’s side was not vulnerable (a term explained below) and 200 points each if declarer’s side was vulnerable. If the contract was redoubled, these values are again multiplied by two. A side fulfilling any doubled (redoubled) contract also receives a bonus of 50 (100) points on its honour score.
   </p>
   <p>
    When either side has scored 100 or more trick points below the line (whether they were scored in one or more deals), it wins a game. Another horizontal line is drawn across the score sheet, below the trick score, to signify the end of the game, and a new game is begun. Only trick scores count toward game; all other points score above the line.
   </p>
   <p>
    When either side has won two games, it wins the rubber and receives a bonus of 700 if its opponents have not won a game or 500 if its opponents have won a game. All the trick and honour points of each side are totaled, and the side with the higher total wins the difference from its opponents’ score. For purposes of settlement or of keeping a running score, this difference is usually reduced to the nearest 100, a difference of 50 or more counting as 100 and a smaller portion of 100 being disregarded. After each rubber there may be a new draw for partners, seats, and deal.
   </p>
   <p>
    When a side has won a game, it is said to be vulnerable and is exposed to heavier undertrick penalties but receives larger bonuses for overtricks at doubled and redoubled contracts and for slams. Vulnerability also may be determined by rotation.
   </p>
   <p>
    If declarer fails to fulfill his contract, his opponents score for each trick by which he falls short (“goes down” or “is set”), as shown in the .
   </p>
   <p>
    The ace, king, queen, jack, and 10 of the trump suit are honours. If any player holds four trump honours in his hand, his side scores 100 above the line; if any player holds all five trump honours, or all four aces at a no-trump contract, his side scores 150.
   </p>
   <p>
    For bidding and making a contract of six (small slam), a bonus of 500 is scored if not vulnerable, 750 if vulnerable. For a grand slam (all seven odd tricks) bid and made, the bonus is 1,000 if not vulnerable, 1,500 if vulnerable. A side bidding six and making seven scores only the small-slam bonus plus one overtrick. A side bidding seven and making only six has not fulfilled its contract, and its opponents score an undertrick penalty.
   </p>
   <p>
    If a player has to leave before a rubber is completed and no satisfactory substitute is available, a side having the only game scores 300 points; a side having the only partscore (trick score of less than 100) in an unfinished game scores 50.
   </p>
  </h2>
 </h1>
 <h1 id="h256384">
  <title>
   The development of the game
  </title>
  <p>
   Bridge was probably born of three-hand whist games. Inveterate whist players, unwilling to forgo their game merely because there were only three available players, played a game called “dummy” (with one hand exposed) long before any bridge game was known or willingly played.
  </p>
  <p>
   The origin of bridge whist is not definitely known, but a similar game appeared in Constantinople before 1870, under the name
   <e type="italic">
    khedive
   </e>
   , and almost the same game had been played in Greece before that. Khedive, whose name had for some reason become
   <xref articleid="582">
    <e type="italic">
     biritch
    </e>
   </xref>
   , was played on the French Riviera in the 1870s. A pamphlet titled
   <e type="italic">
    Biritch; or, Russian Whist
   </e>
   , was issued in London in 1887 and very nearly described bridge whist. There is a story that
   <xref articleid="38877">
    Ludovic Halévy
   </xref>
   , in 1893, tried to persuade some whist-playing friends in Paris to play bridge with him, but they refused. In the same year, however, it was played at the Whist Club in New York City, and in 1894 Lord Brougham, penalized for failure to turn the last (trump) card in a whist game at London’s Portland Club, apologized with the excuse that he forgot he was not playing bridge, “the finest card game ever introduced.”
  </p>
  <p>
   Whist players were prompt to deplore the arrival of bridge, almost unanimously asserting that whist, with all four hands hidden, was far more scientific than bridge. The fallacy of this soon became apparent, for exposure of the dummy provided clarity in thousands of situations in which the whist player had to guess blindly. This provided new opportunities for analysis and greatly stimulated the study of skillful play. By 1897 almost all the leading whist players had succumbed to the attractions of the new game, and even the whist authority “Cavendish” (
   <xref articleid="43930">
    Henry Jones
   </xref>
   ), who had refused for a period in 1897–98 to enter the Portland Club because whist had been all but abandoned there, was converted to bridge before his death in 1899.
  </p>
  <p>
   Bridge whist was the first game of the whist family to appeal to women as much as to men. It quickly became the favoured game of the fashionable world but did not supplant
   <xref articleid="33175">
    euchre
   </xref>
   and the other card games among the middle and lower classes, as auction bridge did later.
  </p>
  <h2 id="h256385">
   <title>
    Development of auction bridge
   </title>
   <p>
    Several accounts of the origin of auction bridge have been advanced. It is probable that just as bridge whist developed from three-hand whist, auction bridge developed from three-hand bridge whist. A letter in the London
    <e type="italic">
     Times
    </e>
    , Jan. 16, 1903, signed by Oswald Crawfurd, describes “auction bridge for three players.” A book by “John Doe” (F. Roe), published in Allahabad, India, in 1904, presents three-hand auction bridge as an invention of Roe and two other members of the Indian civil service when, at an isolated post, they had no “fourth” for bridge whist. Experimental games in England and America apparently followed immediately on the publication of the Crawfurd letter, for by 1904 the best club players were turning to auction bridge. London’s Portland Club adopted auction bridge in 1907, New York City’s Whist Club and other American clubs in the two years following. By 1910 bridge whist was all but obsolete and auction bridge was virtually the only card game played by fashionable society and its emulators.
   </p>
   <p>
    The widespread appeal of auction bridge is attributable partly to the character of the game and partly to the social conditions into which it was born. The science of auction bridge, more complex and more nearly inexhaustible than that of any previous game, created a demand for large numbers of instructors in skillful play. The instructors, as a professional class, served as proselytizers. Concurrently, the rapid growth of the leisure class increased the demand for means for the entertainment of guests, and auction bridge was found to fill this need ideally. The gradual relaxation of church opposition to card playing, but not to gambling, stimulated acceptance of auction bridge, a game most often played without stakes and never for high stakes in the sense that gambling games are.
   </p>
  </h2>
  <h2 id="h256405">
   <title>
    Development of contract bridge
   </title>
   <p>
    This game was developed almost concurrently with auction bridge but was slower to win popularity. At least as early as 1915, auction bridge players tried a variant in which one could score toward game only the odd tricks one had bid. The committee on laws of the Whist Club considered incorporation of this principle into the auction bridge laws in 1917 and again in 1920. They refrained in both instances because they thought such a difficult game would compromise the popularity of auction bridge.
   </p>
   <p>
    Harold S. Vanderbilt (
    <e type="italic">
     see
    </e>
    <xref articleid="74799">
     Vanderbilt family
    </xref>
    ) of New York was one of the expert auction bridge players who had experimented with contract bridge. While on a long sea voyage in 1926, Vanderbilt played
    <xref articleid="60276">
     plafond
    </xref>
    , a French version of auction bridge. In the course of these games, he devised a new system of scoring values, multiplying auction bridge values five times or more; large slam bonuses; and the factor of vulnerability. (With minor changes this became and remains the contract bridge scoring system.)
   </p>
   <p>
    Until 1931 most casual players continued to play auction bridge. The publicity whereby contract bridge found its way to such players was supplied by another of the former auction bridge experts,
    <xref articleid="28147">
     Ely Culbertson
    </xref>
    of New York. Culbertson established contract bridge as the leading card game and himself as its principal authority by a succession of tournament victories and by various maneuvers devised to publicize contract bridge and Culbertson personally. In 1930 Culbertson’s teams won nearly every one of the principal American tournaments, then went to England and defeated three leading British teams. In the winter of 1931–32 Culbertson and his wife, Josephine Culbertson, played and defeated in a 150-rubber match one of the most prominent players among the former auction bridge authorities, Sidney S. Lenz. The progress of the match, called by American newspapers “the bridge battle of the century,” was featured for more than a month on their front pages. The unprecedented publicity made contract bridge a fad not only in the United States but also in South America and Europe.
   </p>
   <p>
    By 1935 the white heat of the fad had cooled. Nevertheless, the sales of books and playing cards for contract bridge increased steadily. By the start of the 21st century, bridge had become so commonplace that it was no longer a remarkable phenomenon and most newspapers in the United States and Great Britain carried regular columns. In particular, bridge was thriving in Europe, with many young players attracted to the game. In contrast, few young people were playing the game in the United States, although it remained popular with older generations. One of the main factors that has limited the growth of the game has been the small or nonexistent prizes awarded at tournaments. The only way to make a living from bridge has been to be hired by wealthy clients as a partner or teammate—“play for pay”—or through writing about the game. Another factor limiting the growth of bridge has been that, like
    <xref articleid="105867">
     chess
    </xref>
    , it is not very telegenic and requires considerable prior experience before a television viewer can appreciate the play.
   </p>
   <p>
    At the top level, bridge became much more scientific at the end of the 20th century, with experts having bidding-system notes that often ran to well over 100 pages in an attempt to cover all possible contingencies, and various unusual conventions and systems were developed. In the 1980s, forcing-pass methods were in vogue, especially in Poland (where they started), Australia, and New Zealand. An initial pass showed a good hand, usually at least 13 high-card points. Any other bid denied 13 points, and there was one call that indicated a very bad hand, normally 0–7 points. It was, of course, dangerous to have to open with no points, especially when vulnerable, but these systems gained popularity primarily because they put the opponents in unusual situations. Also, an opposing pair got to use its bidding system only if it dealt and opened immediately. Toward the end of the 1980s, these systems were banned from international play.
   </p>
  </h2>
 </h1>
 <h1 id="h256386">
  <title>
   Duplicate and tournament bridge
  </title>
  <p>
   Bridge is played in three principal forms: rubber, Chicago, and duplicate. Rubber bridge is the simplest form for four players and is frequently played in casual games among friends. Chicago, or four-deal bridge, is most often used for small card parties in which several tables are used. Because a game of Chicago bridge involves only four deals, it is ideal for allowing each player to play with and against most of the other guests over the course of an evening. Duplicate bridge is played in all serious competitions and in official tournaments.
  </p>
  <h2 id="h256387">
   <title>
    Duplicate bridge
   </title>
   <p>
    The purpose of duplicate bridge is to eliminate, as nearly as possible, the element of luck from the game. After the usual deal and auction, the four players in playing their cards do not gather them up as tricks; instead, each shows the card he plays, then turns it down and keeps it on the table in front of him. After the result of the play has been ascertained and scored, the four hands in their original form are placed in a duplicate board, or tray, which is a rectangular container having four pockets, one for each hand. This board is then passed on to another table, where it is played by four other players. Thus, it is possible to compare results made with identical cards, the conclusion being that the pair making the higher score must have been more skillful.
   </p>
   <p>
    The result of each deal at duplicate contract bridge is first scored as in regular contract bridge, with these exceptions: there are no rubber bonuses, and, when declarer’s side fulfills a game contract, it receives 300 points if not vulnerable, 500 points if vulnerable. For a trick score of less than 100 points, the bonus is 50 points regardless of vulnerability. The bonuses for honours held in one hand are not scored in match-point play.
   </p>
   <p>
    Dealer and vulnerability are assigned by the markings on the duplicate board. Sixteen such boards constitute a full set; although approximately 30 boards are usually played in one session, the series 17–32, 33–48, etc., are respectively identical to the 1–16. North is dealer on board 1, East on board 2, and so on in rotation. Neither side is vulnerable on boards 1, 8, 11, 14; North-South are vulnerable only on boards 2, 5, 12, 15, East-West on boards 3, 6, 9, 16, and both sides on boards 4, 7, 10, 13.
   </p>
   <p>
    Match-point scoring is used in all individual contests, most pair contests, and most team-of-four contests in which more than two teams compete. Each pair’s (or team’s) score for a board is compared with the scores made on that board by all other pairs that played precisely the same hands. A pair receives one match point for every such comparison in which it has the higher score, one-half match point for the same score. The pair or team amassing the most match points during the session is the winner.
   </p>
   <p>
    The European system of match-point scoring in team matches combines the total-point and match-point ideas. This system has been widely adopted in the United States. A team scores international match-points in proportion to its margin of victory on each board.
   </p>
  </h2>
  <h2 id="h256388">
   <title>
    Bridge tournaments
   </title>
   <p>
    The idea of duplicate play achieved great popularity in the United States after Cassius M. Paine and J.L. Sebring patented the duplicate tray in 1891. Duplicate auction bridge became similarly popular in the 1920s, and championship tournaments were played regularly, but the game did not spread to Europe until contract bridge had arrived. The international matches between American and British teams in 1930 so stimulated interest that nearly all serious students of contract bridge took up duplicate play within the next two years. From 1934 until war or the threat of war interrupted them, national and European championships were held annually.
   </p>
   <p>
    In the United States, championship tournaments at auction bridge were conducted by the American Whist League in 1924–35, the American Bridge League in 1927–37, and the U.S. Bridge Association in 1933–37. Also there was an annual team-of-four tournament for the Harold Vanderbilt Cup, the first trophy given (1928) for a national championship at contract bridge. In 1937 all came under the control of a new, consolidated association, the American Contract Bridge League (ACBL). Its membership grew from 9,000 in 1940 to more than 160,000 by the 21st century.
   </p>
   <p>
    Similar contests were held annually in Great Britain by the British Bridge League, founded in 1932, and European championships were conducted by the European Bridge League (EBL), founded the same year. These tournaments continued through 1937 and were resumed in 1946. At the annual tournament of the EBL held in Oslo, Norway, in 1958, the World Bridge Federation was formed to control the world championship matches as previously played and to conduct an Olympiad open to all continents and countries beginning in 1960 and renewable each four years thereafter. Teams in international competition have six players each, of whom four play at a time, plus a nonplaying captain. Twenty-nine nationals from every continent except Antarctica took part in the first World Bridge Olympiad, in Turin, Italy, which was won by the French team.
   </p>
   <p>
    In 2005 the governing bodies of bridge,
    <xref articleid="105867">
     chess
    </xref>
    , draughts (
    <xref articleid="22734">
     checkers
    </xref>
    ), and
    <xref articleid="37127">
     go
    </xref>
    formed the International Mind Sports Association. The aim was to engage in a dialogue with the International Olympic Committee and to try to organize the World Mind Games, or Intellympiad, to be held in the Olympic city directly after a Winter or Summer Games.
   </p>
  </h2>
 </h1>
 <h1 id="h256389">
  <title>
   Laws of bridge
  </title>
  <p>
   As descendants of whist, the several bridge games have always had more detailed laws than those of any other nonathletic game except chess. The Portland Club of London and the Whist Club of New York became traditionally the lawmaking bodies for rubber auction bridge, the game played chiefly in clubs and private homes. With the rise of duplicate and tournament bridge in the 1930s and ’40s, the ACBL and the European Bridge League became predominant in lawmaking.
  </p>
  <p>
   The Portland Club adopted a code of laws for bridge whist in 1895, the Whist Club a different code in 1897. The Whist Club’s laws were revised in 1902, the Portland Club’s never. In 1909 the Portland Club published the first code of laws for auction bridge (revised 1914, 1924, 1928), and in 1910 the Whist Club published its first auction bridge laws (revised 1912, 1913, 1915, 1917, 1920, 1926). After 1910 auction bridge was never officially played under identical laws in Great Britain and elsewhere. Under the American laws, a bid of (for example) three in any suit would overcall a bid of two in any suit. Under British laws, a bid of one no trump, worth 12 points, would overcall a bid of five spades, worth 5 × 2 = 10 points. The American principle prevailed and by 1930 had become universal.
  </p>
  <p>
   The scoring values were changed several times in both countries. At first the scoring was as it had been in bridge whist. Then for a time the game was called royal auction because the spade suit had alternative values: a player might bid either spades, worth two points per trick, or royal spades (in the United States often called “lilies”), worth nine points per trick. The same suit would be trumps in either case, but the declarer’s profit or risk would depend on which scoring value he had established by his bid. The count for a chicane was dropped after the first few years.
  </p>
  <p>
   The first laws of contract bridge were published by the Knickerbocker Whist Club of New York in 1927, but when later in the same year the Whist Club issued a code, the Knickerbocker laws were withdrawn. The Portland Club issued a code in 1929. In 1932 representatives of the Portland and Whist clubs met and agreed on the first international code, to which the Commission Française du Bridge subscribed. Since then, except for a 1941 American code (published 1943) issued unilaterally because the European correspondents were at war when it was written, every code has been international, and the revisions of 1948 and 1949 were promulgated by the ACBL and the EBL, to which the Whist Club and the Portland Club had ceded their claims of prerogative. In turn, these organizations, along with representative bodies from South America, deferred to the newly formed World Bridge Federation (WBF) in 1958. The most recent WBF rules for traditional rubber bridge were adopted in 1993, for duplicate contract bridge in 1997, and for play over the Internet in 2001.
  </p>
 </h1>
 <h1 id="h256390">
  <title>
   Strategy of contract bridge
  </title>
  <p>
   The object in contract bridge is to score as many points as possible and to permit the opponents to score as few points as possible. The strategy employed by the best players in pursuit of this object embraces a technique that in complexity approaches the technique of chess, as well as a scope for deductive analysis, psychology, alertness, and mental ascendancy over one’s opponents. Thus it is an art, which can hardly be taught or even described. The best players of the game (like the best players of bridge whist and auction bridge before them) combine unusual aptitude, interest amounting virtually to obsession, and experience derived from constant play with and against their peers.
  </p>
  <p>
   Nevertheless, the general rules, called systems, enable the casual player to emulate the expert standard in most cases. In whist, the progenitive game, the science was meagre; in bridge whist it improved; in auction bridge the best players were competent but the literature of the game never reflected the best practices; in contract bridge the most popular systems, if strictly followed, have produced nearly 90 percent efficiency.
  </p>
  <p>
   The factors in the systems of contract bridge bidding and play are:
  </p>
  <list type="ul">
   <item>
    1. Valuation. The player who bids accepts danger; if unable to fulfill his contract, he will be subject to penalties. Therefore, he must be able to estimate the trick-taking power of his hand.
   </item>
   <item>
    2. Information. Bridge is essentially a partnership game. Each partner must inform his partner as to the nature and strength of the hand he holds. Assuming such information has been given and received, one partner should be able to decide the best contract for the combined hands.
   </item>
   <item>
    3. Strategy. A bid defeats its own purposes if the information it gives is more valuable to the opponents than to the bidder’s partner. Therefore, ideally, each bid should be designed to inform the bidder’s partner only to the extent necessary while withholding information from the opponents.
   </item>
  </list>
  <p>
   Only a few general principles can be stated for the play of the cards, but to the extent possible they have been exhaustively treated in the literature of the several bridge games. The ethics of the game permit information to be given only by the card led or the card played to a trick. Convention has endowed certain plays with meanings generally understood.
  </p>
  <h2 id="h256391">
   <title>
    Bidding systems
   </title>
   <p>
    Bidding systems have preoccupied the student of bridge since the earliest appearance of contract bridge. The first system proposed was that of Harold S. Vanderbilt, who created the game that became successful as contract bridge. The Vanderbilt Club system provided that a player with a strong hand bid one club, the lowest bid; his partner with a weak hand would bid one diamond and with a strong hand would make some other bid. Despite its technical excellence, the Vanderbilt Club system was not widely accepted. The most successful system of the first 20 years of contract bridge was devised by
    <xref articleid="28147">
     Ely Culbertson
    </xref>
    of New York. The Culbertson system required a player to value his hand by a schedule of high-card combinations called honour tricks and then to bid in accordance with established requirements based on the number of honour tricks held and the length of the player’s suits.
   </p>
   <p>
    Despite competition from other systems advanced by those who had been the principal authorities in auction bridge (the official system), by leading players such as Phillip Hal Sims (the Sims system), and by leading teams such as the Four Aces (the Four Aces system), all during the early 1930s, the Culbertson system was paramount throughout the world until the late 1940s.
   </p>
   <p>
    In 1949
    <xref articleid="37429">
     Charles H. Goren
    </xref>
    of Philadelphia popularized a method of valuation called the point count, an extension of similar methods proposed as early as 1904 but not previously made applicable to more than a fraction of the many hands a bridge player might hold. In other respects Goren’s system was similar to or identical with the methods advocated by Culbertson and the Four Aces.
   </p>
   <p>
    Hundreds of different bidding systems have been proposed for contract bridge, and at all times several dozen systems are in use. Some of these are modifications of the Goren system, or they are substantially the same as the Goren system with the addition of a few special bidding conventions; others are radically different. Bidding systems can be divided into two main groups: natural systems, in which the bidder usually has strength in any suit he bids, and artificial systems, in which most bids are signals designed to show the general strength of the bidder’s hand but do not necessarily promise any strength in the suit bid. (Goren wrote the Goren system section of the bridge article for the 1963 printing of the 14th edition of
    <e type="italic">
     Encyclopædia Britannica
    </e>
    ;
    <e type="italic">
     see
    </e>
    the Britannica Classic:
    <xref articleid="435293">
     Bridge
    </xref>
    .)
   </p>
  </h2>
  <h2 id="h256392">
   <title>
    Slam bidding
   </title>
   <p>
    When a partnership has been able to ascertain that it has at least 33 points in the combined hands plus an adequate trump suit, the only thing that remains is to make certain that the opponents are unable to cash two quick tricks. For this purpose control-showing bids are used. Three systems are most popular: the Blackwood convention, the Gerber convention, and cue bidding.
   </p>
   <h3 id="h256393">
    <title>
     Blackwood convention
    </title>
    <p>
     In this convention, devised in 1934 by
     <xref articleid="2528">
      Easley Blackwood
     </xref>
     of Indianapolis, Ind., a bid of four no trump asks partner to show his total number of aces. A response of five clubs shows no aces (or all four aces); five diamonds shows one ace; five hearts shows two aces; five spades shows three aces. After aces have been shown, the four no-trump bidder may ask for kings by bidding five no trump. The responder now shows kings as he showed aces in response to the four no-trump bid, by bidding six clubs with no kings, six diamonds with one king, and so forth.
    </p>
   </h3>
   <h3 id="h256394">
    <title>
     Gerber convention
    </title>
    <p>
     This was devised in 1938 by John Gerber of Houston, Texas. An unnecessary bid of four clubs, when the bid could not possibly have a natural meaning (such as opener bids one no trump, responder bids four clubs) asks partner to show the number of his aces. A response of four diamonds shows no aces, four hearts shows one ace, and so forth. If the asking hand desires information about kings, he bids five clubs (or, by partnership agreement, the next higher suit over his partner’s ace-showing response; thus, if the responding hand has bid four hearts over four clubs to show one ace, a call of four spades would ask him to show kings and he would reply four no trump to show no kings, five clubs to show one king, and so forth).
    </p>
   </h3>
   <h3 id="h256395">
    <title>
     Cue bidding
    </title>
    <p>
     The individual method of ace showing (cue bidding) is used when both partners have shown strength or when the trump suit has been agreed on. For example, opener bids two spades, responder bids three spades; a bid of four clubs by opener now would show the ace of clubs (or a void) and would invite responder to show an ace if he had one.
    </p>
   </h3>
  </h2>
  <h2 id="h256396">
   <title>
    Leads
   </title>
   <p>
    The card led against declarer is selected so as to give information to the leader’s partner. Certain conventional meanings of leads were established during the bridge whist period and, with slight changes, persisted in contract bridge.
   </p>
   <p>
    In winning or attempting to win a trick to which some other player led, a defender plays the lowest card in an unbroken sequence of high cards; as, the 10 from Q-J-10-8.
   </p>
   <p>
    A standard defender’s signal is the high-low, or come-on: the play or discard of an unnecessarily high card, followed if possible by a lower card of the same suit on a subsequent trick. This denotes a desire to have that suit led.
   </p>
   <p>
    There are many other signals and conventions in defenders’ play. These do not violate the spirit of the game if they are known to the opponents. Declarer need not observe any system in the selection of cards, for he has no partner to inform.
   </p>
  </h2>
 </h1>
 <h1 id="h256397">
  <title>
   Bridge problems
  </title>
  <p>
   Proficiency at the play of the cards in bridge is enhanced by study of double-dummy problems (in which the location of all unplayed cards is known). Putting such knowledge to practical use has been much better accomplished in contract bridge than in any of its predecessor games. For example, a prime problem at whist was the “Great Vienna Coup,” with which the expert whist players had difficulty even when they could see all four hands. Execution of this and similarly difficult plays is commonplace among contract bridge players far below the highest rank.
  </p>
  <p>
   Most double-dummy problems embrace the squeeze (so named by Sidney S. Lenz of New York, because it reminded him of a maneuver in baseball), in which a player has winning cards in two or three suits but is forced to discard one of them. The throw-in play and the trump pickup (generic terms for the group of plays that included the grand coup of whist) are other favourite themes of problem constructors.
  </p>
  <h2 id="h256398">
   <title>
    The Whitfeld six
   </title>
   <p>
    <assembly id="a90621" url="/assembly/view/90621">
     <title>
      Whitfeld six
     </title>
     <media mediaid="96294" type="image" url="/94/96294-004-FE0D1E1A.jpg"/>
     <caption>
      Whitfeld six Card editor of the
      <e type="italic">
       London Field
      </e>
      W.H. Whitfeld published this bridge problem in 1885. South is declarer and has the lead with hearts as trump. With a sophisticated finesse, South can win every trick. South begins by leading the ace of diamonds, which, depending on what the opponents discard, opens a possible finesse of North’s jack of diamonds. Next, South passes the lead to North with a spade that North trumps. North then leads the last heart, and South discards the 10 of clubs. With the lead of the last trump and then the ace of clubs, the defenders are presented with an insurmountable dilemma. East must hold two diamonds or South takes the last two tricks in the suit by discarding a spade. However, in order to hold on to two diamonds, East must discard the jack of spades, which in turn would force West to hold the queen of spades. Since West also needs the queen of diamonds and the jack of clubs to avoid losing a trick, a discard from any of the three suits will allow South to win all of the remaining tricks by an appropriate discard.
     </caption>
     <credit>
      Encyclopædia Britannica, Inc.
     </credit>
    </assembly>
    <assemblyref assemblyid="a90621"/>
    The most famous of all double-dummy problems was proposed by W.H. Whitfeld, a mathematician at the University of Cambridge, in 1885 and is called the Whitfeld six because each hand has six cards. Whist players of the day could make nothing of it, and, despite the advancement in the science of card playing, it would cause trouble even to most experienced contract bridge players.
   </p>
  </h2>
  <h2 id="h256399">
   <title>
    The Vienna coup
   </title>
   <p>
    <assembly id="a90622" url="/assembly/view/90622">
     <title>
      Vienna coup
     </title>
     <media mediaid="96293" type="image" url="/93/96293-004-FE3CB6A7.jpg"/>
     <caption>
      Vienna coup In a Vienna coup a suit needs to be unblocked before a finesse is undertaken. In this example, if South immediately cashes (wins a trick with) the ace of diamonds, East can discard a heart because, after winning a heart trick with North’s ace, there will be no way of cashing South’s queen of hearts. Instead, the ace of hearts should be cashed first (either led by North or led to with South’s low heart), and then the ace of diamonds should be cashed. This play will force East to discard either a heart, making South’s queen of hearts good, or a spade, making North’s jack of spades good.
     </caption>
     <credit>
      Encyclopædia Britannica, Inc.
     </credit>
    </assembly>
    <assemblyref assemblyid="a90622"/>
    The characteristic of the Vienna coup is that a high card must be played early, apparently establishing a card in an opponent’s hand but actually subjecting him to a squeeze that could not have been effected had the high card remained unplayed.
   </p>
   <signature>
    Albert H. Morehead
   </signature>
   <signature>
    Phillip Alder
   </signature>
  </h2>
 </h1>
 <h1 id="h256400">
  <title>
   Bibliography
  </title>
  <p>
   <e type="smallcap">
    Alan Truscott
   </e>
   and
   <e type="smallcap">
    Dorothy Truscott
   </e>
   ,
   <e type="italic">
    The New York Times Bridge Book: An Anecdotal History of the Development, Personalities, and Strategies of the World’s Most Popular Card Game
   </e>
   (2002), is an excellent introduction to the game. The American Contract Bridge League series by
   <e type="smallcap">
    Audrey Grant
   </e>
   , which includes
   <e type="italic">
    The Spade Series: An Introduction to Duplicate Bridge
   </e>
   (1990, reissued 1997),
   <e type="italic">
    The Club Series: Bidding
   </e>
   (1990, reissued 1998),
   <e type="italic">
    The Diamond Series: Play of the Hand
   </e>
   (1999, reissued 2002), and
   <e type="italic">
    The Heart Series: Introduction to Bridge Defense
   </e>
   (1997, reissued 2002), is a comprehensive course.
   <e type="smallcap">
    Eddie Kantar
   </e>
   ,
   <e type="italic">
    Bridge for Dummies
   </e>
   (1997), gives a comprehensive introduction to the game using modern bidding methods.
  </p>
  <signature>
   Phillip Alder
  </signature>
 </h1>
 <copyright>
  Encyclopædia Britannica
 </copyright>
</article>