<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "syndication_xml.dtd">
<article articleid="16617" articletypeid="1" language="en_us" lastupdate="2022-Jun-29 17:32:31" url="/article/bronze/16617" version="3">
 <title>
  bronze
 </title>
 <p>
  <assembly id="a22635" url="/assembly/view/22635">
   <title>
    Brunswick Lion
   </title>
   <media mediaid="30061" type="image" url="/61/30061-004-848EC523.jpg"/>
   <caption>
    Brunswick Lion monument on the Burgplatz in Braunschweig, Germany
   </caption>
   <credit>
    H. Krause-Willemberg/ZEFA
   </credit>
  </assembly>
  <e type="bold">
   bronze
  </e>
  ,
  <assemblyref assemblyid="a22635"/>
  <xref articleid="5832">
   alloy
  </xref>
  traditionally composed of copper and tin. Modern bronze is typically 88 percent copper and about 12 percent tin. Bronze is of exceptional historical interest and still finds wide applications. The earliest bronze artifacts were made about 4500
  <e type="smallcap">
   bce
  </e>
  , though use of bronze in artifacts did not become common until much later, in the 2nd millennium
  <e type="smallcap">
   bce
  </e>
  during the
  <xref articleid="16618">
   Bronze Age
  </xref>
  . The proportions of copper and tin varied widely (from 67 to 95 percent copper in surviving artifacts), but, by the
  <xref articleid="52537">
   Middle Ages
  </xref>
  in Europe, certain proportions were known to yield specific properties. An alloy described in an 11th-century Greek manuscript in the library of St. Mark’s in Venice was cited as having a proportion of one pound copper to two ounces of tin (8 to 1), approximately that used for bronze gunmetal in later times. Some modern bronzes contain no tin at all, having other metals substituted—such as
  <xref articleid="5954">
   aluminum
  </xref>
  ,
  <xref articleid="50515">
   manganese
  </xref>
  , and even
  <xref articleid="78379">
   zinc
  </xref>
  .
 </p>
 <p>
  <assembly id="a266168" url="/assembly/view/266168">
   <title>
    Baal
   </title>
   <media mediaid="231959" type="image" url="/59/231959-004-20B72862.jpg"/>
   <caption>
    A bronze figurine from the Middle Bronze Age (about 2000–1500
    <e type="smallcap">
     bce
    </e>
    ) depicts the god Baal.
   </caption>
   <credit>
    Walters Art Museum, Baltimore; Acquired by Henry Walters, 1928 (54.788)
   </credit>
  </assembly>
  <assemblyref assemblyid="a266168"/>
  Bronze is harder than copper, as a result of alloying that metal with tin or other metals. Bronze is also more fusible (i.e., more readily melted) and is hence easier to cast. It is harder than pure
  <xref articleid="42794">
   iron
  </xref>
  and far more resistant to
  <xref articleid="472131">
   corrosion
  </xref>
  . The substitution of iron for bronze in tools and weapons from about 1000
  <e type="smallcap">
   bce
  </e>
  was the result of the abundance of iron compared with copper and tin rather than any inherent advantages of iron. Besides its traditional use in weapons and tools, bronze was widely used in
  <xref articleid="105949">
   coinage
  </xref>
  ; most “copper” coins were actually bronze, typically with about 4 percent tin and 1 percent zinc.
 </p>
 <p>
  Bell metal, characterized by its sonorous quality when struck, is a bronze with a high tin content of 20–25 percent. Statuary bronze, with a tin content of less than 10 percent and an admixture of zinc and lead, is technically a brass (a copper-zinc alloy). Bronze is improved in hardness and strength by the addition of a small amount of phosphorus; phosphor bronze may contain 1 or 2 percent phosphorus in the ingot and a mere trace after casting, but its strength is nonetheless enhanced for such applications as pump plungers, valves, and bushings. Also useful in mechanical engineering are manganese bronzes, in which there may be little or no tin but considerable amounts of zinc and up to 4.5 percent manganese.
  <xref articleid="5955">
   Aluminum bronzes
  </xref>
  , containing up to 16 percent aluminum and small amounts of other metals such as iron or
  <xref articleid="55747">
   nickel
  </xref>
  , are especially strong and corrosion-resistant; they are cast or wrought into pipe fittings, pumps, gears, ship propellers, and
  <xref articleid="106035">
   turbine
  </xref>
  blades. (For more information about bronze art and implements,
  <e type="italic">
   see
  </e>
  <xref articleid="16619">
   bronze work
  </xref>
  .)
 </p>
 <signature>
  EB Editors
 </signature>
 <copyright>
  Encyclopædia Britannica
 </copyright>
</article>