<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "syndication_xml.dtd">
<article articleid="17993" articletypeid="1" language="en_us" lastupdate="2021-Jun-30 20:53:36" url="/article/bulb/17993" version="5">
 <title>
  bulb
 </title>
 <p>
  <assembly id="a206286" url="/assembly/view/206286">
   <title>
    red onion; yellow onion
   </title>
   <media mediaid="187208" type="image" url="/08/187208-004-EED7150F.jpg"/>
   <caption>
    Red and yellow onions (
    <e type="italic">
     Allium cepa
    </e>
    ).
   </caption>
   <credit>
    © rysp/Fotolia
   </credit>
  </assembly>
  <e type="bold">
   bulb
  </e>
  ,
  <assemblyref assemblyid="a206286"/>
  in
  <xref articleid="110585">
   botany
  </xref>
  , a modified
  <xref articleid="69567">
   stem
  </xref>
  that is the resting stage of certain seed plants, particularly perennial
  <xref articleid="53394">
   monocotyledons
  </xref>
  . A bulb consists of a relatively large, usually globe-shaped, underground
  <xref articleid="471931">
   bud
  </xref>
  with membraneous or fleshy overlapping
  <xref articleid="47499">
   leaves
  </xref>
  arising from a short stem. A bulb’s fleshy leaves—which in some species are actually expanded leaf bases—function as food reserves that enable a plant to lie dormant when water is unavailable (during winter or drought) and resume its active growth when favourable conditions again prevail.
 </p>
 <p>
  <assembly id="a181881" url="/assembly/view/181881">
   <title>
    bulb
   </title>
   <media mediaid="154157" type="image" url="/57/154157-004-83521B3C.jpg"/>
   <caption>
    Plants sprouting out of the ground from bulbs.
   </caption>
   <credit>
    © Herbert Esser/Fotolia
   </credit>
  </assembly>
  <assemblyref assemblyid="a181881"/>
  There are two main types of bulbs. One type, typified by the
  <xref articleid="57140">
   onion
  </xref>
  , has a thin papery covering protecting its fleshy leaves. The other type, the scaly bulb, as seen in true
  <xref articleid="48269">
   lilies
  </xref>
  , has naked storage leaves, unprotected by any papery covering, that make the bulb appear to consist of a series of angular scales. Bulbs can vary in size from insignificant pea-sized structures to those of large crinum lilies (
  <e type="italic">
   Crinum
  </e>
  species), the individual bulbs of which may weigh more than 7 kg (15 pounds).
 </p>
 <p>
  <assembly id="a8459" url="/assembly/view/8459">
   <media mediaid="5649" type="image" url="/49/5649-004-FE5C554D.jpg"/>
   <caption>
    A hyacinth (
    <e type="italic">
     Hyancinthus
    </e>
    ) bulb, an underground stem that produces aerial foliage. The foliage dies back to the bulb, which houses a maturing flower bud. The bulb is common in herbaceous perennials that become dormant in response to a seasonal change in climate or water availability.
   </caption>
   <credit>
    Park Seed Co., Greenwood, South Carolina
   </credit>
  </assembly>
  <assemblyref assemblyid="a8459"/>
  Bulbs enable many common garden ornamentals, such as the
  <xref articleid="54847">
   narcissus
  </xref>
  ,
  <xref articleid="73724">
   tulip
  </xref>
  , and
  <xref articleid="41675">
   hyacinth
  </xref>
  , to produce their
  <xref articleid="34656">
   flowers
  </xref>
  rapidly, almost precociously, in early spring when growing conditions are favourable. Other bulb-producing plants, such as the
  <xref articleid="48269">
   lilies
  </xref>
  , flower in the summer, while a few, such as the meadow saffron, bloom in the fall. Bulb-producing species are especially abundant in the lily (
  <xref articleid="48252">
   Liliaceae
  </xref>
  ) and amaryllis (
  <xref articleid="6016">
   Amaryllidaceae
  </xref>
  ) families. A few bulb-producing species are of economic importance to humans because of the taste and nutritive value of their fleshy leaves; included among such species are the
  <xref articleid="57140">
   onion
  </xref>
  and its relatives the
  <xref articleid="67097">
   shallot
  </xref>
  ,
  <xref articleid="36089">
   garlic
  </xref>
  , and
  <xref articleid="47609">
   leek
  </xref>
  . Other bulbs contain poisonous compounds—such as the red squill (
  <e type="italic">
   Drimia
  </e>
  ), the bulbs of which are the source of a highly effective
  <xref articleid="64023">
   rat poison
  </xref>
  .
 </p>
 <p>
  In
  <xref articleid="109764">
   horticulture
  </xref>
  the term
  <e type="italic">
   bulb
  </e>
  is incorrectly applied to a number of botanical structures that have a similar food-storing function. Among these are the solid
  <xref articleid="26313">
   corms
  </xref>
  of the
  <xref articleid="27950">
   crocus
  </xref>
  and
  <xref articleid="36962">
   gladiolus
  </xref>
  and the elongated
  <xref articleid="63441">
   rhizome
  </xref>
  of some
  <xref articleid="42772">
   irises
  </xref>
  .
 </p>
 <signature>
  EB Editors
 </signature>
 <copyright>
  Encyclopædia Britannica
 </copyright>
</article>