<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "syndication_xml.dtd">
<article articleid="20288" articletypeid="1" language="en_us" lastupdate="2021-Jun-30 21:01:45" url="/article/cardiac-catheterization/20288" version="8">
 <title>
  cardiac catheterization
 </title>
 <p>
  <e type="bold">
   cardiac catheterization
  </e>
  , medical procedure by which a flexible plastic tube (catheter) is inserted into an
  <xref articleid="1571">
   artery
  </xref>
  or
  <xref articleid="74959">
   vein
  </xref>
  . It is used for injecting drugs for therapy or diagnosis, for measuring blood flow and pressure in the
  <xref articleid="39718">
   heart
  </xref>
  and central blood vessels, in performing procedures such as
  <xref articleid="7564">
   angiography
  </xref>
  (X-ray examination of the arteries and veins) and
  <xref articleid="471748">
   angioplasty
  </xref>
  (a procedure used to dilate obstructed arteries), and as a means of passing electrodes into the heart to study, restore, or regulate the heartbeat. Catheterization is central to the diagnosis, therapy, and surgical management of many forms of
  <xref articleid="106245">
   cardiovascular disease
  </xref>
  .
 </p>
 <p>
  The term
  <e type="italic">
   cardiac catheterization
  </e>
  was coined in 1844 by French physiologist
  <xref articleid="78837">
   Claude Bernard
  </xref>
  , who inserted a glass catheter into the heart of a horse. The procedure was first performed in a human by German physician
  <xref articleid="34917">
   Werner Forssmann
  </xref>
  , who in 1929 opened a vein in his own arm, inserted a urethral catheter about 3.2 mm (0.125 inch) in diameter and 76 cm (2.5 feet) long, and passed it to the right side of his heart while photographing his accomplishment with an X-ray machine. In the United States, physiologists
  <xref articleid="26599">
   André Cournand
  </xref>
  and
  <xref articleid="63557">
   Dickinson Richards
  </xref>
  developed clinical applications of Forssmann’s technique, and in 1956 the three shared a
  <xref articleid="56008">
   Nobel Prize
  </xref>
  for their achievements.
 </p>
 <p>
  Catheter materials and construction are very sophisticated, permitting an enormous range of diagnostic and therapeutic techniques to be applied to almost every organ and blood vessel in the body—but especially to the heart. By the 1940s catheters were being placed safely in the right chambers of the heart through veins, and by the 1950s they were being placed in the left chambers through arteries. As these techniques were developed, it became possible to monitor blood pressure and flow in medical and surgical intensive-care units. Through the ability to place one or more catheters inside the heart chambers, all types of heart abnormalities were opened to study.
 </p>
 <p>
  Today iodine contrast medium can be injected through the catheter into veins or directly into the heart chambers (
  <xref articleid="7564">
   angiography
  </xref>
  ). This makes it possible to diagnose and surgically correct many heart conditions, including congenital heart abnormalities. In addition, visualization with a contrast agent enables the identification and replacement or repair of damaged heart valves and blood vessels and even the complete replacement of the heart through transplantation. The injection of contrast medium is particularly valuable in evaluating coronary artery narrowing and is usually performed to quantify the severity of disease present and to establish whether the person is a candidate for surgical intervention with balloon angioplasty or
  <xref articleid="26379">
   coronary bypass surgery
  </xref>
  . It is also used to evaluate patients with
  <xref articleid="7561">
   angina pectoris
  </xref>
  who do not respond to treatment.
 </p>
 <p>
  Special catheterization techniques now permit a cardiologist to study the function and pathology of arterial walls. One notable technique is intravascular ultrasound, in which a tiny ultrasound transducer mounted on the tip of a cardiac catheter is used to generate images of the interior walls of coronary arteries.
 </p>
 <signature>
  William L. Winters Jr., M.D.
 </signature>
 <copyright>
  Encyclopædia Britannica
 </copyright>
</article>