<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "syndication_xml.dtd">
<article articleid="2133" articletypeid="1" language="en_us" lastupdate="2021-Jun-30 20:00:45" url="/article/Utah-University-of/2133" version="4">
 <title>
  University of Utah
 </title>
 <p>
  <assembly id="a162879" url="/assembly/view/162879">
   <title>
    Utah, University of
   </title>
   <media mediaid="153720" type="image" url="/20/153720-004-89BC7A53.jpg"/>
   <caption>
    J. Willard Marriott Library, University of Utah, Salt Lake City, Utah.
   </caption>
   <credit>
    Klubbit
   </credit>
  </assembly>
  <e type="bold">
   University of Utah
  </e>
  ,
  <assemblyref assemblyid="a162879"/>
  public, coeducational institution of higher education in
  <xref articleid="65132">
   Salt Lake City
  </xref>
  , Utah, U.S. It is a comprehensive university with many research opportunities and academic programs. Through 16 colleges and schools it offers some 75 undergraduate degree programs and more than 90 graduate degree programs, as well as more than 50 teaching majors and minors. Adjacent to the main campus is the university’s Health Sciences Center. The University of Utah houses the state’s Museum of Fine Arts, Museum of Natural History, and Red Butte Garden (arboretum). The campus has a replica of Salt Lake Theater, built in 1862, a significant early theatre in the American West. The university’s libraries contain almost three million books. Notable among the school’s research agencies are the Nora Eccles Harrison Cardiovascular Research and Training Institute, the Combustion Research Group, the Center for Human Genome Research, the Hinckley Institute of Politics, and the Middle East Center. Student enrollment is approximately 26,000.
 </p>
 <p>
  The Provisional State of Deseret, a precursor of the state of Utah, established the University of Deseret in 1850. Classes began the same year, but, because of insufficient funding, instruction was suspended from 1853 to 1867. In 1869 the university was reorganized under the leadership of John R. Park, who added science, education, and classical studies to the curriculum; engineering courses began in 1891. In 1892 the school was renamed the University of Utah and in 1900 relocated to a new campus. The College of Mines and Earth Sciences opened in 1901 and the School of Medicine in 1905. In 1982 the world’s first artificial heart transplant was performed at the university. Hotelier
  <xref articleid="51079">
   J. Willard Marriott
  </xref>
  was an alumnus. Dancer
  <xref articleid="82397">
   Willam Christensen
  </xref>
  and educator
  <xref articleid="77380">
   Evelyn Wood
  </xref>
  taught at the university in the 1950s.
 </p>
 <copyright>
  Encyclopædia Britannica
 </copyright>
</article>