<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "syndication_xml.dtd">
<article articleid="24379" articletypeid="1" language="en_us" lastupdate="2021-Jun-30 21:13:44" url="/article/Clifford-Nathan/24379" version="3">
 <title>
  Nathan Clifford
 </title>
 <p>
  <assembly id="a132798" url="/assembly/view/132798">
   <title>
    Clifford, Nathan
   </title>
   <media mediaid="133621" type="image" url="/21/133621-004-D3E43AA8.jpg"/>
   <caption>
    Nathan Clifford.
   </caption>
   <credit>
    Brady-Handy Photograph Collection/Library of Congress, Washington, D.C. (Digital File Number: LC-DIG-cwpbh-00695)
   </credit>
  </assembly>
  <e type="bold">
   Nathan Clifford
  </e>
  ,
  <assemblyref assemblyid="a132798"/>
  (born Aug. 18, 1803, Rumney, N.H., U.S.—died July 25, 1881, Cornish, Maine), associate justice of the United States Supreme Court (1858–81).
 </p>
 <p>
  Admitted to the bar in 1827, Clifford was elected to the Maine legislature in 1830 and became an eloquent exponent of Jacksonian principles. He served four terms, the last two as speaker. In 1834 he was appointed state attorney general and in 1839 elected to the U.S. Congress. He was named attorney general by Pres. James K. Polk in 1846 and served as his special commissioner to Mexico to arrange the Treaty of Guadalupe Hidalgo, which ended the Mexican War in 1848. After completing his duties in Mexico, he returned to private practice in Maine and twice ran unsuccessfully for the U.S. Senate before being appointed to the U.S. Supreme Court in 1858 by Pres. James Buchanan, who had been his friend on the cabinet.
 </p>
 <p>
  He delivered over 400 opinions in his 23 years on the bench, most of which dealt with areas of his special competence—commercial and maritime law and Mexican land grants—and did not address constitutional issues or capture wide public interest. He presided over the court briefly in 1873 after the death of Chief Justice Salmon P. Chase and presided on the commission appointed to canvass the state returns in the disputed Hayes–Tilden election in 1877. He voted with the conservative majority on most of the constitutional issues arising out of the Civil War.
 </p>
 <copyright>
  Encyclopædia Britannica
 </copyright>
</article>