<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "syndication_xml.dtd">
<article articleid="24661" articletypeid="1" language="en_us" lastupdate="2021-Jun-30 21:15:14" url="/article/cognition/24661" version="5">
 <title>
  cognition
 </title>
 <p>
  <e type="bold">
   cognition
  </e>
  , the states and processes involved in knowing, which in their completeness include
  <xref articleid="110465">
   perception
  </xref>
  and judgment. Cognition includes all conscious and unconscious processes by which knowledge is accumulated, such as perceiving, recognizing, conceiving, and
  <xref articleid="62879">
   reasoning
  </xref>
  . Put differently, cognition is a state or experience of knowing that can be distinguished from an experience of feeling or willing.
 </p>
 <p>
  Questions about the nature of cognition and the relationship between the knowing mind and external reality have been debated by philosophers since antiquity (
  <e type="italic">
   see
  </e>
  <xref articleid="106052">
   epistemology: The history of epistemology
  </xref>
  ). Cognition and its development have been studied from many viewpoints and subjected to many interpretations. The essence of cognition is judgment, which occurs when a certain object is distinguished from other objects and is characterized by some concept or concepts. The psychologist is concerned with cognitive processes as they affect
  <xref articleid="47530">
   learning
  </xref>
  and
  <xref articleid="110429">
   behaviour
  </xref>
  .
 </p>
 <p>
  There are two broad approaches to contemporary cognitive theory. The
  <xref articleid="106312">
   information-processing
  </xref>
  approach attempts to understand human thought and reasoning processes by comparing the
  <xref articleid="52811">
   mind
  </xref>
  (or the
  <xref articleid="16178">
   brain
  </xref>
  ) to a sophisticated
  <xref articleid="117728">
   computer
  </xref>
  system that is designed to acquire, process, store, and use information in specific ways (
  <e type="italic">
   see also
  </e>
  <xref articleid="108733" refid="h283980">
   philosophy of mind: The computational-representational theory of thought [CRTT]
  </xref>
  ). The American psychologist Robert Sternberg, for example, examined the information-processing procedures used by people taking
  <xref articleid="42528">
   intelligence tests
  </xref>
  .
  <xref articleid="67856">
   Herbert A. Simon
  </xref>
  , another American social scientist, attempted to understand how the mind processes information, programming computers to mimic human thought processes. Researchers in this area strive to develop a unified theory of cognition by creating computer programs that can learn, solve problems, and remember as humans do.
 </p>
 <p>
  The second approach is based on the work of Swiss psychologist
  <xref articleid="59885">
   Jean Piaget
  </xref>
  , who viewed cognitive adaptation in terms of two basic processes: assimilation and accommodation. Assimilation is the process of interpreting reality in terms of a person’s internal model of the world (based on previous experience); accommodation represents the changes one makes to that model through the process of adjusting to experience. The American psychologist
  <xref articleid="16778">
   Jerome S. Bruner
  </xref>
  broadened Piaget’s concept by suggesting that cognitive processes are influenced by the three modes that are used to represent the world: the enactive mode involves representation through action; the iconic mode uses visual and mental images; and the symbolic mode uses
  <xref articleid="108460">
   language
  </xref>
  .
  <e type="italic">
   See also
  </e>
  <xref articleid="472062">
   cognitive science
  </xref>
  .
 </p>
 <copyright>
  Encyclopædia Britannica
 </copyright>
</article>