<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "syndication_xml.dtd">
<article articleid="24992" articletypeid="1" language="en_us" lastupdate="2021-Jun-30 21:16:55" url="/article/community/24992" version="7">
 <title>
  community
 </title>
 <p>
  <e type="bold">
   community
  </e>
  , also called
  <e type="bold">
   biological community
  </e>
  , in
  <xref articleid="110576">
   biology
  </xref>
  , an interacting group of various
  <xref articleid="69027">
   species
  </xref>
  in a common location. For example, a
  <xref articleid="34863">
   forest
  </xref>
  of
  <xref articleid="108708">
   trees
  </xref>
  and undergrowth
  <xref articleid="108554">
   plants
  </xref>
  , inhabited by
  <xref articleid="110237">
   animals
  </xref>
  and rooted in
  <xref articleid="109555">
   soil
  </xref>
  containing
  <xref articleid="110416">
   bacteria
  </xref>
  and
  <xref articleid="110641">
   fungi
  </xref>
  , constitutes a biological community.
 </p>
 <p>
  A brief treatment of biological communities follows. For full treatment,
  <e type="italic">
   see
  </e>
  <xref articleid="117266">
   Biosphere
  </xref>
  .
 </p>
 <p>
  Among the factors that determine the overall structure of a community are the number of species (
  <xref articleid="395985">
   diversity
  </xref>
  ) within it, the number of each species (abundance) found within it, the interactions among the species, and the ability of the community to return to normal after a disruptive influence such as
  <xref articleid="76989">
   fire
  </xref>
  or
  <xref articleid="31239">
   drought
  </xref>
  . The change of biological communities over time is known as succession, or
  <xref articleid="475409">
   ecological succession
  </xref>
  .
 </p>
 <p>
  <assembly id="a246695" url="/assembly/view/246695">
   <title>
    food web
   </title>
   <media mediaid="167661" type="image" url="/61/167661-004-8E3640FC.jpg"/>
   <caption>
    A food chain shows how matter and energy from food are transferred from one organism to another. In a natural ecosystem many food chains intertwine to form a complex food web.
   </caption>
   <credit>
    Encyclopædia Britannica, Inc./Patrick O'Neill Riley
   </credit>
  </assembly>
  <assemblyref assemblyid="a246695"/>
  The various species in a community each occupy their own ecological niche. The niche of a species includes all of its interactions with other members of the community, including
  <xref articleid="25017">
   competition
  </xref>
  ,
  <xref articleid="61238">
   predation
  </xref>
  ,
  <xref articleid="58426">
   parasitism
  </xref>
  , and
  <xref articleid="54505">
   mutualism
  </xref>
  . The organisms within a community can be positioned along food chains by showing which eats which, and these positions are known as trophic levels. The first level includes the producers—the
  <xref articleid="108553">
   photosynthetic
  </xref>
  plants—which convert the
  <xref articleid="110144">
   Sun’s
  </xref>
  radiant
  <xref articleid="32627">
   energy
  </xref>
  into
  <xref articleid="56550">
   nutrients
  </xref>
  available to other organisms in the community. These plants are eaten by
  <xref articleid="40114">
   herbivores
  </xref>
  (plant-eaters, or primary consumers), the second trophic level. Herbivores are, in turn, eaten by
  <xref articleid="105116">
   carnivores
  </xref>
  (flesh-eaters), which are frequently eaten by larger carnivores (secondary and tertiary consumers, respectively). The food chain ends when the last link dies and is attacked by various bacteria and fungi, the decomposers that break down dead organic matter and thereby release essential nutrients back into the environment.
 </p>
 <p>
  An
  <xref articleid="31944">
   ecosystem
  </xref>
  consists of the biological community of an area together with its physical environment.
 </p>
 <signature>
  EB Editors
 </signature>
 <copyright>
  Encyclopædia Britannica
 </copyright>
</article>