<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "syndication_xml.dtd">
<article articleid="25118" articletypeid="1" language="en_us" lastupdate="2021-Jun-30 21:17:39" url="/article/condensation/25118" version="4">
 <title>
  condensation
 </title>
 <p>
  <assembly id="a146446" url="/assembly/view/146446">
   <title>
    dew on blades of grass
   </title>
   <media mediaid="143276" type="image" url="/76/143276-004-3A401EB0.jpg"/>
   <caption>
    Dew on blades of grass.
   </caption>
   <credit>
    © StanOd/Shutterstock.com
   </credit>
  </assembly>
  <e type="bold">
   condensation
  </e>
  ,
  <assemblyref assemblyid="a146446"/>
  deposition of a
  <xref articleid="110301">
   liquid
  </xref>
  or a
  <xref articleid="68592">
   solid
  </xref>
  from its vapour, generally upon a surface that is cooler than the adjacent
  <xref articleid="110302">
   gas
  </xref>
  . A substance condenses when the
  <xref articleid="61303">
   pressure
  </xref>
  exerted by its vapour exceeds the vapour pressure of the liquid or solid phase of the substance at the
  <xref articleid="71632">
   temperature
  </xref>
  of the surface where condensation occurs.
  <xref articleid="39732">
   Heat
  </xref>
  is released when a vapour condenses. Unless this heat is removed, the surface temperature will increase until it is equal to that of the surrounding vapour.
 </p>
 <p>
  If air were free of tiny particles, called
  <xref articleid="3876">
   aerosols
  </xref>
  , condensation would only occur when the air was extremely
  <xref articleid="65865">
   supersaturated
  </xref>
  with
  <xref articleid="76210">
   water
  </xref>
  vapour. In the
  <xref articleid="126202">
   atmosphere
  </xref>
  , however, there is an abundant supply of aerosols, which serve as nuclei, called
  <xref articleid="25119">
   condensation nuclei
  </xref>
  , on which water vapour may condense. Some are hygroscopic (moisture-attracting), and condensation begins on them when the
  <xref articleid="63125">
   relative humidity
  </xref>
  is less than 100 percent, but other nuclei require some supersaturation before condensation begins.
 </p>
 <p>
  In the atmosphere the relative humidity of the air is increased, and condensation results when air temperature is reduced to the dew point or when sufficient water vapour is added to saturate the air. Condensation accounts for the formation of dew,
  <xref articleid="34725">
   fog
  </xref>
  , and
  <xref articleid="24441">
   clouds
  </xref>
  . For
  <xref articleid="62486">
   rain
  </xref>
  to occur, other physical processes are required.
 </p>
 <copyright>
  Encyclopædia Britannica
 </copyright>
</article>