<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "syndication_xml.dtd">
<article articleid="2526" articletypeid="1" language="en_us" lastupdate="2021-Jun-30 20:03:01" url="/article/environmental-engineering/2526" version="4">
 <title>
  environmental engineering
 </title>
 <p>
  <e type="bold">
   environmental engineering
  </e>
  , the development of processes and infrastructure for the
  <xref articleid="76241">
   supply of water
  </xref>
  , the disposal of waste, and the control of
  <xref articleid="109632">
   pollution
  </xref>
  of all kinds. These endeavours protect
  <xref articleid="110317">
   public health
  </xref>
  by preventing disease transmission, and they preserve the quality of the environment by averting the contamination and degradation of air, water, and land resources.
 </p>
 <p>
  Environmental engineering is a field of broad scope that draws on such disciplines as
  <xref articleid="108655">
   chemistry
  </xref>
  ,
  <xref articleid="110583">
   ecology
  </xref>
  ,
  <xref articleid="106192">
   geology
  </xref>
  ,
  <xref articleid="41715">
   hydraulics
  </xref>
  ,
  <xref articleid="41740">
   hydrology
  </xref>
  ,
  <xref articleid="110586">
   microbiology
  </xref>
  ,
  <xref articleid="109547">
   economics
  </xref>
  , and
  <xref articleid="109827">
   mathematics
  </xref>
  . It was traditionally a specialized field within
  <xref articleid="105844">
   civil engineering
  </xref>
  and was called sanitary engineering until the mid-1960s, when the more accurate name
  <e type="italic">
   environmental engineering
  </e>
  was adopted.
 </p>
 <p>
  Projects in environmental engineering involve the treatment and distribution of drinking water (
  <e type="italic">
   see
  </e>
  <xref articleid="76242">
   water supply system
  </xref>
  ); the collection, treatment, and disposal of wastewater (
  <e type="italic">
   see
  </e>
  <xref articleid="471031">
   wastewater treatment
  </xref>
  ); the
  <xref articleid="471033">
   control of air pollution
  </xref>
  and noise pollution; municipal
  <xref articleid="471032">
   solid-waste management
  </xref>
  and
  <xref articleid="471030">
   hazardous-waste management
  </xref>
  ; the cleanup of hazardous-waste sites; and the preparation of environmental assessments, audits, and impact studies. Mathematical modeling and computer analysis are widely used to evaluate and design the systems required for such tasks. Chemical and mechanical engineers may also be involved in the process. Environmental engineering functions include applied research and teaching; project planning and management; the design, construction, and operation of facilities; the sale and marketing of environmental-control equipment; and the enforcement of environmental standards and regulations.
 </p>
 <p>
  The education of environmental engineers usually involves graduate-level course work, though some colleges and universities allow undergraduates to specialize or take elective courses in the environmental field. Programs offering associate (two-year) degrees are available for training environmental technicians. In the public sector, environmental engineers are employed by national and regional environmental agencies, local health departments, and municipal engineering and public works departments. In the private sector, they are employed by consulting engineering firms, construction contractors, water and sewerage utility companies, and manufacturing industries.
 </p>
 <signature>
  Jerry A. Nathanson
 </signature>
 <h1 id="h286099">
  <title>
   Bibliography
  </title>
  <p>
   <e type="smallcap">
    Jerry A. Nathanson
   </e>
   ,
   <e type="italic">
    Basic Environmental Technology: Water Supply, Waste Management, and Pollution Control
   </e>
   , 5th ed. (2008); and
   <e type="smallcap">
    J. Jeffrey Peirce
   </e>
   ,
   <e type="smallcap">
    P. Arne Vesilind
   </e>
   , and
   <e type="smallcap">
    Ruth Weiner
   </e>
   ,
   <e type="italic">
    Environmental Pollution and Control
   </e>
   , 4th ed. (1997), cover a variety of topics on environmental engineering and pollution control for a nontechnical audience.
   <e type="smallcap">
    William P. Cunningham
   </e>
   ,
   <e type="smallcap">
    Mary Ann Cunningham
   </e>
   , and
   <e type="smallcap">
    Barbara Woodworth Saigo
   </e>
   ,
   <e type="italic">
    Environmental Science: A Global Concern
   </e>
   , 9th ed. (2007), provides broad coverage of fundamental topics in environmental science, with a focus on biological aspects.
  </p>
 </h1>
 <copyright>
  Encyclopædia Britannica
 </copyright>
</article>