<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "syndication_xml.dtd">
<article articleid="26161" articletypeid="1" language="en_us" lastupdate="2021-Jun-30 21:19:55" url="/article/cooperative/26161" version="4">
 <title>
  cooperative
 </title>
 <p>
  <e type="bold">
   cooperative
  </e>
  , organization owned by and operated for the benefit of those using its services. Cooperatives have been successful in a number of fields, including the processing and marketing of farm products, the purchasing of other kinds of equipment and raw materials, and in the wholesaling, retailing, electric power, credit and banking, and housing industries. The income from a retail cooperative is usually returned to the consumers in the form of dividends based on the amounts purchased over a given period of time.
 </p>
 <p>
  Modern consumer cooperatives, usually called co-ops in the United States, are thought to have begun in Great Britain in 1844, with the Rochdale Equitable Pioneers Society The society created a set of organizational and working rules that have been widely adopted. They included open membership, democratic control, no religious or political discrimination, sales at prevailing market prices, and the setting aside of some earnings for education.
 </p>
 <p>
  The cooperative movement developed rapidly in the latter part of the 19th century, particularly in the industrial and mining areas of northern England and Scotland. It spread quickly among the urban working class in Britain, France, Germany, and Sweden and among the rural population of Norway, the Netherlands, Denmark, and Finland.
 </p>
 <p>
  In the United States, attempts at consumer and agricultural marketing cooperatives were made at the beginning of the 19th century. Although most U.S. cooperatives developed in rural areas, consumer and housing cooperatives spread substantially in metropolitan areas in the late 20th century.
 </p>
 <p>
  Cooperatives were introduced in Latin America by European immigrants in the early 1900s; later they were often fostered by state action in connection with agrarian reform. Marketing and credit cooperatives have been important in many African nations, especially since World War II. During the Soviet era, marketing cooperatives of the U.S.S.R. and eastern Europe functioned as part of a centrally controlled purchasing network for farm produce. Cooperative farms in those countries were modeled on the Russian artel, in which all land was pooled and worked in common and income was distributed according to work performed.
  <e type="italic">
   Compare
  </e>
  <xref articleid="26820">
   credit union
  </xref>
  .
 </p>
 <copyright>
  Encyclopædia Britannica
 </copyright>
</article>