<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "syndication_xml.dtd">
<article articleid="2749" articletypeid="1" language="en_us" lastupdate="2021-Jun-30 20:04:16" url="/article/dimension/2749" version="7">
 <title>
  dimension
 </title>
 <p>
  <e type="bold">
   dimension
  </e>
  , in common parlance, the measure of the size of an object, such as a box, usually given as length, width, and height. In mathematics, the notion of dimension is an extension of the idea that a line is one-dimensional, a plane is two-dimensional, and space is three-dimensional. In mathematics and physics one also considers higher-dimensional spaces, such as four-dimensional space-time, where four numbers are needed to characterize a point: three to fix a point in space and one to fix the time. Infinite-dimensional spaces, first studied early in the 20th century, have played an increasingly important role both in mathematics and in parts of physics such as
  <xref articleid="62164">
   quantum field theory
  </xref>
  , where they represent the space of possible states of a
  <xref articleid="110312">
   quantum mechanical
  </xref>
  system.
 </p>
 <p>
  In
  <xref articleid="111075">
   differential geometry
  </xref>
  one considers curves as one-dimensional, since a single number, or parameter, determines a point on a curve—for example, the distance, plus or minus, from a fixed point on the curve. A surface, such as the surface of the Earth, has two dimensions, since each point can be located by a pair of numbers—usually latitude and longitude. Higher-dimensional curved spaces were introduced by the German mathematician
  <xref articleid="63646">
   Bernhard Riemann
  </xref>
  in 1854 and have become both a major subject of study within mathematics and a basic component of modern physics, from
  <xref articleid="106018">
   Albert Einstein
  </xref>
  ’s theory of general relativity and the subsequent development of cosmological models of the universe to late-20th-century
  <xref articleid="70406">
   superstring theory
  </xref>
  .
 </p>
 <p>
  In 1918 the German mathematician Felix Hausdorff introduced the notion of fractional dimension. This concept has proved extremely fruitful, especially in the hands of the Polish-French mathematician Benoit Mandelbrot, who coined the word
  <e type="italic">
   <xref articleid="35083">
    fractal
   </xref>
  </e>
  and showed how fractional dimensions could be useful in many parts of applied mathematics.
 </p>
 <signature>
  Robert Osserman
 </signature>
 <copyright>
  Encyclopædia Britannica
 </copyright>
</article>