<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "syndication_xml.dtd">
<article articleid="28045" articletypeid="1" language="en_us" lastupdate="2021-Oct-15 10:01:03" url="/article/crucifixion/28045" version="10">
 <title>
  crucifixion
 </title>
 <p>
  <e type="bold">
   crucifixion
  </e>
  , an important method of
  <xref articleid="20149">
   capital punishment
  </xref>
  particularly among the
  <xref articleid="476041">
   Persians
  </xref>
  ,
  <xref articleid="66667">
   Seleucids
  </xref>
  ,
  <xref articleid="20548">
   Carthaginians
  </xref>
  , and
  <xref articleid="471348">
   Romans
  </xref>
  from about the 6th century
  <e type="smallcap">
   bce
  </e>
  to the 4th century
  <e type="smallcap">
   ce
  </e>
  .
  <xref articleid="109633">
   Constantine the Great
  </xref>
  , the first Christian emperor, abolished it in the Roman Empire in the early 4th century
  <e type="smallcap">
   ce
  </e>
  out of veneration for
  <xref articleid="106456">
   Jesus Christ
  </xref>
  , the most famous victim of crucifixion.
 </p>
 <h1 id="h1639">
  <title>
   Punishment
  </title>
  <p>
   There were various methods of performing the execution. Usually, the condemned man, after being whipped, or “scourged,” dragged the crossbeam of his cross to the place of punishment, where the upright shaft was already fixed in the ground. Stripped of his clothing either then or earlier at his scourging, he was bound fast with outstretched arms to the crossbeam or nailed firmly to it through the wrists. The crossbeam was then raised high against the upright shaft and made fast to it about 9 to 12 feet (approximately 3 metres) from the ground. Next, the feet were tightly bound or nailed to the upright shaft. A ledge inserted about halfway up the upright shaft gave some support to the body; evidence for a similar ledge for the feet is rare and late. Over the criminal’s head was placed a notice stating his name and his crime. Death ultimately occurred through a combination of constrained blood circulation, organ failure, and
   <xref articleid="9903">
    asphyxiation
   </xref>
   as the body strained under its own weight. It could be hastened by shattering the legs (
   <e type="italic">
    crurifragium
   </e>
   ) with an iron club, which prevented them from supporting the body’s weight and made inhalation more difficult, accelerating both asphyxiation and
   <xref articleid="67460">
    shock
   </xref>
   .
  </p>
  <p>
   Crucifixion was most frequently used to punish political or religious agitators, pirates, slaves, or those who had no
   <xref articleid="600864">
    civil rights
   </xref>
   . In 519
   <e type="smallcap">
    bce
   </e>
   <xref articleid="28778">
    Darius I
   </xref>
   , king of
   <xref articleid="59338">
    Persia
   </xref>
   , crucified 3,000 political opponents in
   <xref articleid="11618">
    Babylon
   </xref>
   ; in 88
   <e type="smallcap">
    bce
   </e>
   Alexander Jannaeus, the Judaean king and high priest, crucified 800 Pharisaic opponents; and about 32
   <e type="smallcap">
    ce
   </e>
   <xref articleid="60010">
    Pontius Pilate
   </xref>
   had Jesus of Nazareth put to death by crucifixion.
  </p>
 </h1>
 <h1 id="h1640">
  <title>
   Crucifixion of Jesus
  </title>
  <p>
   The account of
   <xref articleid="106456">
    Jesus Christ
   </xref>
   ’s crucifixion in the
   <xref articleid="37470">
    Gospels
   </xref>
   begins with his scourging. The Roman soldiers then mocked him as the “King of the Jews” by clothing him in a purple robe and a crown of thorns and led him slowly to Mount Calvary, or
   <xref articleid="37292">
    Golgotha
   </xref>
   ; one Simon of Cyrene was allowed to aid him in carrying the cross. At the place of execution he was stripped and then nailed to the cross, at least nailed by his hands, and above him at the top of the cross was placed the condemnatory inscription stating his crime of professing to be King of the Jews. (The Gospels differ slightly in the wording but agree that the inscription was in “Hebrew,” or
   <xref articleid="9190">
    Aramaic
   </xref>
   , as well as
   <xref articleid="47290">
    Latin
   </xref>
   and
   <xref articleid="109772">
    Greek
   </xref>
   .) On the cross Jesus hung in agony. The soldiers divided his garments and cast lots for his seamless robe. Various onlookers taunted him. Crucified on either side of Jesus were two convicted thieves, whom the soldiers dispatched at eventide by breaking their legs. The soldiers found Jesus already dead, but, to be certain, one of them drove a spear into his side, from which poured blood and water. He was taken down before sunset (in deference to Jewish custom) and buried in a rock-hewn tomb.
  </p>
 </h1>
 <h1 id="h1641">
  <title>
   Crucifixion in art
  </title>
  <p>
   The representation of Christ on the cross has been an important subject of Western art since the early
   <xref articleid="52537">
    Middle Ages
   </xref>
   . Concerned primarily with simple symbolic affirmations of salvation and eternal life, and repelled by the ignominy of the punishment, the early Christians did not represent the Crucifixion realistically before the 5th century; instead, the event was symbolized first by a lamb and, after the official recognition of
   <xref articleid="105945">
    Christianity
   </xref>
   by the Roman state in the early 4th century, by a jewelled cross. By the 6th century, however, representations of the Crucifixion became numerous as a result of current church efforts to combat a
   <xref articleid="40137">
    heresy
   </xref>
   that Christ’s nature was not dual—human and divine—but simply divine and therefore invulnerable. These early Crucifixions were nevertheless triumphant images, showing Christ alive, with open eyes and no trace of suffering, victorious over death. In the 9th century,
   <xref articleid="18408">
    Byzantine art
   </xref>
   began to show a dead Christ, with closed eyes, reflecting current concern with the mystery of his death and the nature of the
   <xref articleid="42239">
    Incarnation
   </xref>
   . This version was adopted in the West in the 13th century with an ever-increasing emphasis on his suffering, in accordance with the
   <xref articleid="109481">
    mysticism
   </xref>
   of the period.
  </p>
  <p>
   <assembly id="a121204" url="/assembly/view/121204">
    <title>
     Giunta Pisano: Crucifixion
    </title>
    <media mediaid="126683" type="image" url="/83/126683-004-348AC50D.jpg"/>
    <caption>
     Crucifixion, painting by Giunta Pisano, c. 1250; in the Basilica of San Domenico, Bologna, Italy.
    </caption>
    <credit>
     Georges Jansoone
    </credit>
   </assembly>
   <assemblyref assemblyid="a121204"/>
   Parallel to this development in the representation of Christ himself was the growth of an increasingly complex
   <xref articleid="41997">
    iconography
   </xref>
   involving other elements traditionally included in the scene. The principal mourners, the
   <xref articleid="51208">
    Virgin Mary
   </xref>
   and
   <xref articleid="43818">
    St. John the Apostle
   </xref>
   , are frequently the only other figures included in the composition. In various expanded versions of the theme, however, there are several other pairs of figures, both historical and symbolic, that traditionally appear to the right and left of the cross: the two thieves, one repentant, who were crucified with Christ; the
   <xref articleid="22105">
    centurion
   </xref>
   who pierced Christ’s side with a lance (and afterward acknowledged him to be the Son of God) and the soldier who offered him vinegar on a sponge; small personifications of the Sun and Moon, which were eclipsed at the Crucifixion; and allegorical figures of the church and the synagogue. Other figures might include the soldiers who cast lots for Christ’s garments and
   <xref articleid="51215">
    St. Mary Magdalene
   </xref>
   .
  </p>
  <p>
   <assembly id="a235004" url="/assembly/view/235004">
    <title>
     Fra Angelico:
     <e type="italic">
      The Crucifixion
     </e>
    </title>
    <media mediaid="198623" type="image" url="/23/198623-004-900566DC.jpg"/>
    <caption>
     <e type="italic">
      The Crucifixion
     </e>
     , tempera painting by Fra Angelico, possibly
     <e type="italic">
      c.
     </e>
     1440; in the Metropolitan Museum of Art, New York City.
    </caption>
    <credit>
     The Metropolitan Museum of Art, New York, Bequest of Benjamin Altman, 1913 (14.40.628), www. metmuseum.org
    </credit>
   </assembly>
   <assembly id="a205652" url="/assembly/view/205652">
    <title>
     Cossa, Francesco del:
     <e type="italic">
      The Crucifixion
     </e>
    </title>
    <media mediaid="186902" type="image" url="/02/186902-004-0919F6CB.jpg"/>
    <caption>
     <e type="italic">
      The Crucifixion
     </e>
     , tempera on panel by Francesco del Cossa, 1473/74; in the collection of the National Gallery of Art, Washington, D.C.
    </caption>
    <credit>
     Courtesy National Gallery of Art, Washington, D.C. (Samuel H. Kress Collection;1952.5.5)
    </credit>
   </assembly>
   <assembly id="a5083" url="/assembly/view/5083">
    <title>
     Andrea Mantegna:
     <e type="italic">
      The Crucifixion
     </e>
    </title>
    <media mediaid="12559" type="image" url="/59/12559-004-20DFD91C.jpg"/>
    <caption>
     <e type="italic">
      The Crucifixion
     </e>
     , painting by Andrea Mantegna, 1456–59; in the Louvre, Paris.
    </caption>
    <credit>
     Giraudon—Art Resource/Encyclopædia Britannica, Inc.
    </credit>
   </assembly>
   <assemblyref assemblyid="a235004"/>
   <assemblyref assemblyid="a205652"/>
   <assemblyref assemblyid="a5083"/>
   With the growth of devotional art at the end of the Middle Ages, depictions of the Crucifixion became vehicles for the portrayal of Christ’s sufferings; calculated to inspire piety in the viewer, this spectacle became the main concern of artists, who often depicted the scene with gruesome realism and sometimes included the horror of a mass of jeering spectators. Some of the Crucifixions from this period include the figure of
   <xref articleid="43819">
    St. John the Baptist
   </xref>
   , pointing to Christ and his sacrifice as he had earlier heralded his coming.
   <xref articleid="102627">
    Renaissance art
   </xref>
   restored a calm idealization to the scene, however, which was preserved, with a more overt expression of emotion, in the
   <xref articleid="13445">
    Baroque period
   </xref>
   . Like most of Christian religious art, the theme of the Crucifixion suffered a decline after the 17th century; some 20th-century artists, however, created highly individual interpretations of the subject.
  </p>
  <signature>
   EB Editors
  </signature>
 </h1>
 <copyright>
  Encyclopædia Britannica
 </copyright>
</article>