<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "syndication_xml.dtd">
<article articleid="28375" articletypeid="1" language="en_us" lastupdate="2022-Jul-28 08:10:04" url="/article/cycling/28375" version="11">
 <title>
  cycling
 </title>
 <p>
  <assembly id="a7522" url="/assembly/view/7522">
   <title>
    Miguel Indurain
   </title>
   <media mediaid="4367" type="image" url="/67/4367-004-520E4E64.jpg"/>
   <caption>
    Miguel Indurain (Spain) riding in the penultimate stage of the 1993 Tour de France; Indurain won the race for the third successive year.
   </caption>
   <credit>
    AP
   </credit>
  </assembly>
  <e type="bold">
   cycling
  </e>
  ,
  <assemblyref assemblyid="a7522"/>
  use of a
  <xref articleid="79113">
   bicycle
  </xref>
  for sport, recreation, or transportation. The sport of cycling consists of professional and amateur races, which are held mostly in continental Europe, the United States, and Asia. The recreational use of the bicycle is widespread in Europe and the United States. Use of the bicycle as a mode of transportation is particularly important in non-Western nations and in flatter countries, some of which, like the Netherlands, have a widespread system of bicycle paths.
 </p>
 <h1 id="h1668">
  <title>
   Early history of the sport
  </title>
  <p>
   Cycling as a sport officially began on May 31, 1868, with a 1,200-metre (1,312-yard) race between the fountains and the entrance of Saint-Cloud Park (near Paris). The winner was James Moore, an 18-year-old expatriate Englishman from Paris. On November 7, 1869, the first city-to-city race was held between Paris and Rouen; again Moore was the winner, having covered the 135 km (84 miles) in 10 hours 25 minutes, including time spent walking his bicycle up the steeper hills. While road racing became common within a few years in continental Europe, in England the deteriorated conditions of the roads made them unsuitable, and therefore the sport there focused on the track or time trials.
  </p>
  <p>
   In the United States the first recorded race was held on May 24, 1878, in Boston, two years after the start of professional baseball and 13 years before basketball was invented. Almost all of the early American racing was on tracks, in long races sometimes employing pacers who rode ahead of contestants at a fast speed and then dropped away. By the 1890s there were about 100 dirt, cement, or wooden tracks around the country, mainly in big cities. More than 600 professionals traveled on this national circuit, which ranged from Boston to San Francisco, with competitions in such cities as St. Louis, Salt Lake City, Denver, and Los Angeles. The sport received an enormous publicity boost on June 30, 1899, when one of these riders, Charles M. Murphy, rode on a wooden track behind a Long Island Rail Road train and covered a mile in 57.8 seconds, earning the nickname of Mile-a-Minute Murphy.
  </p>
  <p>
   A particularly grueling form of racing flourished in the United States in the 1890s: the
   <xref articleid="68042">
    six-day race
   </xref>
   , 142 hours (since the races usually started at midnight and ended, six days later, at 10
   <e type="smallcap">
    pm
   </e>
   ) of nonstop competition with prizes up to $10,000 and an international field of riders. This form of racing was transformed with the change from one-man teams to two-man teams in 1899, and six-day races retained their popularity well into the 1930s. While no longer held in the United States, these races continue to attract large crowds in Belgium, Italy, France, and Germany.
  </p>
 </h1>
 <h1 id="h1669">
  <title>
   Modern sport racing
  </title>
  <p>
   The development of racing as a popular sport in Europe began in the 1890s with the improvement in road conditions and the introduction of some of the one-day classics that continue to this day (for example, the Paris-Roubaix race). After France and Belgium, races were introduced in Italy, Spain, and the Netherlands. In 1903 the 21-day-long
   <xref articleid="73053">
    Tour de France
   </xref>
   was inaugurated and has continued every year since except during World Wars I and II. Ranking just behind this premier race are the grand three-week tours of Italy (the Giro d’Italia) and Spain (the Vuelta a España). Usually, the Giro is held in May and June, the Tour de France in July, the Vuelta in September, and the World Championships in October. Prizes in these races are substantial, amounting to $2.5 million in the Tour de France alone.
  </p>
  <p>
   European road racing was under the sponsorship of bicycle manufacturers until the late 1920s, when national and regional teams were introduced. Trade sponsors returned after World War II but with the waning of bicycle manufacturers, teams began turning to various sponsors, including automobile manufacturers, insurance companies, and banks. The professional road-racing season now begins in January with races in Australia and Malaysia, continues from February through October in Europe and the United States, and closes, again in Asia, in November and December. For most riders, the season includes about 120 days of competition spread over eight months.
  </p>
  <p>
   With the waning of six-day races during the Depression in the United States, American interest in cycling began to fade until the 1980s. American riders dominated the Olympic Games in Los Angeles in 1984, and in 1986 Greg LeMond won the first of his three Tours de France, rekindling American interest. In England, racing declined in popularity after the turn of the 20th century, with the advent of the automobile; despite the occasional Briton who makes a career as a professional on the Continent and a sporadic series of races, such as the Milk Race and the Prutour, both now defunct, the sport remains marginal. Hindering the growth of the sport in England is the public clamour that arises whenever a road is closed for a bicycle race. In Asia and Australia, however, there is no such resistance, and the roads are usually lined with spectators for such races as the Tour Down Under in Australia, the Tour of Langkawi in Malaysia, and the Japan Cup. These races attract many professional teams from Europe and the United States. Many other Asian countries have races also, mainly for amateur teams from the region.
  </p>
  <p>
   Road and track races for men were held at the first modern
   <xref articleid="108519">
    Olympic Games
   </xref>
   in 1896; women entered Olympic competition in road races in 1984 and track races in 1988. Mountain biking, a cross-country race over rough terrain, became an Olympic event for men and women at the 1996 Games in Atlanta. The Atlanta Games also marked the first Olympics at which professionals were allowed to enter the road race and time trial competitions.
  </p>
 </h1>
 <h1 id="h1670">
  <title>
   Competition
  </title>
  <p>
   <assembly id="a7521" url="/assembly/view/7521">
    <title>
     Nakano Koichi racing at the 1986 World Track Championships
    </title>
    <media mediaid="4366" type="image" url="/66/4366-004-66042535.jpg"/>
    <caption>
     Nakano Koichi (Japan) racing to his 10th straight professional sprint cycling title at the 1986 World Track Championships.
    </caption>
    <credit>
     ALLSPORT USA/Mike Powell
    </credit>
   </assembly>
   <assemblyref assemblyid="a7521"/>
   The sport is governed overall by the Union Cycliste Internationale (UCI), which is based in Switzerland, and by each country’s cycling federation. Amateur races are held for both men and women in local, regional, and national competition by age group, ranging upward in age from competitors 12 to 13 years old. In the World Championships, amateurs are no longer differentiated from professionals among men, but the sport is divided into those under 23, called
   <e type="italic">
    espoirs
   </e>
   (hopefuls), and those over that age. Categories of competition during the season include
   <xref articleid="72517">
    time trials
   </xref>
   , which can be an individual or team event; one-day, or classic, races in which distances can vary between 200 and 280 km (124 to 175 miles) for professionals and 140 to 200 km (87 to 124 miles) for amateurs; and multiday, or stage, races, basically a series of classic races run on successive days. The winner of a stage race is the rider with lowest aggregate time for all stages. Also popular, especially in Britain and the United States, are criterium races, which are run over a relatively short distance of 4 to 5 km (2.5 to 3 miles) for a succession of laps totaling up to 100 km (62 miles).
  </p>
  <p>
   Track racing events include the
   <xref articleid="69266">
    sprint
   </xref>
   , the
   <xref articleid="61962">
    pursuit
   </xref>
   , the one-kilometre time trial, the points race, and the keirin, or
   <xref articleid="53975">
    motor-paced race
   </xref>
   . Keirin is especially popular in Japan because betting on the outcome is legal there, much like a horse or dog race. Some European track stars ride on the keirin circuit in Japan, both for the experience and for the salary.
   <xref articleid="28376">
    Cyclo-cross
   </xref>
   , or cross-country racing, established in the mid-1920s, covers rough terrain that may require racers to dismount and walk or run with their bicycles. Mountain biking, over rough terrain, but usually downhill rather than on the flat, is increasingly popular. One difference between cyclo-cross and mountain-bike racing is that cyclo-cross riders are allowed to ride up to three bicycles during a race, whereas in mountain-bike competition the cyclist must carry all the tools necessary to fix the bicycle, as only one bicycle may be used during a race. One other recent form of racing is bicycle motocross (BMX) racing, which can be traced to
   <xref articleid="53971">
    motocross
   </xref>
   racing. Racers (children and adults) ride on dirt tracks which feature a large number of jumps and turns. BMX racing is very popular in the United States, Europe, and Australia. In 2008 BMX racing made its Olympic debut at the Beijing Games in the form of a men’s individual race and a women’s individual race.
  </p>
 </h1>
 <h1 id="h1671">
  <title>
   Doping
  </title>
  <p>
   The use of performance-enhancing drugs is considered to be widespread in cycling, especially after the scandal that shook the Tour de France in 1998 and resulted in the expulsion of one of the leading teams (the Festina team). To circumvent the medications prohibited by the UCI, many professional teams and individual riders employ doctors to administer drugs that are difficult to detect, such as erythropoietin (EPO), a hormone that acts to increase the level of red blood cells and thus the flow of oxygen to muscles. The UCI periodically checks riders for the level of red cells in their blood, with a limit of 50 percent (55 percent for riders from high-altitude regions); anything above that is regarded as an indication of the use of EPO and carries a two-year suspension. Stimulants and antifatigue drugs such as amphetamines are detectable and therefore outmoded performance-enhancing drugs.
  </p>
 </h1>
 <h1 id="h214782">
  <title>
   Recreation
  </title>
  <p>
   Cycling as recreation became organized shortly after racing did. In its early days, cycling brought the sexes together in an unchaperoned way, particularly after the 1880s when cycling became more accessible owing to the invention of the
   <xref articleid="79113" refid="h230025">
    Rover Safety bicycle
   </xref>
   . Public cries of alarm at the prospect of moral chaos arose from this and from the evolution of women’s cycling attire, which grew progressively less enveloping and restrictive.
  </p>
  <p>
   In modern times, recreational cycling has been a cornerstone in fitness campaigns, especially in the United States, where more than 65 million people are believed to ride regularly, including more than 6 million who use bicycles to commute. Bicycle and touring clubs abound in Europe, especially in France, Belgium, Italy, and England. Touring by bicycle (cyclotourism) is also on the increase worldwide. Bicycle paths have been created on the streets of many cities and in national as well as municipal parks, and in the United States more than 10,000 miles (16,000 km) of abandoned railroad corridors have been turned into bicycle paths.
  </p>
 </h1>
 <h1 id="h214783">
  <title>
   Transportation
  </title>
  <p>
   Since its invention, the bicycle has always been an inexpensive and democratic form of transportation. The advent of the automobile slowed the growth of cycling as a means of conveyance in some Western societies, whereas in China and Southeast Asia the bicycle has remained a very popular form of transportation. In Africa and several central European nations many people travel by bicycle. In the 1990s citizens and city planners in industrialized nations began to question the role of the automobile in urban life; some observers blamed the problem of suburban sprawl in countries such as the United States directly on the rise of automobile-based planning and designs. International groups such as Critical Mass formed to encourage traffic laws and city design more conducive to cycling.
  </p>
  <signature>
   EB Editors
  </signature>
  <signature>
   Samuel Abt
  </signature>
 </h1>
 <h1 id="h332055">
  <title>
   Winners of the Tour de France
  </title>
  <p>
   A list of Tour de France winners is provided in the table.
  </p>
 </h1>
 <h1 id="h332056">
  <title>
   Winners of Cycling World Road-Racing Championships
  </title>
  <p>
   A list of cycling world road-racing championship winners is provided in the table.
  </p>
 </h1>
 <h1 id="h332057">
  <title>
   Winners of Cycling World Track Championships
  </title>
  <p>
   A list of cycling world track championship winners is provided in the table.
  </p>
 </h1>
 <copyright>
  Encyclopædia Britannica
 </copyright>
</article>