<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "syndication_xml.dtd">
<article articleid="29855" articletypeid="1" language="en_us" lastupdate="2021-Jun-30 21:33:15" url="/article/Delta/29855" version="3">
 <title>
  Delta
 </title>
 <p>
  <e type="bold">
   Delta
  </e>
  , state, southern
  <xref articleid="110793">
   Nigeria
  </xref>
  . It is bounded by
  <xref articleid="32018">
   Edo
  </xref>
  state to the north,
  <xref articleid="7350">
   Anambra
  </xref>
  state to the east,
  <xref articleid="63805">
   Rivers
  </xref>
  state to the southeast, Bayelsa state to the south, the
  <xref articleid="78618">
   Bight of Benin
  </xref>
  of the Atlantic Ocean to the west, and
  <xref articleid="57115">
   Ondo
  </xref>
  state to the northwest. On the east and south the state is bounded by the lower course and delta of the
  <xref articleid="108301">
   Niger River
  </xref>
  . Delta was created in 1991 from the southern half of former Bendel state.
  <xref articleid="9757">
   Asaba
  </xref>
  , on the Niger River, is the state capital.
 </p>
 <p>
  Most of the state lies at an elevation below 500 feet (150 metres) in the Niger River delta. Mangrove swamps predominate in the delta and merge with freshwater swamps to the north. A maze of interconnected waterways and the
  <xref articleid="34833">
   Forcados
  </xref>
  and
  <xref articleid="32993">
   Escravos
  </xref>
  rivers, which empty into the Bight of Benin, are used for transportation. The state is inhabited by the
  <xref articleid="42055">
   Igbo
  </xref>
  people in the east, the
  <xref articleid="32016">
   Edo
  </xref>
  in the north, and the
  <xref articleid="1638">
   Itsekiri
  </xref>
  ,
  <xref articleid="74470">
   Urhobo
  </xref>
  ,
  <xref articleid="42947">
   Isoko
  </xref>
  , and
  <xref articleid="42087">
   Ijo
  </xref>
  in the south and west.
 </p>
 <p>
  Agriculture is the mainstay of the state’s economy; yams, cassava (manioc), oil palm produce, rice, and corn (maize) are grown for local consumption. Delta is a major exporter of petroleum, rubber, timber, and palm oil and palm kernels via the Niger delta ports of
  <xref articleid="18246">
   Burutu
  </xref>
  , Forcados,
  <xref articleid="45913">
   Koko
  </xref>
  ,
  <xref articleid="65695">
   Sapele
  </xref>
  , and
  <xref articleid="76138">
   Warri
  </xref>
  . Petroleum is exported by pipeline from the
  <xref articleid="74106">
   Ughelli
  </xref>
  fields, and other major oil fields exist near Warri (which possesses an oil refinery), Koko, and Escravos, as well as offshore. The state’s industries include glass and bottle factories, textile mills, and plastics, rubber, plywood, natural gas, boatbuilding, sawmilling, and furniture industries. A major steel-producing complex is at Aladja, adjacent to Warri. A bridge crosses the Niger from Asaba to
  <xref articleid="57141">
   Onitsha
  </xref>
  . Area 6,833 square miles (17,698 square km). Pop. (2006) 4,098,391.
 </p>
 <copyright>
  Encyclopædia Britannica
 </copyright>
</article>