<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "syndication_xml.dtd">
<article articleid="30102" articletypeid="1" language="en_us" lastupdate="2021-Jun-30 21:34:51" url="/article/detergent/30102" version="5">
 <title>
  detergent
 </title>
 <p>
  <assembly id="a89942" url="/assembly/view/89942">
   <media mediaid="94571" type="image" url="/71/94571-004-7DE8ED64.jpg"/>
   <caption>
    The diagrams show how detergent removes oil droplets often contained in dirt. When the detergent dissolves in water, detergent molecules group themselves around an oil droplet (a). The water-repelling part of the molecules (light area) projects into the droplet, while the water-soluble part (dark area) remains in the water (b). The oil is held in suspension by the emulsifying action of the detergent and is carried away with the dirty water (c).
   </caption>
   <credit>
    Encyclopædia Britannica, Inc.
   </credit>
  </assembly>
  <e type="bold">
   detergent
  </e>
  ,
  <assemblyref assemblyid="a89942"/>
  any of various
  <xref articleid="70437">
   surfactants
  </xref>
  (surface-active agents) particularly effective in dislodging foreign matter from soiled surfaces and retaining it in suspension. The term usually denotes a synthetic substance that is not prepared by saponifying fats and oils (as is soap).
 </p>
 <p>
  A brief treatment of detergents follows. For full treatment,
  <e type="italic">
   see
  </e>
  <xref articleid="108583">
   soap and detergent
  </xref>
  .
 </p>
 <p>
  Dishwashing and laundering of
  <xref articleid="24439">
   clothing
  </xref>
  are the principal applications of detergents for which the
  <xref articleid="110301">
   liquid
  </xref>
  bath is
  <xref articleid="76210">
   water
  </xref>
  . Detergents also are used as emulsifiers in many applications. Detergents that function in nonaqueous media include dispersing agents added to lubricating oils used in automotive engines to prevent the accumulation of varnishlike deposits on the cylinder walls, to
  <xref articleid="36148">
   gasoline
  </xref>
  to prevent the buildup of gummy residues in the
  <xref articleid="20272">
   carburetor
  </xref>
  , and to
  <xref articleid="472231">
   dry-cleaning
  </xref>
  solvents to facilitate the removal of soil from garments.
 </p>
 <copyright>
  Encyclopædia Britannica
 </copyright>
</article>