<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "syndication_xml.dtd">
<article articleid="30421" articletypeid="1" language="en_us" lastupdate="2022-Oct-13 08:56:55" url="/article/diffusion/30421" version="5">
 <title>
  diffusion
 </title>
 <p>
  <assembly id="a66779" url="/assembly/view/66779">
   <title>
    ion diffusion across a semipermeable membrane
   </title>
   <media mediaid="54958" type="image" url="/58/54958-004-1272EA1A.jpg"/>
   <caption>
    Diffusion of ions across a semipermeable membrane. (A) A high concentration of KCl is placed on side 1, opposite a semipermeable membrane from a low concentration. The membrane allows only K
    <sup>
     +
    </sup>
    to diffuse, thereby establishing an electrical potential difference across the membrane. (B) The separation of charge creates an electrostatic voltage force, which draws some K
    <sup>
     +
    </sup>
    back to side 1. (C) At equilibrium, there is no net flux of K
    <sup>
     +
    </sup>
    in either direction. Side 1, with the higher concentration of KCl, has a negative charge compared with side 2.
   </caption>
   <credit>
    Encyclopædia Britannica, Inc.
   </credit>
  </assembly>
  <e type="bold">
   diffusion
  </e>
  ,
  <assemblyref assemblyid="a66779"/>
  process resulting from random motion of
  <xref articleid="53247">
   molecules
  </xref>
  by which there is a net flow of
  <xref articleid="51438">
   matter
  </xref>
  from a region of high concentration to a region of low concentration. A familiar example is the perfume of a
  <xref articleid="34656">
   flower
  </xref>
  that quickly permeates the still air of a room.
 </p>
 <p>
  <xref articleid="39732">
   Heat
  </xref>
  conduction in fluids involves thermal energy transported, or diffused, from higher to lower
  <xref articleid="71632">
   temperature
  </xref>
  . Operation of a
  <xref articleid="106041">
   nuclear reactor
  </xref>
  involves the diffusion of
  <xref articleid="55406">
   neutrons
  </xref>
  through a medium that causes frequent scattering but only rare absorption of neutrons.
 </p>
 <p>
  The rate of flow of the diffusing substance is found to be proportional to the concentration gradient. If
  <e type="italic">
   j
  </e>
  is the amount of substance passing through a reference surface of unit area per unit time, if the coordinate
  <e type="italic">
   x
  </e>
  is perpendicular to this reference area, if
  <e type="italic">
   c
  </e>
  is the concentration of the substance, and if the constant of proportionality is
  <e type="italic">
   D,
  </e>
  then
  <e type="italic">
   j
  </e>
  = −
  <e type="italic">
   D
  </e>
  (
  <e type="italic">
   dc
  </e>
  /
  <e type="italic">
   dx
  </e>
  );
  <e type="italic">
   dc
  </e>
  /
  <e type="italic">
   dx
  </e>
  is the rate of change of concentration in the direction
  <e type="italic">
   x,
  </e>
  and the minus sign indicates the flow is from higher to lower concentration.
  <e type="italic">
   D
  </e>
  is called the diffusivity and governs the rate of diffusion.
 </p>
 <signature>
  EB Editors
 </signature>
 <copyright>
  Encyclopædia Britannica
 </copyright>
</article>