<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "syndication_xml.dtd">
<article articleid="30429" articletypeid="1" language="en_us" lastupdate="2021-Jun-30 21:36:50" url="/article/digit/30429" version="1">
 <title>
  digit
 </title>
 <p>
  <e type="bold">
   digit
  </e>
  , in anatomy, finger or toe of land vertebrates, the skeleton of which consists of small bones called phalanges. The tips of the digits are usually protected by keratinous structures, such as claws, nails, or hoofs, which may also be used for defense or manipulation. Digits are numbered one through five, beginning with the inside digit (thumb) when the palm (paw) is face downward.
 </p>
 <p>
  In many species the number of digits has been reduced during the course of evolution. Amphibians and birds typically have four digits on each foot, amphibians having lost digit one (thumb) and birds digit five. Reptiles usually have five digits. Many phalanges have been lost from the bird’s wing; the remainder are often elongated for support in flight. The number of digits in mammals varies greatly. In those with five digits (
  <e type="italic">
   e.g.,
  </e>
  primates, raccoons), the thumb has two phalanges; all other digits have three. In the horse only the third digit remains, covered at the tip by a single hoof. In cattle and other split-hoofed animals, digits three and four remain.
 </p>
 <p>
  The number of phalanges may be multiplied in the fins of sea mammals. In bats the phalanges of digits two to five, and other arm bones, are elongated and support a fleshy wing; the thumb is short and free and carries a claw.
 </p>
 <p>
  Primates have five digits, and most have developed fingernails and toenails in the place of claws and hoofs. These digits tend to be capable of much independent, manipulative action. The human foot is specialized for bipedal locomotion—the toes are shortened, relatively immovable, and nonmanipulative.
 </p>
 <copyright>
  Encyclopædia Britannica
 </copyright>
</article>