<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "syndication_xml.dtd">
<article articleid="30730" articletypeid="1" language="en_us" lastupdate="2022-Mar-21 09:03:53" url="/article/DNA/30730" version="21">
 <title>
  DNA
 </title>
 <p>
  <assembly id="a90501" url="/assembly/view/90501">
   <title>
    initial proposal of DNA structure
   </title>
   <media mediaid="779" type="image" url="/79/779-004-13506D8B.jpg"/>
   <caption>
    The initial proposal of the structure of DNA by James Watson and Francis Crick, which was accompanied by a suggestion on the means of replication.
   </caption>
   <credit>
    Encyclopædia Britannica, Inc.
   </credit>
  </assembly>
  <e type="bold">
   DNA
  </e>
  , abbreviation of
  <e type="bold">
   deoxyribonucleic acid
  </e>
  ,
  <assemblyref assemblyid="a90501"/>
  organic chemical of complex molecular structure that is found in all
  <xref articleid="61465">
   prokaryotic
  </xref>
  and
  <xref articleid="33173">
   eukaryotic
  </xref>
  <xref articleid="106125">
   cells
  </xref>
  and in many
  <xref articleid="106000">
   viruses
  </xref>
  . DNA codes genetic information for the transmission of inherited traits.
 </p>
 <p>
  A brief treatment of DNA follows. For full treatment,
  <e type="italic">
   see
  </e>
  <xref articleid="110582" refid="h261532">
   genetics: DNA and the genetic code
  </xref>
  .
 </p>
 <p>
  <assembly id="a209296" url="/assembly/view/209296">
   <title>
    Learn how Francis Crick and James Watson revolutionized genetics by discerning DNA’s structure
   </title>
   <media mediaid="152199" thumburl="/99/152199-049-895441CC.jpg" type="video" url="6S4aXgMT"/>
   <caption>
    This video introduces the basics of DNA, the chemical that underlies life on Earth.
   </caption>
   <credit>
    Encyclopædia Britannica, Inc.
   </credit>
  </assembly>
  <assembly id="a2659" url="/assembly/view/2659">
   <title>
    DNA structure
   </title>
   <media mediaid="6520" type="image" url="/20/6520-004-CB4513DC.jpg"/>
   <caption>
    DNA structure, showing the nucleotide bases cytosine (C), thymine (T), adenine (A), and guanine (G) linked to a backbone of alternating phosphate (P) and deoxyribose sugar (S) groups. Two sugar-phosphate chains are paired through hydrogen bonds between A and T and between G and C, thus forming the twin-stranded double helix of the DNA molecule.
   </caption>
   <credit>
    Encyclopædia Britannica, Inc.
   </credit>
  </assembly>
  <assemblyref assemblyid="a209296"/>
  <assemblyref assemblyid="a2659"/>
  The chemical DNA was first discovered in 1869, but its role in genetic inheritance was not demonstrated until 1943. In 1953
  <xref articleid="76285">
   James Watson
  </xref>
  and
  <xref articleid="27893">
   Francis Crick
  </xref>
  , aided by the work of biophysicists
  <xref articleid="35187">
   Rosalind Franklin
  </xref>
  and
  <xref articleid="77005">
   Maurice Wilkins
  </xref>
  , determined that the structure of DNA is a double-helix
  <xref articleid="60700">
   polymer
  </xref>
  , a spiral consisting of two DNA strands wound around each other. The breakthrough led to significant advances in scientists’ understanding of DNA replication and hereditary control of cellular activities.
 </p>
 <p>
  <assembly id="a2658" url="/assembly/view/2658">
   <title>
    polynucleotide chain of deoxyribonucleic acid (DNA)
   </title>
   <media mediaid="6519" type="image" url="/19/6519-004-88172EC9.jpg"/>
   <caption>
    Portion of polynucleotide chain of deoxyribonucleic acid (DNA). The inset shows the corresponding pentose sugar and pyrimidine base in ribonucleic acid (RNA).
   </caption>
   <credit>
    Encyclopædia Britannica, Inc.
   </credit>
  </assembly>
  <assemblyref assemblyid="a2658"/>
  Each strand of a DNA molecule is composed of a long chain of monomer
  <xref articleid="56460">
   nucleotides
  </xref>
  . The nucleotides of DNA consist of a deoxyribose sugar molecule to which is attached a
  <xref articleid="59774">
   phosphate
  </xref>
  group and one of four nitrogenous bases: two
  <xref articleid="61952">
   purines
  </xref>
  (
  <xref articleid="3720">
   adenine
  </xref>
  and
  <xref articleid="38302">
   guanine
  </xref>
  ) and two
  <xref articleid="62053">
   pyrimidines
  </xref>
  (
  <xref articleid="28449">
   cytosine
  </xref>
  and
  <xref articleid="72358">
   thymine
  </xref>
  ). The nucleotides are joined together by
  <xref articleid="26644">
   covalent bonds
  </xref>
  between the phosphate of one nucleotide and the sugar of the next, forming a phosphate-sugar backbone from which the nitrogenous bases protrude. One strand is held to another by
  <xref articleid="472561">
   hydrogen bonds
  </xref>
  between the bases; the sequencing of this bonding is specific—i.e., adenine bonds only with thymine, and cytosine only with guanine.
 </p>
 <p>
  The configuration of the DNA molecule is highly stable, allowing it to act as a template for the replication of new DNA molecules, as well as for the production (
  <xref articleid="474441">
   transcription
  </xref>
  ) of the related
  <xref articleid="63829">
   RNA
  </xref>
  (ribonucleic acid) molecule. A segment of DNA that codes for the cell’s synthesis of a specific
  <xref articleid="110575">
   protein
  </xref>
  is called a
  <xref articleid="36352">
   gene
  </xref>
  .
 </p>
 <p>
  DNA replicates by separating into two single strands, each of which serves as a template for a new strand. The new strands are copied by the same principle of hydrogen-bond pairing between bases that exists in the double helix. Two new double-stranded molecules of DNA are produced, each containing one of the original strands and one new strand. This “semiconservative” replication is the key to the stable inheritance of genetic traits.
 </p>
 <p>
  Within a cell, DNA is organized into dense protein-DNA complexes called
  <xref articleid="82456">
   chromosomes
  </xref>
  . In eukaryotes, the chromosomes are located in the
  <xref articleid="56461">
   nucleus
  </xref>
  , although DNA also is found in
  <xref articleid="443654">
   mitochondria
  </xref>
  and
  <xref articleid="82258">
   chloroplasts
  </xref>
  . In prokaryotes, which do not have a membrane-bound nucleus, the DNA is found as a single circular chromosome in the
  <xref articleid="28447">
   cytoplasm
  </xref>
  . Some prokaryotes, such as
  <xref articleid="110416">
   bacteria
  </xref>
  , and a few eukaryotes have extrachromosomal DNA known as
  <xref articleid="60331">
   plasmids
  </xref>
  , which are autonomous, self-replicating genetic material. Plasmids have been used extensively in
  <xref articleid="437419">
   recombinant DNA technology
  </xref>
  to study gene expression.
 </p>
 <p>
  The genetic material of viruses may be single- or double-stranded DNA or RNA.
  <xref articleid="63323">
   Retroviruses
  </xref>
  carry their genetic material as single-stranded RNA and produce the
  <xref articleid="32739">
   enzyme
  </xref>
  <xref articleid="470961">
   reverse transcriptase
  </xref>
  , which can generate DNA from the RNA strand. Four-stranded DNA complexes known as G-quadruplexes have been observed in guanine-rich areas of the
  <xref articleid="439231">
   human genome
  </xref>
  .
 </p>
 <signature>
  EB Editors
 </signature>
 <copyright>
  Encyclopædia Britannica
 </copyright>
</article>