<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "syndication_xml.dtd">
<article articleid="32627" articletypeid="1" language="en_us" lastupdate="2021-Nov-16 15:44:07" url="/article/energy/32627" version="8">
 <title>
  energy
 </title>
 <p>
  <e type="bold">
   energy
  </e>
  , in
  <xref articleid="108654">
   physics
  </xref>
  , the capacity for doing
  <xref articleid="77472">
   work
  </xref>
  . It may exist in
  <xref articleid="61056">
   potential
  </xref>
  ,
  <xref articleid="45490">
   kinetic
  </xref>
  ,
  <xref articleid="72068">
   thermal
  </xref>
  , electrical,
  <xref articleid="472022">
   chemical
  </xref>
  ,
  <xref articleid="56438">
   nuclear
  </xref>
  , or other various forms. There are, moreover,
  <xref articleid="39732">
   heat
  </xref>
  and work—i.e., energy in the process of transfer from one body to another. After it has been transferred, energy is always designated according to its nature. Hence, heat transferred may become thermal energy, while work done may manifest itself in the form of
  <xref articleid="51701">
   mechanical energy
  </xref>
  .
 </p>
 <p>
  All forms of energy are associated with motion. For example, any given body has kinetic energy if it is in motion. A tensioned device such as a
  <xref articleid="16004">
   bow
  </xref>
  or
  <xref articleid="69244">
   spring
  </xref>
  , though at rest, has the potential for creating motion; it contains potential energy because of its configuration. Similarly, nuclear energy is potential energy because it results from the configuration of
  <xref articleid="108593">
   subatomic particles
  </xref>
  in the
  <xref articleid="56462">
   nucleus
  </xref>
  of an
  <xref articleid="110411">
   atom
  </xref>
  .
 </p>
 <p>
  <assembly id="a246704" url="/assembly/view/246704">
   <title>
    Discover how energy moves between thermal, chemical, mechanical, and other forms
   </title>
   <media mediaid="202219" thumburl="/19/202219-049-66479FAD.jpg" type="video" url=""/>
   <caption>
    How energy can change from one form to another. Examples presented include a lightbulb, a car’s engine, and plant photosynthesis.
   </caption>
   <credit>
    Encyclopædia Britannica, Inc.
   </credit>
  </assembly>
  <assemblyref assemblyid="a246704"/>
  Energy can be neither created nor destroyed but only changed from one form to another. This principle is known as the conservation of energy or the
  <xref articleid="108582" refid="h258541">
   first law of thermodynamics
  </xref>
  . For example, when a box slides down a hill, the potential energy that the box has from being located high up on the slope is converted to kinetic energy, energy of motion. As the box slows to a stop through
  <xref articleid="35414">
   friction
  </xref>
  , the kinetic energy from the box’s motion is converted to thermal energy that heats the box and the slope.
 </p>
 <p>
  Energy can be converted from one form to another in various other ways. Usable mechanical or electrical energy is, for instance, produced by many kinds of devices, including fuel-burning heat engines, generators,
  <xref articleid="106044">
   batteries
  </xref>
  ,
  <xref articleid="106045">
   fuel cells
  </xref>
  , and
  <xref articleid="106048">
   magnetohydrodynamic
  </xref>
  systems.
 </p>
 <p>
  In the
  <xref articleid="42610">
   International System of Units
  </xref>
  (SI), energy is measured in
  <xref articleid="44023">
   joules
  </xref>
  . One joule is equal to the work done by a one-
  <xref articleid="55617">
   newton
  </xref>
  <xref articleid="34834">
   force
  </xref>
  acting over a one-
  <xref articleid="52350">
   metre
  </xref>
  distance.
 </p>
 <p>
  Energy is treated in a number of articles. For the development of the concept of energy and the principle of energy conservation,
  <e type="italic">
   see
  </e>
  <xref articleid="108568">
   principles of physical science
  </xref>
  ;
  <xref articleid="110307">
   mechanics
  </xref>
  ;
  <xref articleid="108582">
   thermodynamics
  </xref>
  ; and
  <xref articleid="32628">
   conservation of energy
  </xref>
  . For the major sources of energy and the mechanisms by which the transition of energy from one form to another occurs,
  <e type="italic">
   see
  </e>
  <xref articleid="110442">
   coal
  </xref>
  ;
  <xref articleid="68559">
   solar energy
  </xref>
  ;
  <xref articleid="443102">
   wind power
  </xref>
  ;
  <xref articleid="110414">
   nuclear fission
  </xref>
  ;
  <xref articleid="110441">
   oil shale
  </xref>
  ;
  <xref articleid="110438">
   petroleum
  </xref>
  ;
  <xref articleid="106021">
   electromagnetism
  </xref>
  ; and
  <xref articleid="106034">
   energy conversion
  </xref>
  .
 </p>
 <signature>
  EB Editors
 </signature>
 <copyright>
  Encyclopædia Britannica
 </copyright>
</article>