<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "syndication_xml.dtd">
<article articleid="33291" articletypeid="1" language="en_us" lastupdate="2021-Jun-30 21:53:58" url="/article/eustachian-tube/33291" version="2">
 <title>
  eustachian tube
 </title>
 <p>
  <e type="bold">
   eustachian tube
  </e>
  , also called
  <e type="bold">
   auditory tube
  </e>
  , hollow structure that extends from the middle ear to the
  <xref articleid="59591">
   pharynx
  </xref>
  (throat). The eustachian tube is about 31–38 mm (1.2–1.5 inches) long in humans and lined with mucous membrane. It is directed downward and inward from the tympanic cavity, or middle ear, to the portion of the pharynx called the nasopharynx (the space above the soft
  <xref articleid="58058">
   palate
  </xref>
  and behind and continuous with the nasal passages). The upper end of the eustachian tube is narrow and surrounded by
  <xref articleid="110163">
   bone
  </xref>
  . As it nears the pharynx, the tube becomes wider and cartilaginous. The mucous lining is continuous with that of the middle ear.
  <xref articleid="82643">
   Cilia
  </xref>
  (small hairlike projections) cover it to aid the drainage of mucous secretions from the middle ear to the pharynx.
 </p>
 <p>
  The main function of the eustachian tube is ventilation of the middle ear and maintenance of equalized air pressure on both sides of the
  <xref articleid="73988">
   tympanic membrane
  </xref>
  (eardrum). Closed at most times, the tube opens during swallowing. This permits equalization of the pressure without conscious effort. During an underwater dive or a rapid descent in an airplane, the eustachian tube may remain closed in the face of rapidly increasing surrounding pressure. The pressure on both sides of the eardrum membrane can usually be equalized by holding the nose and blowing, by swallowing, or by wiggling the
  <xref articleid="43439">
   jaws
  </xref>
  .
 </p>
 <copyright>
  Encyclopædia Britannica
 </copyright>
</article>