<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "syndication_xml.dtd">
<article articleid="34098" articletypeid="1" language="en_us" lastupdate="2023-Jan-13 14:54:22" url="/article/ferret/34098" version="12">
 <title>
  ferret
 </title>
 <p>
  <assembly id="a205806" url="/assembly/view/205806">
   <title>
    black-footed ferret
   </title>
   <media mediaid="161459" type="image" url="/59/161459-004-871CDCC3.jpg"/>
   <caption>
    The black-footed ferret (
    <e type="italic">
     Mustela nigripes
    </e>
    ) is one of the rarest mammals in North America, and between 1996 and 2008 it was considered extinct in the wild. Reintroduction programs begun in 1991 have had mixed results. Utah, New Mexico, South Dakota, and Kansas host a handful of small self-sustaining populations. The International Union for Conservation of Nature classified the black-footed ferret as an endangered species in 2008.
   </caption>
   <credit>
    Ryan Hagerty—NCTC Image Library /U.S. Fish and Wildlife Service
   </credit>
  </assembly>
  <e type="bold">
   ferret
  </e>
  , also called
  <e type="bold">
   fitchet
  </e>
  ,
  <assemblyref assemblyid="a205806"/>
  either of two
  <xref articleid="69027">
   species
  </xref>
  of
  <xref articleid="105981">
   carnivores
  </xref>
  , the common ferret (
  <e type="italic">
   Mustela putorius furo
  </e>
  ) and the black-footed ferret (
  <e type="italic">
   M. nigripes
  </e>
  ), belonging to the
  <xref articleid="76361">
   weasel
  </xref>
  family (
  <xref articleid="54480">
   Mustelidae
  </xref>
  ).
 </p>
 <h1 id="h252713">
  <title>
   Common ferret
  </title>
  <p>
   <assembly id="a274530" url="/assembly/view/274530">
    <title>
     common ferret (
     <e type="italic">
      Mustela putorius furo
     </e>
     )
    </title>
    <media mediaid="234962" type="image" url="/62/234962-004-B0BA5FD1.jpg"/>
    <caption>
     The common ferret (
     <e type="italic">
      Mustela putorius furo
     </e>
     ) is a domesticated form of the European polecat (
     <e type="italic">
      M. putorius
     </e>
     ).
    </caption>
    <credit>
     © Genevieve Vallee/Alamy
    </credit>
   </assembly>
   <assemblyref assemblyid="a274530"/>
   The common ferret is a domesticated form of the European
   <xref articleid="60607">
    polecat
   </xref>
   , which it resembles in size and habits and with which it interbreeds, leading most taxonomists to classify the common ferret as a subspecies. The common ferret is found throughout the European polecat’s geographic range—from
   <xref articleid="110712">
    Morocco
   </xref>
   and
   <xref articleid="108580">
    Spain
   </xref>
   through continental
   <xref articleid="106055">
    Europe
   </xref>
   , Britain, and southern
   <xref articleid="66021">
    Scandinavia
   </xref>
   to the
   <xref articleid="106061">
    Ural Mountains
   </xref>
   in
   <xref articleid="109504">
    Russia
   </xref>
   . It was introduced into
   <xref articleid="110716">
    North America
   </xref>
   in the 18th century and into
   <xref articleid="110544">
    Australia
   </xref>
   and
   <xref articleid="108762">
    New Zealand
   </xref>
   during the middle of the 19th century to hunt
   <xref articleid="62348">
    rabbits
   </xref>
   and
   <xref articleid="105980">
    rodents
   </xref>
   , and it was farmed for its
   <xref articleid="35680">
    fur
   </xref>
   .
  </p>
  <p>
   <assembly id="a274531" url="/assembly/view/274531">
    <title>
     common ferret (
     <e type="italic">
      Mustela putorius furo
     </e>
     )
    </title>
    <media mediaid="234981" type="image" url="/81/234981-004-9DA1F39D.jpg"/>
    <caption>
     The common ferret (
     <e type="italic">
      Mustela putorius furo
     </e>
     )—averaging 51 cm (20 inches) in length, including the 13-cm (5.1-inch) tail—is slightly smaller than the European polecat (
     <e type="italic">
      M. putorius
     </e>
     ).
    </caption>
    <credit>
     © jurra8/Shutterstock.com
    </credit>
   </assembly>
   <assemblyref assemblyid="a274531"/>
   Physically speaking, the common ferret differs from the European polecat in that it has yellowish white (sometimes brown) fur and pinkish red eyes. It is also slightly smaller than the polecat, averaging 51 cm (20 inches) in length, including the 13-cm (5.1-inch)
   <xref articleid="70967">
    tail
   </xref>
   . It weighs about 1 kg (2 pounds). On the basis of these differences, some taxonomists have classified the common ferret as a distinct species (
   <e type="italic">
    M. furo
   </e>
   ).
  </p>
  <p>
   Ferrets are popular
   <xref articleid="59409">
    pets
   </xref>
   and are commonly used in
   <xref articleid="75203">
    veterinary research
   </xref>
   . In captivity they become tame and playful and remain inquisitive. Although ferrets are adaptable, their dependence on humans becomes such that they are unable to survive without care and if lost often die within a few days. Ferrets can subsist on a diet of water and meat similar to that given the domestic cat. Easily bred in captivity, females bear two litters of six or seven young each year. Because common ferrets are subject to foot rot, their cages must be kept scrupulously clean.
  </p>
  <p>
   Ferreting—the use of ferrets to drive rabbits,
   <xref articleid="62752">
    rats
   </xref>
   , and other
   <xref articleid="59405">
    vermin
   </xref>
   from their underground burrows—has been practiced since Roman times in Europe and even longer in
   <xref articleid="110518">
    Asia
   </xref>
   . In the case of rabbits, for example, a ferret is released into rabbit burrows to flush them into waiting
   <xref articleid="55344">
    nets
   </xref>
   or traps. The ferret’s long tubular body and short limbs, as well as its aggressive hunting, make it ideal for this function.
  </p>
 </h1>
 <h1 id="h252714">
  <title>
   Black-footed ferret
  </title>
  <p>
   The black-footed ferret of the American
   <xref articleid="110719">
    Great Plains
   </xref>
   is an
   <xref articleid="32604">
    endangered species
   </xref>
   . The black-footed ferret resembles the common ferret in colour but has a black mask across the eyes and brownish black markings on the feet and the tail’s tip. It weighs a kilogram or less, males being slightly larger than females. Body length is 38–50 cm (15–20 inches), with a tail 11–15 cm (about 4–6 inches).
  </p>
  <p>
   Black-footed ferrets live in
   <xref articleid="61181">
    prairie dog
   </xref>
   burrows and eat only prairie dogs, both as prey and as carrion. They were originally found living among prairie dog populations ranging from southern
   <xref articleid="110588">
    Canada
   </xref>
   through the American West to northern
   <xref articleid="108719">
    Mexico
   </xref>
   . As prairie dogs were largely eliminated by the development of agriculture in the
   <xref articleid="110719">
    Great Plains
   </xref>
   , ferrets very nearly went
   <xref articleid="33463">
    extinct
   </xref>
   . By 1987 the last members of a remaining
   <xref articleid="108576">
    population
   </xref>
   of 18 animals had been captured from the wild in
   <xref articleid="111276">
    Wyoming
   </xref>
   , and a captive breeding program was begun. From this group, seven females produced young that survived to adulthood. Since 1991 more than 2,300 of their descendants have been reintroduced to native habitats in Wyoming,
   <xref articleid="111273">
    Montana
   </xref>
   ,
   <xref articleid="111265">
    South Dakota
   </xref>
   ,
   <xref articleid="111258">
    Kansas
   </xref>
   ,
   <xref articleid="111267">
    Arizona
   </xref>
   ,
   <xref articleid="111268">
    New Mexico
   </xref>
   ,
   <xref articleid="111271">
    Colorado
   </xref>
   ,
   <xref articleid="111275">
    Utah
   </xref>
   , and
   <xref articleid="24042">
    Chihuahua
   </xref>
   state, Mexico.
  </p>
  <p>
   These reintroduction programs, however, have had mixed results. While Utah, New Mexico, South Dakota, and Kansas host self-sustaining populations, the species was classified by the
   <xref articleid="438741">
    International Union for Conservation of Nature
   </xref>
   (IUCN) as extinct in the wild between 1996 and 2008. After a population reassessment in 2008, the IUCN listed the black-footed ferret as an endangered species.
  </p>
  <p>
   Black-footed ferrets are solitary except during the breeding season in March and April. Births occur in May and June, and females raise the young (kits) alone. Three kits are the norm, but litters range from one to six. Young are born in a modified burrow and emerge in July to become independent in September or October, at which time the young, especially males, usually disperse. Sexual maturity is attained after a year. Longevity in the wild is not known, but captive animals may live up to 12 years.
  </p>
  <p>
   Ferrets are hunted by
   <xref articleid="37235">
    golden eagles
   </xref>
   and great
   <xref articleid="41082">
    horned owls
   </xref>
   as well as by other carnivores such as
   <xref articleid="26701">
    coyotes
   </xref>
   and
   <xref articleid="11705">
    badgers
   </xref>
   .
   <xref articleid="110471">
    Poisons
   </xref>
   used to control prairie dogs, especially sodium monofluoroacetate (commonly called 1080) and
   <xref articleid="70014">
    strychnine
   </xref>
   , probably contribute to deaths when the ferrets eat poisoned prairie dogs. Moreover, black-footed ferrets are extremely susceptible to many infectious
   <xref articleid="110618">
    diseases
   </xref>
   such as
   <xref articleid="19986">
    canine distemper
   </xref>
   . Bubonic
   <xref articleid="60279">
    plague
   </xref>
   can severely reduce populations of prairie dogs and thus cause
   <xref articleid="34792">
    food
   </xref>
   shortages for black-footed ferrets, but it is unknown whether ferrets themselves contract plague.
  </p>
  <signature>
   EB Editors
  </signature>
 </h1>
 <copyright>
  Encyclopædia Britannica
 </copyright>
</article>