<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "syndication_xml.dtd">
<article articleid="343052" articletypeid="1" language="en_us" lastupdate="2021-Jul-01 05:27:12" url="/article/small-body/343052" version="8">
 <title>
  small body
 </title>
 <p>
  <assembly id="a17684" url="/assembly/view/17684">
   <title>
    asteroid Ida and its satellite, Dactyl
   </title>
   <media mediaid="21224" type="image" url="/24/21224-004-D06DC628.jpg"/>
   <caption>
    Asteroid Ida and its satellite, Dactyl, photographed by the Galileo spacecraft on August 28, 1993, from a distance of about 10,870 km (6,750 miles). Ida is about 56 km (35 miles) long and shows the irregular shape and impact craters characteristic of many asteroids. The Galileo image revealed that Ida is accompanied by a tiny companion about 1.5 km (1 mile) wide, the first proof that some asteroids have natural satellites.
   </caption>
   <credit>
    Photo NASA/JPL/Caltech
   </credit>
  </assembly>
  <assembly id="a60533" url="/assembly/view/60533">
   <title>
    Comet Halley nucleus
   </title>
   <media mediaid="4300" type="image" url="/00/4300-004-932A3155.jpg"/>
   <caption>
    Composite image of the nucleus of Comet Halley produced from 68 photographs taken on March 13–14, 1986, by the Halley Multicolour Camera onboard the Giotto spacecraft.
   </caption>
   <credit>
    Courtesy of H.U. Keller; copyright Max-Planck-Institut für Aeronomie, Lindau, Ger., 1986
   </credit>
  </assembly>
  <e type="bold">
   small body
  </e>
  , also called
  <e type="bold">
   small solar system body (SSSB)
  </e>
  ,
  <assemblyref assemblyid="a17684"/>
  <assemblyref assemblyid="a60533"/>
  any natural
  <xref articleid="110143">
   solar system
  </xref>
  object other than the
  <xref articleid="110144">
   Sun
  </xref>
  and the major
  <xref articleid="60298">
   planets
  </xref>
  and
  <xref articleid="435823">
   dwarf planets
  </xref>
  and their satellites (moons). The small bodies populate the solar system in vast numbers and include the mostly rocky
  <xref articleid="110155">
   asteroids
  </xref>
  , or minor planets, the predominantly icy
  <xref articleid="110156">
   comets
  </xref>
  , and the fragments of such bodies—commonly called
  <xref articleid="110158">
   meteoroids
  </xref>
  —over a continuum of sizes down to microscopic grains known as
  <xref articleid="126477">
   interplanetary dust particles
  </xref>
  or micrometeoroids. The term
  <e type="italic">
   small body
  </e>
  is sometimes restricted to objects that can be observed telescopically while still outside
  <xref articleid="110147">
   Earth
  </xref>
  ’s
  <xref articleid="126202">
   atmosphere
  </xref>
  . In practice, that results in a lower limit of a few metres on the diameters of small bodies.
 </p>
 <p>
  The use of
  <e type="italic">
   meteoroid
  </e>
  has expanded to describe any small chunk of matter in interplanetary space, especially one less than a few tens of metres in size. The term formerly was limited to small bodies that were near enough to Earth to eventually enter its atmosphere. In that narrower meaning,
  <e type="italic">
   meteoroid
  </e>
  is usually linked with the terms
  <e type="italic">
   meteor
  </e>
  ,
  <e type="italic">
   meteorite
  </e>
  , or both. As a meteoroid travels through the atmosphere, friction heats it up, creating a glowing trail of hot ionized gases (
  <xref articleid="110303">
   plasma
  </xref>
  ) called a
  <xref articleid="110158">
   meteor
  </xref>
  . If the object survives both its passage through the atmosphere and its subsequent impact on the ground, it is called a
  <xref articleid="110159">
   meteorite
  </xref>
  . Over 99 percent of meteorites are fragments of asteroids. A small group is known to be of lunar origin, and a second group is generally acknowledged to have come from
  <xref articleid="110149">
   Mars
  </xref>
  (
  <e type="italic">
   see
  </e>
  <xref articleid="110149" refid="h234168">
   Mars: Meteorites from Mars
  </xref>
  ). There is also reason to believe that some are fragments of the rocky remnants of comets, although that remains to be firmly established.
 </p>
 <h1 id="h331316">
  <title>
   Populations
  </title>
  <p>
   The largest known small bodies, in the conventional sense, are several icy
   <xref articleid="342992">
    Kuiper belt
   </xref>
   objects found orbiting the Sun beyond the
   <xref articleid="57286">
    orbit
   </xref>
   of
   <xref articleid="110153">
    Neptune
   </xref>
   .
   <xref articleid="22142">
    Ceres
   </xref>
   —which is the largest main-belt asteroid and is now considered a
   <xref articleid="435823">
    dwarf planet
   </xref>
   —is roughly 950 km (590 miles) in diameter. The distant Kuiper belt object
   <xref articleid="435821">
    Eris
   </xref>
   , roughly the same size as
   <xref articleid="110154">
    Pluto
   </xref>
   , which has a diameter of about 2,350 km (1,460 miles), is also designated a dwarf planet rather than a small body, as are
   <xref articleid="471197">
    Haumea
   </xref>
   and
   <xref articleid="470948">
    Makemake
   </xref>
   , both of which have diameters of about 1,450 km (900 miles). These four dwarf planets are known as plutoids. At least four other Kuiper belt objects are also believed to be larger than Ceres. In the 1990s astronomers recognized that
   <xref articleid="110154">
    Pluto
   </xref>
   , which has a diameter of about 2,300 km (1,400 miles), is a giant icy leftover from the time when the planets formed. Pluto had been classified as a planet from its discovery in 1930 but was reclassified as a dwarf planet in 2006. Primarily for historical reasons, the moons of the planets are not considered small bodies. Nevertheless, many moons are asteroid-size or smaller, and some are probably captured asteroids or comet nuclei.
  </p>
  <p>
   Although small bodies are found throughout the solar system, most of those known are concentrated in several regions. Those regions in which they travel in fairly stable orbits include (1) the main asteroid belt, between the orbits of Mars and
   <xref articleid="110150">
    Jupiter
   </xref>
   , (2) the gravitationally stable points (
   <xref articleid="46840">
    Lagrangian points
   </xref>
   ) along the orbital paths of Jupiter, Mars,
   <xref articleid="110152">
    Uranus
   </xref>
   , Neptune, and Earth where objects called
   <xref articleid="110155" refid="h258986">
    Trojan asteroids
   </xref>
   are clustered (
   <e type="italic">
    see
   </e>
   <xref articleid="110308" refid="h77433">
    celestial mechanics: The restricted three-body problem
   </xref>
   ), (3) the Kuiper belt, a disk-shaped zone of icy bodies whose members are also called trans-Neptunian objects because they all have orbits beyond that of Neptune, and (4) the spherical
   <xref articleid="342991">
    Oort cloud
   </xref>
   of icy bodies inferred to be orbiting the Sun at distances typically more than 1,000 times that of Neptune or Pluto. In none of the above categories is
   <xref articleid="473724">
    Sedna
   </xref>
   , an object discovered in 2003 in the outer reaches of the solar system that is perhaps as large as 40 percent the size of Pluto. Sedna has a highly elliptical orbit in which its closest approach to the Sun is more than twice that of Neptune—i.e., billions of kilometres beyond the recognized extent of the Kuiper belt; it may be a member of a population of objects lying between the Kuiper belt and the Oort cloud.
  </p>
  <p>
   Other small bodies travel in unstable orbits that cross the paths of one or more of the planets. Those include (1) most observed comets, (2)
   <xref articleid="110155" refid="h258983">
    near-Earth asteroids
   </xref>
   , most with orbits that cross either Earth’s orbit or Mars’s orbit and some with orbits that lie mostly or entirely inside Earth’s orbit and cross the orbits of
   <xref articleid="110146">
    Venus
   </xref>
   or of both Venus and
   <xref articleid="110145">
    Mercury
   </xref>
   while closely approaching Earth’s, (3)
   <xref articleid="342994">
    Centaur objects
   </xref>
   , icy bodies that are thought to have been gravitationally perturbed out of the Kuiper belt and now travel mainly between the orbits of Jupiter and Neptune, and (4) individual idiosyncratic planet-crossing objects such as the asteroid Hidalgo, which travels between the inner edge of the asteroid belt and a point just beyond the orbit of
   <xref articleid="110151">
    Saturn
   </xref>
   . All objects in planet-crossing orbits eventually collide with the Sun or a planet or are permanently ejected from the solar system, although some survive for long periods (up to hundreds of millions of years) because of stabilizing resonances.
  </p>
 </h1>
 <h1 id="h331317">
  <title>
   Origins
  </title>
  <p>
   Essentially all the small bodies are thought to be remnant material from the planet-building process that took place during the formation of the solar system from the solar nebula. (
   <e type="italic">
    See
   </e>
   <xref articleid="110143" refid="h242062">
    solar system: Formation of the solar nebula
   </xref>
   .) Near the hot nascent Sun, closer than Jupiter’s present orbit, only the less-volatile high-temperature-freezing-point substances such as metals and silicates could condense from the nebula. Beginning as tiny grains, that material gradually accreted under mutual gravitational influence to become large rocky bodies up to hundreds of kilometres in diameter. Most of those large objects, called
   <xref articleid="60302">
    planetesimals
   </xref>
   , ultimately combined to form the dense rocky planets of the inner solar system (Mercury through Mars). In the outer solar system, near Jupiter’s present orbit and beyond, temperatures were cool enough to allow abundant volatile substances such as water and carbon dioxide to condense to their ices. Although rocky planetesimals likewise accreted there, the significant additional mass contributed by the ices allowed the growth of the low-density gas-rich outer planets (Jupiter through Neptune).
  </p>
  <p>
   Nevertheless, in the inner and the outer solar system, there remained rocky bodies and predominantly icy bodies, respectively, that were never incorporated into planets or captured as planetary satellites. It is now believed that many of these bodies were subsequently mixed together and relocated from their formation locations by the migration of the giant planets. Today, in the inner solar system, these remnants are represented chiefly by the asteroids and their fragments; in the outer solar system, by the objects in and derived from the Kuiper belt and the Oort cloud. Comets originate, and most are still located, in the Kuiper belt and the Oort cloud. Except for the very largest Kuiper belt objects (diameters greater than about 100 km [60 miles]), comets in the Kuiper belt and beyond are unobservable because of their great distances from Earth. It is not until they enter the realm of the planets that they develop comas and tails.
  </p>
 </h1>
 <h1 id="h331318">
  <title>
   Differences between comets and asteroids
  </title>
  <p>
   <assembly id="a74720" url="/assembly/view/74720">
    <title>
     Comet Wild 2
    </title>
    <media mediaid="81402" type="image" url="/02/81402-004-A5FFF661.jpg"/>
    <caption>
     The icy nucleus of Comet Wild 2, in a composite image taken by the U.S. Stardust spacecraft during its close approach to the comet on January 2, 2004. The image consists of a short exposure to resolve fine details of the surface and a longer exposure to capture the faint jets of gas and dust streaming into space. Wild 2’s nucleus is about 5 km (3 miles) across.
    </caption>
    <credit>
     NASA/JPL/Stardust/University of Washington, Seattle
    </credit>
   </assembly>
   <assemblyref assemblyid="a74720"/>
   There are several characteristics based on physical differences, location, and orbital properties that traditionally have distinguished comets from asteroids. An object is classified as a comet when it displays “cometary activity”—i.e., a coma or tail (or any evidence of gas or dust coming from it). Objects in the Oort cloud, although they may not all have formed in their present location, are considered to be comet nuclei. Because of their great distance from the Sun, they do not display cometary activity. Nevertheless, they are believed to be made of the same volatile material as the observed comets and so have the potential to become active. Finally, any object on a nonreturning (parabolic or hyperbolic) orbit is generally considered to be a comet.
  </p>
  <p>
   Although such distinctions apply most of the time, they are not always sufficient to classify an individual object as an asteroid or a comet. For example, an object found to be receding from the Sun on a nonreturning orbit and displaying no cometary activity could be a comet, or it could be a planet-crossing asteroid being ejected from the solar system after a close encounter with a planet, most likely Jupiter. Again, objects on some planet-crossing orbits may have originated in either the Kuiper belt or the asteroid belt. Unless such an object reveals itself by displaying cometary activity, there is usually no way to determine its origin and thus to classify it unequivocally. The object may have formed as an icy body but lost its volatile materials during a series of passes into the inner solar system. Its burned-out remnant of rocky material would presently have more physical characteristics in common with asteroids than with other comets.
  </p>
  <p>
   One small body group with both cometary and asteroidal characteristics is that of the main-belt comets (or active asteroids). The first group member, 133P/(7968) Elst-Pizarro, was discovered in 1996, when that “asteroid’s” cometlike activity was first noted. Main-belt comets have orbits in the main asteroid belt but, like comets, have comae and tails.
  </p>
  <signature>
   Edward F. Tedesco
  </signature>
 </h1>
 <copyright>
  Encyclopædia Britannica
 </copyright>
</article>