<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "syndication_xml.dtd">
<article articleid="34575" articletypeid="1" language="en_us" lastupdate="2021-Jun-30 22:01:35" url="/article/flight/34575" version="4">
 <title>
  flight
 </title>
 <p>
  <e type="bold">
   flight
  </e>
  , in animals, locomotion of either of two basic types—powered, or true, flight and gliding. Winged (true) flight is found only in insects (most orders), most birds, and bats. The evolutionary modifications necessary for true flight in warm-blooded animals include those of the forelimbs into wings; lightening and fusion of bones; shortening of the torso; enlargement of the heart and thoracic muscles; and improved vision. Similar modifications in insects have occurred through different evolutionary pathways. The advantages conferred by flight are also great: in terms of numbers of species as well as numbers of individuals, insects, birds, and bats are among the most successful animal groups.
 </p>
 <p>
  Gliding flight may be of two types: gravitational gliding and soaring. Gravitational gliding may be directed, in which case the animal launches itself toward a definite target, or passive (parachuting), in which case the organism slows its descent, relying on wind for horizontal motion. Adaptations for directed gliding serve primarily to enhance the glide ratio (the amount of horizontal distance covered per unit descent) and include winglike modifications of fins (several fish groups), webs between digits (a frog,
  <e type="italic">
   Rhacophorus;
  </e>
  several lizards), distensible rib-supported vanes (lizards of the genus
  <e type="italic">
   Draco;
  </e>
  several snakes), and a fold of skin between the forelimbs and hind limbs (marsupial gliders; colugo; sciurid and anomalurid flying squirrels).
 </p>
 <p>
  <assembly id="a4958" url="/assembly/view/4958">
   <title>
    California condor
   </title>
   <media mediaid="7752" type="image" url="/52/7752-004-A630B2F2.jpg"/>
   <caption>
    California condor (
    <e type="italic">
     Gymnogyps californianus
    </e>
    ).
   </caption>
   <credit>
    John Borneman—The National Audubon Society Collection/Photo Researchers
   </credit>
  </assembly>
  <assemblyref assemblyid="a4958"/>
  Soaring is sustained gliding without power input. It is attained by many birds (especially large forms, such as condors and albatrosses) and a few insects (
  <e type="italic">
   e.g.,
  </e>
  monarch butterfly). In order to remain airborne, the soarer must glide in a column of air that is rising at a rate exceeding the relative rate of descent of the gliding animal.
 </p>
 <copyright>
  Encyclopædia Britannica
 </copyright>
</article>