<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "syndication_xml.dtd">
<article articleid="34656" articletypeid="1" language="en_us" lastupdate="2021-Jun-30 22:02:03" url="/article/flower/34656" version="13">
 <title>
  flower
 </title>
 <p>
  <assembly id="a73068" url="/assembly/view/73068">
   <media mediaid="73184" type="image" url="/84/73184-004-E5A450B5.jpg"/>
   <caption>
    Sunflower field in Fargo, North Dakota.
   </caption>
   <credit>
    Bruce Fritz—ARS/USDA
   </credit>
  </assembly>
  <e type="bold">
   flower
  </e>
  ,
  <assemblyref assemblyid="a73068"/>
  the characteristic reproductive structure of
  <xref articleid="111083">
   angiosperms
  </xref>
  . As popularly used, the term “flower” especially applies when part or all of the reproductive structure is distinctive in colour and form.
 </p>
 <p>
  In their range of colour, size, form, and anatomical arrangement, flowers present a seemingly endless variety of combinations. They range in size from minute blossoms to giant blooms. In some plants, such as
  <xref articleid="60855">
   poppy
  </xref>
  ,
  <xref articleid="50050">
   magnolia
  </xref>
  ,
  <xref articleid="73724">
   tulip
  </xref>
  , and
  <xref articleid="59530">
   petunia
  </xref>
  , each flower is relatively large and showy and is produced singly, while in other plants, such as
  <xref articleid="471800">
   aster
  </xref>
  ,
  <xref articleid="68361">
   snapdragon
  </xref>
  , and
  <xref articleid="48249">
   lilac
  </xref>
  , the individual flowers may be very small and are borne in a distinctive cluster known as an
  <xref articleid="42396">
   inflorescence
  </xref>
  . Regardless of their variety, all flowers have a uniform function, the reproduction of the species through the production of
  <xref articleid="473280">
   seed
  </xref>
  .
 </p>
 <h1 id="h343911">
  <title>
   Form and types
  </title>
  <p>
   <assembly id="a148669" url="/assembly/view/148669">
    <title>
     flower parts
    </title>
    <media mediaid="91239" type="image" url="/39/91239-004-44353E32.jpg"/>
    <caption>
     Parts of a flower.
    </caption>
    <credit>
     Encyclopædia Britannica, Inc.
    </credit>
   </assembly>
   <assembly id="a50549" url="/assembly/view/50549">
    <media mediaid="58073" type="image" url="/73/58073-004-3E87023C.jpg"/>
    <caption>
     (Left) Generalized flower with parts; (right) diagram showing arrangement of floral parts in cross section at the flower’s base
    </caption>
    <credit>
     Encyclopædia Britannica, Inc.
    </credit>
   </assembly>
   <assemblyref assemblyid="a148669"/>
   <assemblyref assemblyid="a50549"/>
   Basically, each flower consists of a floral axis upon which are borne the essential organs of reproduction (
   <xref articleid="473383">
    stamens
   </xref>
   and
   <xref articleid="60194">
    pistils
   </xref>
   ) and usually accessory organs (sepals and petals); the latter may serve to both attract pollinating insects and protect the essential organs. The floral axis is a greatly modified stem; unlike vegetative stems, which bear
   <xref articleid="47499">
    leaves
   </xref>
   , it is usually contracted, so that the parts of the flower are crowded together on the stem tip, the receptacle. The flower parts are usually arrayed in whorls (or cycles) but may also be disposed spirally, especially if the axis is elongate. There are commonly four distinct whorls of flower parts: (1) an outer calyx consisting of sepals; within it lies (2) the corolla, consisting of petals; (3) the androecium, or group of stamens; and in the centre is (4) the gynoecium, consisting of the pistils.
  </p>
  <p>
   <assembly id="a140107" url="/assembly/view/140107">
    <title>
     pistil
    </title>
    <media mediaid="137317" type="image" url="/17/137317-004-1F1BDE94.jpg"/>
    <caption>
     Lily with a pistil surrounded by stamens.
    </caption>
    <credit>
     iStockphoto/Thinkstock
    </credit>
   </assembly>
   <assemblyref assemblyid="a140107"/>
   The sepals and petals together make up the perianth, or floral envelope. The sepals are usually greenish and often resemble reduced leaves, while the petals are usually colourful and showy. Sepals and petals that are indistinguishable, as in lilies and tulips, are sometimes referred to as tepals. The androecium, or male parts of the flower, comprise the stamens, each of which consists of a supporting filament and an anther, in which pollen is produced. The gynoecium, or female parts of the flower, comprises one or more pistils, each of which consists of an ovary, with an upright extension, the style, on the top of which rests the stigma, the pollen-receptive surface. The ovary encloses the
   <xref articleid="57780">
    ovules
   </xref>
   , or potential seeds. A pistil may be simple, made up of a single
   <xref articleid="471977">
    carpel
   </xref>
   , or ovule-bearing modified leaf; or compound, formed from several carpels joined together.
  </p>
  <p>
   <assembly id="a8397" url="/assembly/view/8397">
    <media mediaid="5632" type="image" url="/32/5632-004-8445C644.jpg"/>
    <caption>
     A perfect flower with floral structures in multiples of three,
     <e type="italic">
      Tulipa
     </e>
     (tulip) has a three-lobed stigma, six stamens, and six distinct perianth parts.
    </caption>
    <credit>
     © Harry Haralambou/Peter Arnold, Inc.
    </credit>
   </assembly>
   A flower having sepals, petals, stamens, and pistils is complete; lacking one or more of such structures, it is said to be incomplete. Stamens and pistils are not present together in all flowers. When both are present the flower is said to be perfect, or bisexual, regardless of a lack of any other part that renders it incomplete (
   <e type="italic">
    see
   </e>
   <assemblyref assemblyid="a8397">
    photograph
   </assemblyref>
   ). A flower that lacks stamens is pistillate, or female, while one that lacks pistils is said to be staminate, or male. When the same plant bears unisexual flowers of both sexes, it is said to be monoecious (e.g., tuberous begonia, hazel, oak, corn); when the male and female flowers are on different plants, the plant is dioecious (e.g., date, holly, cottonwood, willow); when there are male, female, and bisexual flowers on the same plant, the plant is termed polygamous.
  </p>
  <p>
   <assembly id="a226898" url="/assembly/view/226898">
    <title>
     Compare the Rafflesia arnoldii’s massive bloom with Amorphophallus titanum’s towering inflorescence
    </title>
    <media mediaid="195546" thumburl="/46/195546-049-53B4F9AE.jpg" type="video" url=""/>
    <caption>
     An overview of the world’s largest blooms: the monster flower (
     <e type="italic">
      Rafflesia arnoldii
     </e>
     ) and the titan arum (
     <e type="italic">
      Amorphophallus titanum
     </e>
     ). To attract pollinators, both produce a rotting-meat scent, which has earned them the nickname “corpse flower.”
    </caption>
    <credit>
     Encyclopædia Britannica, Inc.
    </credit>
   </assembly>
   <assembly id="a8457" url="/assembly/view/8457">
    <media mediaid="5645" type="image" url="/45/5645-004-7461C1BD.jpg"/>
    <caption>
     The radiate head of the treasure flower (
     <e type="italic">
      Gazania rigens
     </e>
     ), a daisylike inflorescence composed of disk flowers in the centre surrounded by marginal ray flowers.
    </caption>
    <credit>
     E.S. Ross
    </credit>
   </assembly>
   <assembly id="a8446" url="/assembly/view/8446">
    <media mediaid="5630" type="image" url="/30/5630-004-3E069604.jpg"/>
    <caption>
     Bilateral symmetry of the orchid (
     <e type="italic">
      Vanda
     </e>
     )
    </caption>
    <credit>
     E.S. Ross
    </credit>
   </assembly>
   <assemblyref assemblyid="a226898"/>
   A flower may be radially symmetrical (
   <e type="italic">
    see
   </e>
   <assemblyref assemblyid="a8457">
    photograph
   </assemblyref>
   ), as in roses and petunias, in which case it is termed regular or actinomorphic. A bilaterally symmetrical flower, as in orchids (
   <e type="italic">
    see
   </e>
   <assemblyref assemblyid="a8446">
    photograph
   </assemblyref>
   ) and snapdragons, is irregular or zygomorphic.
  </p>
 </h1>
 <h1 id="h343912">
  <title>
   Pollination
  </title>
  <p>
   <assembly id="a53831" url="/assembly/view/53831">
    <title>
     how flowering plants reproduce
    </title>
    <media mediaid="62941" type="image" url="/41/62941-004-E3F5377B.jpg"/>
    <caption>
     Reproduction in flowering plants begins with pollination, the transfer of pollen from anther to stigma on the same flower or to the stigma of another flower on the same plant (self-pollination) or from the anther on one plant to the stigma of another plant (cross-pollination). Once the pollen grain lodges on the stigma, a pollen tube grows from the pollen grain to an ovule. Two sperm nuclei then pass through the pollen tube. One of them unites with the egg nucleus and produces a zygote. The other sperm nucleus unites with two polar nuclei to produce an endosperm nucleus. The fertilized ovule develops into a seed.
    </caption>
    <credit>
     Encyclopædia Britannica, Inc.
    </credit>
   </assembly>
   <assemblyref assemblyid="a53831"/>
   The stamens and pistils are directly involved with the production of
   <xref articleid="473280">
    seed
   </xref>
   . The stamen bears microsporangia (spore cases) in which are developed numerous microspores (potential
   <xref articleid="60648">
    pollen
   </xref>
   grains); the pistil bears ovules, each enclosing an egg cell. When a microspore germinates, it is known as a pollen grain. When the pollen sacs in a stamen’s anther are ripe, the anther releases them and the pollen is shed.
   <xref articleid="110806">
    Fertilization
   </xref>
   can occur only if the pollen grains are transferred from the anther to the stigma of a pistil, a process known as
   <xref articleid="110808">
    pollination
   </xref>
   .
  </p>
  <p>
   <assembly id="a148671" url="/assembly/view/148671">
    <title>
     self-pollination
    </title>
    <media mediaid="95387" type="image" url="/87/95387-004-63854D5B.jpg"/>
    <caption>
     The process of self-pollination in an angiosperm.
    </caption>
    <credit>
     Encyclopædia Britannica, Inc.
    </credit>
   </assembly>
   <assembly id="a89769" url="/assembly/view/89769">
    <media mediaid="95388" type="image" url="/88/95388-004-6E2508A9.jpg"/>
    <caption>
     Most plants depend on a carrier, such as a bee, to bring pollen to them from another plant.
    </caption>
    <credit>
     Encyclopædia Britannica, Inc.
    </credit>
   </assembly>
   <assembly id="a8438" url="/assembly/view/8438">
    <media mediaid="5619" type="image" url="/19/5619-004-06529655.jpg"/>
    <caption>
     Spikes of sedge (
     <e type="italic">
      Carex pendula
     </e>
     ) showing reduced floral parts adapted to wind pollination. The pollen bursts forth from the pendulous inflorescences as they sway in the wind.
    </caption>
    <credit>
     © Stephen Dalton/Natural History Photographic Agency
    </credit>
   </assembly>
   <assembly id="a8436" url="/assembly/view/8436">
    <title>
     iris
    </title>
    <media mediaid="5613" type="image" url="/13/5613-004-125C8AD7.jpg"/>
    <caption>
     A blue iris (
     <e type="italic">
      Iris
     </e>
     ) with contrasting yellow nectar guides indicating the location of the nectar to the honeybee (
     <e type="italic">
      Apis mellifera
     </e>
     ). Flecks of pollen grains dislodged from the stamens by the foraging bee can be seen on the bee’s body.
    </caption>
    <credit>
     © G.A. Maclean/Oxford Scientific Films
    </credit>
   </assembly>
   <assemblyref assemblyid="a148671"/>
   <assemblyref assemblyid="a89769"/>
   There are two chief kinds of pollination: (1) self-pollination, the pollination of a stigma by pollen from the same flower or another flower on the same plant; and (2) cross-pollination, the transfer of pollen from the anther of a flower of one plant to the stigma of the flower of another plant of the same species. Self-pollination occurs in many species, but in the others, perhaps the majority, it is prevented by such adaptations as the structure of the flower, self-incompatibility, and the maturation of stamens and pistils of the same flower or plant at different times. Cross-pollination may be brought about by a number of agents, chiefly insects and wind. Wind-pollinated flowers (
   <e type="italic">
    see
   </e>
   <assemblyref assemblyid="a8438">
    photograph
   </assemblyref>
   ) generally can be recognized by their lack of colour, odour, or nectar, while animal-pollinated flowers (
   <e type="italic">
    see
   </e>
   <assemblyref assemblyid="a8436">
    photograph
   </assemblyref>
   ) are conspicuous by virtue of their structure, colour, or the production of scent or
   <xref articleid="55160">
    nectar
   </xref>
   .
  </p>
  <p>
   After a pollen grain has reached the stigma, it germinates, and a pollen tube protrudes from it. This tube, containing two male gametes (sperms), extends into the ovary and reaches the ovule, discharging its gametes so that one fertilizes the egg cell, which becomes an embryo, and the other joins with two polar nuclei to form the
   <xref articleid="32623">
    endosperm
   </xref>
   . (Normally many pollen grains fall on a stigma; they all may germinate, but only one pollen tube enters any one ovule.) Following fertilization, the embryo is on its way to becoming a seed, and at this time the ovary itself enlarges to form the
   <xref articleid="35520">
    fruit
   </xref>
   .
  </p>
 </h1>
 <h1 id="h343913">
  <title>
   Cultural significance
  </title>
  <p>
   Flowers have been symbols of beauty in most civilizations of the world, and flower giving is still among the most popular of social amenities. As gifts, flowers serve as expressions of affection for spouses, other family members, and friends; as decorations at weddings and other ceremonies; as tokens of respect for the deceased; as cheering gifts to the bedridden; and as expressions of thanks or appreciation. Most flowers bought by the public are grown in commercial greenhouses or horticultural fields and then sold through wholesalers to retail florists.
   <e type="italic">
    See also
   </e>
   articles on individual flowers (e.g.,
   <xref articleid="20398">
    carnation
   </xref>
   ;
   <xref articleid="49030">
    lotus
   </xref>
   ;
   <xref articleid="59530">
    petunia
   </xref>
   ;
   <xref articleid="64083">
    rose
   </xref>
   ;
   <xref articleid="73724">
    tulip
   </xref>
   ).
  </p>
  <signature>
   EB Editors
  </signature>
 </h1>
 <copyright>
  Encyclopædia Britannica
 </copyright>
</article>