<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "syndication_xml.dtd">
<article articleid="34721" articletypeid="1" language="en_us" lastupdate="2021-Jun-30 22:02:30" url="/article/focusing/34721" version="4">
 <title>
  focusing
 </title>
 <p>
  <assembly id="a91409" url="/assembly/view/91409">
   <title>
    double convex lens
   </title>
   <media mediaid="96592" type="image" url="/92/96592-004-10A78D14.jpg"/>
   <caption>
    A double convex lens, or converging lens, focuses the diverging, or blurred, light rays from a distant object by refracting (bending) the rays twice. At the front side of the lens, the rays are bent toward the normal (the perpendicular to the surface) because the glass is a denser medium than the air, and, at the back side of the lens, the rays are bent away from the normal as the rays pass into the less-dense medium of the air. This double bending causes the rays to converge at a focal point behind the lens so that a sharper image can be seen or photographed.
   </caption>
   <credit>
    Encyclopædia Britannica, Inc.
   </credit>
  </assembly>
  <e type="bold">
   focusing
  </e>
  , also called
  <e type="bold">
   ocular accommodation
  </e>
  ,
  <assemblyref assemblyid="a91409"/>
  ability of the
  <xref articleid="47769">
   lens
  </xref>
  to alter its shape to allow objects to be seen clearly.
 </p>
 <p>
  <assembly id="a100398" url="/assembly/view/100398">
   <media mediaid="85239" type="image" url="/39/85239-004-1AC74BF9.jpg"/>
   <caption>
    The shape of the lens plays an important role in allowing the eye to bring objects into focus. Different types of corrective lenses are used, depending on an individual’s ability to change lens curvature for accommodation. Convex lenses produce magnified images of objects, whereas concave lenses produce small images of objects.
   </caption>
   <credit>
    Encyclopædia Britannica, Inc.
   </credit>
  </assembly>
  <assemblyref assemblyid="a100398"/>
  In humans, the forward surface of the lens is made more convex for seeing objects up close. At the same time, the
  <xref articleid="61930">
   pupil
  </xref>
  becomes smaller, and the two
  <xref articleid="109527">
   eyes
  </xref>
  turn inward (i.e., cross or converge) to the point that their gaze is fixed on the object. The capsule, or envelope enclosing the lens of the eye, is attached by suspensory
  <xref articleid="48211">
   ligaments
  </xref>
  (called zonular fibres) to the ringlike ciliary
  <xref articleid="110701">
   muscle
  </xref>
  that encircles the lens. The inside diameter of this muscle is greatest when the muscle is relaxed and smallest when the muscle is contracted. Thus, when the gaze is fixed on a distant object, as when a
  <xref articleid="18803">
   camera
  </xref>
  is set at infinity, the ciliary muscle relaxes, the muscle’s inside diameter is increased, more pull is exerted on the lens by the ligaments, and the front surface of the lens is flattened. When near objects are viewed, the ciliary muscle contracts, the ligaments relax, and the lens, being elastic, bulges in front and gains more curvature. This increased curvature enhances the focusing power of the lens and brings the nearer object to better focus on the
  <xref articleid="63313">
   retina
  </xref>
  . This process, known as accommodation, is controlled by parasympathetic fibres of the third (oculomotor)
  <xref articleid="26759">
   cranial nerve
  </xref>
  . As a person ages, the lens hardens and slowly loses its ability to change shape and bring near objects into better focus. This condition is called
  <xref articleid="61272">
   presbyopia
  </xref>
  and generally becomes evident after age 40.
 </p>
 <signature>
  Daniel M. Albert
 </signature>
 <signature>
  David M. Gamm M.D.
 </signature>
 <copyright>
  Encyclopædia Britannica
 </copyright>
</article>