<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "syndication_xml.dtd">
<article articleid="35365" articletypeid="1" language="en_us" lastupdate="2021-Jun-30 22:06:50" url="/article/frequency/35365" version="5">
 <title>
  frequency
 </title>
 <p>
  <e type="bold">
   frequency
  </e>
  , in
  <xref articleid="108654">
   physics
  </xref>
  , the number of
  <xref articleid="473598">
   waves
  </xref>
  that pass a fixed point in unit time; also, the number of cycles or vibrations undergone during one unit of time by a body in
  <xref articleid="59261">
   periodic motion
  </xref>
  . A body in periodic motion is said to have undergone one cycle or one vibration after passing through a series of events or positions and returning to its original state.
  <e type="italic">
   See also
  </e>
  <xref articleid="7613">
   angular velocity
  </xref>
  ;
  <xref articleid="67869">
   simple harmonic motion
  </xref>
  .
 </p>
 <p>
  If the period, or time interval, required to complete one cycle or vibration is
  <fraction>
   <num>
    1
   </num>
   <den>
    2
   </den>
  </fraction>
  second, the frequency is 2 per second; if the period is
  <fraction>
   <num>
    1
   </num>
   <den>
    100
   </den>
  </fraction>
  of an hour, the frequency is 100 per hour. In general, the frequency is the reciprocal of the period, or time interval; i.e., frequency = 1/period = 1/(time interval). The frequency with which the
  <xref articleid="53598">
   Moon
  </xref>
  revolves around
  <xref articleid="110147">
   Earth
  </xref>
  is slightly more than 12 cycles per year. The frequency of the A string of a
  <xref articleid="75451">
   violin
  </xref>
  is 440 vibrations or cycles per second.
 </p>
 <p>
  The symbols most often used for frequency are
  <e type="italic">
   f
  </e>
  and the Greek letters nu (ν) and omega (ω). Nu is used more often when specifying
  <xref articleid="106022">
   electromagnetic waves
  </xref>
  , such as
  <xref articleid="110443">
   light
  </xref>
  ,
  <xref articleid="77656">
   X-rays
  </xref>
  , and
  <xref articleid="35974">
   gamma rays
  </xref>
  . Omega is usually used to describe the angular frequency—that is, how much an object rotates or revolves in radians per unit time. Usually, frequency is expressed in the
  <xref articleid="40251">
   hertz
  </xref>
  unit, named in honour of the 19th-century German physicist
  <xref articleid="40253">
   Heinrich Rudolf Hertz
  </xref>
  , one hertz being equal to one cycle per second, abbreviated Hz; one kilohertz (kHz) is 1,000 Hz, and one megahertz (MHz) is 1,000,000 Hz. In
  <xref articleid="110407">
   spectroscopy
  </xref>
  another unit of frequency, the
  <xref articleid="76322">
   wavenumber
  </xref>
  , the number of waves in a unit of distance, is sometimes used.
 </p>
 <signature>
  EB Editors
 </signature>
 <copyright>
  Encyclopædia Britannica
 </copyright>
</article>