<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "syndication_xml.dtd">
<article articleid="35520" articletypeid="1" language="en_us" lastupdate="2022-Apr-25 07:28:29" url="/article/fruit/35520" version="14">
 <title>
  fruit
 </title>
 <p>
  <assembly id="a106974" url="/assembly/view/106974">
   <title>
    apricots
   </title>
   <media mediaid="75886" type="image" url="/86/75886-004-BF2B31CA.jpg"/>
   <caption>
    Apricots.
   </caption>
   <credit>
    © Andreas-Semerad/iStock.com
   </credit>
  </assembly>
  <e type="bold">
   fruit
  </e>
  ,
  <assemblyref assemblyid="a106974"/>
  the fleshy or dry ripened
  <xref articleid="57757">
   ovary
  </xref>
  of a
  <xref articleid="111083">
   flowering plant
  </xref>
  , enclosing the seed or seeds. Thus,
  <xref articleid="8093">
   apricots
  </xref>
  ,
  <xref articleid="12094">
   bananas
  </xref>
  , and
  <xref articleid="37748">
   grapes
  </xref>
  , as well as
  <xref articleid="13929">
   bean
  </xref>
  pods,
  <xref articleid="26316">
   corn
  </xref>
  grains,
  <xref articleid="72825">
   tomatoes
  </xref>
  ,
  <xref articleid="28116">
   cucumbers
  </xref>
  , and (in their shells)
  <xref articleid="471695">
   acorns
  </xref>
  and
  <xref articleid="5864">
   almonds
  </xref>
  , are all technically fruits. Popularly, however, the term is restricted to the ripened ovaries that are sweet and either succulent or pulpy. For treatment of the cultivation of fruits,
  <e type="italic">
   see
  </e>
  <xref articleid="111037">
   fruit farming
  </xref>
  . For treatment of the nutrient composition and processing of fruits,
  <e type="italic">
   see
  </e>
  <xref articleid="111125">
   fruit processing
  </xref>
  .
 </p>
 <p>
  Botanically, a fruit is a mature ovary and its associated parts. It usually contains seeds, which have developed from the enclosed
  <xref articleid="57780">
   ovule
  </xref>
  after fertilization, although development without
  <xref articleid="110806">
   fertilization
  </xref>
  , called parthenocarpy, is known, for example, in bananas. Fertilization induces various changes in a
  <xref articleid="34656">
   flower
  </xref>
  : the anthers and stigma wither, the petals drop off, and the sepals may be shed or undergo modifications; the ovary enlarges, and the ovules develop into seeds, each containing an embryo plant. The principal purpose of the fruit is the protection and dissemination of the seed. (
  <e type="italic">
   See also
  </e>
  <xref articleid="473280">
   seed
  </xref>
  .)
 </p>
 <p>
  <assembly id="a142640" url="/assembly/view/142640">
   <title>
    Afghanistan: opium poppies
   </title>
   <media mediaid="130261" type="image" url="/61/130261-004-BE5F4C02.jpg"/>
   <caption>
    Collecting resin from opium poppy capsules in a field in Afghanistan, 2008.
   </caption>
   <credit>
    © Venelin Petkov/Dreamstime.com
   </credit>
  </assembly>
  <assemblyref assemblyid="a142640"/>
  Fruits are important sources of
  <xref articleid="472324">
   dietary fibre
  </xref>
  , vitamins (especially
  <xref articleid="75556">
   vitamin C
  </xref>
  ), and
  <xref articleid="7869">
   antioxidants
  </xref>
  . Although fresh fruits are subject to spoilage, their shelf life can be extended by refrigeration or by the removal of oxygen from their storage or packaging containers. Fruits can be processed into juices, jams, and jellies and preserved by dehydration, canning, fermentation, and pickling. Waxes, such as those from bayberries (wax myrtles), and vegetable ivory from the hard fruits of a South American palm species (
  <e type="italic">
   Phytelephas macrocarpa
  </e>
  ) are important fruit-derived products. Various drugs come from fruits, such as
  <xref articleid="53799">
   morphine
  </xref>
  from the fruit of the
  <xref articleid="472986">
   opium poppy
  </xref>
  .
 </p>
 <h1 id="h340189">
  <title>
   Types of fruits
  </title>
  <p>
   <assembly id="a263300" url="/assembly/view/263300">
    <title>
     legume fruit
    </title>
    <media mediaid="174549" type="image" url="/49/174549-004-8FE77B35.jpg"/>
    <caption>
     An open legume fruit of the common pea (
     <e type="italic">
      Pisum sativum
     </e>
     ), showing the immature seeds inside.
    </caption>
    <credit>
     AdstockRF
    </credit>
   </assembly>
   <assemblyref assemblyid="a263300"/>
   The concept of “fruit” is based on such an odd mixture of practical and theoretical considerations that it accommodates cases in which one flower gives rise to several fruits (
   <xref articleid="47212">
    larkspur
   </xref>
   ) as well as cases in which several flowers cooperate in producing one fruit (
   <xref articleid="54200">
    mulberry
   </xref>
   ).
   <xref articleid="58846">
    Pea
   </xref>
   and
   <xref articleid="13929">
    bean
   </xref>
   plants, exemplifying the simplest situation, show in each flower a single
   <xref articleid="60194">
    pistil
   </xref>
   (female structure), traditionally thought of as a megasporophyll or
   <xref articleid="471977">
    carpel
   </xref>
   . The carpel is believed to be the evolutionary product of an originally leaflike organ bearing
   <xref articleid="57780">
    ovules
   </xref>
   along its margin. This organ was somehow folded along the median line, with a meeting and coalescing of the margins of each half, the result being a miniature closed but hollow pod with one row of ovules along the suture. In many members of the
   <xref articleid="623310">
    rose
   </xref>
   and
   <xref articleid="62694">
    buttercup
   </xref>
   families, each flower contains a number of similar single-carpelled pistils, separate and distinct, which together represent what is known as an apocarpous gynoecium. In other cases, two to several carpels (still thought of as megasporophylls, although perhaps not always justifiably) are assumed to have fused to produce a single compound gynoecium (pistil), whose basal part, or ovary, may be uniloculate (with one cavity) or pluriloculate (with several compartments), depending on the method of carpel fusion.
  </p>
  <p>
   Most fruits develop from a single pistil. A fruit resulting from the apocarpous gynoecium (several pistils) of a single flower may be referred to as an aggregate fruit. A multiple fruit represents the gynoecia of several flowers. When additional flower parts, such as the stem axis or floral tube, are retained or participate in fruit formation, as in the
   <xref articleid="8076">
    apple
   </xref>
   or
   <xref articleid="69934">
    strawberry
   </xref>
   , an accessory fruit results.
  </p>
  <p>
   <assembly id="a117903" url="/assembly/view/117903">
    <title>
     seedless watermelon
    </title>
    <media mediaid="124170" type="image" url="/70/124170-004-220109BF.jpg"/>
    <caption>
     A seedless watermelon.
    </caption>
    <credit>
     © bhofack2—iStock/Getty Images
    </credit>
   </assembly>
   <assemblyref assemblyid="a117903"/>
   Certain plants, mostly cultivated varieties, spontaneously produce fruits in the absence of
   <xref articleid="110808">
    pollination
   </xref>
   and
   <xref articleid="110806">
    fertilization
   </xref>
   ; such natural parthenocarpy leads to seedless fruits such as
   <xref articleid="12094">
    bananas
   </xref>
   ,
   <xref articleid="57261">
    oranges
   </xref>
   ,
   <xref articleid="37748">
    grapes
   </xref>
   , and
   <xref articleid="28116">
    cucumbers
   </xref>
   . Since 1934, seedless fruits of
   <xref articleid="72825">
    tomato
   </xref>
   , cucumber,
   <xref articleid="59164">
    peppers
   </xref>
   ,
   <xref articleid="40808">
    holly
   </xref>
   , and others have been obtained for commercial use by administering plant growth substances, such as indoleacetic acid, indolebutyric acid, naphthalene acetic acid, and β-naphthoxyacetic acid, to the ovaries in flowers (induced parthenocarpy).
  </p>
  <p>
   Classification systems for mature fruits take into account the number of carpels constituting the original ovary, dehiscence (opening) versus indehiscence, and dryness versus fleshiness. The properties of the ripened ovary wall, or pericarp, which may develop entirely or in part into fleshy, fibrous, or stony tissue, are important. Often three distinct pericarp layers can be identified: the outer (exocarp), the middle (mesocarp), and the inner (endocarp). All purely morphological systems (i.e., classification schemes based on structural features) are artificial. They ignore the fact that fruits can be understood only functionally and dynamically.
  </p>
  <p>
   There are two broad categories of fruits: fleshy fruits, in which the pericarp and accessory parts develop into succulent tissues, as in
   <xref articleid="32077">
    eggplants
   </xref>
   ,
   <xref articleid="57261">
    oranges
   </xref>
   , and
   <xref articleid="69934">
    strawberries
   </xref>
   ; and dry fruits, in which the entire pericarp becomes dry at maturity. Fleshy fruits include (1) the berries, such as
   <xref articleid="72825">
    tomatoes
   </xref>
   , blueberries, and
   <xref articleid="23855">
    cherries
   </xref>
   , in which the entire pericarp and the accessory parts are succulent tissue, (2) aggregate fruits, such as
   <xref articleid="15523">
    blackberries
   </xref>
   and strawberries, which form from a single flower with many pistils, each of which develops into fruitlets, and (3) multiple fruits, such as
   <xref articleid="60080">
    pineapples
   </xref>
   and
   <xref articleid="54200">
    mulberries
   </xref>
   , which develop from the mature ovaries of an entire inflorescence. Dry fruits include the
   <xref articleid="47652">
    legumes
   </xref>
   ,
   <xref articleid="22133">
    cereal grains
   </xref>
   ,
   <xref articleid="20188">
    capsulate fruits
   </xref>
   , and
   <xref articleid="56543">
    nuts
   </xref>
   .
  </p>
  <p>
   <assembly id="a211664" url="/assembly/view/211664">
    <title>
     Brazil nut
    </title>
    <media mediaid="190779" type="image" url="/79/190779-004-D0AC91D4.jpg"/>
    <caption>
     Hard indehiscent fruits of the Brazil nut tree (
     <e type="italic">
      Bertholletia excelsa
     </e>
     ). The fruit on the left has been opened to reveal the large edible seeds in their shells. The tree is found in the Amazonian forests of Brazil, Peru, Colombia, and Ecuador.
    </caption>
    <credit>
     Fernanda Preto/Alamy
    </credit>
   </assembly>
   <assemblyref assemblyid="a211664"/>
   As strikingly exemplified by the word
   <e type="italic">
    nut
   </e>
   , popular terms often do not properly describe the botanical nature of certain fruits. A
   <xref articleid="16287">
    Brazil nut
   </xref>
   , for example, is a thick-walled seed enclosed in a likewise thick-walled capsule along with several sister seeds. A
   <xref articleid="24606">
    coconut
   </xref>
   is a
   <xref articleid="31262">
    drupe
   </xref>
   (a stony-seeded fruit) with a fibrous outer part. A
   <xref articleid="75998">
    walnut
   </xref>
   is a drupe in which the pericarp has differentiated into a fleshy outer husk and an inner hard “shell”; the “meat” represents the seed—two large convoluted
   <xref articleid="26542">
    cotyledons
   </xref>
   , a minute epicotyl and hypocotyl, and a thin papery seed coat. A
   <xref articleid="58869">
    peanut
   </xref>
   is an indehiscent legume fruit. An
   <xref articleid="5864">
    almond
   </xref>
   is a drupe “stone”; i.e., the hardened endocarp usually contains a single seed. Botanically speaking, blackberries and
   <xref articleid="62742">
    raspberries
   </xref>
   are not true
   <xref articleid="78881">
    berries
   </xref>
   but aggregates of tiny drupes. A
   <xref articleid="44170">
    juniper
   </xref>
   “berry” is not a fruit at all but the
   <xref articleid="25136">
    cone
   </xref>
   of a
   <xref articleid="110285">
    gymnosperm
   </xref>
   . A mulberry is a multiple fruit made up of small nutlets surrounded by fleshy sepals. And strawberry represents a much-swollen receptacle (the tip of the flower stalk bearing the flower parts) bearing on its convex surface an aggregation of tiny brown
   <xref articleid="3525">
    achenes
   </xref>
   (small single-seeded fruits).
  </p>
 </h1>
 <h1 id="h340190">
  <title>
   Dispersal
  </title>
  <p>
   Fruits play an important role in the seed dispersal of many plant species. In dehiscent fruits, such as poppy capsules, the seeds are usually dispersed directly from the fruits, which may remain on the plant. In fleshy or indehiscent fruits, the seeds and fruit are commonly moved away from the parent plant together. In many plants, such as
   <xref articleid="37759">
    grasses
   </xref>
   and
   <xref articleid="47934">
    lettuce
   </xref>
   , the outer integument and ovary wall are completely fused, so seed and fruit form one entity; such seeds and fruits can logically be described together as “dispersal units,” or diaspores. For further discussion on seed dispersal,
   <e type="italic">
    see
   </e>
   <xref articleid="473280" refid="h339731">
    seed: agents of dispersal
   </xref>
   .
  </p>
  <h2 id="h340191">
   <title>
    Animal dispersal
   </title>
   <p>
    A wide variety of animals aid in the dispersal of seeds, fruits, and diaspores. Many birds and mammals, ranging in size from mice and
    <xref articleid="44555">
     kangaroo rats
    </xref>
    to
    <xref articleid="32357">
     elephants
    </xref>
    , act as dispersers when they eat fruits and diaspores. In the tropics, chiropterochory (dispersal by large bats such as flying foxes,
    <e type="italic">
     Pteropus
    </e>
    ) is particularly important. Fruits adapted to these animals are relatively large and drab in colour with large seeds and a striking (often rank) odour. Such fruits are accessible to bats because of the pagoda-like structure of the tree canopy, fruit placement on the main trunk, or suspension from long stalks that hang free of the foliage. Examples include
    <xref articleid="50525">
     mangoes
    </xref>
    ,
    <xref articleid="38335">
     guavas
    </xref>
    ,
    <xref articleid="16301">
     breadfruit
    </xref>
    ,
    <xref articleid="20424">
     carob
    </xref>
    , and several
    <xref articleid="34185">
     fig
    </xref>
    species. In South Africa a desert melon (
    <e type="italic">
     Cucumis humifructus
    </e>
    ) participates in a symbiotic relationship with
    <xref articleid="3204">
     aardvarks
    </xref>
    —the animals eat the fruit for its water content and bury their own dung, which contains the seeds, near their burrows.
   </p>
   <p>
    <assembly id="a263301" url="/assembly/view/263301">
     <title>
      burdock
     </title>
     <media mediaid="157782" type="image" url="/82/157782-004-3CF89A5D.jpg"/>
     <caption>
      Burdock (
      <e type="italic">
       Arctium
      </e>
      species) fruit.
     </caption>
     <credit>
      © Rubik Oleg/stock.adobe.com
     </credit>
    </assembly>
    <assemblyref assemblyid="a263301"/>
    Additionally, furry terrestrial mammals are the agents most frequently involved in epizoochory, the inadvertent carrying by animals of dispersal units. Burlike fruits, or those diaspores provided with spines, hooks, claws, bristles, barbs, grapples, and prickles, are genuine hitchhikers, clinging tenaciously to their carriers. Their functional shape is achieved in various ways: in
    <xref articleid="14083">
     cleavers
    </xref>
    , or goose grass (
    <e type="italic">
     Galium aparine
    </e>
    ), and in enchanter’s nightshade (
    <e type="italic">
     Circaea lutetiana
    </e>
    ), the hooks are part of the fruit itself; in common
    <xref articleid="4083">
     agrimony
    </xref>
    (
    <e type="italic">
     Agrimonia eupatoria
    </e>
    ), the fruit is covered by a persistent calyx (the sepals, parts of the flower, which remain attached beyond the usual period) equipped with hooks; and in
    <xref articleid="11413">
     wood avens
    </xref>
    (
    <e type="italic">
     Geum urbanum
    </e>
    ), the persistent styles have hooked tips. Other examples are bur marigolds, or
    <xref articleid="79123">
     beggar’s-ticks
    </xref>
    (
    <e type="italic">
     Bidens
    </e>
    species);
    <xref articleid="17939">
     buffalo bur
    </xref>
    (
    <e type="italic">
     Solanum rostratum
    </e>
    );
    <xref articleid="471938">
     burdock
    </xref>
    (
    <e type="italic">
     Arctium
    </e>
    );
    <e type="italic">
     Acaena
    </e>
    ; and many
    <e type="italic">
     Medicago
    </e>
    species. The last-named, with dispersal units highly resistant to damage from hot water and certain chemicals (dyes), have achieved wide global distribution through the wool trade. A somewhat different principle is employed by the so-called trample burrs, said to lodge themselves between the hooves of large grazing mammals. Examples are mule grab (
    <e type="italic">
     Proboscidea
    </e>
    ) and the African grapple plant (
    <e type="italic">
     Harpagophytum
    </e>
    ). In water burrs, such as those of the water chestnut
    <e type="italic">
     Trapa
    </e>
    , the spines should probably be considered as anchoring devices.
   </p>
   <p>
    <assembly id="a155752" url="/assembly/view/155752">
     <title>
      chesnut-mandibled toucan
     </title>
     <media mediaid="146384" type="image" url="/84/146384-004-47401008.jpg"/>
     <caption>
      Chestnut-mandibled, or Swainson’s, toucan (
      <e type="italic">
       Ramphastos swainsonii
      </e>
      ) consuming a nut.
     </caption>
     <credit>
      © pablo_hernan/Fotolia
     </credit>
    </assembly>
    <assemblyref assemblyid="a155752"/>
    Birds, being preening animals, rarely carry burlike diaspores on their bodies. They do, however, transport the very sticky (viscid) fruits of
    <e type="italic">
     Pisonia
    </e>
    , a tropical tree of the four-o’clock family, to distant Pacific islands in this way. Small diaspores, such as those of sedges and certain grasses, may also be carried in the mud sticking to waterfowl and terrestrial birds.
   </p>
   <p>
    Synzoochory, deliberate carrying of diaspores by animals, is practiced when birds carry diaspores in their beaks. The European mistle thrush (
    <e type="italic">
     Turdus viscivorus
    </e>
    ) deposits the viscid seeds of
    <xref articleid="53005">
     mistletoe
    </xref>
    (
    <e type="italic">
     Viscum album
    </e>
    ) on potential host plants when, after a meal of the berries, it whets its bill on branches or simply regurgitates the seeds. The North American (
    <e type="italic">
     Phoradendron
    </e>
    ) and Australian (
    <e type="italic">
     Amyema
    </e>
    ) mistletoes are dispersed by various birds, and the comparable tropical species of the plant family
    <xref articleid="48946">
     Loranthaceae
    </xref>
    by flower-peckers (of the bird family
    <xref articleid="30324">
     Dicaeidae
    </xref>
    ), which have a highly specialized
    <xref articleid="36945">
     gizzard
    </xref>
    that allows seeds to pass through but retains insects. Plants may also profit from the forgetfulness and sloppy habits of certain nut-eating birds that cache part of their food but neglect to recover everything or that drop units on their way to a hiding place. Best known in this respect are the
    <xref articleid="56546">
     nutcrackers
    </xref>
    (
    <e type="italic">
     Nucifraga
    </e>
    ), which feed largely on the “nuts” of
    <xref articleid="14091">
     beech
    </xref>
    ,
    <xref articleid="56599">
     oak
    </xref>
    ,
    <xref articleid="75998">
     walnut
    </xref>
    ,
    <xref articleid="23893">
     chestnut
    </xref>
    , and
    <xref articleid="34250">
     hazelnut
    </xref>
    ; the
    <xref articleid="43450">
     jays
    </xref>
    (
    <e type="italic">
     Garrulus
    </e>
    ), which hide hazelnuts and acorns; the
    <xref articleid="56547">
     nuthatches
    </xref>
    ; and the California
    <xref articleid="77419">
     woodpecker
    </xref>
    (
    <e type="italic">
     Melanerpes formicivorus
    </e>
    ), which may embed literally thousands of acorns,
    <xref articleid="5864">
     almonds
    </xref>
    , and
    <xref articleid="58898">
     pecan
    </xref>
    nuts in bark fissures or holes of trees.
    <xref articleid="105980">
     Rodents
    </xref>
    may aid in dispersal by stealing the embedded diaspores and burying them. In Germany, an average jay may transport about 4,600 acorns per season, over distances of up to 4 km (2.5 miles).
   </p>
   <p>
    <assembly id="a217510" url="/assembly/view/217510">
     <title>
      Bohemian waxwing
     </title>
     <media mediaid="157760" type="image" url="/60/157760-004-C20E497A.jpg"/>
     <caption>
      Bohemian waxwing (
      <e type="italic">
       Bombycilla garrulus
      </e>
      ) eating fruit.
     </caption>
     <credit>
      © Ornitolog82/Fotolia
     </credit>
    </assembly>
    <assemblyref assemblyid="a217510"/>
    Most ornithochores (plants with bird-dispersed seeds) have conspicuous diaspores attractive to such fruit-eating birds as
    <xref articleid="72307">
     thrushes
    </xref>
    ,
    <xref articleid="59990">
     pigeons
    </xref>
    ,
    <xref articleid="13307">
     barbets
    </xref>
    (members of the bird family Capitonidae),
    <xref articleid="73033">
     toucans
    </xref>
    (family Ramphastidae), and
    <xref articleid="41074">
     hornbills
    </xref>
    (family Bucerotidae), all of which either excrete or regurgitate the hard part undamaged. Such diaspores have a fleshy, sweet, or oil-containing edible part; a striking colour (often red or orange); no pronounced smell; protection against being eaten prematurely, in the form of acids and tannins that are present only in the green fruit; protection of the seed against digestion, afforded by bitterness, hardness, or the presence of poisonous compounds; permanent attachment; and, finally, absence of a hard outer cover. In contrast to bat-dispersed diaspores, they occupy no special position on the plant. Examples are rose hips,
    <xref articleid="60444">
     plums
    </xref>
    ,
    <xref articleid="30804">
     dogwood
    </xref>
    fruits,
    <xref articleid="13304">
     barberry
    </xref>
    , red
    <xref articleid="28266">
     currant
    </xref>
    ,
    <xref articleid="54200">
     mulberry
    </xref>
    ,
    <xref articleid="56548">
     nutmeg
    </xref>
    fruits,
    <xref articleid="34227">
     figs
    </xref>
    ,
    <xref articleid="15523">
     blackberries
    </xref>
    , and others. The natural and abundant occurrence of
    <xref articleid="33231">
     <e type="italic">
      Euonymus
     </e>
    </xref>
    , which is a largely tropical genus, in temperate Europe and Asia, can be understood only in connection with the activities of birds. Birds also contributed substantially to the repopulation with plants of the Krakatoa island group in Indonesia after the catastrophic volcanic eruption there in 1883. Birds have made
    <xref articleid="47134">
     <e type="italic">
      Lantana
     </e>
    </xref>
    (originally American) a pest in Indonesia and Australia; the same is true of black cherries (
    <e type="italic">
     Prunus serotina
    </e>
    ) in parts of Europe,
    <e type="italic">
     Rubus
    </e>
    species in Brazil and New Zealand, and
    <xref articleid="57030">
     olives
    </xref>
    (
    <e type="italic">
     Olea europaea
    </e>
    ) in Australia.
   </p>
   <p>
    Many intact fruits and seeds can serve as fish bait—those of
    <e type="italic">
     Sonneratia
    </e>
    , for example, for the catfish
    <e type="italic">
     Arius maculatus
    </e>
    . Certain Amazon River fishes react positively to the audible “explosions” of the ripe fruits of
    <e type="italic">
     Eperua rubiginosa
    </e>
    . The largest freshwater wetlands in the world, found in Brazil’s
    <xref articleid="58287">
     Pantanal
    </xref>
    , become inundated with seasonal floods at a time when many plants are releasing their fruits. Pacu fish (
    <e type="italic">
     Metynnis
    </e>
    ) feed on submerged and floating fruits and disperse the seeds when they defecate. It is thought that at least one plant species (
    <e type="italic">
     Bactris glaucescens
    </e>
    ) relies exclusively on pacu for seed dispersal.
   </p>
   <p>
    <xref articleid="35001">
     Fossil
    </xref>
    evidence indicates that saurochory, dispersal by
    <xref articleid="110251">
     reptiles
    </xref>
    , is very ancient. The giant Galapagos tortoise is important for the dispersal of local cacti and tomatoes, and
    <xref articleid="42074">
     iguanas
    </xref>
    are known to eat and disperse a number of smaller fruits, including the iguana hackberry (
    <e type="italic">
     Celtis iguanaea
    </e>
    ). The name
    <xref articleid="5817">
     alligator apple
    </xref>
    , for
    <e type="italic">
     Annona glabra
    </e>
    , refers to its method of dispersal, an example of saurochory.
   </p>
  </h2>
  <h2 id="h340192">
   <title>
    Wind dispersal
   </title>
   <p>
    <assembly id="a263302" url="/assembly/view/263302">
     <title>
      linden
     </title>
     <media mediaid="219531" type="image" url="/31/219531-004-8D0DAB14.jpg"/>
     <caption>
      American linden (
      <e type="italic">
       Tilia americana
      </e>
      ). The light green structures are bracts that aid in seed dispersal.
     </caption>
     <credit>
      © Tatyana Azarova/Dreamstime.com
     </credit>
    </assembly>
    <assemblyref assemblyid="a263302"/>
    Winged fruits are most common in trees and shrubs, such as
    <xref articleid="50699">
     maple
    </xref>
    ,
    <xref articleid="1603">
     ash
    </xref>
    ,
    <xref articleid="32455">
     elm
    </xref>
    ,
    <xref articleid="80294">
     birch
    </xref>
    ,
    <xref articleid="5528">
     alder
    </xref>
    , and
    <xref articleid="30588">
     dipterocarps
    </xref>
    (a family of about 600 species of Old World tropical trees). The one-winged propeller type, as found in maple, is called a samara. When fruits have several wings on their sides, rotation may result, as in
    <xref articleid="63474">
     rhubarb
    </xref>
    and
    <xref articleid="30755">
     dock
    </xref>
    species. Sometimes accessory parts form the wings—for example, the bracts (small green leaflike structures that grow just below flowers) in
    <xref articleid="48359">
     linden
    </xref>
    (
    <e type="italic">
     Tilia
    </e>
    ).
   </p>
   <p>
    <assembly id="a235277" url="/assembly/view/235277">
     <title>
      salsify
     </title>
     <media mediaid="119444" type="image" url="/44/119444-004-A66C64A8.jpg"/>
     <caption>
      Cluster of plumed fruits on a salsify plant (
      <e type="italic">
       Tragopogon porrifolius
      </e>
      ).
     </caption>
     <credit>
      Encyclopædia Britannica, Inc.
     </credit>
    </assembly>
    <assemblyref assemblyid="a235277"/>
    Many fruits form plumes, some derived from persisting and ultimately hairy styles, as in clematis, avens, and anemones; some from the perianth, as in the sedge family (
    <xref articleid="111113">
     Cyperaceae
    </xref>
    ); and some from the pappus, a calyx structure, as in
    <xref articleid="28693">
     dandelion
    </xref>
    and Jack-go-to-bed-at-noon (
    <e type="italic">
     Tragopogon
    </e>
    ). In woolly fruits and seeds, the pericarp or the seed coat is covered with cottonlike hairs—e.g.,
    <xref articleid="77102">
     willow
    </xref>
    ,
    <xref articleid="60841">
     poplar
    </xref>
    or
    <xref articleid="26536">
     cottonwood
    </xref>
    ,
    <xref articleid="26524">
     cotton
    </xref>
    , and
    <xref articleid="12045">
     balsa
    </xref>
    . In some cases, the hairs may serve double duty in that they function in water dispersal as well as in wind dispersal.
   </p>
   <p>
    <xref articleid="60855">
     Poppies
    </xref>
    have a mechanism in which the wind has to swing the slender fruitstalk back and forth before the seeds are thrown out through pores near the top of the capsule. The inflated indehiscent pods of
    <e type="italic">
     Colutea arborea
    </e>
    , a steppe plant, represent balloons capable of limited air travel before they hit the ground and become windblown tumbleweeds.
   </p>
  </h2>
  <h2 id="h340193">
   <title>
    Other forms of dispersal
   </title>
   <p>
    Geocarpy is defined as either the production of fruits underground, as in the arum lilies (
    <e type="italic">
     Stylochiton
    </e>
    and
    <e type="italic">
     Biarum
    </e>
    ), in which the flowers are already subterranean, or the active burying of fruits by the mother plant, as in the
    <xref articleid="58869">
     peanut
    </xref>
    (
    <e type="italic">
     Arachis hypogaea
    </e>
    ). In the American hog peanut (
    <e type="italic">
     Amphicarpa bracteata
    </e>
    ), pods of a special type are buried by the plant and are cached by
    <xref articleid="69300">
     squirrels
    </xref>
    later on. Kenilworth ivy (
    <e type="italic">
     Cymbalaria
    </e>
    ), which normally grows on stone or brick walls, stashes its fruits away in crevices after strikingly extending the flower stalks. Not surprisingly, geocarpy is most often encountered in desert plants; however, it also occurs in violet species, in subterranean clover (
    <e type="italic">
     Trifolium subterraneum
    </e>
    ), and in
    <xref articleid="14122">
     begonias
    </xref>
    (
    <e type="italic">
     Begonia hypogaea
    </e>
    ) of the African rainforest.
   </p>
   <p>
    Barochory, the dispersal of seeds and fruits by gravity alone, is demonstrated by the heavy fruits of
    <xref articleid="41103">
     horse chestnut
    </xref>
    .
   </p>
   <signature>
    EB Editors
   </signature>
  </h2>
 </h1>
 <copyright>
  Encyclopædia Britannica
 </copyright>
</article>