<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "syndication_xml.dtd">
<article articleid="3688" articletypeid="1" language="en_us" lastupdate="2022-Sep-23 08:28:02" url="/article/adaptation/3688" version="12">
 <title>
  adaptation
 </title>
 <p>
  <assembly id="a74644" url="/assembly/view/74644">
   <title>
    Discover how Galapagos finches underwent adaptive radiation and aided Darwin in his theory of evolution
   </title>
   <media mediaid="21998" thumburl="/98/21998-049-D63CD246.jpg" type="video" url="Rdd4Pvcr"/>
   <caption>
    The 14 species of Galapagos finches differ from each other mainly in beak structure and feeding habits. The birds are believed to have undergone adaptive radiation from a single ancestral species, evolving to fill a variety of unoccupied ecological niches.
   </caption>
   <credit>
    Encyclopædia Britannica, Inc.
   </credit>
  </assembly>
  <e type="bold">
   adaptation
  </e>
  ,
  <assemblyref assemblyid="a74644"/>
  in
  <xref articleid="110576">
   biology
  </xref>
  , the process by which a
  <xref articleid="69027">
   species
  </xref>
  becomes fitted to its
  <xref articleid="32733">
   environment
  </xref>
  ; it is the result of
  <xref articleid="55046">
   natural selection
  </xref>
  ’s acting upon heritable
  <xref articleid="74851">
   variation
  </xref>
  over several generations. Organisms are adapted to their environments in a great variety of ways: in their structure,
  <xref articleid="110578">
   physiology
  </xref>
  , and
  <xref articleid="110582">
   genetics
  </xref>
  , in their
  <xref articleid="110421">
   locomotion
  </xref>
  or dispersal, in their means of defense and attack, in their
  <xref articleid="110805">
   reproduction
  </xref>
  and
  <xref articleid="30148">
   development
  </xref>
  , and in other respects.
 </p>
 <p>
  <assembly id="a138645" url="/assembly/view/138645">
   <title>
    light gray peppered moth (
    <e type="italic">
     Biston betularia
    </e>
    )
   </title>
   <media mediaid="59011" type="image" url="/11/59011-004-F2BFB969.jpg"/>
   <caption>
    A light gray peppered moth (
    <e type="italic">
     Biston betularia
    </e>
    ) and a darkly pigmented variant rest near each other on the trunk of a soot-covered oak tree. Against this background, the light gray moth is more easily noticed than the darker variant.
   </caption>
   <credit>
    From the experiments of Dr. H.B.D. Kettlewell, University of Oxford; photographs by John S. Haywood
   </credit>
  </assembly>
  <assembly id="a138655" url="/assembly/view/138655">
   <title>
    dark coloured peppered moth (
    <e type="italic">
     Biston betularia
    </e>
    )
   </title>
   <media mediaid="59012" type="image" url="/12/59012-004-3F583FEF.jpg"/>
   <caption>
    Against the background of a lichen-covered oak tree, a darkly pigmented peppered moth (
    <e type="italic">
     Biston betularia
    </e>
    ) stands out, while the light gray moth (left) remains inconspicuous.
   </caption>
   <credit>
    From the experiments of Dr. H.B.D. Kettlewell, University of Oxford; photographs by John S. Haywood
   </credit>
  </assembly>
  <assemblyref assemblyid="a138645"/>
  <assemblyref assemblyid="a138655"/>
  The word
  <e type="italic">
   adaptation
  </e>
  does not stem from its current usage in evolutionary biology but rather dates back to the early 17th century, when it indicated a relation between design and function or how something fits into something else. In biology this general idea has been coopted so that
  <e type="italic">
   adaptation
  </e>
  has three meanings. First, in a physiological sense, an
  <xref articleid="110237">
   animal
  </xref>
  or
  <xref articleid="108554">
   plant
  </xref>
  can adapt by adjusting to its immediate environment—for instance, by changing its temperature or
  <xref articleid="109831">
   metabolism
  </xref>
  with an increase in altitude. Second, and more commonly, the word
  <e type="italic">
   adaptation
  </e>
  refers either to the process of becoming adapted or to the features of organisms that promote reproductive success relative to other possible features. Here the process of adaptation is driven by genetic variations among individuals that become adapted to—that is, have greater success in—a specific environmental context. A classic example is shown by the melanistic (dark)
  <xref articleid="59622">
   phenotype
  </xref>
  of the
  <xref articleid="59166">
   peppered moth
  </xref>
  (
  <e type="italic">
   Biston betularia
  </e>
  ), which increased in numbers in Britain following the
  <xref articleid="42370">
   Industrial Revolution
  </xref>
  as dark-coloured moths appeared cryptic against soot-darkened
  <xref articleid="108708">
   trees
  </xref>
  and escaped
  <xref articleid="61238">
   predation
  </xref>
  by
  <xref articleid="105921">
   birds
  </xref>
  . The process of adaptation occurs through an eventual change in the
  <xref articleid="36352">
   gene
  </xref>
  frequency relative to advantages conferred by a particular characteristic, as with the
  <xref articleid="109619">
   coloration
  </xref>
  of
  <xref articleid="77199">
   wings
  </xref>
  in the
  <xref articleid="53946">
   moths
  </xref>
  .
 </p>
 <p>
  <assembly id="a146135" url="/assembly/view/146135">
   <title>
    adaptations
   </title>
   <media mediaid="91569" type="image" url="/69/91569-004-9D3A750F.jpg"/>
   <caption>
    The habitat adaptations of walruses (thick skin to protect against cold conditions), hippopotamuses (nostrils on the top of the snout), and ducks (webbed feet).
   </caption>
   <credit>
    Encyclopædia Britannica, Inc.
   </credit>
  </assembly>
  <assemblyref assemblyid="a146135"/>
  The third and more popular view of adaptation is in regard to the form of a feature that has evolved by natural selection for a specific function. Examples include the long
  <xref articleid="55149">
   necks
  </xref>
  of
  <xref articleid="36897">
   giraffes
  </xref>
  for feeding in the tops of trees, the streamlined bodies of aquatic
  <xref articleid="111049">
   fish
  </xref>
  and
  <xref articleid="105972">
   mammals
  </xref>
  , the light
  <xref articleid="110163">
   bones
  </xref>
  of flying birds and mammals, and the long daggerlike canine teeth of
  <xref articleid="105981">
   carnivores
  </xref>
  .
 </p>
 <p>
  <assembly id="a121524" url="/assembly/view/121524">
   <media mediaid="100252" type="image" url="/52/100252-004-090BDB7D.jpg"/>
   <caption>
    Giant panda (
    <e type="italic">
     Ailuropoda melanoleuca
    </e>
    ) feeding in a bamboo forest, Szechwan province, China.
   </caption>
   <credit>
    © Jupiterimages Corporation
   </credit>
  </assembly>
  <assemblyref assemblyid="a121524"/>
  All biologists agree that organismal
  <xref articleid="22497">
   traits
  </xref>
  commonly reflect adaptations. However, much disagreement has arisen over the role of history and constraint in the appearance of traits as well as the best methodology for showing that a trait is truly an adaptation. A trait may be a function of history rather than adaptation. The so-called
  <xref articleid="58234">
   panda’s
  </xref>
  <xref articleid="72318">
   thumb
  </xref>
  , or radial sesamoid bone, is a
  <xref articleid="77567">
   wrist
  </xref>
  bone that now functions as an opposable thumb, allowing giant pandas to grasp and manipulate
  <xref articleid="12079">
   bamboo
  </xref>
  stems with dexterity. The ancestors of giant pandas and all closely related species, such as
  <xref articleid="15468">
   black bears
  </xref>
  ,
  <xref articleid="62361">
   raccoons
  </xref>
  , and
  <xref articleid="58235">
   red pandas
  </xref>
  , also have sesamoid bones, though the latter species do not feed on bamboo or use the bone for feeding
  <xref articleid="110417">
   behaviour
  </xref>
  . Therefore, this bone is not an adaptation for bamboo feeding.
 </p>
 <p>
  The English naturalist
  <xref articleid="109642">
   Charles Darwin
  </xref>
  , in
  <e type="italic">
   On the Origin of Species by Means of Natural Selection
  </e>
  (1859), recognized the problem of determining whether a feature evolved for the function it currently serves:
 </p>
 <quote>
  <p>
   The sutures of the skulls of young mammals have been advanced as a beautiful adaptation for aiding parturition [birth], and no doubt they facilitate, or may be indispensable for this act; but as sutures occur in the skulls of young birds and
   <xref articleid="110251">
    reptiles
   </xref>
   , which only have to escape from a broken egg, we may infer that this structure has arisen from the laws of growth, and has been taken advantage of in the parturition of the higher animals.
  </p>
 </quote>
 <p>
  Thus, before explaining that a trait is an adaptation, it is necessary to identify whether it is also shown in ancestors and therefore may have evolved historically for different functions from those that it now serves.
 </p>
 <p>
  Another problem in designating a trait as an adaptation is that the trait may be a necessary consequence, or constraint, of
  <xref articleid="108654">
   physics
  </xref>
  or
  <xref articleid="108655">
   chemistry
  </xref>
  . One of the most common forms of constraint involves the function of anatomical traits that differ in size. For example,
  <xref articleid="19987">
   canine teeth
  </xref>
  are larger in
  <xref articleid="105116">
   carnivores
  </xref>
  than in
  <xref articleid="40114">
   herbivores
  </xref>
  . This difference in size is often explained as an adaptation for
  <xref articleid="61238">
   predation
  </xref>
  . However, the size of canine teeth is also related to overall body size (such scaling is known as
  <xref articleid="395991">
   allometry
  </xref>
  ), as shown by large carnivores such as
  <xref articleid="47834">
   leopards
  </xref>
  that have bigger canines than do small carnivores such as
  <xref articleid="76361">
   weasels
  </xref>
  . Thus, differences in many animal and plant characteristics, such as the sizes of young, duration of developmental periods (e.g.,
  <xref articleid="36626">
   gestation
  </xref>
  , longevity), or patterns and sizes of tree
  <xref articleid="47499">
   leaves
  </xref>
  , are related to physical size constraints.
 </p>
 <p>
  <assembly id="a74641" url="/assembly/view/74641">
   <title>
    adaptive radiation in Galapagos finches
   </title>
   <media mediaid="54911" type="image" url="/11/54911-004-A446EA92.jpg"/>
   <caption>
    Fourteen species of Galapagos finches that evolved from a common ancestor. The different shapes of their bills, suited to different diets and habitats, show the process of adaptive radiation.
   </caption>
   <credit>
    Encyclopædia Britannica, Inc.
   </credit>
  </assembly>
  <assemblyref assemblyid="a74641"/>
  Adaptive explanations in biology are difficult to test because they include many traits and require different methodologies. Experimental approaches are important for showing that any small variability, as in many physiological or behavioral differences, is an adaptation. The most rigorous methods are those that combine experimental approaches with information from natural settings—for example, in showing that the beaks of different species of
  <xref articleid="35841">
   Galapagos finch
  </xref>
  are shaped differently because they are adapted to feed on
  <xref articleid="473280">
   seeds
  </xref>
  of different sizes.
 </p>
 <p>
  The comparative method, using comparisons across species that have evolved independently, is an effective means for studying historical and physical constraints. This approach involves using
  <xref articleid="108592">
   statistical methods
  </xref>
  to account for differences in size (allometry) and
  <xref articleid="59860">
   evolutionary trees
  </xref>
  (
  <xref articleid="59861">
   phylogenies
  </xref>
  ) for tracing trait evolution among lineages.
 </p>
 <signature>
  John L. Gittleman
 </signature>
 <h1 id="h281251">
  <title>
   Bibliography
  </title>
  <p>
   Good introductions to adaptation are included in
   <e type="smallcap">
    George C. Williams
   </e>
   ,
   <e type="italic">
    Adaptation and Natural Selection
   </e>
   (1966, reissued 1996);
   <e type="smallcap">
    Michael R. Rose
   </e>
   and
   <e type="smallcap">
    George V. Lauder
   </e>
   (eds.),
   <e type="italic">
    Adaptation
   </e>
   (1996); and
   <e type="smallcap">
    Stephen Jay Gould
   </e>
   ,
   <e type="italic">
    The Structure of Evolutionary Theory
   </e>
   (2002).
  </p>
 </h1>
 <copyright>
  Encyclopædia Britannica
 </copyright>
</article>