<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "syndication_xml.dtd">
<article articleid="37797" articletypeid="1" language="en_us" lastupdate="2021-Jun-30 22:21:01" url="/article/gravity-centre-of/37797" version="9">
 <title>
  centre of gravity
 </title>
 <p>
  <assembly id="a53659" url="/assembly/view/53659">
   <title>
    centre of gravity
   </title>
   <media mediaid="63044" type="image" url="/44/63044-004-2DF6DD5C.jpg"/>
   <caption>
    When a drum is stood on end, its centre of gravity (CG) is firmly supported, and the drum is in stable equilibrium (A). If the drum is tilted slightly to either side (B), the pull of gravity on this centre creates a torque, or turning force, around the new point of support and pulls the drum back to the stable position. A drum balanced on its rim (C) is in unstable equilibrium. Even a tiny displacement (D) will create a torque that will turn the drum farther from the unstable position.
   </caption>
   <credit>
    Encyclopædia Britannica, Inc.
   </credit>
  </assembly>
  <e type="bold">
   centre of gravity
  </e>
  ,
  <assemblyref assemblyid="a53659"/>
  in physics, an imaginary point in a body of matter where, for convenience in certain calculations, the total weight of the body may be thought to be concentrated. The concept is sometimes useful in designing static structures (e.g., buildings and bridges) or in predicting the behaviour of a moving body when it is acted on by
  <xref articleid="106265">
   gravity
  </xref>
  .
 </p>
 <p>
  In a uniform gravitational field the centre of gravity is identical to the centre of
  <xref articleid="51285">
   mass
  </xref>
  , a term preferred by physicists. The two do not always coincide, however. For example, the
  <xref articleid="110148">
   Moon’s
  </xref>
  centre of mass is very close to its geometric centre (it is not exact because the Moon is not a perfect uniform sphere), but its centre of gravity is slightly displaced toward
  <xref articleid="110147">
   Earth
  </xref>
  because of the stronger gravitational force on the Moon’s near side.
 </p>
 <p>
  The location of a body’s centre of gravity may coincide with the geometric centre of the body, especially in a symmetrically shaped object composed of homogeneous material. An asymmetrical object composed of a variety of materials with different masses, however, is likely to have a centre of gravity located at some distance from its geometric centre. In some cases, such as hollow bodies or irregularly shaped objects, the centre of gravity (or centre of mass) may occur in space at a point external to the physical material—e.g., in the centre of a
  <xref articleid="108495">
   tennis
  </xref>
  ball or between the legs of a chair.
 </p>
 <p>
  <assembly id="a5743" url="/assembly/view/5743">
   <title>
    centre of gravity
   </title>
   <media mediaid="1012" type="image" url="/12/1012-004-56771D36.jpg"/>
   <caption>
    Centre of gravity. The red dot is the centre of gravity G.
   </caption>
   <credit>
    Encyclopædia Britannica, Inc.
   </credit>
  </assembly>
  <assemblyref assemblyid="a5743"/>
  Published tables and handbooks list the centres of gravity for most common geometric shapes. For a triangular metal plate such as that depicted in the figure, the calculation would involve a summation of the moments of the weights of all the particles that make up the metal plate about point A. By equating this sum to the plate’s weight W, multiplied by the unknown distance from the centre of gravity G to AC, the position of G relative to AC can be determined. The summation of the moments can be obtained easily and precisely by means of integral
  <xref articleid="18631">
   calculus
  </xref>
  .
 </p>
 <p>
  The centre of gravity of any body can also be determined by a simple physical procedure. For example, for the plate in the figure, the point G can be located by suspending the plate by a cord attached at point A and then by a cord attached at C. When the plate is suspended from A, the line AD is vertical; when it is suspended from C, the line CE is vertical. The centre of gravity is at the intersection of AD and CE. When an object is suspended from any single point, its centre of gravity lies directly beneath that point.
 </p>
 <signature>
  EB Editors
 </signature>
 <copyright>
  Encyclopædia Britannica
 </copyright>
</article>