<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "syndication_xml.dtd">
<article articleid="38142" articletypeid="1" language="en_us" lastupdate="2021-Jun-30 22:23:47" url="/article/grinding-machine/38142" version="2">
 <title>
  grinding machine
 </title>
 <p>
  <e type="bold">
   grinding machine
  </e>
  , tool that employs a rotating abrasive wheel to change the shape or dimensions of a hard, usually metallic, body.
 </p>
 <p>
  All of the many types of grinding machines use a grinding wheel made from one of the manufactured abrasives, silicon carbide or aluminum oxide. The wheel is manufactured by mixing selected sizes of abrasive granules with a bonding agent (such as clay, resin, rubber, shellac, or silicate of soda) and fusing them together by baking or firing. The grade (hardness) of a wheel is determined by the ratio of bond to abrasive. Properly, a grinding wheel is self-sharpening because as it is worked, the dull grains break off, exposing fresh, sharp grains. The harder the grade, the more slowly the wheel releases the grains.
 </p>
 <p>
  The shapes that can be produced by machine grinding depend on the shapes that can be cut with a diamond or other “dresser” on the sides and edge of the grinding wheel and the manner in which the workpiece is moved relative to the wheel. To grind a cylindrical form in a workpiece, the piece is rotated as it is fed against the grinding wheel. To grind an internal surface, a small wheel is so mounted that it can move back and forth inside the hollow of the workpiece, which is gripped in a rotating chuck.
 </p>
 <p>
  On a surface grinder, a flat magnetic plate or a vise holds the workpiece in place on a table that moves back and forth under the rotating abrasive wheel. At the end of each traverse the table is moved automatically a short distance at right angles to the direction of travel.
 </p>
 <p>
  Many special guiding machines and devices are available for grinding tools.
 </p>
 <copyright>
  Encyclopædia Britannica
 </copyright>
</article>