<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "syndication_xml.dtd">
<article articleid="389134" articletypeid="1" language="en_us" lastupdate="2023-Mar-03 11:42:17" url="/article/art/389134" version="11">
 <title>
  art
 </title>
 <p>
  <e type="bold">
   art
  </e>
  , also called (to distinguish it from other art forms)
  <e type="bold">
   visual art
  </e>
  , a visual object or experience consciously created through an expression of skill or imagination. The term
  <e type="italic">
   art
  </e>
  encompasses diverse media such as
  <xref articleid="108604">
   painting
  </xref>
  ,
  <xref articleid="109518">
   sculpture
  </xref>
  ,
  <xref articleid="109438">
   printmaking
  </xref>
  ,
  <xref articleid="106184">
   drawing
  </xref>
  ,
  <xref articleid="29712">
   decorative arts
  </xref>
  ,
  <xref articleid="108551">
   photography
  </xref>
  , and installation.
 </p>
 <p>
  <e type="italic">
   <xref articleid="389457">
    (Read Sister Wendy’s Britannica essay on art appreciation.)
   </xref>
  </e>
 </p>
 <p>
  <assembly id="a2749" url="/assembly/view/2749">
   <title>
    memorial board
   </title>
   <media mediaid="3181" type="image" url="/81/3181-004-C293B758.jpg"/>
   <caption>
    Memorial board, wood. From the Sawos people, Sepik central coast, Papua New Guinea, in the Museum of Ethnology, Berlin.
   </caption>
   <credit>
    Museum für Völkerkunde, Staatliche Museen zu Berling—Preussischer Kulturbesitz; photograph, Dietrich Graf
   </credit>
  </assembly>
  <assemblyref assemblyid="a2749"/>
  The various visual arts exist within a continuum that ranges from purely aesthetic purposes at one end to purely utilitarian purposes at the other. Such a polarity of purpose is reflected in the commonly used terms
  <e type="italic">
   artist
  </e>
  and
  <e type="italic">
   artisan
  </e>
  , the latter understood as one who gives considerable attention to the utilitarian. This should by no means be taken as a rigid scheme, however. Even within one form of art, motives may vary widely; thus a potter or a weaver may create a highly functional work that is at the same time beautiful—a salad bowl, for example, or a blanket—or may create works that have no purpose beyond being admired. In cultures such as those of Africa and Oceania, a definition of art that encompasses this continuum has existed for centuries. In the West, however, by the mid-18th century the development of academies for painting and sculpture established a sense that these media were “art” and therefore separate from more utilitarian media. This separation of art forms continued among art institutions until the late 20th century, when such rigid distinctions began to be questioned.
 </p>
 <p>
  Particularly in the 20th century, a different sort of debate arose over the definition of
  <e type="italic">
   art
  </e>
  . A seminal moment in this discussion occurred in 1917, when
  <xref articleid="28498">
   Dada
  </xref>
  artist Marcel Duchamp submitted a porcelain urinal entitled
  <e type="italic">
   Fountain
  </e>
  to a public exhibition in
  <xref articleid="108761">
   New York City
  </xref>
  . Through this act, Duchamp put forth a new definition of what constitutes a work of art: he implied that it is enough for an artist to deem something “art” and put it in a publicly accepted venue. Implicit within this gesture was a challenge to the established art institutions—such as museums, exhibiting groups, and galleries—that have the power to determine what is and is not considered art. Such intellectual experimentation continued throughout the 20th century in movements such as conceptual art and
  <xref articleid="52851">
   minimalism
  </xref>
  . By the turn of the 21st century, a variety of new media (e.g.,
  <xref articleid="435737">
   video art
  </xref>
  ) further challenged traditional definitions of art.
 </p>
 <p>
  Art is treated in a number of articles. For general discussions of the foundations, principles, practice, and character of art,
  <e type="italic">
   see
  </e>
  <xref articleid="106009">
   aesthetics
  </xref>
  .
  <e type="italic">
   See also
  </e>
  <xref articleid="111003">
   art conservation and restoration
  </xref>
  .
 </p>
 <p>
  For the technical and theoretical aspects of traditional categories of art,
  <e type="italic">
   see
  </e>
  <xref articleid="106184">
   drawing
  </xref>
  ;
  <xref articleid="108604">
   painting
  </xref>
  ;
  <xref articleid="109438">
   printmaking
  </xref>
  ;
  <xref articleid="109518">
   sculpture
  </xref>
  . For technical and historical discussions of decorative arts and furnishings,
  <e type="italic">
   see
  </e>
  <xref articleid="108352">
   basketry
  </xref>
  ;
  <xref articleid="108354">
   enamelwork
  </xref>
  ;
  <xref articleid="108350">
   floral decoration
  </xref>
  ;
  <xref articleid="108347">
   furniture
  </xref>
  ;
  <xref articleid="108358">
   glassware
  </xref>
  ;
  <xref articleid="108346">
   interior design
  </xref>
  ;
  <xref articleid="108355">
   lacquerwork
  </xref>
  ;
  <xref articleid="108353">
   metalwork
  </xref>
  ;
  <xref articleid="108356">
   mosaic
  </xref>
  ;
  <xref articleid="108351">
   pottery
  </xref>
  ;
  <xref articleid="108348">
   rug and carpet
  </xref>
  ;
  <xref articleid="108357">
   stained glass
  </xref>
  ;
  <xref articleid="108349">
   tapestry
  </xref>
  .
  <e type="italic">
   See
  </e>
  <xref articleid="108551">
   photography
  </xref>
  for a complete history of that medium.
 </p>
 <p>
  For treatments of the various arts as practiced by specific peoples and cultures,
  <e type="italic">
   see
  </e>
  , for example,
  <xref articleid="384738">
   African art
  </xref>
  ;
  <xref articleid="106127">
   Central Asian arts
  </xref>
  ;
  <xref articleid="106017">
   Egyptian art and architecture
  </xref>
  ;
  <xref articleid="106442">
   Islamic arts
  </xref>
  ;
  <xref articleid="108517">
   Oceanic art and architecture
  </xref>
  ;
  <xref articleid="109585">
   South Asian arts
  </xref>
  .
 </p>
 <signature>
  EB Editors
 </signature>
 <copyright>
  Encyclopædia Britannica
 </copyright>
</article>