<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "syndication_xml.dtd">
<article articleid="389635" articletypeid="1" language="en_us" lastupdate="2021-Jul-01 05:37:16" url="/article/prison/389635" version="7">
 <title>
  prison
 </title>
 <p>
  <e type="bold">
   prison
  </e>
  , an institution for the confinement of persons who have been remanded (held) in custody by a judicial authority or who have been deprived of their liberty following conviction for a crime. A person found guilty of a
  <xref articleid="33956">
   felony
  </xref>
  or a misdemeanour may be required to serve a prison sentence. The holding of accused persons awaiting trial remains an important function of contemporary prisons, and in some countries such persons constitute the majority of the prison population. In the United Kingdom, for example, generally about one-fifth of the prison population is unconvicted or unsentenced, while more than two-thirds of those in custody in India are pretrial detainees.
 </p>
 <p>
  Until the late 18th century, prisons were used primarily for the confinement of debtors, persons accused of crimes and awaiting trial, and convicts awaiting the imposition of their sentences—usually death or transportation (
  <xref articleid="29982">
   deportation
  </xref>
  ) overseas. A sentence of imprisonment was rarely imposed—and then only for minor crimes.
 </p>
 <p>
  As the use of
  <xref articleid="20149">
   capital punishment
  </xref>
  began to decline in the late 18th century, the prison was increasingly used by courts as a place of
  <xref articleid="389636">
   punishment
  </xref>
  , eventually becoming the chief means of punishing serious offenders. The use of imprisonment subsequently spread worldwide, often by means of colonial empires that brought the practice to countries with no indigenous concept of prisons. By the early 21st century a majority of countries had abolished the death penalty (in law or in practice), and imprisonment was consequently the most severe form of punishment their courts could impose.
 </p>
 <h1 id="h272176">
  <title>
   Development of the prison system
  </title>
  <p>
   <assembly id="a96160" url="/assembly/view/96160">
    <title>
     Newgate Prison
    </title>
    <media mediaid="12447" type="image" url="/47/12447-004-E2A824B0.jpg"/>
    <caption>
     Newgate Prison, London, drawing by George Dance the Younger; in Sir John Soane’s Museum, London.
    </caption>
    <credit>
     Courtesy of the trustees of Sir John Soane's Museum; photograph, Geremy Butler
    </credit>
   </assembly>
   <assemblyref assemblyid="a96160"/>
   During the 16th century a number of houses of correction were established in Europe for the rehabilitation of minor offenders and vagrants; they emphasized strict discipline and hard labour. Over time, imprisonment came to be accepted as an appropriate method of punishing convicted criminals. Poor sanitation in these institutions caused widespread disease among prisoners, who were generally held unsegregated, without any consideration for gender or legal status. Outbreaks of
   <xref articleid="74006">
    epidemic typhus
   </xref>
   , known as “jail fever,” occasionally killed not only prisoners but also jailers and (more rarely) judges and lawyers involved in trials. The modern prison developed in the late 18th century in part as a reaction to the conditions of the local jails of the time.
  </p>
  <h2 id="h272177">
   <title>
    Emergence of the penitentiary
   </title>
   <p>
    <assembly id="a11767" url="/assembly/view/11767">
     <title>
      John Howard
     </title>
     <media mediaid="10910" type="image" url="/10/10910-004-85079C82.jpg"/>
     <caption>
      John Howard, oil painting by Mather Brown; in the National Portrait Gallery, London.
     </caption>
     <credit>
      Courtesy of the National Portrait Gallery, London
     </credit>
    </assembly>
    <assemblyref assemblyid="a11767"/>
    The concept of the prison as a penitentiary (that is, as a place of punishment and personal reform) was advocated in this period by the English jurist and philosopher
    <xref articleid="78656">
     Jeremy Bentham
    </xref>
    , among others. The appalling conditions and official corruption in many local prisons of late 18th-century England and Wales were exposed by the English prison reformer
    <xref articleid="41228">
     John Howard
    </xref>
    , whose works
    <e type="italic">
     The State of the Prisons in England and Wales
    </e>
    (1777) and
    <e type="italic">
     An Account of the Principal Lazarettos in Europe
    </e>
    (1789) were based on extensive travels. The public outrage that Bentham and Howard helped generate led to a national system of inspection and the construction of “convict prisons” for those serving longer sentences. Consequently, in the early 19th century, penitentiaries were established in the U.S. states of Pennsylvania and New York.
   </p>
   <p>
    As use of the new type of prison expanded, administrators began to experiment with new methods of prisoner rehabilitation. Solitary confinement of criminals came to be viewed as an ideal, because it was thought that solitude would help the offender to become penitent and that penitence would result in rehabilitation. In the United States the idea was first implemented at Eastern State Penitentiary in Philadelphia in 1829. Each prisoner remained in his cell or its adjoining yard, worked alone at trades such as weaving, carpentry, or shoemaking, and saw no one except the officers of the institution and an occasional visitor from outside. This method of prison management, known as the “separate system” or the “
    <xref articleid="59096">
     Pennsylvania system
    </xref>
    ,” became a model for penal institutions constructed in several other U.S. states and throughout much of Europe.
   </p>
   <p>
    A competing philosophy of prison management, known as the “silent system” or the “
    <xref articleid="11202">
     Auburn system
    </xref>
    ,” arose at roughly the same time. Although constant silence was strictly enforced, the distinguishing feature of this system was that prisoners were permitted to work together in the daytime (at night they were confined to individual cells). Both systems held to the basic premise that contact between convicts should be prohibited in order to minimize the bad influence inmates might have on one another. Vigorous competition between supporters of the two systems followed until about 1850, by which time most U.S. states had adopted the silent system.
   </p>
   <p>
    <assembly id="a13246" url="/assembly/view/13246">
     <title>
      former penal settlement at Kingston
     </title>
     <media mediaid="3091" type="image" url="/91/3091-004-EBB22C97.jpg"/>
     <caption>
      Ruined officers’ quarters of the former penal settlement at Kingston on Norfolk Island.
     </caption>
     <credit>
      Photographic Library of Australia
     </credit>
    </assembly>
    <assemblyref assemblyid="a13246"/>
    The concept of personal reform became increasingly important in
    <xref articleid="59103">
     penology
    </xref>
    , resulting in experimentation with various methods. One example was the
    <xref articleid="51005">
     mark system
    </xref>
    , which was developed about 1840 by Capt. Alexander Maconochie at
    <xref articleid="56126">
     Norfolk Island
    </xref>
    , an English penal colony east of Australia. Instead of serving fixed sentences, prisoners were required to earn credits, or “marks,” in amounts proportional to the seriousness of their offenses. Credits were accumulated through good conduct, hard work, and study, and they could be withheld or subtracted for indolence or misbehaviour. Prisoners who obtained the required number of credits became eligible for release. The mark system presaged the use of
    <xref articleid="42269">
     indeterminate sentences
    </xref>
    , individualized treatment, and
    <xref articleid="58550">
     parole
    </xref>
    . Above all it emphasized training and performance, rather than solitude, as the chief mechanisms of reform.
   </p>
   <p>
    Further refinements in the mark system were developed in the mid-19th century by Sir Walter Crofton, the director of Irish prisons. In his program, known as the
    <xref articleid="42785">
     Irish system
    </xref>
    , prisoners progressed through three stages of confinement before they were returned to civilian life. The first portion of the sentence was served in isolation. After that, prisoners were assigned to group work projects. Finally, for six months or more before release, the prisoners were transferred to “intermediate prisons,” where they were supervised by unarmed guards and given sufficient freedom and responsibility to demonstrate their fitness for release. Release nonetheless depended upon the continued good conduct of the offender, who could be returned to prison if necessary.
   </p>
   <p>
    Many features of the Irish system were adopted by reformatories constructed in the United States in the late 19th century for the treatment of youthful and first offenders. The leaders of the
    <xref articleid="63025">
     reformatory
    </xref>
    movement advocated the classification and segregation of various types of prisoners, individualized treatment emphasizing
    <xref articleid="75632">
     vocational education
    </xref>
    and industrial employment, indeterminate sentences and rewards for good behaviour, and parole or conditional release. The reformatory philosophy gradually permeated the entire U.S. prison system, and the American innovations, in combination with the Irish system, had great impact upon European prison practices, leading to innovations such as the
    <xref articleid="80788">
     Borstal system
    </xref>
    of rehabilitation for youthful offenders in the 20th century.
   </p>
  </h2>
  <h2 id="h272178">
   <title>
    The purpose of imprisonment
   </title>
   <p>
    There are a number of accepted reasons for the use of imprisonment. One approach aims to deter those who would otherwise commit crimes (general deterrence) and to make it less likely that those who serve a prison sentence will commit crimes after their release (individual deterrence). A second approach focuses on issuing punishment to, or obtaining retribution from, those who have committed serious crimes. A third approach encourages the personal reform of those who are sent to prison. Finally, in some cases it is necessary to protect the public from those who commit crimes—particularly from those who do so persistently. In individual cases, all or some of these justifications may apply. The increasing importance of the notion of reform has led some prison systems to be called correctional institutions.
   </p>
   <p>
    This description of imprisonment applies mainly to the countries of Europe and North America. In China imprisonment was historically used as a means of reforming the minds of criminals, and it obliged prisoners to work in support of the state. Imprisonment in the Soviet Union similarly became a method of forcing so-called enemies of the state to labour on its behalf and, in so doing, to recognize the error of their ways. Developing countries faced a different challenge as they confronted prison systems that in many cases symbolized a legacy of colonial domination. Given the difficulty of replacing the structure and organization of an existing prison system, many countries consequently struggled to implement effective forms of punishment that were also decent and humane.
   </p>
  </h2>
 </h1>
 <h1 id="h272179">
  <title>
   Types of prisons
  </title>
  <p>
   Prisoners are distributed among a variety of types of institutions. Most countries operate national prison systems that are supplemented by state or provincial counterparts. In the United States, for example, criminals sentenced for federal offenses are held in institutions of varying levels of security operated by the Federal Bureau of Prisons. The majority of prisoners are held in state institutions, some of which house several thousand inmates in high-security facilities. Prisoners who have been charged with minor offenses, or who are serving short sentences, are most commonly held in municipal jails.
  </p>
  <p>
   In countries with a federal system of government, such as Brazil, Germany and India, prisons are administered not by the national government but by individual states.
  </p>
  <p>
   The vast majority of prisoners worldwide are adult males. Of these, a minority have committed very serious crimes; it is the responsibility of prison systems to protect the public from such convicts at all costs. Other prisoners are career criminals who regularly commit burglaries and thefts, and who accept that from time to time they will be caught, convicted, and sentenced to a period of imprisonment. Also common among prisoners are people on the margins of society who commit minor offences; they may be drug addicts or alcoholics, they may be mentally disordered, or they may feel that they have lost their place in society through unemployment or homelessness (
   <e type="italic">
    see
   </e>
   <xref articleid="5729">
    alienation
   </xref>
   ). Most prison systems have different sorts of prisons to contain these different groups. For the most serious criminals, there are high-security prisons, where the movement of every prisoner is closely supervised so that they have little chance of escaping. For the majority there are medium-security prisons, where prisoners are expected to work, attend educational programs, or participate in other activities that prepare them for release. Finally, there are prisons that have a very low level of security for those who present no threat to public safety.
  </p>
  <h2 id="h272180">
   <title>
    Supervision
   </title>
   <p>
    In the 19th and early 20th centuries, prisons were viewed as total institutions that exert control over every aspect of a prisoner’s life. In addition to scheduled routines—such as for meals, rising and retiring, exercising, and bathing—many other aspects of the prisoner’s life were subject to strict supervision. In the later 20th century, however, penologists recognized that not all prisoners required such close supervision and that excessive surveillance risked institutionalizing the prisoner to such a degree that it could undermine his preparation for release. Many countries have since encouraged prisoners to take responsibility for their actions, to use their time in prison to examine their previous behaviour, and to learn skills that will help them to lead a law-abiding life after their sentence has been served. Prison programs may involve education, industrial work, vocational training, and instruction in what are known as “life skills” or “survival skills.”
   </p>
   <p>
    Wherever possible, prisoners are permitted to maintain (or in some cases develop) contact with their families. This is important not only for the prisoner but also for the family members, who have a right—as expressed in Article 12 of the
    <xref articleid="74356">
     Universal Declaration of Human Rights
    </xref>
    (1948)—to maintain contact with their parent, child, or sibling. In some countries, visits with families take place under close supervision, in rooms where staff are always present and where visitors and prisoners are allowed little direct contact. Prisoners in maximum-security facilities are sometimes separated from their visitors by solid glass screens. Prisons in some eastern European and Central Asian countries provide special visiting units where families and prisoners can live together for up to three days. Similar arrangements exist in Canada and some U.S. states. Several Latin American countries permit family members to enter the prisoners’ living accommodations on weekends.
   </p>
  </h2>
  <h2 id="h272181">
   <title>
    Order and discipline
   </title>
   <p>
    Although prisons are intended to be institutions where good order prevails, it is possible for order to break down in certain circumstances. It is the responsibility of prison administrators to ensure that each arriving prisoner understands what type of behaviour is expected and what acts are forbidden. In addition, there must be a clear set of disciplinary sanctions for acts of indiscipline. In all such cases the normal processes of natural justice should apply. This means that a prisoner who is accused of violating prison rules should be told what the charge is and who is leveling it. The accused prisoner should have the opportunity to attend a disciplinary hearing, to enter a defense, and to question the evidence presented.
   </p>
   <p>
    Any resulting punishment should be proportional to the offense that was committed. Serious acts, which would usually be classified as criminal, should be dealt with in a more serious manner; in some countries, such as the United Kingdom, this involves referring the case to the civil police. In other countries, such as France and Spain, these cases are handled by a visiting judge or magistrate.
   </p>
  </h2>
  <h2 id="h272182">
   <title>
    Oversight
   </title>
   <p>
    Many countries recognize the need for third-party oversight of their prison systems. The United Kingdom and the state of Western Australia appoint independent inspectors for this purpose, while many countries in continental Europe appoint a visiting judge who oversees prison systems. There are also forms of independent regional inspection; the member countries of the Council of Europe, for example, are subject to inspection by the Committee for the Prevention of Torture and Inhuman or Degrading Treatment or Punishment. On the African continent, the African Commission on Human and People’s Rights appoints a Special Rapporteur on Prisons, who is charged with examining conditions in all detention facilities and upholding human rights norms as defined by national and international bodies.
   </p>
  </h2>
  <h2 id="h272183">
   <title>
    Privatization
   </title>
   <p>
    As governments faced the problems created by burgeoning prison populations in the late 20th century—including overcrowding, poor sanitation, and riots—a few sought a solution in turning over prison management to the private sector. Privately run prisons were in operation in Australia, the United Kingdom, and the United States by the late 1990s. In the following decade a number of countries, including Brazil, France, and South Africa, hired private contractors to build prisons and to manage some of their day-to-day operations.
   </p>
   <p>
    The term
    <e type="italic">
     prison privatization
    </e>
    can be applied to a variety of arrangements involving nongovernmental contractors. One privatization model, which originated in France and later spread to a number of countries, arranges responsibilities such that state employees control any functions that relate to deprivation of liberty while other services are contracted out to nongovernmental companies. Services in the latter group may include maintenance of buildings and other infrastructure, transportation, accommodation, food service, health services, work programs, and vocational training.
   </p>
   <p>
    In a further model of privatization, the entire operation of a prison is contracted to a commercial business or a not-for-profit organization. In this model the state builds and retains ownership of the prison buildings, but it enters into a contract with a company that operates and manages the prison.
   </p>
   <p>
    A more extensive model of privatization occurs in cases where a commercial company (often a consortium of companies) takes a prison from drawing board to final operation. In this model the state enters into a contract with the business or consortium. The latter agrees to provide a set number of prison places to a contractual standard; the state in turn agrees to pay for the set number of places over a contractually agreed-upon period of time.
   </p>
   <p>
    A fundamental change accompanying the introduction of privatization is the concept of the market model of prisons. As a consequence of this model, many of the costs of increased imprisonment are hidden in the short term. In fiscal terms, high capital expenditure is converted into long-term revenue expenditure, which reduces current (short-term) financial costs while increasing future (long-term) costs to the public.
   </p>
  </h2>
 </h1>
 <h1 id="h272184">
  <title>
   Prison populations
  </title>
  <h2 id="h272185">
   <title>
    National trends
   </title>
   <p>
    By the early 21st century there were more than 9 million men, women, and children in prisons around the world, most of whom were located in three countries: the United States (with more than 2 million prisoners), China (with more than 1.5 million prisoners), and Russia (with roughly 1 million prisoners). Prior to the mid-20th century the number of incarcerated individuals worldwide had been far lower.
   </p>
   <p>
    The general rise in prison populations has been attributed to a variety of factors. Available evidence suggests that it is a consequence of greater public awareness (and fear) of crime, even in jurisdictions that have not experienced an increase in crime rates; changes in legislation that leave judges little sentencing flexibility in individual cases; and police targeting of drug-related offenses since the 1980s. It is nonetheless very difficult to identify a correspondence between crime rates and rates of imprisonment.
   </p>
   <p>
    In 1880 England’s prison population stood at 32,000. After the prisons came under central government control, there was a long period of decline in the number of prisoners, probably the result of changes in sentencing laws and practices. By the end of World War I the daily average prison population had decreased to roughly 10,000, and it remained relatively stable during the interwar years. After World War II there was a period of steady increase that continued unabated for several decades. From a daily average figure of about 12,000 in 1945, the English prison population grew despite a variety of legal changes designed to contain it. By the 1960s it had reached 30,000—the level of the 1880s—and by the mid-1970s it surpassed 40,000, notwithstanding the introduction of a parole system and suspended sentences. In the early 21st century the total prison population in England and Wales exceeded 80,000. A similar trend occurred in the United States. Roughly 250,000 persons were incarcerated in penitentiaries in 1975, but the number of prisoners increased exponentially through the remainder of the 20th century.
   </p>
   <p>
    Although most industrialized societies experienced a rapid increase in prison populations after World War II, the opposite trend was observed in the Netherlands, where the prison population was halved from 1950 to 1975. By 1990, owing to shorter sentences for common offenses, there were fewer than 2,500 convicted offenders (in addition to another 3,000 awaiting trial) imprisoned in the entire country. However, when sentences were lengthened in the 1990s, the prison population increased to nearly 15,000 by the end of that decade, and it exceeded 21,000 by the end of 2005. Another country that experienced a decrease in prison population in the last decades of the 20th century was Finland, where shorter sentences and the increased use of parole and suspended sentences caused the number of incarcerated people to fall by two-fifths during the 1990s. The country had fewer than 4,000 people in prison at the end of 2005.
   </p>
   <p>
    In most prison systems, minority groups are significantly overrepresented. This is especially true of racial minorities, such as African Americans in the United States, Roma in central Europe, Aborigines in Australia, and Maori in New Zealand.
   </p>
   <p>
    Females account for less than one-tenth of the prison population in most countries. Some countries, however, have experienced an increase in the number of women prisoners. Of these, a certain proportion is associated with drug convictions, either for drug abuse or, as is more often the case for women from countries such as Nigeria and Jamaica, for serving as “drug mules” (carriers of drugs). Women and younger prisoners, unless they are being tried as adults, are held in separate prisons. Many women who end up in prison have been physically or sexually abused, and in most cases their needs are quite different from those of male prisoners, especially with respect to psychological support and vocational-skills training. In addition, many will have been the primary caregivers for their children. Juvenile offenders also have special needs; they generally receive age-appropriate education and vocational training with an emphasis on preventing
    <xref articleid="62896">
     recidivism
    </xref>
    .
   </p>
  </h2>
  <h2 id="h272186">
   <title>
    Prisoners’ rights
   </title>
   <p>
    As an aspect of human rights, the concept of prisoners’ rights has been upheld by a number of international declarations and national constitutions. The underlying assumption—that people who are detained or imprisoned do not cease to be human beings, no matter how serious the associated crime—was expressed in the
    <xref articleid="106289" refid="h219340">
     International Covenant on Civil and Political Rights
    </xref>
    , Article 10, which states, “All persons deprived of their liberty shall be treated with humanity and with respect for the inherent dignity of the human person.” This rests on the principle that the deprivation of liberty (that is, imprisonment) is the operative punishment and that it should not be augmented by unnecessarily restrictive conditions.
   </p>
   <p>
    The implications of this principle have been recognized by many countries. In the United States, for example, prisoners may bring legal action under the provisions of the U.S. Constitution—notably the
    <xref articleid="488724">
     Eighth Amendment
    </xref>
    ’s prohibition of “cruel and unusual punishments” and the
    <xref articleid="474682">
     Fourteenth Amendment
    </xref>
    ’s guarantees of
    <xref articleid="31369">
     due process
    </xref>
    and
    <xref articleid="32834">
     equal protection
    </xref>
    of the laws. In some cases, courts have ordered state prison administrators to make major improvements in prison conditions and disciplinary procedures or to close down particular institutions. In Europe, prisoners have the right to take cases to the
    <xref articleid="389483">
     European Court of Human Rights
    </xref>
    , but they may also utilize national courts.
   </p>
   <p>
    Intergovernmental organizations (such as the United Nations) and nongovernmental organizations (such as
    <xref articleid="7211">
     Amnesty International
    </xref>
    ) have lobbied worldwide in defense of prisoners’ rights, such as the right to expect personal safety and security while in prison. Prison authorities are particularly responsible for ensuring the safety of those most likely to be attacked or abused by fellow prisoners; these include former law enforcement officers sentenced for corruption (or similar crimes) and those guilty of sexual offenses against children. In some systems, such offenders have been put in solitary confinement for their own protection. Prison administrators are also responsible for protecting the racial, cultural, and religious rights of prisoners.
   </p>
  </h2>
 </h1>
 <h1 id="h272187">
  <title>
   Alternatives to prison
  </title>
  <p>
   In most criminal justice systems the majority of offenders are dealt with by means other than custody—that is, by fines and other financial penalties, probation, supervision, or orders to make reparation in some practical form to the community.
  </p>
  <h2 id="h272188">
   <title>
    Fines
   </title>
   <p>
    The most common penalty is the fine. For example, in the 1980s in England, about four-fifths of all defendants found guilty of crimes were fined. The imposition of a fine acts as a simple penalty that avoids the disadvantages of many other forms of sentence. It is inexpensive to administer and avoids the associated consequences, such as social stigma and job loss, that may follow imprisonment. However, fines are essentially regressive, meaning that they may be less burdensome for affluent offenders than for less affluent ones. There is the additional possibility that the convicted offender lacks the financial resources, or earns such a small income, that he cannot pay anything more than a minimal fine. In response to this problem, some countries (notably Sweden) have allowed the court to calculate a fine based on a number of days’ earnings.
   </p>
   <p>
    Enforcement of fines can be problematic. Some offenders who are fined have to be brought back to court for nonpayment. If an offender fails to pay a fine as a result of willful neglect or culpable default, he may be committed to prison, or his property can be seized and sold, while a
    <xref articleid="36110">
     garnishment
    </xref>
    order can be used to obtain any funds in a bank account. The length of time for which an offender may be committed to prison for deliberate nonpayment of a fine depends on the amount outstanding, though in some cases this involves very short periods (such as one to two weeks). If offenders are able to pay the outstanding amount, they can gain immediate release, and if they pay a portion of the fine, the term of imprisonment can be reduced proportionately.
   </p>
  </h2>
  <h2 id="h272189">
   <title>
    Restitution
   </title>
   <p>
    Related to the fine is an order to pay restitution (also known by the term
    <e type="italic">
     compensation
    </e>
    ), which has been a popular alternative to punitive sentencing in some countries. Instead of emphasizing punishment of the offender, however, most restitution programs are intended to assist or compensate the victims of crime. Victims of violent crime in some jurisdictions, including Great Britain, Australia, and Canada, are entitled to restitution from public funds, even in cases where the offender is identified and can afford to pay restitution. Generally, this type of program is administered by a criminal-injuries compensation board, to which the victim must present evidence of the violence and the resulting extent of loss. When restitution is required of the offender, it often amounts to payment for loss of property, repayment of stolen money, or payment for medical costs stemming from injury.
   </p>
  </h2>
  <h2 id="h272190">
   <title>
    Other penalties
   </title>
   <p>
    Several means of penalizing offenders involve neither prison terms nor the payment of money. One alternative, community supervision, may take many different forms but essentially involves the suspension of a sentence subject to the condition that the offender agree to a specified period of supervision by a probation officer and comply with such other requirements set forth by the court. In some countries this supervision is carried out by a probation service. An offender who obeys the supervision order and does not commit any further offense will usually avoid any further penalty. An offender who fails to meet the requirements, however, can be brought back before the court and be punished for the original offense as well as any later ones committed. In many U.S. states this form of probation has been combined with a suspended sentence, which is the sentence that would have been served if the offender had broken the order. In the country of England such sentences are not fixed in advance, and the court has complete discretion in the event of a breach by the offender. English law also allows suspended sentences of imprisonment for a specified period (not more than two years), on condition that the offender commit no further offense during the period of suspension. In contrast to probation, suspended sentences do not require supervision or any other condition.
   </p>
   <p>
    Reparation, which mandates that an offender provide services to the victim or to the community, has gained in popularity in a number of jurisdictions. Many countries have instituted the use of the community service order, also known as a noncustodial penalty. Under such an arrangement the court is empowered to order anyone convicted of an offense that could be punished with imprisonment to perform a specified number of hours of unpaid work for the community, usually over a period of 12 months. So that community service orders do not amount to
    <xref articleid="34837">
     forced labour
    </xref>
    , an offender must consent to the order before it is issued. It is typically carried out during the leisure time of the offender under the direction of the probation service. The work varies depending on the area, the time of year, and the offender’s abilities: in some cases it may involve heavy physical labour, but in others it may require duties such as the provision of help to individuals with physical or mental disabilities. Offenders completing the community service order receive no further penalty unless they fail to carry out the work without a reasonable excuse, in which case they can be resentenced for the original offense. This form of judicial disposal has been introduced throughout much of Europe and in a number of countries in sub-Saharan Africa, including Kenya and Malawi.
   </p>
   <p>
    When compared with imprisonment, community service is far less expensive to administer, less damaging to the offender and his family, and more useful to the community. Critics of noncustodial and probational penalties say that the measures are too lenient, while proponents say that imprisonment for minor and nonviolent crimes is costly and less effective than supervised terms of community service. The vast majority of offenders complete their community service orders satisfactorily.
   </p>
   <p>
    Other alternatives to prison are based on the idea of preventing offenders from committing future offenses. The most familiar approach involves disqualifying an offender from driving a motor vehicle or from holding a driver’s license. This practice is commonly used when dealing with offenders who have committed serious driving offenses (such as driving while intoxicated) or repeated but less serious offenses (such as speeding). Other forms of disqualification are imposed on offenders convicted of particular types of crimes. For example, a company director convicted of accounting fraud may be barred from directing another company or joining a corporate board; a corrupt politician may be blocked from holding future public office; and parents who abuse their children may be deprived of parental rights. Finally, new technologies, such as electronic monitoring through ankle bracelets and other surveillance devices, have allowed probation and parole officers to restrict the movement of offenders who live in their own homes or in supervised accommodations.
   </p>
   <signature>
    Andrew G. Coyle
   </signature>
  </h2>
 </h1>
 <h1 id="h272191">
  <title>
   Bibliography
  </title>
  <p>
   Useful reference works on prisons in general and on the use of imprisonment include
   <e type="smallcap">
    Norval Morris
   </e>
   and
   <e type="smallcap">
    David J. Rothman
   </e>
   (eds.),
   <e type="italic">
    The Oxford History of the Prison: The Practice of Punishment in Western Society
   </e>
   (1995);
   <e type="smallcap">
    Mark Colvin
   </e>
   ,
   <e type="italic">
    Penitentiaries, Reformatories, and Chain Gangs: Social Theory and the History of Punishment in Nineteenth-Century America
   </e>
   (1997);
   <e type="smallcap">
    Robert P. Weiss
   </e>
   and
   <e type="smallcap">
    Nigel South
   </e>
   (eds.),
   <e type="italic">
    Comparing Prison Systems: Toward a Comparative and International Penology
   </e>
   (1998);
   <e type="smallcap">
    Jonathan Simon
   </e>
   ,
   <e type="italic">
    Poor Discipline: Parole and the Social Control of the Underclass, 1890–1990
   </e>
   (1993);
   <e type="smallcap">
    Michel Foucault
   </e>
   ,
   <e type="italic">
    Discipline and Punish: The Birth of the Prison
   </e>
   (1995);
   <e type="smallcap">
    Michael Ignatieff
   </e>
   ,
   <e type="italic">
    A Just Measure of Pain
   </e>
   (1978, reissued 1989);
   <e type="smallcap">
    David Cayley
   </e>
   ,
   <e type="italic">
    The Expanding Prison: The Crisis in Crime and Punishment and the Search for Alternatives
   </e>
   (1998);
   <e type="smallcap">
    Nils Christie
   </e>
   ,
   <e type="italic">
    Crime Control as Industry: Towards Gulags, Western Style
   </e>
   (2000); and
   <e type="smallcap">
    Nigel Rodley
   </e>
   ,
   <e type="italic">
    The Treatment of Prisoners under International Law
   </e>
   , 2nd ed. (2000).
  </p>
  <p>
   Works examining sentencing and the role of prisons include
   <e type="smallcap">
    Michael Tonry
   </e>
   and
   <e type="smallcap">
    Kathleen Hatlestad
   </e>
   (eds.),
   <e type="italic">
    Sentencing Reform in Overcrowded Times: A Comparative Perspective
   </e>
   (1997);
   <e type="smallcap">
    Norval Morris
   </e>
   and
   <e type="smallcap">
    Michael Tonry
   </e>
   ,
   <e type="italic">
    Between Prison and Probation: Intermediate Punishments in a Rational Sentencing System
   </e>
   (1990);
   <e type="smallcap">
    Peter H. Rossi
   </e>
   and
   <e type="smallcap">
    Richard A. Berk
   </e>
   ,
   <e type="italic">
    Just Punishments
   </e>
   (1997);
   <e type="smallcap">
    Gresham Sykes
   </e>
   ,
   <e type="italic">
    The Society of Captives
   </e>
   (1958);
   <e type="smallcap">
    Donald Cressey
   </e>
   ,
   <e type="italic">
    The Prison: Studies in Institutional Organisation and Change
   </e>
   (1961);
   <e type="smallcap">
    Thomas Mathiesen
   </e>
   ,
   <e type="italic">
    Prison on Trial
   </e>
   , 3rd ed. (2006);
   <e type="smallcap">
    Vivien Stern
   </e>
   ,
   <e type="italic">
    A Sin Against the Future: Imprisonment in the World
   </e>
   (1998); and
   <e type="smallcap">
    Dirk van Zyl Smit
   </e>
   and
   <e type="smallcap">
    Frieder Dünkel
   </e>
   ,
   <e type="italic">
    Imprisonment Today and Tomorrow
   </e>
   , 2nd ed. (2001).
  </p>
 </h1>
 <copyright>
  Encyclopædia Britannica
 </copyright>
</article>