<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "syndication_xml.dtd">
<article articleid="39122" articletypeid="1" language="en_us" lastupdate="2022-Jan-03 09:25:30" url="/article/hand/39122" version="4">
 <title>
  hand
 </title>
 <p>
  <assembly id="a101313" url="/assembly/view/101313">
   <title>
    bones of the human hand
   </title>
   <media mediaid="99194" type="image" url="/94/99194-004-D742EF27.jpg"/>
   <caption>
    Bones of the hand, showing the carpal bones (wrist bones), metacarpal bones (bones of the hand proper), and phalanges (finger bones).
   </caption>
   <credit>
    Encyclopædia Britannica, Inc.
   </credit>
  </assembly>
  <e type="bold">
   hand
  </e>
  ,
  <assemblyref assemblyid="a101313"/>
  grasping organ at the end of the forelimb of certain vertebrates that exhibits great mobility and flexibility in the digits and in the whole organ. It is made up of the
  <xref articleid="77567">
   wrist
  </xref>
  joint, the
  <xref articleid="20452">
   carpal bones
  </xref>
  , the metacarpal bones, and the phalanges. The digits include a medial thumb (when viewed with the palm down), containing two phalanges, and four fingers, each containing three phalanges.
 </p>
 <p>
  <assembly id="a73005" url="/assembly/view/73005">
   <title>
    power and precision grips
   </title>
   <media mediaid="52984" type="image" url="/84/52984-004-9D503C89.jpg"/>
   <caption>
    A fully opposable thumb gives the human hand its unique power grip (left) and precision grip (right).
   </caption>
   <credit>
    Encyclopædia Britannica, Inc.
   </credit>
  </assembly>
  <assemblyref assemblyid="a73005"/>
  The major function of the hand in all vertebrates except human beings is locomotion; bipedal locomotion in humans frees the hands for a largely manipulative function. In primates the tips of the fingers are covered by
  <xref articleid="54686">
   fingernails
  </xref>
  —a specialization that improves manipulation. The palms and undersides of the fingers are marked by creases and covered by ridges called palm prints and
  <xref articleid="34291">
   fingerprints
  </xref>
  , which function to improve tactile sensitivity and grip. The friction ridges are arranged in general patterns that are peculiar to each species but that differ in detail. No two individuals are alike, and in humans the patterns are used for identification. The thumb is usually set at an angle distinct from the other digits; in humans and the great apes it rotates at the carpometacarpal joint, and it is therefore opposable to the other fingers and may be used in combination with them to pick up small objects.
 </p>
 <p>
  <assembly id="a71621" url="/assembly/view/71621">
   <title>
    white-cheeked gibbon (
    <e type="italic">
     Nomascus leucogenys
    </e>
    )
   </title>
   <media mediaid="76393" type="image" url="/93/76393-004-E4F720B1.jpg"/>
   <caption>
    White-cheeked gibbons (
    <e type="italic">
     Nomascus leucogenys
    </e>
    ) are native to Southeast Asia.
   </caption>
   <credit>
    Encyclopædia Britannica, Inc.
   </credit>
  </assembly>
  <assemblyref assemblyid="a71621"/>
  Among the
  <xref articleid="7985">
   apes
  </xref>
  and some New World
  <xref articleid="53371">
   monkeys
  </xref>
  , the hand is specialized for
  <xref articleid="16092">
   brachiation
  </xref>
  —hand-over-hand swinging through the trees. Digits two to five are elongated and used in clasping tree limbs; the thumb is reduced and little used in swinging. Terrestrial monkeys, such as the
  <xref articleid="11612">
   baboon
  </xref>
  , do not have reduced thumbs and can carry out precise movements with fingers and opposing thumb. The development of dexterity in the hands and increase in brain size are believed to have occurred together in the
  <xref articleid="117282">
   evolution of humans
  </xref>
  .
 </p>
 <signature>
  EB Editors
 </signature>
 <copyright>
  Encyclopædia Britannica
 </copyright>
</article>