<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "syndication_xml.dtd">
<article articleid="40012" articletypeid="1" language="en_us" lastupdate="2021-Jun-30 22:36:05" url="/article/Henrician-Articles/40012" version="1">
 <title>
  Henrician Articles
 </title>
 <p>
  <e type="bold">
   Henrician Articles
  </e>
  , Polish
  <e type="bold">
   Artykuly Henrykowskie
  </e>
  , (1573) statement of the rights and privileges of the Polish gentry (
  <e type="italic">
   szlachta
  </e>
  ) that all elected kings of Poland, beginning with Henry of Valois (elected May 11, 1573), were obliged to confirm and that severely limited the authority of the Polish monarchy. After King Sigismund II Augustus died (July 1572), Henry of Valois, duc d’Anjou and the future Henry III of France, emerged as the favourite candidate for election to the Polish throne. The Polish Protestants, however, feared that the Roman Catholic Henry, who had been partly responsible for the slaughter of French Protestants during the Massacre of St. Bartholomew’s Day (Aug. 23–24, 1572), would institute repressive measures against them if he were elected king of Poland. They therefore demanded that the Polish nobility, assembled for the election of a king, explicitly define the constitutional limits of royal power before choosing the new monarch.
 </p>
 <p>
  The resulting statement, known as the Henrician Articles, provided that the king convoke the Polish Sejm (legislature) every two years and between sessions regularly hold council with a rotating group of senators, chosen by the Sejm. The articles reserved for the Sejm the right to choose the king’s successor as well as his bride and also restricted the king’s power over the army and legislation. In addition, the king was obliged to confirm the Compact of Warsaw (Jan. 28, 1573), which guaranteed religious liberty in Poland. The articles also stated that if the king did not fulfill his obligations and honour the Henrician Articles, the gentry would automatically be absolved from its allegiance to him.
 </p>
 <p>
  The Henrician Articles remained the fundamental law of Poland until 1795.
 </p>
 <copyright>
  Encyclopædia Britannica
 </copyright>
</article>