<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "syndication_xml.dtd">
<article articleid="40377" articletypeid="1" language="en_us" lastupdate="2021-Jun-30 22:38:22" url="/article/hide-and-seek/40377" version="4">
 <title>
  hide-and-seek
 </title>
 <p>
  <assembly id="a113003" url="/assembly/view/113003">
   <title>
    hide-and-seek
   </title>
   <media mediaid="117074" type="image" url="/74/117074-004-D6C810CB.jpg"/>
   <caption>
    Children playing hide-and-seek, oil on tinplate by Friedrich Eduard Meyerheim.
   </caption>
   <credit/>
  </assembly>
  <e type="bold">
   hide-and-seek
  </e>
  ,
  <assemblyref assemblyid="a113003"/>
  old and popular
  <xref articleid="24076">
   children’s game
  </xref>
  in which one player closes his or her eyes for a brief period (often counting to 100) while the other players hide. The seeker then opens his eyes and tries to find the hiders; the first one found is the next seeker, and the last is the winner of the round. In one of many forms of the game, the hiders try to run back to “home base” while the seeker is away looking for them; if all of the hiders return safely, the seeker repeats as seeker in the next round.
 </p>
 <p>
  The game is played differently in various regions; sometimes the seeker may be helped by those he finds. Alternatively, only one child hides and is sought by all the rest, as in sardines, where the hider is joined by seekers surreptitiously as they find him (the name of the game coming from the crowded condition of the hiding place). Hide-and-seek appears to be equivalent to the game
  <e type="italic">
   apodidraskinda,
  </e>
  described by the 2nd-century Greek writer Julius Pollux. In modern Greece hide-and-seek is called
  <e type="italic">
   kryfto
  </e>
  .
 </p>
 <p>
  The game is played throughout the world. In Spain the game is called
  <e type="italic">
   el escondite
  </e>
  , in France
  <e type="italic">
   jeu de cache-cache
  </e>
  , in Israel
  <e type="italic">
   machboim
  </e>
  , in South Korea
  <e type="italic">
   sumbaggoggil
  </e>
  , and, in Romania
  <e type="italic">
   de-av-ati ascunselea
  </e>
  . Hide-and-seek is known throughout South and Central America under such names as
  <e type="italic">
   tuja
  </e>
  (Bolivia),
  <e type="italic">
   escondidas
  </e>
  (Ecuador and Chile), and
  <e type="italic">
   cucumbè
  </e>
  (Honduras and El Salvador).
 </p>
 <p>
  There are many variants on the game. For instance, the Igbo children in Nigeria play
  <e type="italic">
   oro
  </e>
  , a combination of hide-and-seek and
  <xref articleid="70905">
   tag
  </xref>
  in which the seeker stands in the centre of a large circle that has been drawn in the sand and tells other players to hide. The seeker then steps out of the circle, finds, and then chases the other children, who must run into the circle to be safe. The child touched before reaching the circle must be the next seeker.
 </p>
 <signature>
  EB Editors
 </signature>
 <copyright>
  Encyclopædia Britannica
 </copyright>
</article>