<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "syndication_xml.dtd">
<article articleid="41473" articletypeid="1" language="en_us" lastupdate="2021-Jun-30 22:45:07" url="/article/human-migration/41473" version="5">
 <title>
  human migration
 </title>
 <p>
  <assembly id="a243616" url="/assembly/view/243616">
   <title>
    refugees in Slovenia
   </title>
   <media mediaid="187480" type="image" url="/80/187480-004-60F2F5A4.jpg"/>
   <caption>
    A long line of refugees from the Middle East, primarily from war-torn Syria and Iraq, being escorted across Slovenia by local officials, 2015.
   </caption>
   <credit>
    © Janossy Gergely/Shutterstock.com
   </credit>
  </assembly>
  <e type="bold">
   human migration
  </e>
  ,
  <assemblyref assemblyid="a243616"/>
  the permanent change of residence by an individual or group; it excludes such movements as nomadism, migrant labour, commuting, and tourism, all of which are transitory in nature.
 </p>
 <p>
  A brief treatment of human migration follows. For further discussion,
  <e type="italic">
   see
  </e>
  <xref articleid="108576" refid="h60665">
   population: Migration
  </xref>
  .
 </p>
 <p>
  Migrations fall into several broad categories. First, internal and international migration may be distinguished. Within any country there are movements of individuals and families from one area to another (for example, from rural areas to the cities), and this is distinct from movements from one country to another. Second, migration may be voluntary or forced. Most voluntary migration, whether internal or external, is undertaken in search of better economic opportunities or housing. Forced migrations usually involve people who have been expelled by governments during war or other political upheavals or who have been forcibly transported as slaves or prisoners. Intermediate between these two categories are the voluntary migrations of refugees fleeing war,
  <xref articleid="33683">
   famine
  </xref>
  , or natural disasters.
 </p>
 <p>
  Human migrations within recorded history have transformed the entire aspect of lands and continents and the racial, ethnic, and linguistic composition of their populations. The map of
  <xref articleid="106055">
   Europe
  </xref>
  , for example, is the product of several major early migrations involving the
  <xref articleid="36579">
   Germanic peoples
  </xref>
  , the
  <xref articleid="68162">
   Slavs
  </xref>
  , and the Turks, among others. And in the course of 400 years—from the late 16th through the 20th century—the
  <xref articleid="6141">
   Americas
  </xref>
  ,
  <xref articleid="110544">
   Australia
  </xref>
  ,
  <xref articleid="56698">
   Oceania
  </xref>
  , the northern half of Asia, and parts of Africa were colonized by European migrants. The overseas migration of Europeans during this period totaled about 60 million people.
 </p>
 <p>
  <assembly id="a60769" url="/assembly/view/60769">
   <title>
    Swedish immigrants en route to the western United States, mid-19th century
   </title>
   <media mediaid="70455" type="image" url="/55/70455-004-AE145B92.jpg"/>
   <caption>
    Illustration depicting Swedish immigrants en route to the western United States in the mid-19th century. By 1840 the U.S. population had risen to 17 million, and the flood of immigration that was to double this figure in 25 years had begun. Many of these immigrants were from the British Isles, Germany, and Scandinavia.
   </caption>
   <credit>
    Library of Congress, Washington, D.C.
   </credit>
  </assembly>
  <assemblyref assemblyid="a60769"/>
  The largest migration in history was the so-called Great Atlantic Migration from Europe to
  <xref articleid="110716">
   North America
  </xref>
  , the first major wave of which began in the 1840s with mass movements from
  <xref articleid="106328">
   Ireland
  </xref>
  and
  <xref articleid="106260">
   Germany
  </xref>
  . In the 1880s a second and larger wave developed from eastern and southern Europe; between 1880 and 1910 some 17 million Europeans entered the United States. The total number of Europeans reaching the
  <xref articleid="111233">
   United States
  </xref>
  amounted to 37 million between 1820 and 1980.
 </p>
 <p>
  <assembly id="a232410" url="/assembly/view/232410">
   <title>
    naturalization
   </title>
   <media mediaid="198541" type="image" url="/41/198541-004-4CC472E4.jpg"/>
   <caption>
    Pres. Barack Obama speaking to new U.S. citizens during a naturalization ceremony held in Washington, D.C., 2015.
   </caption>
   <credit>
    National Archives, Washington, D.C.
   </credit>
  </assembly>
  <assemblyref assemblyid="a232410"/>
  From 1801 to 1914 about 7.5 million migrants moved from European to Asiatic Russia (i.e.,
  <xref articleid="67598">
   Siberia
  </xref>
  ), and between
  <xref articleid="110198">
   World Wars I
  </xref>
  and
  <xref articleid="110199">
   II
  </xref>
  about 6 million more, not counting innumerable deportees to Soviet labour camps, voluntarily migrated there. Since World War II the largest voluntary migrations have involved groups from developing countries moving to the industrialized nations. Some 13 million migrants became permanent residents of western Europe from the 1960s through the ’80s, and more than 10 million permanent immigrants were admitted legally to the United States in that same period, with illegal immigration adding several millions more.
 </p>
 <p>
  Slave migrations and mass expulsions also have been part of human history for millennia. The largest slave migrations were probably those compelled by European slave traders operating in
  <xref articleid="108290">
   Africa
  </xref>
  from the 16th to the 19th century; perhaps 20 million slaves were consigned to the Americas, though substantial numbers died in the appalling conditions of the
  <xref articleid="52545">
   Atlantic passage
  </xref>
  . The largest mass expulsions have probably been those imposed by Nazi Germany, which deported 7–8 million persons during World War II (1939–45), and by the Soviet Union, which forcibly expelled 9–10 million ethnic Germans from eastern Europe into Germany in the closing year of the war and afterward. Some 14 million people fled in one direction or another during the partition of British India into
  <xref articleid="111197">
   India
  </xref>
  and
  <xref articleid="108520">
   Pakistan
  </xref>
  in the late 1940s. The largest migrations in the second half of the 20th century and the beginning of the 21st century have consisted of refugees fleeing war, such as the estimated 3–4 million people who fled
  <xref articleid="106010">
   Afghanistan
  </xref>
  in the 1980s and the 5–6 million who departed
  <xref articleid="395623">
   Syria
  </xref>
  in the 2010s.
 </p>
 <p>
  The dominant trend in internal migration during the 20th century was the movement from rural to urban areas. As a consequence, urban growth since World War II has been very rapid in much of the world, particularly in developing countries.
 </p>
 <signature>
  EB Editors
 </signature>
 <copyright>
  Encyclopædia Britannica
 </copyright>
</article>