<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "syndication_xml.dtd">
<article articleid="41660" articletypeid="1" language="en_us" lastupdate="2022-Mar-18 18:30:49" url="/article/Huygens-principle/41660" version="2">
 <title>
  Huygens’ principle
 </title>
 <p>
  <assembly id="a3156" url="/assembly/view/3156">
   <title>
    Huygens’ principle
   </title>
   <media mediaid="5704" type="image" url="/04/5704-004-0E039DFE.jpg"/>
   <caption>
    (A) Huygens’ principle applied to both plane and spherical waves. Each point on the wave front
    <e type="italic">
     AA
    </e>
    ′ can be thought of as a radiator of a spherical wave that expands out with velocity
    <e type="italic">
     c
    </e>
    , traveling a distance
    <e type="italic">
     ct
    </e>
    after time
    <e type="italic">
     t
    </e>
    . A secondary wave front
    <e type="italic">
     BB
    </e>
    ′ is formed from the addition of all the wave amplitudes from the wave front
    <e type="italic">
     AA
    </e>
    ′. (B) Huygens’ construction of a diffracted wave from a transmission grating. The wave front is constructed by adding spherical waves from each slit of the grating. The wave emitted at a given slit is delayed by one full cycle with respect to the wave from an adjacent slit.
   </caption>
   <credit>
    Encyclopædia Britannica, Inc.
   </credit>
  </assembly>
  <e type="bold">
   Huygens’ principle
  </e>
  , also called
  <e type="bold">
   Huygens-Fresnel principle
  </e>
  ,
  <assemblyref assemblyid="a3156"/>
  a statement that all points of a wave front of sound in a transmitting medium or of light in a vacuum or transparent medium may be regarded as new sources of wavelets that expand in every direction at a rate depending on their velocities. Proposed by the Dutch mathematician, physicist, and astronomer Christiaan Huygens in 1690, it is a powerful method for studying various optical phenomena.
 </p>
 <p>
  <assembly id="a3537" url="/assembly/view/3537">
   <title>
    Huygens’ principle
   </title>
   <media mediaid="4321" type="image" url="/21/4321-004-C2D80BB7.jpg"/>
   <caption>
    Originating along the fronts of (A) circular waves and (B) plane waves, wavelets recombine to produce the propagating wave front. (C) The diffraction of sound around a corner arising from Huygens’ wavelets.
   </caption>
   <credit>
    Encyclopædia Britannica, Inc.
   </credit>
  </assembly>
  <assemblyref assemblyid="a3537"/>
  A surface tangent to the wavelets constitutes the new wave front and is called the envelope of the wavelets. If a medium is homogeneous and has the same properties throughout (i.e., is isotropic), permitting light or sound to travel with the same speed regardless of its direction of propagation, the three-dimensional envelope of a point source will be spherical; otherwise, as is the case of light with many crystals, the envelope will be ellipsoidal in shape (
  <e type="italic">
   see
  </e>
  <xref articleid="1617">
   double refraction
  </xref>
  ). An extended light source will consist of an infinite number of point sources and may be thought of as generating a plane wave front.
 </p>
 <signature>
  EB Editors
 </signature>
 <copyright>
  Encyclopædia Britannica
 </copyright>
</article>