<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "syndication_xml.dtd">
<article articleid="42705" articletypeid="1" language="en_us" lastupdate="2022-Jun-13 17:10:19" url="/article/ionization/42705" version="2">
 <title>
  ionization
 </title>
 <p>
  <e type="bold">
   ionization
  </e>
  , in
  <xref articleid="108655">
   chemistry
  </xref>
  and
  <xref articleid="108654">
   physics
  </xref>
  , any process by which electrically neutral
  <xref articleid="110411">
   atoms
  </xref>
  or
  <xref articleid="53247">
   molecules
  </xref>
  are converted to electrically charged atoms or molecules (
  <xref articleid="42688">
   ions
  </xref>
  ) through gaining or losing
  <xref articleid="32316">
   electrons
  </xref>
  . Ionization is one of the principal ways that radiation, such as charged particles and
  <xref articleid="77656">
   X rays
  </xref>
  , transfers its energy to matter.
 </p>
 <p>
  In chemistry, ionization often occurs in a liquid
  <xref articleid="68634">
   solution
  </xref>
  . For example, neutral molecules of
  <xref articleid="41729">
   hydrogen chloride
  </xref>
  gas, HCl, react with similarly polar
  <xref articleid="76210">
   water
  </xref>
  molecules, H
  <sub>
   2
  </sub>
  O, to produce positive hydronium ions, H
  <sub>
   3
  </sub>
  O
  <sup>
   +
  </sup>
  , and negative chloride ions, Cl
  <sup>
   -
  </sup>
  . At the surface of a piece of metallic
  <xref articleid="78379">
   zinc
  </xref>
  in contact with an acidic solution, zinc atoms, Zn, lose electrons to hydrogen ions and become colourless zinc ions, Zn
  <sup>
   2
  </sup>
  <sup>
   +
  </sup>
  .
 </p>
 <p>
  Ionization by collision occurs in gases at low
  <xref articleid="61303">
   pressures
  </xref>
  when an
  <xref articleid="32273">
   electric current
  </xref>
  is passed through them. If the electrons constituting the current have sufficient energy (the ionization energy is different for each substance), they force other electrons out of the neutral gas molecules, producing ion pairs that individually consist of the resultant positive ion and detached negative electron. Negative ions are also formed as some of the electrons attach themselves to neutral gas molecules. Gases may also be ionized by intermolecular collisions at high
  <xref articleid="71632">
   temperatures
  </xref>
  .
 </p>
 <p>
  Ionization, in general, occurs whenever sufficiently energetic charged particles or radiant energy travel through gases,
  <xref articleid="110301">
   liquids
  </xref>
  , or
  <xref articleid="68592">
   solids
  </xref>
  . Charged particles, such as
  <xref articleid="5891">
   alpha particles
  </xref>
  and electrons from
  <xref articleid="110413">
   radioactive
  </xref>
  materials, cause extensive ionization along their paths. Energetic neutral particles, such as
  <xref articleid="55406">
   neutrons
  </xref>
  and
  <xref articleid="55405">
   neutrinos
  </xref>
  , are more penetrating and cause almost no ionization. Pulses of radiant energy, such as X-ray and
  <xref articleid="35974">
   gamma-ray
  </xref>
  <xref articleid="59817">
   photons
  </xref>
  , can eject electrons from atoms by the
  <xref articleid="59805">
   photoelectric effect
  </xref>
  to cause ionization. The energetic electrons resulting from the absorption of radiant energy and the passage of charged particles in turn may cause further ionization, called secondary ionization. A certain minimal level of ionization is present in Earth’s atmosphere because of continuous absorption of
  <xref articleid="26471">
   cosmic rays
  </xref>
  from space and
  <xref articleid="74181">
   ultraviolet radiation
  </xref>
  from the
  <xref articleid="110144">
   Sun
  </xref>
  .
 </p>
 <signature>
  EB Editors
 </signature>
 <copyright>
  Encyclopædia Britannica
 </copyright>
</article>