<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "syndication_xml.dtd">
<article articleid="438923" articletypeid="1" language="en_us" lastupdate="2021-Jul-01 05:48:28" url="/article/60-Minutes/438923" version="6">
 <title>
  60 Minutes
 </title>
 <p>
  <e type="bold">
   60 Minutes
  </e>
  , prime-time American television news show. It debuted in 1968 on
  <xref articleid="21946">
   CBS
  </xref>
  and has become one of the most successful programs in broadcast history.
 </p>
 <p>
  Created by Don Hewitt and grounded in investigative journalism,
  <e type="italic">
   60 Minutes
  </e>
  is television’s longest continually running prime-time series. The first of the so-called TV newsmagazines, the program has become the industry standard for television journalism and has influenced similar (but less successful) programs on other networks.
  <e type="italic">
   60 Minutes
  </e>
  placed in
  <xref articleid="472952">
   Nielsen
  </xref>
  ’s annual top 10 for a record 23 consecutive seasons and has won more
  <xref articleid="32545">
   Emmy Awards
  </xref>
  than any other prime-time program.
 </p>
 <p>
  In each episode
  <e type="italic">
   60 Minutes
  </e>
  correspondents offer in-depth reporting on a range of issues of national interest, from politics to entertainment. The topics may originate in-house as reporter-driven pieces, or they may involve current events already receiving media attention. The correspondents have earned strong reputations and numerous awards for gaining unique access to sources and interviewees and for delivering compelling information. The program’s best-known reporter, the often tenacious Mike Wallace, worked as a full-time correspondent from 1968 to 2006, and during that time he won 20 Emmy Awards and three
  <xref articleid="598981">
   Peabody Awards
  </xref>
  . Other correspondents have included
  <xref articleid="571038">
   Dan Rather
  </xref>
  , Morley Safer, Lesley Stahl,
  <xref articleid="399785">
   Ed Bradley
  </xref>
  , Scott Pelley, Bob Simon, Steve Kroft, Lara Logan,
  <xref articleid="471638">
   Anderson Cooper
  </xref>
  , Norah O’Donnell, and Jon Wertheim.
 </p>
 <p>
  The show typically operates according to a fixed format, usually combining two serious news investigations with a personal profile or human-interest story. From 1979 to 2011
  <xref articleid="571498">
   Andy Rooney
  </xref>
  delivered a light or comedic commentary at the end of most episodes. At different times in the past, the show included a point-counterpoint segment, offering a conservative and a liberal perspective on a topic.
 </p>
 <signature>
  EB Editors
 </signature>
 <copyright>
  Encyclopædia Britannica
 </copyright>
</article>