<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "syndication_xml.dtd">
<article articleid="44137" articletypeid="1" language="en_us" lastupdate="2021-Jun-30 23:00:35" url="/article/jump-rope/44137" version="3">
 <title>
  jump rope
 </title>
 <p>
  <assembly id="a150036" url="/assembly/view/150036">
   <title>
    jumping rope
   </title>
   <media mediaid="145566" type="image" url="/66/145566-004-3B1DCA92.jpg"/>
   <caption>
    Jumping rope.
   </caption>
   <credit>
    Brand X Picture—Jupiterimages/Thinkstock
   </credit>
  </assembly>
  <e type="bold">
   jump rope
  </e>
  , also called
  <e type="bold">
   skip rope
  </e>
  ,
  <assemblyref assemblyid="a150036"/>
  <xref articleid="24076">
   children’s game
  </xref>
  played by individuals or teams with a piece of rope, which may have handles attached at each end. Jump rope, which dates back to the 19th century, is traditionally a girls’ playground or sidewalk activity in which two players turn a rope (holding it by its ends and swinging it in a circle) and the other players take turns jumping it while chanting a rhyme or counting. When it is played as a game, each player is required to move in while the rope is turning, complete the jump, and move out without contacting or stopping the rope; the jumps required usually become more complicated as the game proceeds.
 </p>
 <p>
  There are many types of jumps, including single, double, backward, crossed-feet, hot pepper (twice as fast as usual), quarter turns, half turns, full turns, and two-at-a-time (jumpers); in double Dutch, two ropes (or one long rope such as a clothesline that has been doubled) are turned simultaneously in opposite directions; in criss-cross, performed by one person holding both ends of the rope, the arms are crossed back and forth on alternate turns of the rope.
 </p>
 <p>
  There are countless chants, many originally from Germany and England, associated with jump rope, which often dictate the actions or stunts to be performed, such as:
 </p>
 <poetry>
  <line>
   One, two, touch my shoe,
  </line>
  <line>
   Three, four, touch the floor,
  </line>
  <line>
   Five, six, pick up sticks,
  </line>
  <line>
   Seven, eight, double rate,
  </line>
  <line>
   Nine, ten, out again.
  </line>
 </poetry>
 <p>
  In another version:
 </p>
 <poetry>
  <line>
   Apples, peaches, pears, and plums,
  </line>
  <line>
   Tell me when your birthday comes...
  </line>
 </poetry>
 <p>
  the jumper chants the names of the months, then the days up to the date of her birthday.
 </p>
 <p>
  More recent chants reflect inner-city culture. For instance:
 </p>
 <poetry>
  <line>
   Hey D.J., let’s sing that song, keep a footin’ all night long,
  </line>
  <line>
   Hey D.J., let’s sing that song, keep a hoppin’ all night long,
  </line>
  <line>
   Hey D.J., let’s sing that song, keep a turning, all night long,
  </line>
  <line>
   Hey D.J., let’s sing that song, keep a clapping all night long.
  </line>
 </poetry>
 <p>
  In Chinese and Vietnamese jump rope, a stationary rope or string, commonly elastic, is held in a rectangular configuration around two players’ legs; the jumper performs designated hops in and out of the rectangle, with the rope being raised on each successive jump.
 </p>
 <p>
  Single rope jumping or rope skipping is a popular form of cardiovascular exercise. This exercise originated with prizefighters to help develop their lungs and legs.
 </p>
 <copyright>
  Encyclopædia Britannica
 </copyright>
</article>