<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "syndication_xml.dtd">
<article articleid="443507" articletypeid="1" language="en_us" lastupdate="2021-Jul-01 05:51:04" url="/article/genetically-modified-organism/443507" version="16">
 <title>
  genetically modified organism (GMO)
 </title>
 <p>
  <assembly id="a128160" url="/assembly/view/128160">
   <title>
    genetically modified barley
   </title>
   <media mediaid="131365" type="image" url="/65/131365-004-AD0B5A1A.jpg"/>
   <caption>
    Genetically modified (GM) barley grown by researchers on a site belonging to Giessen University (Justus-Liebig-Universität) in Germany. The GM barley was investigated for its effects on soil quality.
   </caption>
   <credit>
    Ralph Orlowski/Getty Images
   </credit>
  </assembly>
  <e type="bold">
   genetically modified organism (GMO)
  </e>
  ,
  <assemblyref assemblyid="a128160"/>
  organism whose genome has been engineered in the laboratory in order to favour the expression of desired physiological traits or the generation of desired biological products. In conventional
  <xref articleid="48590">
   livestock
  </xref>
  production, crop farming, and even pet breeding, it has long been the practice to breed select individuals of a species in order to produce offspring that have desirable traits. In
  <xref articleid="110582">
   genetic
  </xref>
  modification, however, recombinant genetic technologies are employed to produce organisms whose genomes have been precisely altered at the molecular level, usually by the inclusion of
  <xref articleid="36352">
   genes
  </xref>
  from unrelated species of organisms that code for traits that would not be obtained easily through conventional selective breeding.
 </p>
 <p>
  <assembly id="a122433" url="/assembly/view/122433">
   <title>
    genetically modified organisms
   </title>
   <media mediaid="117844" type="image" url="/44/117844-004-46C4F162.jpg"/>
   <caption>
    Genetically modified organisms are produced using scientific methods that include recombinant DNA technology.
   </caption>
   <credit>
    Encyclopædia Britannica, Inc.
   </credit>
  </assembly>
  <assemblyref assemblyid="a122433"/>
  Genetically modified organisms (GMOs) are produced using scientific methods that include
  <xref articleid="437419">
   recombinant DNA technology
  </xref>
  and reproductive
  <xref articleid="473902">
   cloning
  </xref>
  . In reproductive cloning, a
  <xref articleid="56461">
   nucleus
  </xref>
  is extracted from a cell of the individual to be cloned and is inserted into the enucleated
  <xref articleid="28447">
   cytoplasm
  </xref>
  of a host
  <xref articleid="32069">
   egg
  </xref>
  (an enucleated egg is an egg cell that has had its own nucleus removed). The process results in the generation of an offspring that is genetically identical to the donor individual. The first animal produced by means of this cloning technique with a nucleus from an adult donor cell (as opposed to a donor embryo) was a sheep named
  <xref articleid="470939">
   Dolly
  </xref>
  , born in 1996. Since then a number of other animals, including
  <xref articleid="59987">
   pigs
  </xref>
  ,
  <xref articleid="106287">
   horses
  </xref>
  , and
  <xref articleid="108360">
   dogs
  </xref>
  , have been generated by reproductive cloning technology. Recombinant DNA technology, on the other hand, involves the insertion of one or more individual genes from an organism of one species into the
  <xref articleid="30730">
   DNA
  </xref>
  (deoxyribonucleic acid) of another. Whole-genome replacement, involving the transplantation of one
  <xref articleid="110416">
   bacterial
  </xref>
  genome into the “cell body,” or cytoplasm, of another microorganism, has been reported, although this technology is still limited to basic scientific applications.
 </p>
 <p>
  GMOs produced through genetic technologies have become a part of everyday life, entering into society through agriculture,
  <xref articleid="110314">
   medicine
  </xref>
  , research, and environmental management. However, while GMOs have benefited human society in many ways, some disadvantages exist; therefore, the production of GMOs remains a highly controversial topic in many parts of the world.
 </p>
 <h1 id="h279977">
  <title>
   GMOs in agriculture
  </title>
  <p>
   <assembly id="a128155" url="/assembly/view/128155">
    <title>
     genetically engineered corn (maize)
    </title>
    <media mediaid="131361" type="image" url="/61/131361-004-07890150.jpg"/>
    <caption>
     Genetically engineered corn (maize).
    </caption>
    <credit>
     © S74/Shutterstock.com
    </credit>
   </assembly>
   <assemblyref assemblyid="a128155"/>
   Genetically modified (GM) foods were first approved for human consumption in the United States in 1994, and by 2014–15 about 90 percent of the
   <xref articleid="26316">
    corn
   </xref>
   ,
   <xref articleid="26524">
    cotton
   </xref>
   , and
   <xref articleid="68954">
    soybeans
   </xref>
   planted in the United States were GM. By the end of 2014, GM crops covered nearly 1.8 million square kilometres (695,000 square miles) of land in more than two dozen countries worldwide. The majority of GM crops were grown in the Americas.
  </p>
  <p>
   Engineered crops can dramatically increase per area crop yields and, in some cases, reduce the use of chemical
   <xref articleid="42490">
    insecticides
   </xref>
   . For example, the application of wide-spectrum insecticides declined in many areas growing plants, such as
   <xref articleid="61051">
    potatoes
   </xref>
   , cotton, and corn, that were endowed with a gene from the bacterium
   <e type="italic">
    Bacillus thuringiensis
   </e>
   , which produces a natural insecticide called Bt toxin. Field studies conducted in India in which Bt cotton was compared with non-Bt cotton demonstrated a 30–80 percent increase in yield from the GM crop. This increase was attributed to marked improvement in the GM plants’ ability to overcome bollworm infestation, which was otherwise common. Studies of Bt cotton production in Arizona, U.S., demonstrated only small gains in yield—about 5 percent—with an estimated cost reduction of $25–$65 (USD) per acre owing to decreased
   <xref articleid="59408">
    pesticide
   </xref>
   applications. In China, where farmers first gained access to Bt cotton in 1997, the GM crop was initially successful. Farmers who had planted Bt cotton reduced their pesticide use by 50–80 percent and increased their earnings by as much as 36 percent. By 2004, however, farmers who had been growing Bt cotton for several years found that the benefits of the crop eroded as populations of secondary insect pests, such as mirids, increased. Farmers once again were forced to spray broad-spectrum pesticides throughout the growing season, such that the average revenue for Bt growers was 8 percent lower than that of farmers who grew conventional cotton. Meanwhile, Bt resistance had also evolved in field populations of major cotton pests, including both the cotton bollworm (
   <e type="italic">
    Helicoverpa armigera
   </e>
   ) and the pink bollworm (
   <e type="italic">
    Pectinophora gossypiella
   </e>
   ).
  </p>
  <p>
   Other GM plants were engineered for resistance to a specific chemical
   <xref articleid="40113">
    herbicide
   </xref>
   , rather than resistance to a natural predator or pest. Herbicide-resistant crops (HRC) have been available since the mid-1980s; these crops enable effective chemical control of
   <xref articleid="76413">
    weeds
   </xref>
   , since only the HRC plants can survive in fields treated with the corresponding herbicide. Many HRCs are resistant to glyphosate (Roundup), enabling liberal application of the chemical, which is highly effective against weeds. Such crops have been especially valuable for no-till farming, which helps prevent soil erosion. However, because HRCs encourage increased application of chemicals to the soil, rather than decreased application, they remain controversial with regard to their environmental impact. In addition, in order to reduce the risk of selecting for herbicide-resistant weeds, farmers must use multiple diverse weed-management strategies.
  </p>
  <p>
   Another example of a GM crop is “golden”
   <xref articleid="63531">
    rice
   </xref>
   , which originally was intended for Asia and was genetically modified to produce almost 20 times the beta-
   <xref articleid="20444">
    carotene
   </xref>
   of previous varieties. Golden rice was created by modifying the rice genome to include a gene from the
   <xref articleid="28511">
    daffodil
   </xref>
   <e type="italic">
    Narcissus pseudonarcissus
   </e>
   that produces an
   <xref articleid="32739">
    enzyme
   </xref>
   known as phyotene synthase and a gene from the bacterium
   <e type="italic">
    Erwinia uredovora
   </e>
   that produces an enzyme called phyotene desaturase. The introduction of these genes enabled beta-carotene, which is converted to
   <xref articleid="75546">
    vitamin A
   </xref>
   in the human liver, to accumulate in the rice
   <xref articleid="32623">
    endosperm
   </xref>
   —the edible part of the rice plant—thereby increasing the amount of beta-carotene available for vitamin A synthesis in the body. In 2004 the same researchers who developed the original golden rice plant improved upon the model, generating golden rice 2, which showed a 23-fold increase in carotenoid production.
  </p>
  <p>
   Another form of modified rice was generated to help combat
   <xref articleid="42794">
    iron
   </xref>
   deficiency, which impacts close to 30 percent of the world population. This GM crop was engineered by introducing into the rice genome a ferritin gene from the common
   <xref articleid="13929">
    bean
   </xref>
   ,
   <e type="italic">
    Phaseolus vulgaris
   </e>
   , that produces a protein capable of binding iron, as well as a gene from the fungus
   <xref articleid="9898">
    <e type="italic">
     Aspergillus fumigatus
    </e>
   </xref>
   that produces an enzyme capable of digesting compounds that increase iron bioavailability via digestion of phytate (an inhibitor of iron absorption). The iron-fortified GM rice was engineered to overexpress an existing rice gene that produces a cysteine-rich metallothioneinlike (metal-binding) protein that enhances iron absorption.
  </p>
  <p>
   A variety of other crops modified to endure the weather extremes common in other parts of the globe are also in production.
  </p>
 </h1>
 <h1 id="h279978">
  <title>
   GMOs in medicine and research
  </title>
  <p>
   GMOs have emerged as one of the mainstays of biomedical research since the 1980s. For example, GM animal models of human
   <xref articleid="111159">
    genetic diseases
   </xref>
   enabled researchers to test novel therapies and to explore the roles of candidate risk factors and modifiers of disease outcome. GM microbes, plants, and animals also revolutionized the production of complex
   <xref articleid="59583">
    pharmaceuticals
   </xref>
   by enabling the generation of safer and cheaper
   <xref articleid="74606">
    vaccines
   </xref>
   and therapeutics. Pharmaceutical products range from recombinant
   <xref articleid="40078">
    hepatitis
   </xref>
   B vaccine produced by GM baker’s
   <xref articleid="77888">
    yeast
   </xref>
   to injectable
   <xref articleid="42512">
    insulin
   </xref>
   (for diabetics) produced in GM
   <e type="italic">
    Escherichia coli
   </e>
   bacteria and to factor VIII (for hemophiliacs) and tissue plasminogen activator (tPA, for
   <xref articleid="39719">
    heart attack
   </xref>
   or
   <xref articleid="69985">
    stroke
   </xref>
   patients), both of which are produced in GM mammalian cells grown in laboratory culture. Furthermore, GM plants that produce “edible vaccines” are under development. An edible vaccine is an antigenic protein that is produced in the consumable parts of a plant (e.g., fruit) and absorbed into the bloodstream when the parts are eaten. Once absorbed into the body, the protein stimulates the immune system to produce antibodies against the pathogen from which the antigen was derived. Such vaccines could offer a safe, inexpensive, and painless way to provide vaccines, particularly in less-developed regions of the world, where the limited availability of refrigeration and sterile needles has been problematic for some traditional vaccines. Novel DNA vaccines may be useful in the struggle to prevent diseases that have proved resistant to traditional vaccination approaches, including HIV/
   <xref articleid="4173">
    AIDS
   </xref>
   ,
   <xref articleid="73667">
    tuberculosis
   </xref>
   , and
   <xref articleid="106118">
    cancer
   </xref>
   .
  </p>
  <p>
   Genetic modification of
   <xref articleid="105953">
    insects
   </xref>
   has become an important area of research, especially in the struggle to prevent parasitic diseases. For example, GM
   <xref articleid="53915">
    mosquitoes
   </xref>
   have been developed that express a small protein called SM1, which blocks entry of the
   <xref articleid="50282">
    malaria
   </xref>
   parasite,
   <e type="italic">
    Plasmodium
   </e>
   , into the mosquito’s gut. This results in the disruption of the parasite’s life cycle and renders the mosquito malaria-resistant. Introduction of these GM mosquitoes into the wild could help reduce transmission of the malaria parasite. In another example, male
   <e type="italic">
    Aedes aegypti
   </e>
   mosquitoes engineered with a method known as the sterile insect technique transmit a gene to their offspring that causes the offspring to die before becoming sexually mature. In field trials in a Brazil suburb,
   <e type="italic">
    A. aegypti
   </e>
   populations declined by 95 percent following the sustained release of sterile GM males.
  </p>
  <p>
   Finally, genetic modification of humans via
   <xref articleid="472416">
    gene therapy
   </xref>
   is becoming a treatment option for diseases ranging from rare
   <xref articleid="109832">
    metabolic disorders
   </xref>
   to cancer. Coupling
   <xref articleid="398729">
    stem cell
   </xref>
   technology with recombinant DNA methods allows stem cells derived from a patient to be modified in the laboratory to introduce a desired gene. For example, a normal beta-globin gene may be introduced into the DNA of
   <xref articleid="80586">
    bone marrow
   </xref>
   -derived hematopoietic stem cells from a patient with
   <xref articleid="67625">
    sickle cell anemia
   </xref>
   ; introduction of these GM
   <xref articleid="106125">
    cells
   </xref>
   into the patient could cure the disease without the need for a matched donor.
  </p>
 </h1>
 <h1 id="h279979">
  <title>
   Role of GMOs in environmental management
  </title>
  <p>
   <assembly id="a245665" url="/assembly/view/245665">
    <title>
     Know about genetically modified organisms, their importance, and impact on the environment
    </title>
    <media mediaid="215351" thumburl="/51/215351-049-D5241738.jpg" type="video" url=""/>
    <caption>
     Questions and answers about genetically modified organisms.
    </caption>
    <credit>
     Encyclopædia Britannica, Inc.
    </credit>
   </assembly>
   <assemblyref assemblyid="a245665"/>
   Another application of GMOs is in the management of environmental issues. For example, some
   <xref articleid="110416">
    bacteria
   </xref>
   can produce biodegradable
   <xref articleid="108561">
    plastics
   </xref>
   , and the transfer of that ability to microbes that can be easily grown in the laboratory may enable the wide-scale “greening” of the plastics industry. In the early 1990s, Zeneca, a British company, developed a microbially produced biodegradable plastic called Biopol (polyhydroxyalkanoate, or PHA). The plastic was made with the use of a GM bacterium,
   <e type="italic">
    Ralstonia eutropha
   </e>
   , to convert
   <xref articleid="37084">
    glucose
   </xref>
   and a variety of organic acids into a flexible
   <xref articleid="60700">
    polymer
   </xref>
   . GMOs endowed with the bacterially encoded ability to metabolize
   <xref articleid="56871">
    oil
   </xref>
   and heavy
   <xref articleid="52266">
    metals
   </xref>
   may provide efficient bioremediation strategies.
  </p>
 </h1>
 <h1 id="h279980">
  <title>
   Sociopolitical relevance of GMOs
  </title>
  <p>
   While GMOs offer many potential benefits to society, the potential risks associated with them have fueled controversy, especially in the food industry. Many skeptics warn about the dangers that GM crops may pose to human health. For example, genetic manipulation may potentially alter the allergenic properties of crops. Whether some GM crops, such as golden rice, deliver on the promise of improved health benefits is also unclear. The release of GM mosquitoes and other GMOs into the environment also raised concerns. More-established risks were associated with the potential spread of engineered crop genes to native flora and the possible evolution of insecticide-resistant “superbugs.”
  </p>
  <p>
   From the late 1990s, the European Union (EU) addressed such concerns by implementing strict GMO labeling laws. In the early 2000s, all GM foods and GM animal feeds in the EU were required to be labeled if they consisted of or contained GM products in a proportion greater than 0.9 percent. By contrast, in the United States, foods containing GM ingredients did not require special labeling, though the issue was hotly debated at national and state levels. Many opponents of GM products focused their arguments on unknown risks to food safety. However, despite the concerns of some consumer and health groups, especially in Europe, numerous scientific panels, including the U.S.
   <xref articleid="34794">
    Food and Drug Administration
   </xref>
   , concluded that consumption of GM foods was safe, even in cases involving GM foods with genetic material from very distantly related organisms.
  </p>
  <p>
   The strict regulations on GM products in the EU have been a source of tension in agricultural trade. In the late 1990s, the EU declared a moratorium on the import and use of GM crops. However, the ban—which led to trade disputes with other countries, particularly the United States, where GM foods had been accepted openly—was considered unjustified by the
   <xref articleid="2425">
    World Trade Organization
   </xref>
   . In consequence, the EU implemented regulatory changes that allowed for the import of certain GM crops. Within Europe, however, only one GM crop, a type of insect-resistant corn (maize), was cultivated. Some countries, including certain African states, had likewise rejected GM products. Still other countries, such as Canada, China, Argentina, and Australia, had open policies on GM foods.
  </p>
  <p/>
  <p>
   The use of GMOs in medicine and research has produced a debate that is more philosophical in nature. For example, while genetic researchers believe they are working to cure disease and ameliorate suffering, many people worry that current gene therapy approaches may one day be applied to produce “designer” children or to lengthen the natural human life span. Similar to many other technologies, gene therapy and the production and application of GMOs can be used to address and resolve complicated scientific, medical, and environmental issues, but they must be used wisely.
  </p>
  <signature>
   Julia M. Diaz
  </signature>
  <signature>
   Judith L. Fridovich-Keil
  </signature>
  <signature>
   EB Editors
  </signature>
 </h1>
 <h1 id="h279985">
  <title>
   Bibliography
  </title>
  <p>
   <e type="smallcap">
    Nigel G. Halford
   </e>
   ,
   <e type="italic">
    Genetically Modified Crops
   </e>
   , 2nd ed. (2012), gives a historical account of genetic technology in the food industry, discusses the safety of contemporary GM foods, and comments on the future of GM crops.
   <e type="smallcap">
    Pascale Piguet
   </e>
   and
   <e type="smallcap">
    Philippe Poindron
   </e>
   (eds.),
   <e type="italic">
    Genetically Modified Organisms and Genetic Engineering in Research and Therapy
   </e>
   (2012), offers background on the science of genetic engineering and the development and use of GMOs in research and medicine.
  </p>
  <p>
   <e type="smallcap">
    John E.J. Rasko
   </e>
   ,
   <e type="smallcap">
    Gabrielle O’Sullivan
   </e>
   , and
   <e type="smallcap">
    Rachel A. Ankeny
   </e>
   ,
   <e type="italic">
    The Ethics of Inheritable Genetic Modification: A Dividing Line?
   </e>
   (2006), explores the application of gene technology to human medicine and the ethical implications of human genetic modification. Issues of intellectual property associated with GMOs are discussed in
   <e type="smallcap">
    Charles Lawson
   </e>
   and
   <e type="smallcap">
    Berris Charnley
   </e>
   (eds.),
   <e type="italic">
    Intellectual Property and Genetically Modified Organisms: A Convergence in Laws
   </e>
   (2015).
  </p>
  <p>
   <e type="smallcap">
    Rebecca Grumet
   </e>
   et al. (eds.),
   <e type="italic">
    Environmental Safety of Genetically Engineered Crops
   </e>
   (2010), explores environmental issues associated with the use of GMOs.
   <e type="smallcap">
    Alan McHughen
   </e>
   ,
   <e type="italic">
    Pandora’s Picnic Basket: The Potential and Hazards of Genetically Modified Foods
   </e>
   (2000), provides a skeptical perspective on the safety of GM foods, focusing on the policies related to production and distribution of GM foods. Risks associated with the use of GM crops and approaches to mitigating potential environmental impacts are addressed in
   <e type="smallcap">
    George T. Tzotzos
   </e>
   ,
   <e type="smallcap">
    Graham P. Head
   </e>
   , and
   <e type="smallcap">
    Roger Hull
   </e>
   ,
   <e type="italic">
    Genetically Modified Plants: Assessing Safety and Managing Risk
   </e>
   (2009).
   <e type="smallcap">
    John C. Avise
   </e>
   ,
   <e type="italic">
    The Hope, Hype, and Reality of Genetic Engineering: Remarkable Stories from Agriculture, Industry, Medicine, and the Environment
   </e>
   (2004), covers a broad range of topics, from agriculture to medicine to bioterrorism.
  </p>
  <signature>
   Julia M. Diaz
  </signature>
  <signature>
   Judith L. Fridovich-Keil
  </signature>
  <signature>
   EB Editors
  </signature>
 </h1>
 <copyright>
  Encyclopædia Britannica
 </copyright>
</article>