<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "syndication_xml.dtd">
<article articleid="443741" articletypeid="1" language="en_us" lastupdate="2021-Sep-22 08:30:57" url="/article/After-Dark/443741" version="3">
 <title>
  After Dark
 </title>
 <p>
  <e type="bold">
   After Dark
  </e>
  , series of interactive screensaver software created by the American software company Berkeley Systems from the late 1980s to the mid-1990s. The series later developed into a collection of games and gained a large cult following.
 </p>
 <p>
  The original After Dark software allowed users to apply interesting and engaging screensavers, ranging from animated bagels to
  <e type="italic">
   Looney Tunes
  </e>
  cartoon characters. Many of the screensavers released through After Dark were linked by a common character, pattern, or theme. Later products provided screensavers that doubled as
  <xref articleid="1562">
   electronic games
  </xref>
  .
 </p>
 <p>
  The most recognizable symbol of After Dark is the “flying toaster,” which appeared in numerous popular culture references in the early 1990s. The flying toaster software also included music, namely “Ride of the Valkyries” by German composer
  <xref articleid="75844">
   Richard Wagner
  </xref>
  . The winged appliances generated several software releases, and they live on today by virtue of dedicated fans who have worked to update the toasters for new
  <xref articleid="1489">
   operating systems
  </xref>
  .
 </p>
 <p>
  Although After Dark is remembered today for its whimsical qualities, it did have moments of controversy. In 1993 the Delrina Corporation put out a competing screensaver in which the animated characters from the
  <e type="italic">
   Opus N’ Bill
  </e>
  cartoon strip blasted flying toasters out of the sky in an After Dark parody. After a lawsuit was filed by Berkeley, Delrina changed the wings on their toasters to propellers. In a turnabout in 1994, the American psychedelic rock band
  <xref articleid="117534">
   Jefferson Airplane
  </xref>
  sued After Dark, claiming the flying toaster was copied from their 1973
  <e type="italic">
   Thirty Seconds over Winterland
  </e>
  album cover. Similar as the two designs were, Jefferson Airplane had not registered the trademark early enough, and the lawsuit was dismissed.
 </p>
 <signature>
  EB Editors
 </signature>
 <copyright>
  Encyclopædia Britannica
 </copyright>
</article>