<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "syndication_xml.dtd">
<article articleid="443789" articletypeid="1" language="en_us" lastupdate="2021-Jul-01 05:52:25" url="/article/Days-of-Our-Lives/443789" version="4">
 <title>
  Days of Our Lives
 </title>
 <p>
  <e type="bold">
   Days of Our Lives
  </e>
  , American television
  <xref articleid="68419">
   soap opera
  </xref>
  that has been broadcast nearly every weekday since its 1965 debut on the
  <xref articleid="54963">
   National Broadcasting Company
  </xref>
  (NBC) network. The influential series won numerous Daytime
  <xref articleid="32545">
   Emmy Awards
  </xref>
  and became a fixture of American daytime programming.
 </p>
 <p>
  <e type="italic">
   Days of Our Lives
  </e>
  originally concerned the tumultuous lives of the Horton family, residents of Salem, a fictional Midwestern suburb. But throughout the show’s long run, the sagas of additional families, such as the Bradys and DiMeras, were introduced. Like other soap operas,
  <e type="italic">
   Days of Our Lives
  </e>
  often deals with love, family, marriage,
  <xref articleid="3806">
   adultery
  </xref>
  , divorce, death, and sex. Many of the show’s ongoing story lines have involved characters in protracted tragic love triangles or with secrets that could harm themselves or their loved ones. Over the years, cast members have frequently changed, with many actors leaving the show and then sometimes returning. One of the most-enduring performers was Frances Reid, who played matriarch Alice Horton; she was a regular on the show from its debut until 2007. MacDonald Carey, who appeared in many Hollywood motion pictures in the 1940s and ’50s, played Alice’s husband, Dr. Tom Horton, and was the soap’s main attraction for many years.
 </p>
 <p>
  Initially praised for its relatively realistic portrayal of American families and for tackling
  <xref articleid="70845">
   taboo
  </xref>
  subjects, the show later introduced more action-oriented plots as well as elements of the supernatural. It has attracted an international following and has spent time in the number one daytime slot as well as in the ratings cellar. The show’s long run has secured
  <e type="italic">
   Days of Our Lives
  </e>
  (and its familiar over-the-credits introduction, “Like sands through the hourglass, so are the days of our lives”) a place in television history.
 </p>
 <signature>
  EB Editors
 </signature>
 <copyright>
  Encyclopædia Britannica
 </copyright>
</article>