<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "syndication_xml.dtd">
<article articleid="443902" articletypeid="1" language="en_us" lastupdate="2021-Jul-01 05:53:10" url="/article/Pong/443902" version="2">
 <title>
  Pong
 </title>
 <p>
  <e type="bold">
   Pong
  </e>
  , groundbreaking
  <xref articleid="1562">
   electronic game
  </xref>
  released in 1972 by the American game manufacturer
  <xref articleid="438621">
   Atari, Inc.
  </xref>
  One of the earliest video games,
  <e type="italic">
   Pong
  </e>
  became wildly popular and helped launch the video game industry. The original
  <e type="italic">
   Pong
  </e>
  consisted of two paddles that players used to volley a small ball back and forth across a screen.
 </p>
 <p>
  The German-born American television engineer Ralph Baer laid the groundwork for
  <e type="italic">
   Pong
  </e>
  in 1958 when he proposed making simple video games that people could play on their home television sets. The Magnavox Odyssey, known as the first console video game system, was released in 1972 and offered a game of
  <xref articleid="70842">
   table tennis
  </xref>
  , or Ping-Pong. Atari founder Nolan Bushnell created
  <e type="italic">
   Pong
  </e>
  , his version of this concept, as an arcade game. A small company at the time, Atari began manufacturing the games in an old roller skating rink, and by 1972 the company had sold more than 8,000
  <e type="italic">
   Pong
  </e>
  arcade machines. In 1975 Atari turned
  <e type="italic">
   Pong
  </e>
  into a console system game. After striking an exclusive deal with
  <xref articleid="66487">
   Sears, Roebuck and Company
  </xref>
  ,
  <e type="italic">
   Pong
  </e>
  was soon in the homes of many American families.
  <e type="italic">
   Pong
  </e>
  ’s popularity declined in the 1980s as video games temporarily went out of style, but it had already secured its place in history as the most popular arcade game up to that time.
 </p>
 <p>
  In 1974 the makers of the Magnavox Odyssey sued Atari for stealing the concept for
  <e type="italic">
   Pong
  </e>
  . Magnavox won the lawsuit in 1977, upholding the company’s patent, but by then Atari had already licensed the patent for $700,000.
 </p>
 <copyright>
  Encyclopædia Britannica
 </copyright>
</article>