<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "syndication_xml.dtd">
<article articleid="443906" articletypeid="1" language="en_us" lastupdate="2022-Feb-02 17:27:20" url="/article/raster-graphics/443906" version="5">
 <title>
  raster graphics
 </title>
 <p>
  <e type="bold">
   raster graphics
  </e>
  , also called
  <e type="bold">
   bitmap graphics
  </e>
  , a type of digital image that uses tiny rectangular pixels, or picture elements, arranged in a grid formation to represent an image. Because the format can support a wide range of colours and depict subtle graduated tones, it is well suited for displaying continuous-tone images such as photographs or shaded drawings, along with other detailed images.
 </p>
 <p>
  Raster graphics have origins in
  <xref articleid="106102">
   television
  </xref>
  technology, with images constructed much like the pictures on a television screen. A raster graphic is made up of a collection of tiny, uniformly sized pixels, which are arranged in a two-dimensional grid made up of columns and rows. Each pixel contains one or more bits of information, depending on the degree of detail in the image. For example, a black-and-white image contains only one
  <xref articleid="80319">
   bit
  </xref>
  per pixel (a
  <xref articleid="471867">
   binary
  </xref>
  bit can be in one of two states; thus, a single bit can represent white or black); an image with shading and colour commonly contains 24 bits of information per pixel—with 2
  <sup>
   24
  </sup>
  , or more than 16 million, possible states per pixel. Known as “truecolor,” 24-bit colour can realistically depict colour images. The number of bits stored in each pixel is known as the colour depth. The number of pixels in a display, called resolution, affects how much detail can be depicted in an image. Resolution is often expressed as the number of pixels in a column times the number of pixels in a row (for example, 800 × 600).
 </p>
 <p>
  Detailed images often result in large file sizes, although file size can be managed through
  <xref articleid="2216">
   data compression
  </xref>
  . Compression can be either lossy (meaning that some data is discarded) or lossless (no data is lost). Popular raster file formats include
  <xref articleid="443821">
   GIF
  </xref>
  (graphics interchange format) and
  <xref articleid="443848">
   JPEG
  </xref>
  (joint photographic experts group), which are lossy formats, and BMP (Windows bitmap) and TIFF (tagged image file format), which are lossless.
 </p>
 <p>
  Although raster graphics saw some use in the 1970s and ’80s, it was mostly limited to expensive graphics
  <xref articleid="1514">
   workstations
  </xref>
  (i.e., high-end computers that were specially optimized for working with graphics). As the graphics capability of
  <xref articleid="2247">
   personal computers
  </xref>
  improved in the 1990s, raster graphics became widely used. Images produced from optical scanners and
  <xref articleid="443006">
   digital cameras
  </xref>
  are raster graphics, as are most images on the
  <xref articleid="1458">
   Internet
  </xref>
  . A commonly used graphics program for working with raster images is
  <xref articleid="443896">
   Adobe Photoshop
  </xref>
  .
 </p>
 <signature>
  EB Editors
 </signature>
 <copyright>
  Encyclopædia Britannica
 </copyright>
</article>