<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "syndication_xml.dtd">
<article articleid="444135" articletypeid="1" language="en_us" lastupdate="2021-Jul-01 05:53:57" url="/article/Rain/444135" version="5">
 <title>
  Rain
 </title>
 <p>
  <assembly id="a235774" url="/assembly/view/235774">
   <title>
    Rain
   </title>
   <media mediaid="200223" type="image" url="/23/200223-004-5727C5B7.jpg"/>
   <caption>
    Rain (right), 2011.
   </caption>
   <credit>
    © Chung Jin Mac/Dreamstime.com
   </credit>
  </assembly>
  <e type="bold">
   Rain
  </e>
  , Korean
  <e type="bold">
   Bi
  </e>
  , original name
  <e type="bold">
   Jung Ji-Hoon
  </e>
  ,
  <assemblyref assemblyid="a235774"/>
  (born June 25, 1982, Seoul or Seosan, South Korea), South Korean pop singer and actor known for his boyish good looks and smooth
  <xref articleid="117537">
   hip-hop
  </xref>
  dance moves.
 </p>
 <p>
  Rain began performing in his teens as a rapper in a short-lived band called Fanclub and later became a backup dancer for popular Korean singer Park Ji-Yoon. Deciding to pursue a solo music career, he released his first album,
  <e type="italic">
   Bad Guy
  </e>
  , in 2002. With a commanding stage presence and extravagant concert performances, he quickly topped the South Korean pop charts. The following year he starred in a Korean television serial,
  <e type="italic">
   Sang Doo! Let’s Go to School
  </e>
  , and released a second album,
  <e type="italic">
   How to Avoid the Sun
  </e>
  . Another successful television soap opera,
  <e type="italic">
   Full House
  </e>
  , followed; it was widely broadcast in Asia. In 2004, following the successful release of his third album,
  <e type="italic">
   It’s Raining
  </e>
  , Rain made his first concert tour of Japan. By 2005 he dominated the charts throughout East and Southeast Asia and sold out arenas across the region. He was also arguably the chief object of the Asian craze for Korean pop culture. His Rainy Day concert tour sold out throughout Asia; he had become a heartthrob to millions of fans around the world, aided by the Internet and DVDs.
 </p>
 <p>
  In 2006 Rain made concert appearances in New York City and Las Vegas, recorded a duet with the American R&amp;B singer Omarion, released his fourth album,
  <e type="italic">
   Rain’s World
  </e>
  , and made his film debut in
  <e type="italic">
   I’m a Cyborg, but That’s OK
  </e>
  . In 2008 Rain appeared in his first Hollywood movie,
  <e type="italic">
   Speed Racer
  </e>
  , and released the album
  <e type="italic">
   Rainism
  </e>
  . The following year he starred in the action drama
  <e type="italic">
   Ninja Assassin
  </e>
  .
 </p>
 <p>
  Rain’s entertainment career was put on hold in 2011–13 while he performed his mandatory national military service. He subsequently recorded the album
  <e type="italic">
   Rain Effect
  </e>
  (2014) and the EP
  <e type="italic">
   My Life
  </e>
  (2017), and he continued acting on television and in films.
 </p>
 <signature>
  EB Editors
 </signature>
 <copyright>
  Encyclopædia Britannica
 </copyright>
</article>