<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "syndication_xml.dtd">
<article articleid="45490" articletypeid="1" language="en_us" lastupdate="2021-Nov-16 15:44:08" url="/article/kinetic-energy/45490" version="9">
 <title>
  kinetic energy
 </title>
 <p>
  <e type="bold">
   kinetic energy
  </e>
  , form of
  <xref articleid="32627">
   energy
  </xref>
  that an object or a particle has by reason of its motion. If
  <xref articleid="77472">
   work
  </xref>
  , which transfers energy, is done on an object by applying a net
  <xref articleid="34834">
   force
  </xref>
  , the object speeds up and thereby gains kinetic energy. Kinetic energy is a property of a moving object or particle and depends not only on its motion but also on its
  <xref articleid="51285">
   mass
  </xref>
  . The kind of motion may be translation (or motion along a path from one place to another), rotation about an axis, vibration, or any combination of motions.
 </p>
 <p>
  Translational kinetic energy of a body is equal to one-half the product of its mass,
  <e type="italic">
   m
  </e>
  , and the square of its velocity,
  <e type="italic">
   v
  </e>
  , or
  <fraction>
   <num>
    1
   </num>
   <den>
    2
   </den>
  </fraction>
  <e type="italic">
   mv
  </e>
  <sup>
   2
  </sup>
  .
 </p>
 <p>
  This formula is valid only for low to relatively high speeds; for extremely high-speed particles it yields values that are too small. When the speed of an object approaches that of
  <xref articleid="471069">
   light
  </xref>
  (3 × 10
  <sup>
   8
  </sup>
  metres per second, or 186,000 miles per second), its mass increases, and the laws of
  <xref articleid="109465">
   relativity
  </xref>
  must be used.
  <xref articleid="110309" refid="h77443">
   Relativistic kinetic energy
  </xref>
  is equal to the increase in the mass of a particle over that which it has at rest multiplied by the square of the speed of light.
 </p>
 <p>
  <assembly id="a174512" url="/assembly/view/174512">
   <title>
    Uncover the forces of potential energy, kinetic energy, and friction behind a grandfather clock’s pendulum
   </title>
   <media mediaid="161914" thumburl="/14/161914-049-BAB034A5.jpg" type="video" url=""/>
   <caption>
    Changes in potential and kinetic energy as a pendulum swings.
   </caption>
   <credit>
    Encyclopædia Britannica, Inc.
   </credit>
  </assembly>
  <assemblyref assemblyid="a174512"/>
  The unit of energy in the
  <xref articleid="52350">
   metre
  </xref>
  -
  <xref articleid="45447">
   kilogram
  </xref>
  -
  <xref articleid="66514">
   second
  </xref>
  system is the
  <xref articleid="44023">
   joule
  </xref>
  . A two-kilogram mass (something weighing 4.4 pounds on
  <xref articleid="110147">
   Earth
  </xref>
  ) moving at a speed of one metre per second (slightly more than two
  <xref articleid="52657">
   miles
  </xref>
  per hour) has a kinetic energy of one joule. In the centimetre-gram-second system the unit of energy is the
  <xref articleid="32887">
   erg
  </xref>
  , 10
  <sup>
   −7
  </sup>
  joule, equivalent to the kinetic energy of a
  <xref articleid="53915">
   mosquito
  </xref>
  in flight. Other units of energy also are used, in specific contexts, such as the still smaller unit, the
  <xref articleid="32330">
   electron volt
  </xref>
  , on the
  <xref articleid="110411">
   atomic
  </xref>
  and
  <xref articleid="108593">
   subatomic
  </xref>
  scale.
 </p>
 <p>
  For a rotating body, the
  <xref articleid="42379">
   moment of inertia
  </xref>
  ,
  <e type="italic">
   I
  </e>
  , corresponds to mass, and the angular velocity (omega),
  <e type="italic">
   ω
  </e>
  , corresponds to linear, or translational, velocity. Accordingly, rotational kinetic energy is equal to one-half the product of the moment of inertia and the square of the angular velocity, or
  <fraction>
   <num>
    1
   </num>
   <den>
    2
   </den>
  </fraction>
  <e type="italic">
   Iω
  </e>
  <sup>
   2
  </sup>
  .
 </p>
 <p>
  The total kinetic energy of a body or a system is equal to the sum of the kinetic energies resulting from each type of motion.
  <e type="italic">
   See
  </e>
  <xref articleid="110307" refid="h77555">
   mechanics: Rotation about a moving axis
  </xref>
  .
 </p>
 <signature>
  EB Editors
 </signature>
 <copyright>
  Encyclopædia Britannica
 </copyright>
</article>