<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "syndication_xml.dtd">
<article articleid="46110" articletypeid="1" language="en_us" lastupdate="2021-Jun-30 23:11:31" url="/article/Košice-government/46110" version="1">
 <title>
  Košice government
 </title>
 <p>
  <e type="bold">
   Košice government
  </e>
  , Košice also spelled
  <e type="bold">
   Koszyce
  </e>
  , pro-Soviet Czechoslovak provisional government that inaugurated far-reaching socialist programs during the single year of its rule after World War II and made way for the eventual Communist domination of Czechoslovakia.
 </p>
 <p>
  Appointed by Edvard Beneš, the former president of prewar Czechoslovakia and the head of the Czechoslovak government-in-exile during the war, the government was formed at Košice, in Slovakia, on April 3, 1945. Its premier was the pro-Soviet Zdeněk Fierlinger, a former diplomat who had represented the Czechoslovak government in Moscow; its cabinet contained ministers from four Czech and two Slovak political parties. The seven Communist ministers of the Košice government, however, not only formed the largest group from a single party but also controlled the key ministries of interior, agriculture, finance, education, and information.
 </p>
 <p>
  After the Košice government assumed control of the liberated Czechoslovak lands, it organized people’s committees to function as local governments and also developed a distinctly pro-Soviet foreign policy, on the basis of which it obtained the Teschen district from Poland (through Soviet intervention) but ceded sub-Carpathian Ruthenia to the Soviet Union. In addition, it approved the nationalization of key industries, power plants and networks, banks, and other financial, credit, and insurance institutions.
 </p>
 <p>
  After parliamentary elections were held in May 1946, the Košice government, whose activities had increased the Communists’ popularity, was succeeded by a new government, whose Communist premier, Klement Gottwald, retained many of the Communist ministers who had served in the Košice government.
 </p>
 <copyright>
  Encyclopædia Britannica
 </copyright>
</article>