<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "syndication_xml.dtd">
<article articleid="471673" articletypeid="1" language="en_us" lastupdate="2021-Jul-01 05:58:33" url="/article/People/471673" version="4">
 <title>
  People
 </title>
 <p>
  <e type="bold">
   People
  </e>
  , weekly American
  <xref articleid="49969">
   magazine
  </xref>
  specializing in stories about the personal lives of celebrities. The
  <xref articleid="108761">
   New York
  </xref>
  -based magazine is one of the best-selling weeklies in the world and the most profitable asset of its publisher,
  <xref articleid="72518">
   Time, Inc
  </xref>
  .
 </p>
 <p>
  In the decades since the American actress
  <xref articleid="627658">
   Mia Farrow
  </xref>
  appeared on the cover of its first issue in March 1974,
  <e type="italic">
   People
  </e>
  covers have showcased hundreds of film stars, musicians, performers, and political figures. Regular features include celebrity news and sightings, a fashion guide, movie and music reviews, and human-interest stories about ordinary people coping with extraordinary challenges. Annual special issues include
  <e type="italic">
   Oscar Style
  </e>
  ,
  <e type="italic">
   World’s Most Beautiful People
  </e>
  ,
  <e type="italic">
   Hottest Bachelors
  </e>
  ,
  <e type="italic">
   Best and Worst Dressed
  </e>
  ,
  <e type="italic">
   Sexiest Man Alive
  </e>
  , and a best-of-the-year issue. Sister publications have included a Spanish-language version, the now-defunct
  <e type="italic">
   Teen People
  </e>
  , and
  <e type="italic">
   People StyleWatch
  </e>
  , a shopping guide to current celebrity fashion trends.
 </p>
 <p>
  <e type="italic">
   People
  </e>
  faced little serious competition until the early 21st century. Known for its intimate coverage of celebrities and political figures, the magazine earned a trusted place in American popular culture because of its refusal to publish unsubstantiated rumours. But
  <e type="italic">
   People
  </e>
  has also been criticized for paying exorbitant sums for exclusive photographs, thereby rapidly inflating costs in bidding wars among rival publications.
 </p>
 <copyright>
  Encyclopædia Britannica
 </copyright>
</article>