<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "syndication_xml.dtd">
<article articleid="471660" articletypeid="1" language="en_us" lastupdate="2021-Jul-01 05:58:29" url="/article/Discover/471660" version="4">
 <title>
  Discover
 </title>
 <p>
  <e type="bold">
   Discover
  </e>
  , American popular science magazine founded in 1980 by Time, Inc., at the suggestion of the American journalist Leon Jaroff, who became the magazine’s first managing editor.
  <e type="italic">
   Discover
  </e>
  is published in New York City.
 </p>
 <p>
  While working as a writer and editor for
  <e type="italic">
   <xref articleid="72508">
    Time
   </xref>
  </e>
  magazine in the early 1970s, Jaroff noticed that any cover of
  <e type="italic">
   Time
  </e>
  with a
  <xref articleid="109517">
   science
  </xref>
  - or
  <xref articleid="110313">
   medicine
  </xref>
  -related subject had significantly higher newsstand sales. To take advantage of the increasing public interest in science and medicine, Jaroff suggested that Time, Inc., publish a science-specific magazine. Finally, in 1980, Time started
  <e type="italic">
   Discover
  </e>
  magazine and hired Jaroff as its first managing editor. The magazine was sold to the
  <xref articleid="30636">
   Walt Disney Company
  </xref>
  in 1991 and then purchased in 2005 by Bob Guccione, Jr., who made it the flagship publication of the new Discover Media, LLC.
 </p>
 <p>
  Under the slogan “Science, Technology, and the Future,”
  <e type="italic">
   Discover
  </e>
  publishes consumer-oriented scientific information. It provides in-depth coverage of scientific topics while at the same time keeping articles relatively short and without too much technical detail or jargon. A wide range of scientific fields are covered, including astronomy, medicine, paleontology, and zoology. The magazine often includes profiles of or interviews with scientists and is known for its remarkable graphics.
  <e type="italic">
   Discover
  </e>
  has both online and print versions, as well as a number of
  <xref articleid="404269">
   blogs
  </xref>
  and a
  <xref articleid="471403">
   podcast
  </xref>
  . A separate magazine aimed at children,
  <e type="italic">
   KIDS Discover
  </e>
  , was created in 1991.
 </p>
 <copyright>
  Encyclopædia Britannica
 </copyright>
</article>