<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "syndication_xml.dtd">
<article articleid="472325" articletypeid="1" language="en_us" lastupdate="2022-Mar-16 18:57:19" url="/article/field/472325" version="2">
 <title>
  field
 </title>
 <p>
  <assembly id="a66082" url="/assembly/view/66082">
   <title>
    magnets and their associated magnetic field lines
   </title>
   <media mediaid="72192" type="image" url="/92/72192-004-15BEDC42.jpg"/>
   <caption>
    A permanent magnet (such as a bar or disk magnet) possesses a magnetic field by virtue of the alignment of all the magnetic particles it is composed of. An electromagnet is generated by a current flowing through a wire loop at the centre of the field.
   </caption>
   <credit>
    © Merriam-Webster Inc.
   </credit>
  </assembly>
  <e type="bold">
   field
  </e>
  ,
  <assemblyref assemblyid="a66082"/>
  in
  <xref articleid="108654">
   physics
  </xref>
  , a region in which each point has a physical quantity associated with it. The quantity could be a number, as in the case of a scalar field such as the
  <xref articleid="40396">
   Higgs field
  </xref>
  , or it could be a
  <xref articleid="218451">
   vector
  </xref>
  , as in the case of fields such as the gravitational field, which are associated with a
  <xref articleid="34834">
   force
  </xref>
  . Objects fall to the ground because they are affected by the force of
  <xref articleid="110147">
   Earth
  </xref>
  ’s gravitational field (
  <e type="italic">
   see
  </e>
  <xref articleid="106265">
   gravitation
  </xref>
  ). A paper clip, placed in the
  <xref articleid="50022">
   magnetic field
  </xref>
  surrounding a
  <xref articleid="50017">
   magnet
  </xref>
  , is pulled toward the magnet, and two like magnetic poles repel each other when one is placed in the other’s magnetic field. An
  <xref articleid="32278">
   electric field
  </xref>
  surrounds an
  <xref articleid="32271">
   electric charge
  </xref>
  ; when another charged particle is placed in that region, it experiences an electric force that either attracts or repels it. The strength of a field, or the forces in a particular region, can be represented by field lines; the closer the lines, the stronger the forces in that part of the field.
  <e type="italic">
   See also
  </e>
  <xref articleid="32310">
   electromagnetic field
  </xref>
  .
 </p>
 <signature>
  EB Editors
 </signature>
 <copyright>
  Encyclopædia Britannica
 </copyright>
</article>