<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "syndication_xml.dtd">
<article articleid="473728" articletypeid="1" language="en_us" lastupdate="2021-Jul-01 06:07:38" url="/article/Venus-Express/473728" version="5">
 <title>
  Venus Express
 </title>
 <p>
  <e type="bold">
   Venus Express
  </e>
  ,
  <xref articleid="33274">
   European Space Agency
  </xref>
  spacecraft that orbited the
  <xref articleid="60298">
   planet
  </xref>
  <xref articleid="110146">
   Venus
  </xref>
  . The design of Venus Express was based on that of the earlier
  <xref articleid="473716">
   Mars Express
  </xref>
  . It was launched on November 9, 2005, by a Russian Soyuz-Fregat rocket and went into
  <xref articleid="57286">
   orbit
  </xref>
  around Venus on April 11, 2006. Near-
  <xref articleid="42403">
   infrared
  </xref>
  and other instruments studied the structure and composition of the middle and upper Venusian atmosphere. Venus Express observed small amounts of water and a large ratio of
  <xref articleid="30119">
   deuterium
  </xref>
  to
  <xref articleid="110604">
   hydrogen
  </xref>
  , both of which could be explained by the presence of oceans early in Venus’s history. Radio waves characteristic of lightning in Venus’s clouds were discovered.
 </p>
 <p>
  <assembly id="a155719" url="/assembly/view/155719">
   <title>
    Observe a volcanic peak on Venus captured by Magellan spacecraft
   </title>
   <media mediaid="145488" thumburl="/88/145488-049-499166E6.jpg" type="video" url=""/>
   <caption>
    Volcanic peak on Venus captured by Magellan spacecraft.
   </caption>
   <credit>
    NASA/JPL
   </credit>
  </assembly>
  <assemblyref assemblyid="a155719"/>
  Venus Express completed its originally planned mission on July 24, 2007, but the mission was extended through 2014. It also made observations of
  <xref articleid="110147">
   Earth
  </xref>
  in the hope of finding spectroscopic signatures of
  <xref articleid="106478">
   life
  </xref>
  that could possibly be seen on
  <xref articleid="439223">
   extrasolar planets
  </xref>
  . Beginning in May 2014, Venus Express conducted a series of maneuvers in which its orbit was lowered to about 130 km (80 miles) to explore the upper atmosphere. Communication was lost with the probe in January 2015, and Venus Express burnt up in the atmosphere some time thereafter.
 </p>
 <copyright>
  Encyclopædia Britannica
 </copyright>
</article>