<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "syndication_xml.dtd">
<article articleid="474204" articletypeid="1" language="en_us" lastupdate="2021-Jul-01 06:09:34" url="/article/high-voltage-electron-microscope/474204" version="2">
 <title>
  high-voltage electron microscope
 </title>
 <p>
  <e type="bold">
   high-voltage electron microscope
  </e>
  , type of
  <xref articleid="32323">
   electron microscope
  </xref>
  that has been constructed to operate at accelerating voltages in excess of the 200–300 kV normally used in the conventional
  <xref articleid="474201">
   transmission electron microscope
  </xref>
  . High-voltage microscopes now in commercial production are designed for accelerating voltages of up to 1,500 kV.
 </p>
 <p>
  These instruments have several advantages over the conventional transmission electron microscope: (1) the theoretical resolving power of the instrument increases as the accelerating voltage increases; (2) thick specimens are easily penetrated by the beam; (3) chromatic aberration caused by energy losses and scattering in the specimen is decreased; and (4) specimen heating and irradiation damage of organic samples are decreased. Many metals and
  <xref articleid="66711">
   semiconductors
  </xref>
  suffer increased damage at these high energies, however, because the incident
  <xref articleid="32316">
   electrons
  </xref>
  may knock an
  <xref articleid="110411">
   atom
  </xref>
  from its correct position in the crystal lattice.
 </p>
 <p>
  Although the gain in resolution at 1,000 kV is theoretically about two and a half times that of a 100-kV instrument, such increases have not been fully achieved in practice. It is primarily for the increased penetrating power and consequent reduction in chromatic aberration that the high-voltage instruments are used, as in the study of metals and
  <xref articleid="5832">
   alloys
  </xref>
  , for example. Some biological systems, such as
  <xref articleid="110416">
   bacteria
  </xref>
  and whole
  <xref articleid="106125">
   cells
  </xref>
  contained within a quartz chamber, may also be examined at high voltage. However, specimen damage due to the energetic electron beam is considerable.
 </p>
 <signature>
  Savile Bradbury
 </signature>
 <signature>
  David C. Joy
 </signature>
 <signature>
  Brian J. Ford
 </signature>
 <copyright>
  Encyclopædia Britannica
 </copyright>
</article>