<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "syndication_xml.dtd">
<article articleid="474651" articletypeid="1" language="en_us" lastupdate="2021-Jul-01 06:11:52" url="/article/single-nucleotide-polymorphism/474651" version="3">
 <title>
  single nucleotide polymorphism (SNP)
 </title>
 <p>
  <e type="bold">
   single nucleotide polymorphism (SNP)
  </e>
  , variation in a genetic sequence that affects only one of the basic building blocks—
  <xref articleid="3720">
   adenine
  </xref>
  (A),
  <xref articleid="38302">
   guanine
  </xref>
  (G),
  <xref articleid="72358">
   thymine
  </xref>
  (T), or
  <xref articleid="28449">
   cytosine
  </xref>
  (C)—in a segment of a
  <xref articleid="30730">
   DNA
  </xref>
  molecule and that occurs in more than 1 percent of a population.
 </p>
 <p>
  An example of an SNP is the substitution of a C for a G in the
  <xref articleid="56460">
   nucleotide
  </xref>
  sequence AACGAT, thereby producing the sequence AACCAT. The DNA of humans may contain many SNPs, since these variations occur at a rate of one in every 100–300 nucleotides in the
  <xref articleid="439231">
   human genome
  </xref>
  . In fact, roughly 90 percent of the genetic variation that exists between humans is the result of SNPs. Although the majority of variations do not alter cellular function and thus have no effect, some SNPs have been discovered to contribute to the development of diseases such as
  <xref articleid="106118">
   cancer
  </xref>
  and to influence physiological responses to
  <xref articleid="106187">
   drugs
  </xref>
  .
 </p>
 <p>
  SNPs act as chromosomal tags to specific regions of DNA, and these regions can be scanned for variations that may be involved in a human disease or disorder. SNPs found to be associated with disease may be useful for diagnostic purposes. In addition, identifying which variations are involved in altering responses to drugs could facilitate the development of personalized medicine. This approach to treatment is based on the concept that genetic screening for specific SNPs in a person’s genome can be used to select drugs most appropriate for that individual. Personalized medicine could be used to avoid potentially dangerous drug responses that are the result of altered cellular
  <xref articleid="109831">
   metabolism
  </xref>
  caused by a specific SNP.
 </p>
 <p>
  In the realm of basic genetics research, SNPs can be used to identify the locations of
  <xref articleid="36352">
   genes
  </xref>
  on
  <xref articleid="82456">
   chromosomes
  </xref>
  . Scanning a genome to find where SNPs occur helps scientists construct chromosome maps that enable the identification of genes contributing to specific traits.
 </p>
 <signature>
  EB Editors
 </signature>
 <copyright>
  Encyclopædia Britannica
 </copyright>
</article>