<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "syndication_xml.dtd">
<article articleid="475366" articletypeid="1" language="en_us" lastupdate="2021-Jul-01 06:13:26" url="/article/antigenic-drift/475366" version="3">
 <title>
  antigenic drift
 </title>
 <p>
  <e type="bold">
   antigenic drift
  </e>
  , random genetic
  <xref articleid="54492">
   mutation
  </xref>
  of an infectious agent resulting in minor changes in
  <xref articleid="110575">
   proteins
  </xref>
  called
  <xref articleid="7823">
   antigens
  </xref>
  , which stimulate the production of
  <xref articleid="7812">
   antibodies
  </xref>
  by the
  <xref articleid="109569">
   immune systems
  </xref>
  of humans and animals. These mutations typically produce antigens to which only part of a population may be immune. Thus, infectious agents that have evolved through antigenic drift may cause potentially severe disease and can spread quickly within a population of humans or animals.
 </p>
 <p>
  The process of antigenic drift is best characterized in
  <xref articleid="42398">
   influenza
  </xref>
  type A
  <xref articleid="106000">
   viruses
  </xref>
  . The viral coats, or outer surfaces, of these viruses contain two major antigenic glycoproteins—hemagglutinin (H) and neuraminidase (N)—which differ between influenza A subtypes (e.g., H1N1, H3N2, H5N1). The subtle mutations accumulated through antigenic drift of these subtypes give rise to different strains of each subtype. The
  <xref articleid="36352">
   genes
  </xref>
  affected are typically those that encode the epitope portion of the H or N antigen. The epitope is the part of an antigen to which antibodies bind to target a virus for destruction by the immune system. The emergence of a new strain of influenza A due to antigenic drift can cause an influenza
  <xref articleid="32787">
   epidemic
  </xref>
  or
  <xref articleid="475350">
   pandemic
  </xref>
  .
 </p>
 <p>
  Antigenic drift is also known to occur in
  <xref articleid="472525">
   HIV
  </xref>
  (human immunodeficiency virus), which causes
  <xref articleid="4173">
   AIDS
  </xref>
  , and in certain
  <xref articleid="63437">
   rhinoviruses
  </xref>
  , which cause
  <xref articleid="24968">
   common colds
  </xref>
  in humans. It also has been suspected to occur in some
  <xref articleid="106118">
   cancer
  </xref>
  -causing viruses in humans. Antigenic drift of such viruses is believed to enable the viruses to escape destruction by immune cells, thereby promoting virus survival and facilitating cancer development.
 </p>
 <copyright>
  Encyclopædia Britannica
 </copyright>
</article>