<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "syndication_xml.dtd">
<article articleid="476768" articletypeid="1" language="en_us" lastupdate="2021-Dec-20 15:40:52" url="/article/augmented-reality/476768" version="6">
 <title>
  augmented reality
 </title>
 <p>
  <e type="bold">
   augmented reality
  </e>
  , in
  <xref articleid="117728">
   computer
  </xref>
  programming, a process of combining or “augmenting” video or photographic displays by overlaying the images with useful computer-generated data. The earliest applications of augmented reality were almost certainly the “heads-up-displays” (HUDs) used in military airplanes and tanks, in which instrument panel-type information is projected onto the same cockpit canopy or viewfinder through which a crew member sees the external surroundings. Faster
  <xref articleid="472096">
   computer processors
  </xref>
  have made it feasible to combine such data displays with real-time video. Among the earliest and most prominent examples of this type of augmented reality, as first shown on the
  <xref articleid="2396">
   Fox Broadcasting Company
  </xref>
  ’s network in the mid-1990s, were the yellow first-down stripes superimposed on television images of American
  <xref articleid="108490">
   gridiron football
  </xref>
  fields and the virtual flight paths added to help television viewers track the paths of
  <xref articleid="108494">
   hockey
  </xref>
  pucks and
  <xref articleid="108496">
   golf
  </xref>
  balls.
 </p>
 <p>
  Augmented reality is commonly used in
  <xref articleid="473936">
   electronic first-person shooter games
  </xref>
  to add environmental, health, and other information to players’ viewpoints. (Various militaries have begun to experiment with adding similar overlays to real soldiers using personal head-mounted visors.) Augmented reality applications also have been developed for
  <xref articleid="474140">
   smartphones
  </xref>
  to display information such as building addresses, real estate signs, retail sales offers, and restaurant reviews on specific sites seen through the devices’ viewfinder or electronic displays. Such information may be supplied using a global positioning system (
  <xref articleid="396001">
   GPS
  </xref>
  ) linked to a commercial or
  <xref articleid="389944">
   open-source
  </xref>
  <xref articleid="29424">
   database
  </xref>
  . Some visionaries hope to take the next step of adding such informational displays to lightweight sunglasses, and proponents of
  <xref articleid="471385">
   social networking
  </xref>
  envision all sorts of personal identification tags being added to such displays.
 </p>
 <signature>
  William L. Hosch
 </signature>
 <copyright>
  Encyclopædia Britannica
 </copyright>
</article>