<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "syndication_xml.dtd">
<article articleid="476920" articletypeid="1" language="en_us" lastupdate="2021-Jul-01 06:18:52" url="/article/hot-flash/476920" version="2">
 <title>
  hot flash
 </title>
 <p>
  <e type="bold">
   hot flash
  </e>
  , symptom of declining
  <xref articleid="33102">
   estrogen
  </xref>
  levels associated with
  <xref articleid="110813">
   menopause
  </xref>
  that is characterized by a sensation of warmth of the face and upper body, flushing of the
  <xref articleid="106316">
   skin
  </xref>
  , sweating,
  <xref articleid="70865">
   tachycardia
  </xref>
  (accelerated heart rate), irritability, and
  <xref articleid="1622">
   headache
  </xref>
  . A hot flash typically lasts for a few minutes and may be followed by a sensation of cold and even shivering. It usually begins as a sense of warmth over the upper chest. It then spreads to the neck and face and may extend over the entire body, sometimes giving rise to a prickling sensation.
 </p>
 <p>
  About 75 percent of women have hot flashes at the time of menopause (which typically occurs between ages 45 and 55) and about 30 percent may still have hot flashes five years later. The frequency of hot flashes varies from one or two per day to one per hour. Hot flashes may be a source of embarrassment during the day because they tend to cause blushing, which may be disturbing, particularly in company. The flashes may recur frequently during the night and may interfere with
  <xref articleid="109539">
   sleep
  </xref>
  . They seem to be caused by sudden autonomic nerve activation that stimulates the dilation of
  <xref articleid="15707">
   blood vessels
  </xref>
  that supply the skin, leading to an increase in skin temperature and
  <xref articleid="59359">
   perspiration
  </xref>
  .
 </p>
 <p>
  Young women who have had their
  <xref articleid="57758">
   ovaries
  </xref>
  removed because of disease or for other reasons will develop hot flashes within a week following the operation.
 </p>
 <copyright>
  Encyclopædia Britannica
 </copyright>
</article>