<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "syndication_xml.dtd">
<article articleid="477388" articletypeid="1" language="en_us" lastupdate="2021-Jul-01 06:21:44" url="/article/She-Done-Him-Wrong/477388" version="5">
 <title>
  She Done Him Wrong
 </title>
 <p>
  <e type="bold">
   She Done Him Wrong
  </e>
  , American romantic comedy film, released in 1933, that helped establish both
  <xref articleid="76585">
   Mae West
  </xref>
  and
  <xref articleid="37731">
   Cary Grant
  </xref>
  as major movie stars.
 </p>
 <p>
  The film is set in 1890s Manhattan and centres on Lady Lou (played by West), who works at a saloon and is the mistress of its crooked owner, Gus Jordan (Noah Beery, Sr.). As Gus’s criminal activities begin to fall under the suspicion of a candidate for sheriff (David Landau), Lou falls for Captain Cummings (Cary Grant), a mission worker who frequents the bar. After a manic string of events that leads Lou to inadvertently kill one of Gus’s accomplices, the saloon is raided by Cummings, who reveals that he is an undercover policeman. Lou is apprehended along with Gus and several others, but once they are outside, Cummings escorts her to a coach, where he presents her with a diamond ring.
 </p>
 <p>
  Though
  <e type="italic">
   She Done Him Wrong
  </e>
  marked West’s first leading role, she was already a major force in show business by the time it was produced, having starred on the stage since the age of seven. In fact, the film was based on her controversially seductive play
  <e type="italic">
   Diamond Lil
  </e>
  (1928), and it retained in the film adaptation one of her most famous (and often transposed) lines, “Why don’t you come up sometime and see me?” West’s salacious persona caused concern for
  <xref articleid="58408">
   Paramount Pictures
  </xref>
  , but the film’s success helped to rescue the studio from a dire financial period. However, the suggestiveness of the script and West’s liberated view of female sexuality gave impetus to the new guidelines for industry censorship known as the
  <xref articleid="472498">
   Hays Production Code
  </xref>
  , which had been enacted in 1930 but were not widely enforced until the year after the film was produced.
 </p>
 <h1 id="h294159">
  <title>
   Production notes and credits
  </title>
  <list type="ul">
   <item>
    Studio: Paramount Pictures
   </item>
   <item>
    Director: Lowell Sherman
   </item>
   <item>
    Producer: William LeBaron
   </item>
   <item>
    Writers: Mae West, Harvey F. Thew, and John Bright
   </item>
   <item>
    Music: Ralph Rainger
   </item>
   <item>
    Running time: 66 minutes
   </item>
  </list>
 </h1>
 <h1 id="h294160">
  <title>
   Cast
  </title>
  <list type="ul">
   <item>
    Mae West (Lady Lou)
   </item>
   <item>
    Cary Grant (Captain Cummings)
   </item>
   <item>
    Owen Moore (Chick Clark)
   </item>
   <item>
    Gilbert Roland (Serge Stanieff)
   </item>
   <item>
    Noah Beery, Sr. (Gus Jordan)
   </item>
   <item>
    David Landau (Dan Flynn)
   </item>
  </list>
 </h1>
 <h1 id="h294161">
  <title>
   Academy Award nominations
  </title>
  <list type="ul">
   <item>
    Picture
   </item>
  </list>
  <signature>
   Lee Pfeiffer
  </signature>
 </h1>
 <copyright>
  Encyclopædia Britannica
 </copyright>
</article>