<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "syndication_xml.dtd">
<article articleid="477431" articletypeid="1" language="en_us" lastupdate="2021-Jul-01 06:22:00" url="/article/Shot-in-the-Dark-A/477431" version="3">
 <title>
  A Shot in the Dark
 </title>
 <p>
  <e type="bold">
   A Shot in the Dark
  </e>
  , British screwball comedy film, released in 1964, that was the second installment in the Pink Panther series.
 </p>
 <p>
  Ludicrously bumbling French Inspector Jacques Clouseau (played by
  <xref articleid="106396">
   Peter Sellers
  </xref>
  ) is called on to investigate a murder, but he is instantly smitten with the crime’s main suspect, a housemaid named Maria (Elke Sommer). While Clouseau spends more time clearing her name than investigating, other murders occur. The film introduces two characters that became mainstays in the Pink Panther series: Clouseau’s long-suffering boss, Commissioner Dreyfus (
  <xref articleid="489685">
   Herbert Lom
  </xref>
  ), and the loyal but inept manservant Cato (Burt Kwouk), who keeps Clouseau in shape by attacking him at unlikely moments.
 </p>
 <p>
  <e type="italic">
   A Shot in the Dark
  </e>
  was based on a stage play, and the character of Clouseau was written into the story in order to make it a vehicle for Sellers. The movie was actually completed before
  <xref articleid="477430">
   <e type="italic">
    The Pink Panther
   </e>
  </xref>
  (1963), but this “sequel” was released a few months after the first film in the series. The peculiar production history helps explain why
  <e type="italic">
   A Shot in the Dark
  </e>
  fails to reference the titular Pink Panther, a large diamond introduced in the first film. Both movies were directed by
  <xref articleid="472256">
   Blake Edwards
  </xref>
  , who helmed many of the later installments in the series.
 </p>
 <h1 id="h296347">
  <title>
   Production notes and credits
  </title>
  <list type="ul">
   <item>
    Studio:
    <xref articleid="74285">
     United Artists
    </xref>
   </item>
   <item>
    Director: Blake Edwards
   </item>
   <item>
    Writers: Blake Edwards and William Peter Blatty
   </item>
   <item>
    Music: Henry Mancini
   </item>
   <item>
    Running time: 102 minutes
   </item>
  </list>
 </h1>
 <h1 id="h296348">
  <title>
   Cast
  </title>
  <list type="ul">
   <item>
    Peter Sellers (Jacques Clouseau)
   </item>
   <item>
    Elke Sommer (Maria Gambrelli)
   </item>
   <item>
    George Sanders (Benjamin Ballon)
   </item>
   <item>
    Herbert Lom (Charles Dreyfus)
   </item>
   <item>
    Tracy Reed (Dominique Ballon)
   </item>
   <item>
    Graham Stark (Hercule LaJoy)
   </item>
   <item>
    Burt Kwouk (Kato)
   </item>
  </list>
  <signature>
   Lee Pfeiffer
  </signature>
 </h1>
 <copyright>
  Encyclopædia Britannica
 </copyright>
</article>