<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "syndication_xml.dtd">
<article articleid="485476" articletypeid="1" language="en_us" lastupdate="2021-Jul-01 06:26:59" url="/article/Leaves-of-Grass/485476" version="4">
 <title>
  Leaves of Grass
 </title>
 <p>
  <e type="bold">
   Leaves of Grass
  </e>
  , collection of poetry by American author
  <xref articleid="76878">
   Walt Whitman
  </xref>
  , first presented as a group of 12 poems published anonymously in 1855. It was followed by five revised and three reissued editions during the author’s lifetime. Poems not published in his lifetime were added in 1897. The unconventional and expansive language and subjects of the poems exerted a strong influence on American and foreign literature but also led to the book’s suppression on charges of indecency.
 </p>
 <p>
  The first edition included noted poems such as “
  <xref articleid="486681">
   Song of Myself
  </xref>
  ” and “
  <xref articleid="485228">
   I Sing the Body Electric
  </xref>
  ,” celebrating the beauty of the human body, physical health, and sexual passion. In a preface that was deleted from later editions, Whitman maintained that a poet’s style should be simple and natural, without orthodox metre or rhyme, like an animal or tree in harmony with its environment.
 </p>
 <p>
  <assembly id="a237449" url="/assembly/view/237449">
   <title>
    Learn about Whitman’s novel Life and Adventures of Jack Engle and how it adumbrated themes in Leaves of Grass
   </title>
   <media mediaid="194290" thumburl="/90/194290-049-CDD5AE48.jpg" type="video" url=""/>
   <caption>
    Learn more about Walt Whitman’s novel,
    <e type="italic">
     Life and Adventures of Jack Engle
    </e>
    (2017), which was rediscovered in 2016 and republished the following year and was said to foreshadow his best-known collection of verse,
    <e type="italic">
     Leaves of Grass
    </e>
    (first published in 1855).
   </caption>
   <credit>
    Encyclopædia Britannica, Inc.
   </credit>
  </assembly>
  <assemblyref assemblyid="a237449"/>
  Among the 122 new poems in the third edition (1860–61) were Whitman’s “Calamus” poems, which record an intense homosexual love affair. His Civil War poems,
  <e type="italic">
   <xref articleid="484641">
    Drum-Taps
   </xref>
  </e>
  (1865) and
  <e type="italic">
   Sequel to Drum-Taps
  </e>
  (1865), were included in the fourth edition (1867). The seventh edition (1881–82) grouped the poems in their final order, and the eighth edition (1889) incorporated his
  <e type="italic">
   November Boughs
  </e>
  (1888). “Garrulous to the very last” (as he wrote), he contemplated death yet also wrote buoyant poems for his ninth, “deathbed” edition (1891–92).
 </p>
 <copyright>
  Encyclopædia Britannica
 </copyright>
</article>