<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "syndication_xml.dtd">
<article articleid="486054" articletypeid="1" language="en_us" lastupdate="2021-Jul-01 06:28:25" url="/article/Parallel-Lives/486054" version="2">
 <title>
  Parallel Lives
 </title>
 <p>
  <e type="bold">
   Parallel Lives
  </e>
  , also called
  <e type="bold">
   Lives
  </e>
  , influential collection of biographies of famous Greek and Roman soldiers, legislators, orators, and statesmen written as
  <e type="italic">
   Bioi parallëloi
  </e>
  by the Greek writer
  <xref articleid="60464">
   Plutarch
  </xref>
  near the end of his life. By comparing a famous Roman with a famous Greek, Plutarch intended to provide model patterns of behaviour and to encourage mutual respect between Greeks and Romans. Twenty-two pairs and four single biographies have survived. One of the better known comparisons is that of the Greek orator
  <xref articleid="29911">
   Demosthenes
  </xref>
  with the Roman orator
  <xref articleid="82616">
   Cicero
  </xref>
  . Plutarch’s biographies of Alexander the Great and Caesar are also notable, though his comparison of the two is not extant.
 </p>
 <p>
  The form of
  <e type="italic">
   Parallel Lives
  </e>
  was new, not closely linked with either previous biography or Hellenistic history. Plutarch’s method was to give details of the birth, youth, achievements, and death of his characters, followed by a formal comparison. His biographies are enriched with frequent ethical reflections and anecdotes. He is essentially a moralist whose aim is to edify the reader.
 </p>
 <p>
  A well-known English translation by
  <xref articleid="56167">
   Sir Thomas North
  </xref>
  in 1579,
  <e type="italic">
   Lives of the Noble Grecians and Romans
  </e>
  , was the source of
  <xref articleid="109536">
   William Shakespeare
  </xref>
  ’s Roman history plays and influenced his conception of the tragic hero.
  <xref articleid="76029">
   Izaak Walton
  </xref>
  and
  <xref articleid="31281">
   John Dryden
  </xref>
  also published translations of the work.
 </p>
 <copyright>
  Encyclopædia Britannica
 </copyright>
</article>