<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "syndication_xml.dtd">
<article articleid="487727" articletypeid="1" language="en_us" lastupdate="2021-Jul-01 06:32:35" url="/article/Day-the-Earth-Stood-Still-The/487727" version="3">
 <title>
  The Day the Earth Stood Still
 </title>
 <p>
  <e type="bold">
   The Day the Earth Stood Still
  </e>
  , American
  <xref articleid="66289">
   science-fiction
  </xref>
  film, released in 1951, that is considered a classic of the genre and that reflects the fears and anxiety of the
  <xref articleid="24721">
   Cold War
  </xref>
  era and nascent atomic age.
 </p>
 <p>
  A flying saucer lands in Washington, D.C., carrying Klaatu (played by Michael Rennie) and his
  <xref articleid="63935">
   robot
  </xref>
  servant Gort (Lock Martin). Klaatu is shot shortly after landing and is taken to an army hospital. Klaatu tells the president’s secretary that he wants to meet the leaders of
  <xref articleid="110147">
   Earth
  </xref>
  but soon is told that an agreement on a meeting site has proved impossible to obtain. Klaatu subsequently escapes from the hospital and takes a room in a boarding house, where he befriends a young widow, Helen Benson (
  <xref articleid="343271">
   Patricia Neal
  </xref>
  ), and her son, Bobby (Billy Gray). With Bobby’s help, Klaatu meets the eminent scientist Professor Barnhardt (Sam Jaffe) and reveals that he is a representative from a federation of other planets sent to Earth to warn humankind that their experiments with atomic weapons are threatening the safety of other civilizations. After Barnhardt tells Klaatu that he needs to demonstrate his power to Earth’s leaders, Klaatu arranges for the loss of all power on Earth except where such loss would be life-threatening. Realizing that he is the alien visitor, Helen helps Klaatu get back to his saucer. Before leaving, Klaatu warns Barnhardt and his fellow scientists that unless humankind gives up violence, other planets will destroy Earth in their own defense.
 </p>
 <p>
  The special effects, such as the landing of Klaatu’s saucer and the heat ray that Gort emits, are cleverly staged. The phrase “Klaatu barada nikto” (a line of instruction spoken to Gort) has appeared frequently in fiction and in popular culture. Bernard Herrmann’s score was innovative for its day because of its use of the
  <xref articleid="72060">
   theremin
  </xref>
  and other electronic instruments.
 </p>
 <h1 id="h296564">
  <title>
   Production notes and credits
  </title>
  <list type="ul">
   <item>
    Studio:
    <xref articleid="73943">
     20th Century Fox
    </xref>
   </item>
   <item>
    Director:
    <xref articleid="77262">
     Robert Wise
    </xref>
   </item>
   <item>
    Producer: Julian Blaustein
   </item>
   <item>
    Writer: Edmund H. North
   </item>
   <item>
    Music: Bernard Herrmann
   </item>
   <item>
    Running time: 92 minutes
   </item>
  </list>
 </h1>
 <h1 id="h296565">
  <title>
   Cast
  </title>
  <list type="ul">
   <item>
    Michael Rennie (Klaatu)
   </item>
   <item>
    Patricia Neal (Helen Benson)
   </item>
   <item>
    Hugh Marlowe (Tom Stevens)
   </item>
   <item>
    Sam Jaffe (Professor Barnhardt)
   </item>
   <item>
    Billy Gray (Bobby)
   </item>
   <item>
    Lock Martin (Gort)
   </item>
  </list>
  <signature>
   Lee Pfeiffer
  </signature>
 </h1>
 <copyright>
  Encyclopædia Britannica
 </copyright>
</article>