<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "syndication_xml.dtd">
<article articleid="488834" articletypeid="1" language="en_us" lastupdate="2022-Jul-28 08:04:24" url="/article/invention/488834" version="5">
 <title>
  invention
 </title>
 <p>
  <assembly id="a149067" url="/assembly/view/149067">
   <title>
    incandescent lightbulb
   </title>
   <media mediaid="129641" type="image" url="/41/129641-004-450EA0C2.jpg"/>
   <caption>
    The incandescent lightbulb—the quintessential invention, attributed to Thomas Alva Edison in 1879.
   </caption>
   <credit>
    © Pulsar75/Shutterstock.com
   </credit>
  </assembly>
  <e type="bold">
   invention
  </e>
  ,
  <assemblyref assemblyid="a149067"/>
  the act of bringing ideas or objects together in a novel way to create something that did not exist before.
 </p>
 <h1 id="h298208">
  <title>
   Building models of what might be
  </title>
  <p>
   <assembly id="a73012" url="/assembly/view/73012">
    <title>
     stone tools
    </title>
    <media mediaid="79501" type="image" url="/01/79501-004-C491192C.jpg"/>
    <caption>
     Replica stone tools of the Acheulean industry, used by
     <e type="italic">
      Homo erectus
     </e>
     and early modern humans, and of the Mousterian industry, used by Neanderthals. (Top, left to right) Mid-Acheulean bifacial hand ax and Acheulean banded-flint hand ax. (Centre) Acheulean hand tool. (Bottom, left to right) Mousterian bifacial hand ax, scraper, and bifacial point.
    </caption>
    <credit>
     © Bone Clones, www.boneclones.com
    </credit>
   </assembly>
   <assemblyref assemblyid="a73012"/>
   Ever since the first prehistoric stone tools, humans have lived in a world shaped by invention. Indeed, the brain appears to be a natural inventor. As part of the act of perception, humans assemble, arrange, and manipulate incoming sensory information so as to build a dynamic, constantly updated model of the outside world. The survival value of such a model lies in the fact that it functions as a template against which to match new experiences, so as to rapidly identify anything anomalous that might be life-threatening. Such a model would also make it possible to predict danger. The predictive act would involve the construction of hypothetical models of the way the world might be at some future point. Such models could include elements that might, for whatever reason, be assembled into novel submodels (inventive ideas).
  </p>
  <p>
   <assembly id="a230081" url="/assembly/view/230081">
    <title>
     Sumerian cuneiform tablet
    </title>
    <media mediaid="197632" type="image" url="/32/197632-004-F9A1242F.jpg"/>
    <caption>
     Sumerian cuneiform tablet, probably from Erech (Uruk), Mesopotamia, c. 3100–2900
     <e type="smallcap">
      bce
     </e>
     ; in the Metropolitan Museum of Art, New York City.
    </caption>
    <credit>
     The Metropolitan Museum of Art, New York; Purchase, Raymond and Beverly Sackler Gift, 1988, 1988.433.1, www.metmuseum.org
    </credit>
   </assembly>
   <assemblyref assemblyid="a230081"/>
   One of the earliest and most literal examples of this model-building paradigm in action was the ancient Mesopotamian invention of
   <xref articleid="110475" refid="h53658">
    writing
   </xref>
   . As early as 8000
   <e type="smallcap">
    bce
   </e>
   tiny geometric clay models, used to represent sheep and grain, were kept in clay envelopes, to be used as inventory tallies or else to represent goods during barter. Over time, the tokens were pressed onto the exterior of the wet envelope, which at some point was flattened into a tablet. By about 3100
   <e type="smallcap">
    bce
   </e>
   the impressions had become abstract designs marked on the tablet with a cut reed stalk. These pictograms, known today as
   <xref articleid="110476">
    cuneiform
   </xref>
   , were the first writing. And they changed the world.
  </p>
  <p>
   Inventions almost always cause change. Paleolithic stone weapons made hunting possible and thereby triggered the emergence of permanent top-down command structures. The
   <xref articleid="102489">
    printing press
   </xref>
   , introduced by
   <xref articleid="38592" refid="h2940">
    Johannes Gutenberg
   </xref>
   in the 15th century, once and for all curtailed the traditional authority of elders. The
   <xref articleid="74000">
    typewriter
   </xref>
   , brought onto the market by
   <xref articleid="67482">
    Christopher Latham Sholes
   </xref>
   in the 1870s, was instrumental in freeing women from housework and changing their social status for good (and also increasing the divorce rate).
  </p>
 </h1>
 <h1 id="h298209">
  <title>
   What inventors are
  </title>
  <p>
   Inventors are often extremely observant. In the 1940s Swiss engineer George de Mestral saw tiny hooks on the burrs clinging to his hunting jacket and invented the hook-and-loop fastener system known as Velcro.
  </p>
  <p>
   Invention can be serendipitous. In the late 1800s a German medical scientist,
   <xref articleid="32103" refid="h2053">
    Paul Ehrlich
   </xref>
   , spilled some new dye into a Petri dish containing bacilli, saw that the dye selectively stained and killed some of them, and invented chemotherapy. In the mid-1800s an American businessman,
   <xref articleid="37388">
    Charles Goodyear
   </xref>
   , dropped a
   <xref articleid="23536" refid="h289654">
    rubber
   </xref>
   mixture containing sulfur on his hot stove and invented
   <xref articleid="75786">
    vulcanization
   </xref>
   .
  </p>
  <p>
   Inventors do it for money. Austrian chemist
   <xref articleid="76517">
    Auer von Welsbach
   </xref>
   , in developing the gas mantle in the 1880s, provided 30 extra years of profitability to the shareholders of gaslight companies (which at the time were threatened by the new electric light).
  </p>
  <p>
   Inventions are often unintended. In the early 1890s
   <xref articleid="3529">
    Edward Acheson
   </xref>
   , an American entrepreneur in the field of electric lighting, was seeking to invent artificial diamonds when an electrified mix of
   <xref articleid="24703">
    coke
   </xref>
   and clay produced the ultrahard abrasive
   <xref articleid="471972">
    Carborundum
   </xref>
   . In an attempt to develop artificial
   <xref articleid="62289">
    quinine
   </xref>
   in the mid-1800s, British chemist
   <xref articleid="59280">
    William Perkin
   </xref>
   ’s investigation of
   <xref articleid="24505">
    coal tar
   </xref>
   instead created the first artificial
   <xref articleid="108379" refid="h277835">
    dye
   </xref>
   , tyrian purple—which later fell into Ehrlich’s Petri dish.
  </p>
  <p>
   <assembly id="a250537" url="/assembly/view/250537">
    <title>
     Evangelista Torricelli
    </title>
    <media mediaid="154616" type="image" url="/16/154616-004-6F40939B.jpg"/>
    <caption>
     Evangelista Torricelli.
    </caption>
    <credit>
     Steve Nicklas, NOS, NGS—National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration/Department of Commerce
    </credit>
   </assembly>
   <assemblyref assemblyid="a250537"/>
   Inventors solve puzzles. In the course of investigating why suction pumps would lift water only about 9 metres (30 feet),
   <xref articleid="72977">
    Evangelista Torricelli
   </xref>
   identified air pressure and invented the
   <xref articleid="13436">
    barometer
   </xref>
   .
  </p>
  <p>
   Inventors are dogged. The American inventor
   <xref articleid="106218">
    Thomas Edison
   </xref>
   , who tested thousands of materials before he chose
   <xref articleid="12079">
    bamboo
   </xref>
   to make the carbon filament for his
   <xref articleid="42238">
    incandescent lightbulb
   </xref>
   , described his work as "one percent inspiration and 99 percent perspiration.” At his laboratory in Menlo Park, New Jersey, Edison’s approach was to identify a potential gap in the market and fill it with an invention. His workers were told, “There’s a way to do it better. Find it.”
  </p>
 </h1>
 <h1 id="h298210">
  <title>
   Serendipity and inspiration
  </title>
  <p>
   The key to inventive success often requires being in the right place at the right time.
   <xref articleid="67482">
    Christopher Latham Sholes
   </xref>
   and Carlos Glidden took their invention to arms manufacturer Remington just when that company’s production lines were running down after the end of the
   <xref articleid="6104">
    American Civil War
   </xref>
   . A quick retool turned Remington into the world’s first typewriter manufacturer.
  </p>
  <p>
   An invention developed for one purpose will sometimes find use in entirely different circumstances. In medieval Afghanistan somebody invented a leather loop to hang on the side of a camel for use as a step when loading the animal. By 1066 the Normans had put the loop on each side of a horse and invented the
   <xref articleid="69738">
    stirrup
   </xref>
   . With their feet thus firmly anchored, at the
   <xref articleid="39483">
    Battle of Hastings
   </xref>
   that year Norman knights hit opposing English foot soldiers with their lances and the full weight of the horse without being unseated by the shock of the encounter. The Normans won the battle and took over England (and made English the French-Saxon mix it is today).
  </p>
  <p>
   One invention can inspire another. Gaslight distribution pipes gave Edison the idea for his electricity network. Perforated cards used to control the
   <xref articleid="43218">
    Jacquard loom
   </xref>
   led
   <xref articleid="40802">
    Herman Hollerith
   </xref>
   to invent punch cards for tabulator use in the 1890 U.S. census.
  </p>
 </h1>
 <h1 id="h298211">
  <title>
   The quickening pace of invention
  </title>
  <p>
   Above all, invention appears primarily to involve a “1 + 1 = 3” process similar to the brain’s model-building activity, in which concepts or techniques are brought together for the first time and the outcome is more than the sum of the parts (e.g., spray + gasoline =
   <xref articleid="20272">
    carburetor
   </xref>
   ).
  </p>
  <p>
   The more often ideas come together, the more frequently invention occurs. The rate of invention increased sharply, each time, when the exchange of ideas became easier after the invention of the printing press,
   <xref articleid="117784">
    telecommunications
   </xref>
   , the
   <xref articleid="117728">
    computer
   </xref>
   , and above all the
   <xref articleid="1458">
    Internet
   </xref>
   . Today new fields such as
   <xref articleid="437561">
    data mining
   </xref>
   and
   <xref articleid="384821">
    nanotechnology
   </xref>
   offer would-be inventors (or semi-intelligent software programs) massive amounts of “1 + 1 = 3” opportunities. As a result, the rate of innovation seems poised to increase dramatically in the coming decades.
  </p>
  <p>
   It is going to become harder than ever to keep up with the secondary results of invention as the general public gains access to information and technology denied them for millennia and as billions of brains, each with its own natural inventive capabilities, innovate faster than social institutions can adapt. In some cases, as occurred during the global
   <xref articleid="603098">
    financial crisis of 2007–08
   </xref>
   , institutions will face severe challenges from the introduction of technologies for which their old-fashioned infrastructures will be ill-prepared. It may be that the only safe way to deal with the potentially disruptive effects of an avalanche of invention, so as to develop the new social processes required to manage a permanent state of change, will be to do what the brain does: invent a comprehensive virtual world in which one can safely test innovative ideas before applying them.
  </p>
  <signature>
   James Burke
  </signature>
 </h1>
 <h1 id="h298212">
  <title>
   A chronology of invention
  </title>
  <p>
   Notable inventors and their inventions are listed in the table.
  </p>
 </h1>
 <copyright>
  Encyclopædia Britannica
 </copyright>
</article>