<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "syndication_xml.dtd">
<article articleid="52266" articletypeid="1" language="en_us" lastupdate="2021-Jun-30 23:45:52" url="/article/metal/52266" version="5">
 <title>
  metal
 </title>
 <p>
  <assembly id="a110514" url="/assembly/view/110514">
   <title>
    block of gold
   </title>
   <media mediaid="101122" type="image" url="/22/101122-004-87A8A663.jpg"/>
   <caption>
    Block of metallic gold.
   </caption>
   <credit>
    © Jupiterimages Corporation
   </credit>
  </assembly>
  <e type="bold">
   metal
  </e>
  ,
  <assemblyref assemblyid="a110514"/>
  any of a class of substances characterized by high electrical and thermal conductivity as well as by malleability, ductility, and high reflectivity of light.
 </p>
 <p>
  Approximately three-quarters of all known chemical elements are metals. The most abundant varieties in the Earth’s crust are
  <xref articleid="5954">
   aluminum
  </xref>
  ,
  <xref articleid="42794">
   iron
  </xref>
  ,
  <xref articleid="18627">
   calcium
  </xref>
  ,
  <xref articleid="68494">
   sodium
  </xref>
  ,
  <xref articleid="61048">
   potassium
  </xref>
  , and
  <xref articleid="50015">
   magnesium
  </xref>
  . The vast majority of metals are found in ores (mineral-bearing substances), but a few such as
  <xref articleid="26194">
   copper
  </xref>
  ,
  <xref articleid="37211">
   gold
  </xref>
  ,
  <xref articleid="60356">
   platinum
  </xref>
  , and
  <xref articleid="67807">
   silver
  </xref>
  frequently occur in the free state because they do not readily react with other elements.
 </p>
 <p>
  Metals are usually crystalline solids. In most cases, they have a relatively simple crystal structure distinguished by a close packing of atoms and a high degree of symmetry. Typically, the atoms of metals contain less than half the full complement of electrons in their outermost shell. Because of this characteristic, metals tend not to form compounds with each other. They do, however, combine more readily with nonmetals (e.g., oxygen and sulfur), which generally have more than half the maximum number of valence electrons. Metals differ widely in their chemical reactivity. The most reactive include lithium, potassium, and radium, whereas those of low reactivity are gold, silver, palladium, and platinum.
 </p>
 <p>
  The high electrical and thermal conductivities of the simple metals (i.e., the non-transition metals of the periodic table) are best explained by reference to the free-electron theory. According to this concept, the individual atoms in such metals have lost their valence electrons to the entire solid, and these free electrons that give rise to conductivity move as a group throughout the solid. In the case of the more complex metals (i.e., the transition elements), conductivities are better explained by the
  <xref articleid="12112">
   band theory
  </xref>
  , which takes into account not only the presence of free electrons but also their interaction with so-called
  <e type="italic">
   d
  </e>
  electrons.
 </p>
 <p>
  The mechanical properties of metals, such as hardness, ability to resist repeated stressing (fatigue strength), ductility, and malleability, are often attributed to defects or imperfections in their crystal structure. The absence of a layer of atoms in its densely packed structure, for example, enables a metal to deform plastically, and prevents it from being brittle.
 </p>
 <signature>
  EB Editors
 </signature>
 <copyright>
  Encyclopædia Britannica
 </copyright>
</article>