<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "syndication_xml.dtd">
<article articleid="52890" articletypeid="1" language="en_us" lastupdate="2022-Jul-21 17:11:33" url="/article/mint/52890" version="7">
 <title>
  mint
 </title>
 <p>
  <e type="bold">
   mint
  </e>
  , (genus
  <e type="italic">
   Mentha
  </e>
  ), genus of 25 species of fragrant herbs of the mint family (
  <xref articleid="46962">
   Lamiaceae
  </xref>
  ). Native to Eurasia, North America, southern Africa, and Australia, mints are widely distributed throughout the temperate areas of the world and have naturalized in many places. A number of species, particularly
  <xref articleid="59168">
   peppermint
  </xref>
  and
  <xref articleid="69020">
   spearmint
  </xref>
  , are used as flavourings for foods (including candy and gum) and for
  <xref articleid="48466">
   liqueur
  </xref>
  and dentifrices. The
  <xref articleid="33048">
   essential oils
  </xref>
  of mints are used as scents in perfumery. Some species are commonly used in herbal medicine.
 </p>
 <h1 id="h350139">
  <title>
   Physical description
  </title>
  <p>
   <assembly id="a144214" url="/assembly/view/144214">
    <title>
     peppermint
    </title>
    <media mediaid="139046" type="image" url="/46/139046-004-A9BCAFDE.jpg"/>
    <caption>
     Peppermint (
     <e type="italic">
      Mentha
     </e>
     ×
     <e type="italic">
      piperita
     </e>
     ).
    </caption>
    <credit>
     © Gul Kocher/Fotolia
    </credit>
   </assembly>
   <assemblyref assemblyid="a144214"/>
   Mints have square stems and opposite aromatic
   <xref articleid="47499">
    leaves
   </xref>
   . Many can spread vegetatively by
   <xref articleid="69787">
    stolons
   </xref>
   and can be aggressive in gardens. The small
   <xref articleid="34656">
    flowers
   </xref>
   are usually pale purple, pink, or white in colour and are arranged in clusters, either forming whorls or crowded together in a terminal spike. The flowers are not typical of other members of the family, having four rather than five united petals. The volatile oils are contained in resinous dots in the leaves and stems.
  </p>
 </h1>
 <h1 id="h350140">
  <title>
   Major species
  </title>
  <p>
   <xref articleid="69020">
    Spearmint
   </xref>
   (
   <e type="italic">
    Mentha spicata
   </e>
   ) grows to about 90 cm (3 feet) in height, with open spikes of pink or lilac flowers and stalkless leaves; it has the characteristic mint fragrance.
   <xref articleid="59168">
    Peppermint
   </xref>
   (
   <e type="italic">
    Mentha
   </e>
   ×
   <e type="italic">
    piperita
   </e>
   ), a hybrid between spearmint and water mint, has a heavy scent, stalked leaves, and reddish lilac flowers in dense spikes. Water mint (
   <e type="italic">
    M. aquatica
   </e>
   ) commonly grows in ditches and has rounded flower spikes and stalked hairy leaves. Wild mint (
   <e type="italic">
    M. arvensis
   </e>
   ), native in North America and Eurasia, reaches about 1 metre (about 3.3 feet) in height.
  </p>
  <p>
   Pennyroyal (
   <e type="italic">
    M. pulegium
   </e>
   ) has small oval obtuse leaves and flowers in axillary whorls and is remarkable for its creeping habit and pungent odour. It has been used in folk medicine to induce
   <xref articleid="59359">
    perspiration
   </xref>
   and
   <xref articleid="110812">
    menstruation
   </xref>
   . The plant has also been used as an herbal
   <xref articleid="487583">
    abortifacient
   </xref>
   , though such preparations are unlikely to terminate a
   <xref articleid="110815">
    pregnancy
   </xref>
   . Pennyroyal can induce potentially lethal reactions such as vomiting,
   <xref articleid="472506">
    hemorrhages
   </xref>
   , and organ failure in people who ingest it. Pennyroyal oil in particular is highly toxic and should not be ingested.
  </p>
 </h1>
 <h1 id="h350141">
  <title>
   Related species
  </title>
  <p>
   Other members of the family Lamiaceae are also known as mints: the
   <xref articleid="78744">
    bergamots
   </xref>
   , or bee balms (genus
   <e type="italic">
    Monarda
   </e>
   ), are sometimes called horsemint; members of the genus
   <e type="italic">
    Pycnanthemum
   </e>
   are called mountain mints;
   <xref articleid="21832">
    catnip
   </xref>
   (
   <e type="italic">
    Nepeta cataria
   </e>
   ) is also known as catmint;
   <xref articleid="30665">
    dittany
   </xref>
   (
   <e type="italic">
    Cunila origanoides
   </e>
   ) is called stonemint; and plants of the Australian genus
   <e type="italic">
    Prostanthera
   </e>
   are called mint bushes.
  </p>
 </h1>
 <signature>
  EB Editors
 </signature>
 <copyright>
  Encyclopædia Britannica
 </copyright>
</article>