<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "syndication_xml.dtd">
<article articleid="53598" articletypeid="1" language="en_us" lastupdate="2023-Mar-10 15:57:29" url="/article/moon/53598" version="14">
 <title>
  moon
 </title>
 <p>
  <assembly id="a71535" url="/assembly/view/71535">
   <title>
    Europa
   </title>
   <media mediaid="75385" type="image" url="/85/75385-004-F20E950A.jpg"/>
   <caption>
    Crescent view of Europa, one of Jupiter’s four large, Galilean moons, in a composite of images made by the Galileo spacecraft in 1995 and 1998. Colours have been exaggerated in processing to reveal subtle differences in surface materials. The reddish lines in the moon’s icy crust are cracks and ridges, some of them thousands of kilometres long, while the reddish mottling indicates areas of disrupted ice, where large ice blocks have shifted. The red material may be salt minerals deposited by liquid water that emerged from below the surface. The relatively few craters indicate that the icy crust has been relatively warm and mobile for at least a good part of Europa’s early history.
   </caption>
   <credit>
    NASA/JPL/University of Arizona
   </credit>
  </assembly>
  <e type="bold">
   moon
  </e>
  ,
  <assemblyref assemblyid="a71535"/>
  any natural satellite orbiting another body. In the
  <xref articleid="110143">
   solar system
  </xref>
  there are 219 moons orbiting the
  <xref articleid="60298">
   planets
  </xref>
  .
  <xref articleid="110147">
   Earth
  </xref>
  ,
  <xref articleid="110149">
   Mars
  </xref>
  ,
  <xref articleid="110150">
   Jupiter
  </xref>
  ,
  <xref articleid="110151">
   Saturn
  </xref>
  ,
  <xref articleid="110152">
   Uranus
  </xref>
  , and
  <xref articleid="110153">
   Neptune
  </xref>
  have 1, 2, 92, 83, 27, and 14 moons, respectively. Other bodies in the solar system, such as
  <xref articleid="435823">
   dwarf planets
  </xref>
  ,
  <xref articleid="110155">
   asteroids
  </xref>
  , and
  <xref articleid="342992">
   Kuiper belt
  </xref>
  objects, also have moons. No moons have yet been discovered around
  <xref articleid="439223">
   extrasolar planets
  </xref>
  . The solar system’s moons range in size from tens of metres across, the diameter of small bodies in orbit around asteroids, to 5,262 km (3,270 miles), the diameter of Jupiter’s moon
  <xref articleid="36012">
   Ganymede
  </xref>
  .
 </p>
 <p>
  <assembly id="a274429" url="/assembly/view/274429">
   <title>
    Explore the phases of the moon and their effectiveness in tracking time
   </title>
   <media mediaid="236546" thumburl="" type="video" url="NaAnUuSs"/>
   <caption>
    Learn about the phases of the moon and their effectiveness in tracking time.
   </caption>
   <credit>
    Encyclopædia Britannica, Inc.
   </credit>
  </assembly>
  <assemblyref assemblyid="a274429"/>
  Some moons are of interest because they have conditions that may be favourable for
  <xref articleid="106478">
   life
  </xref>
  . For example, Jupiter’s moon
  <xref articleid="33259">
   Europa
  </xref>
  has an ocean underneath its icy surface. Saturn’s moon
  <xref articleid="32584">
   Enceladus
  </xref>
  has
  <xref articleid="36646">
   geysers
  </xref>
  that spew out
  <xref articleid="76210">
   water
  </xref>
  and
  <xref articleid="57352">
   organic molecules
  </xref>
  .
 </p>
 <p>
  During nine
  <xref articleid="8019">
   Apollo
  </xref>
  space missions, 24 astronauts (all Americans) went to Earth’s
  <xref articleid="110148">
   Moon
  </xref>
  , and 12 of them walked on its surface. With the launch of the
  <xref articleid="635036">
   Artemis
  </xref>
  space program in 2017,
  <xref articleid="54947">
   NASA
  </xref>
  aims to return humans to the Moon by 2025, with the goal of establishing a sustainable presence there and on other planets.
 </p>
 <signature>
  Erik Gregersen
 </signature>
 <copyright>
  Encyclopædia Britannica
 </copyright>
</article>