<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "syndication_xml.dtd">
<article articleid="53960" articletypeid="1" language="en_us" lastupdate="2021-Jun-30 23:55:16" url="/article/motion-equation-of/53960" version="6">
 <title>
  equation of motion
 </title>
 <p>
  <e type="bold">
   equation of motion
  </e>
  , mathematical formula that describes the position, velocity, or acceleration of a body relative to a given frame of reference. Newton’s second law, which states that the force
  <e type="italic">
   F
  </e>
  acting on a body is equal to the mass
  <e type="italic">
   m
  </e>
  of the body multiplied by the acceleration
  <e type="italic">
   a
  </e>
  of its centre of mass,
  <e type="italic">
   F
  </e>
  =
  <e type="italic">
   ma,
  </e>
  is the basic equation of motion in classical mechanics. If the force acting on a body is known as a function of time, the velocity and position of the body as functions of time can, theoretically, be derived from Newton’s equation by a process known as integration. For example, a falling body accelerates at a constant rate,
  <e type="italic">
   g
  </e>
  . Acceleration is the rate of change of velocity with respect to time, so that by integration the velocity
  <e type="italic">
   v
  </e>
  in terms of time
  <e type="italic">
   t
  </e>
  is given by
  <e type="italic">
   v
  </e>
  =
  <e type="italic">
   gt
  </e>
  . Velocity is the time rate of change of position
  <e type="italic">
   S,
  </e>
  and, consequently, integration of the velocity equation yields
  <e type="italic">
   S
  </e>
  =
  <fraction>
   <num>
    1
   </num>
   <den>
    2
   </den>
  </fraction>
  <e type="italic">
   gt
  </e>
  <sup>
   2
  </sup>
  .
 </p>
 <p>
  If the force acting on a body is specified as a function of position or velocity, the integration of Newton’s equation may be more difficult. When a body is constrained to move in a specified manner on a fixed path, it may be possible to derive the position-time equation; from this equation the velocity-time and acceleration-time equations can, theoretically, be obtained by a process known as differentiation.
 </p>
 <signature>
  EB Editors
 </signature>
 <copyright>
  Encyclopædia Britannica
 </copyright>
</article>