<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "syndication_xml.dtd">
<article articleid="55085" articletypeid="1" language="en_us" lastupdate="2021-Jul-01 00:01:37" url="/article/navigation-chart/55085" version="3">
 <title>
  navigation chart
 </title>
 <p>
  <e type="bold">
   navigation chart
  </e>
  , map designed and used primarily for
  <xref articleid="108753">
   navigation
  </xref>
  . A nautical chart presents most of the information used by the marine navigator, including
  <xref articleid="47303">
   latitude and longitude
  </xref>
  scales, topographical features, navigation aids such as
  <xref articleid="117294">
   lighthouses
  </xref>
  and radio beacons, magnetic information, indications of reefs and shoals, water depth, and warning notices. Such information allows both plotting a safe course and checking progress while sailing.
 </p>
 <p>
  The first navigation charts were made at the end of the 13th century. The appearance of the magnetic
  <xref articleid="25014">
   compass
  </xref>
  100 years earlier is considered to have been the catalyst for the development of charts. Earlier, seamen had relied on the proximity of a familiar coast, on the position of celestial bodies, or on meteorological phenomena such as, in the Indian Ocean, the monsoon winds. The less-predictable winds and weather of the Mediterranean spurred the development there of the first charts. These were plane charts (taking no account of the Earth’s curvature) that were regularly crossed by rhumb lines, or
  <xref articleid="49173">
   loxodromes
  </xref>
  , that corresponded to the direction from which the wind was likely to blow.
 </p>
 <p>
  Plane maps were not suitable for navigation in far northern or southern latitudes, and by the 17th century they were replaced by
  <xref articleid="52078">
   Mercator projection charts
  </xref>
  that showed compass directions as straight lines. Projections other than the Mercator are also used, especially in very high latitudes.
 </p>
 <p>
  Aeronautical charts are similar to nautical charts but emphasize such things as topography, heights of obstructions, airports, and airways. They are usually drawn on the
  <xref articleid="46945">
   Lambert conformal projection
  </xref>
  , which correctly preserves angles between different locations on the surface of the Earth.
 </p>
 <copyright>
  Encyclopædia Britannica
 </copyright>
</article>