<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "syndication_xml.dtd">
<article articleid="55272" articletypeid="1" language="en_us" lastupdate="2021-Jul-01 00:02:40" url="/article/neon/55272" version="8">
 <title>
  neon (Ne)
 </title>
 <p>
  <assembly id="a64457" url="/assembly/view/64457">
   <media mediaid="22390" type="image" url="/90/22390-004-16442944.jpg"/>
   <caption/>
   <credit>
    Encyclopædia Britannica, Inc.
   </credit>
  </assembly>
  <e type="bold">
   neon (Ne)
  </e>
  ,
  <assemblyref assemblyid="a64457"/>
  <xref articleid="110602">
   chemical element
  </xref>
  , inert gas of Group 18 (
  <xref articleid="110613">
   noble gases
  </xref>
  ) of the
  <xref articleid="110603">
   periodic table
  </xref>
  , used in electric signs and
  <xref articleid="34676">
   fluorescent lamps
  </xref>
  . Colourless, odourless, tasteless, and lighter than air, neon gas occurs in minute quantities in
  <xref articleid="110147">
   Earth’s
  </xref>
  <xref articleid="126202">
   atmosphere
  </xref>
  and trapped within the rocks of Earth’s
  <xref articleid="28060">
   crust
  </xref>
  . Though neon is about 3
  <fraction>
   <num>
    1
   </num>
   <den>
    2
   </den>
  </fraction>
  times as plentiful as
  <xref articleid="1713">
   helium
  </xref>
  in the atmosphere, dry air contains only 0.0018 percent neon by volume. This element is more abundant in the cosmos than on Earth. Neon liquefies at −246.048 °C (−411 °F) and freezes at a temperature only 2
  <fraction>
   <num>
    1
   </num>
   <den>
    2
   </den>
  </fraction>
  ° lower. When under low pressure, it emits a bright orange-red light if an
  <xref articleid="32273">
   electrical current
  </xref>
  is passed through it. This property is utilized in neon signs (which first became familiar in the 1920s), in some fluorescent and gaseous conduction lamps, and in high-voltage testers. The name
  <e type="italic">
   neon
  </e>
  is derived from the Greek word
  <e type="italic">
   neos
  </e>
  , “new.”
 </p>
 <p>
  Neon was discovered (1898) by the British chemists
  <xref articleid="62617">
   Sir William Ramsay
  </xref>
  and Morris W. Travers as a component of the most volatile fraction of liquefied crude
  <xref articleid="9382">
   argon
  </xref>
  obtained from air. It was immediately recognized as a new element by its unique glow when electrically stimulated. Its only commercial source is the atmosphere, in which it is 18 parts per million by volume. Because its boiling point is −246 °C (−411 °F), neon remains, along with helium and
  <xref articleid="110604">
   hydrogen
  </xref>
  , in the small fraction of air that resists liquefaction upon cooling to −195.8 °C (−320.4 °F, the boiling point of liquid nitrogen). Neon is isolated from this cold, gaseous mixture by bringing it into contact with activated
  <xref articleid="22505">
   charcoal
  </xref>
  , which adsorbs the neon and hydrogen; removal of hydrogen is effected by adding enough
  <xref articleid="57841">
   oxygen
  </xref>
  to convert it all to water, which, along with any surplus oxygen, condenses upon cooling. Processing 88,000 pounds of liquid air will produce one pound of neon.
 </p>
 <p>
  No stable chemical compounds of neon have been observed.
  <xref articleid="53247">
   Molecules
  </xref>
  of the element consist of single
  <xref articleid="110411">
   atoms
  </xref>
  . Natural neon is a mixture of three stable
  <xref articleid="110412">
   isotopes
  </xref>
  : neon-20 (90.92 percent); neon-21 (0.26 percent); and neon-22 (8.82 percent). Neon was the first element shown to consist of more than one stable isotope. In 1913, application of the technique of
  <xref articleid="110406">
   mass spectrometry
  </xref>
  revealed the existence of neon-20 and neon-22. The third stable isotope, neon-21 was detected later. Twelve
  <xref articleid="62419">
   radioactive isotopes
  </xref>
  of neon also have been identified.
 </p>
 <signature>
  EB Editors
 </signature>
 <table class="element">
  <tbody>
   <tr>
    <td>
     atomic number
    </td>
    <td>
     10
    </td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td>
     atomic weight
    </td>
    <td>
     20.183
    </td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td>
     melting point
    </td>
    <td>
     −248.67 °C (−415.5 °F)
    </td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td>
     boiling point
    </td>
    <td>
     −246.048 °C (−411 °F)
    </td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td>
     density (1 atm, 0° C)
    </td>
    <td>
     0.89990 g/litre
    </td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td>
     oxidation state
    </td>
    <td>
     0
    </td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td>
     electron config.
    </td>
    <td>
     1
     <e type="italic">
      s
     </e>
     <sup>
      2
     </sup>
     2
     <e type="italic">
      s
     </e>
     <sup>
      2
     </sup>
     2
     <e type="italic">
      p
     </e>
     <sup>
      6
     </sup>
    </td>
   </tr>
  </tbody>
 </table>
 <copyright>
  Encyclopædia Britannica
 </copyright>
</article>