<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "syndication_xml.dtd">
<article articleid="57228" articletypeid="1" language="en_us" lastupdate="2021-Jul-01 00:14:00" url="/article/optical-crystallography/57228" version="4">
 <title>
  optical crystallography
 </title>
 <p>
  <e type="bold">
   optical crystallography
  </e>
  , branch of
  <xref articleid="472151">
   crystallography
  </xref>
  that deals with the optical properties of
  <xref articleid="110297">
   crystals
  </xref>
  . It is of considerable interest theoretically and has the greatest practical importance. The
  <xref articleid="66286">
   science
  </xref>
  of petrography is largely based on the study of the appearance of thin, transparent sections of
  <xref articleid="109695">
   rocks
  </xref>
  in a
  <xref articleid="108723">
   microscope
  </xref>
  fitted with polarizers. In the absence of external crystalline form, as with the
  <xref articleid="109683">
   minerals
  </xref>
  in a rock, a mineral often may be readily identified by the determination of some of its optical properties.
 </p>
 <p>
  <assembly id="a149097" url="/assembly/view/149097">
   <title>
    crystal systems
   </title>
   <media mediaid="105673" type="image" url="/73/105673-004-055DB233.jpg"/>
   <caption>
    The seven primitive crystal systems.
   </caption>
   <credit>
    Encyclopædia Britannica, Inc.
   </credit>
  </assembly>
  <assemblyref assemblyid="a149097"/>
  According to their action on transmitted plane-polarized
  <xref articleid="110443">
   light
  </xref>
  , all crystals may be assigned to one or another of the five groups enumerated below, which correspond to the seven systems of crystallization (in the second group, three systems are included together). The several
  <xref articleid="70723">
   symmetry
  </xref>
  classes of each system are optically the same, except in rare cases:
 </p>
 <p>
  1. Optically isotropic crystals (
  <xref articleid="42957">
   isometric system
  </xref>
  ), which exhibit only one index of
  <xref articleid="63033">
   refraction
  </xref>
  for light of each
  <xref articleid="109620">
   colour
  </xref>
  ;
 </p>
 <p>
  2. Optically uniaxial crystals (
  <xref articleid="71853">
   tetragonal
  </xref>
  ,
  <xref articleid="40331">
   hexagonal
  </xref>
  , and rhombohedral [or trigonal] systems), which exhibit double refraction and yield two refractive indices for light of each colour, one parallel to the optical axis and one perpendicular to the optical axis;
 </p>
 <p>
  3. Optically biaxial crystals (all of which exhibit three principal refractive indices, one along each of the mutually perpendicular optical axes) in which the three optical axes correspond to the three crystallographic axes (
  <xref articleid="57496">
   orthorhombic system
  </xref>
  );
 </p>
 <p>
  4. Optically biaxial crystals in which only one of the three optical axes corresponds to a crystallographic axis (
  <xref articleid="53392">
   monoclinic system
  </xref>
  );
 </p>
 <p>
  5. Optically biaxial crystals with no fixed and definite relation between the optical and crystallographic axes (
  <xref articleid="73360">
   triclinic system
  </xref>
  ).
 </p>
 <copyright>
  Encyclopædia Britannica
 </copyright>
</article>