<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "syndication_xml.dtd">
<article articleid="58282" articletypeid="1" language="en_us" lastupdate="2021-Oct-15 10:07:10" url="/article/panorama/58282" version="5">
 <title>
  panorama
 </title>
 <p>
  <e type="bold">
   panorama
  </e>
  , in the visual arts, continuous narrative scene or landscape painted to conform to a flat or curved background, which surrounds or is unrolled before the viewer.
 </p>
 <p>
  Panoramas are usually painted in a broad and direct manner, akin to scene, or theatrical, painting. Popular in the late 18th and the 19th centuries, the panorama was essentially the antecedent of the stereopticon and of
  <xref articleid="110698">
   motion pictures
  </xref>
  , especially
  <xref articleid="7644">
   animations
  </xref>
  and the process called
  <xref articleid="82670">
   Cinerama
  </xref>
  . The true panorama is exhibited on the walls of a large cylinder, the earliest version about 18 metres (60 feet) in diameter and later ones as large as 40 metres (130 feet) in diameter. The viewer, who stands on a platform in the cylinder centre, turns around and successively sees all points of the horizon. The effect of being surrounded by a landscape or event may be heightened by the use of indirect lighting to give the illusion that light is emanating from the painting itself.
 </p>
 <p>
  The first panorama was executed by the Scottish painter Robert Barker, who exhibited in Edinburgh in 1788 a view of that city, followed by panoramas of London and battle scenes from the Napoleonic Wars. Another early panorama painter, the American
  <xref articleid="74803">
   John Vanderlyn
  </xref>
  , painted in 1816–19
  <e type="italic">
   The Palace and Gardens of Versailles
  </e>
  (preserved in the
  <xref articleid="52363">
   Metropolitan Museum of Art
  </xref>
  , New York City), exhibiting it until 1829 in a
  <xref articleid="64208">
   rotunda
  </xref>
  that he built on a leased corner of City Hall Park in New York City. By the mid-19th century panoramas became a widespread popular form of entertainment. Among the important works of that period was Henri Philippoteaux’s
  <e type="italic">
   Siege of Paris
  </e>
  , depicting an event in the
  <xref articleid="35149">
   Franco-Prussian War
  </xref>
  . His son Paul painted the panorama
  <e type="italic">
   The Battle of Gettysburg
  </e>
  (1883), exhibiting it in several American cities before its permanent installation in
  <xref articleid="36636">
   Gettysburg
  </xref>
  , Pennsylvania. Other examples survive at
  <xref articleid="38786">
   The Hague
  </xref>
  and in
  <xref articleid="62197">
   Quebec city
  </xref>
  . A higher form of panoramic art is the Chinese and Japanese traditional hand
  <xref articleid="66397">
   scroll painting
  </xref>
  on paper or silk. (
  <e type="italic">
   See also
  </e>
  <xref articleid="30561">
   diorama
  </xref>
  ;
  <xref articleid="28383">
   cyclorama
  </xref>
  .)
 </p>
 <h1 id="h279294">
  <title>
   Bibliography
  </title>
  <p>
   <e type="smallcap">
    Richard D. Altick
   </e>
   ,
   <e type="italic">
    Shows of London
   </e>
   (1978);
   <e type="smallcap">
    Stephan Oettermann
   </e>
   ,
   <e type="italic">
    The Panorama: History of a Mass Medium
   </e>
   , trans. by
   <e type="smallcap">
    Deborah Lucas Schneider
   </e>
   (1997; originally published in German, 1980).
  </p>
 </h1>
 <copyright>
  Encyclopædia Britannica
 </copyright>
</article>