<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "syndication_xml.dtd">
<article articleid="59964" articletypeid="1" language="en_us" lastupdate="2021-Jul-01 00:29:40" url="/article/pier/59964" version="3">
 <title>
  pier
 </title>
 <p>
  <e type="bold">
   pier
  </e>
  , in
  <xref articleid="106103">
   building construction
  </xref>
  , vertical loadbearing member, such as an intermediate support for adjacent ends of two
  <xref articleid="117290">
   bridge
  </xref>
  spans. In foundations for large buildings, piers are usually cylindrical concrete shafts, cast in prepared holes, but in bridges they take the form of
  <xref articleid="18575">
   caissons
  </xref>
  , which are sunk into position. Piers serve the same purpose as
  <xref articleid="60016">
   piles
  </xref>
  but are not installed by hammers and, if based on a stable substrate, will support a greater load than a pile.
 </p>
 <p>
  Especially adapted to large construction jobs, pier shafts having widths of more than 1.8 metres (6 feet) have been excavated to depths greater than 30 metres (98 feet). The lower portion of a pier may be widened to better distribute the downward pressure of a massive overlying structure. Formerly hand-dug shafts were widely used for piers where
  <xref articleid="38222">
   groundwater
  </xref>
  presented no serious problem, but hand excavation has been largely superseded by the use of rotary or percussion drilling. The massive
  <xref articleid="11235">
   augers
  </xref>
  used to drill shafts for the piers of modern
  <xref articleid="68143">
   skyscrapers
  </xref>
  are mounted vertically on derricks, and the piers themselves are sufficiently long and wide to support the tremendous weight of even the tallest building.
 </p>
 <p>
  <assembly id="a245303" url="/assembly/view/245303">
   <title>
    caisson
   </title>
   <media mediaid="215577" type="image" url="/77/215577-004-0DAFA039.jpg"/>
   <caption>
    Construction workers building a caisson.
   </caption>
   <credit>
    © KnoB/stock.adobe.com
   </credit>
  </assembly>
  <assemblyref assemblyid="a245303"/>
  Piers for bridges are often installed by the caisson method. The caisson is a hollow boxlike structure that is sunk down through the water and then through the ground to the bearing stratum by excavating from its interior; it ultimately becomes a permanent part of the completed pier.
 </p>
 <signature>
  EB Editors
 </signature>
 <copyright>
  Encyclopædia Britannica
 </copyright>
</article>