<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "syndication_xml.dtd">
<article articleid="600993" articletypeid="1" language="en_us" lastupdate="2021-Jul-01 06:47:30" url="/article/organizational-culture/600993" version="3">
 <title>
  organizational culture
 </title>
 <p>
  <e type="bold">
   organizational culture
  </e>
  , conventionally defined as the ensemble of beliefs, assumptions, values, norms, artifacts, symbols, actions, and language patterns shared by all members of an organization. In this view, culture is thought to be an acquired body of knowledge whose interpretation and understanding provide the identity of the organization and a sense of shared identity among its members. This approach assumes clarity and organizationwide consensus among members and discounts ambiguity.
 </p>
 <p>
  However, organizational culture can also be viewed from at least two other perspectives. A different perspective centres not on the whole but rather on the consensus reached within the different subcultures of the organization, which often conflict with each other. Outside the confines of the subcultures, ambiguity and inconsistency exist organizationwide (e.g., where members may say one thing and do another).Yet another approach discounts consensus and consistency as defining characteristics of culture and focuses on ambiguity as the essence of culture. Here, agreement and disagreement are constantly changing and no stable organizationwide or subculture consensus exists.
 </p>
 <p>
  Understanding and interpreting organizational culture is important, as it affects organizational development, productivity, and learning at all levels. The underlying cultural assumptions can both enable and constrain what an organization is able to do.
 </p>
 <h1 id="h307908">
  <title>
   Culture as organizational personality
  </title>
  <p>
   Organizational culture has been referred to as an organization’s psychological assets. It can be viewed as holistic (or more than the sum of its parts), historically determined (a collection of rituals and symbols), socially constructed (or created and preserved by the group who form it), and difficult to change. A culture contains patterns of assumptions that lead to behaviours that work for the organization. Many of those assumptions are underlying, unquestioned, and forgotten and may, for the most part, be unconscious to organization members. Even so, such collective beliefs shape organizational behaviour. Therefore, people’s actions and preferences may not always be their own but, rather, are largely influenced by socialization processes based in the culture or subcultures of the organization to which they belong. Behaviours are controlled by the beliefs, norms, values, and assumptions rather than being restrained by formal rules, authority, and the norms of rational behaviour. As a result, an organization’s “personality” may be more important to performance and motivation than the exercise of rewards and sanctions.
  </p>
 </h1>
 <h1 id="h307910">
  <title>
   Manifestations of organizational culture
  </title>
  <p>
   Culture can manifest itself in a number of ways. Visible, but often indecipherable, are the behavioral regularities in the way people interact. Examples include the language used, customs and traditions practiced, and rituals employed in a wide variety of situations. Next and also visible are those publicly announced principles and values the group claims to be trying to achieve and the ideologies and broad policies that guide a group’s actions. They may represent a formal philosophy presented to employees and stakeholders alike as well as the implicit rules for getting along in the organization (“the way we do things around here”). Also included in that level is the climate or the feeling conveyed by the group in physical layouts and the way members interact with each other, stakeholders, and outsiders. Less-visible manifestations include habits of thinking; shared mental models that guide perceptions, thought, and language used by the group; and shared meanings and symbols that include ideas, feelings, and images that may not be appreciated consciously by members.
  </p>
 </h1>
 <h1 id="h307911">
  <title>
   Organizational culture and change
  </title>
  <p>
   An organization’s culture can be strong or weak, functional or dysfunctional. In an organization with a long history, stories and heroes may more strongly reflect its values. For instance, in organizations with strong cultures, such as the military and others with long traditions, the indoctrination of its members is standard and enduring; values are continuously reinforced in terms of rituals, symbols, and rules or expectations for patterns of behaviour. Those features of culture are internalized throughout a person’s membership in the organization and perhaps beyond. In such organizations, when its members are faced with uncertainty, they can often make decisions without direction and take action consistent with the mission. Conversely, strong cultures can inhibit organizational transformation where greater flexibility and adaptation are required to respond to changes in the external environment.
  </p>
  <p>
   Organizations need to be agile and able to adjust to the rapid and exceedingly high degrees of technological change in order to maintain their effectiveness. Organizational change may require cultural change. Therefore, recognition and understanding of the patterns of basic underlying assumptions that guide behaviour in an organization are essential.
  </p>
  <signature>
   Richard Huff
  </signature>
 </h1>
 <h1 id="h307912">
  <title>
   Bibliography
  </title>
  <p>
   <e type="smallcap">
    Geert Hofstede
   </e>
   ,
   <e type="italic">
    Cultures and Organizations: Software of the Mind
   </e>
   (1991);
   <e type="smallcap">
    Anne M. Khademian
   </e>
   ,
   <e type="italic">
    Working with Culture: How the Job Gets Done in Public Programs
   </e>
   (2002);
   <e type="smallcap">
    Joanne Martin
   </e>
   ,
   <e type="italic">
    Cultures in Organizations: Three Perspectives
   </e>
   (1992);
   <e type="smallcap">
    Edgar H. Schein
   </e>
   ,
   <e type="italic">
    Organizational Culture and Leadership
   </e>
   , 4th ed. (2010).
  </p>
  <signature>
   Richard Huff
  </signature>
 </h1>
 <copyright>
  Encyclopædia Britannica
 </copyright>
</article>