<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "syndication_xml.dtd">
<article articleid="60305" articletypeid="1" language="en_us" lastupdate="2021-Jul-01 00:31:45" url="/article/plankton/60305" version="15">
 <title>
  plankton
 </title>
 <p>
  <assembly id="a127446" url="/assembly/view/127446">
   <title>
    phytoplankton
   </title>
   <media mediaid="129565" type="image" url="/65/129565-004-C0EF77C5.jpg"/>
   <caption>
    Phytoplankton from the species
    <e type="italic">
     Pleurosigma angulatum
    </e>
    , which is found in parts of the North Atlantic Ocean and the Mediterranean Sea, as seen through a microscope.
   </caption>
   <credit>
    AbleStock.com/Thinkstock
   </credit>
  </assembly>
  <e type="bold">
   plankton
  </e>
  ,
  <assemblyref assemblyid="a127446"/>
  marine and freshwater organisms that, because they are nonmotile or too small or weak to swim against the current, exist in a drifting state. The term
  <e type="italic">
   plankton
  </e>
  is a collective name for all such organisms—including certain
  <xref articleid="106080">
   algae
  </xref>
  ,
  <xref articleid="110416">
   bacteria
  </xref>
  ,
  <xref articleid="110250">
   protozoans
  </xref>
  ,
  <xref articleid="110242">
   crustaceans
  </xref>
  ,
  <xref articleid="110323">
   mollusks
  </xref>
  , and
  <xref articleid="110240">
   coelenterates
  </xref>
  , as well as representatives from almost every other phylum of
  <xref articleid="110237">
   animals
  </xref>
  . Plankton is distinguished from nekton, which is composed of strong-swimming animals, and from benthos, which includes sessile, creeping, and burrowing organisms on the seafloor. Large floating
  <xref articleid="66498">
   seaweeds
  </xref>
  (for example,
  <e type="italic">
   Sargassum
  </e>
  , which constitutes the
  <xref articleid="65767">
   Sargasso Sea
  </xref>
  ) and various related multicellular algae are not considered plankton but pleuston. Pleuston are forms of life that live at the interface of air and water. Organisms resting or swimming on the surface film of the water are called neuston (e.g., the alga
  <e type="italic">
   Ochromonas
  </e>
  ).
 </p>
 <p>
  Plankton is the productive base of both marine and freshwater
  <xref articleid="31944">
   ecosystems
  </xref>
  , providing
  <xref articleid="34792">
   food
  </xref>
  for larger animals and indirectly for humans, whose
  <xref articleid="34399">
   fisheries
  </xref>
  depend upon plankton. As a human resource, plankton has only begun to be developed and exploited, in view of its high biological productivity and wide extent. It has been demonstrated on several occasions that large-scale cultures of algae are technically feasible. The unicellular
  <xref articleid="37947">
   green alga
  </xref>
  <e type="italic">
   Chlorella
  </e>
  has been used particularly in this connection. Through ample culture conditions, production is directed toward
  <xref articleid="110575">
   protein
  </xref>
  content greater than 50 percent. Although this protein has a suitable balance of essential
  <xref articleid="7182">
   amino acids
  </xref>
  , its low degree of digestibility prevents practical use. Phytoplankton may become increasingly important in
  <xref articleid="111026">
   space travel
  </xref>
  as a source for food and for
  <xref articleid="117582">
   gas exchange
  </xref>
  . The
  <xref articleid="20249">
   carbon dioxide
  </xref>
  released during respiration of spacecraft personnel would be transformed into organic substances by the algae, while the
  <xref articleid="57841">
   oxygen
  </xref>
  liberated during this process would support
  <xref articleid="117582">
   human respiration
  </xref>
  .
 </p>
 <h1 id="h283872">
  <title>
   Phytoplankton
  </title>
  <p>
   <assembly id="a160474" url="/assembly/view/160474">
    <title>
     Learn how phytoplankton supply oxygen via photosynthesis and serve as the first link in the marine food chain
    </title>
    <media mediaid="152183" thumburl="/83/152183-049-3B008ECE.jpg" type="video" url=""/>
    <caption>
     Learn about phytoplankton’s role as the oxygen-producing foundation of many marine food chains.
    </caption>
    <credit>
     Encyclopædia Britannica, Inc.
    </credit>
   </assembly>
   <assemblyref assemblyid="a160474"/>
   The plantlike community of plankton is called phytoplankton, and the animal-like community is known as zooplankton. This convenient division is not without fault, for, strictly speaking, many planktonic organisms are neither clearly plant nor animal but rather are better described as
   <xref articleid="110249">
    protists
   </xref>
   . When size is used as a criterion, plankton can be subdivided into macroplankton, microplankton, and nannoplankton, though no sharp lines can be drawn between these categories. Macroplankton can be collected with a coarse net, and morphological details of individual organisms are easily discernible. These forms, 1 mm (0.04 inch) or more in length, ordinarily do not include phytoplankton. Microplankton (also called net plankton) is composed of organisms between 0.05 and 1 mm (0.002 and 0.04 inch) in size and is a mixture of phytoplankton and zooplankton. The lower limit of its size range is fixed by the aperture of the finest cloth used for plankton nets. Nannoplankton (dwarf plankton) passes through all nets and consists of forms of a size less than 0.05 mm. Phytoplanktonic organisms dominate the nannoplankton.
  </p>
  <p>
   <assembly id="a18425" url="/assembly/view/18425">
    <title>
     Observe diatoms, microscopic sea organisms encased in silicified cell walls with intricate designs
    </title>
    <media mediaid="22235" thumburl="/35/22235-049-754998EA.jpg" type="video" url=""/>
    <caption>
     Learn about phytoplankton, which include diatoms such as
     <e type="italic">
      Navicula
     </e>
     and
     <e type="italic">
      Ditylum
     </e>
     .
    </caption>
    <credit>
     Encyclopædia Britannica, Inc.
    </credit>
   </assembly>
   <assemblyref assemblyid="a18425"/>
   The chief components of marine phytoplankton are found within the algal groups and include
   <xref articleid="30298">
    diatoms
   </xref>
   ,
   <xref articleid="30511">
    dinoflagellates
   </xref>
   and coccolithophorids. Silicoflagellates,
   <xref articleid="28081">
    cryptomonads
   </xref>
   , and green algae are found in most plankton samples. Freshwater phytoplankton, usually rich in green algae, also includes diatoms,
   <xref articleid="15751">
    blue-green algae
   </xref>
   , and true
   <xref articleid="34460">
    flagellates
   </xref>
   .
  </p>
  <p>
   In the oceans, phytoplankton
   <xref articleid="79265">
    biomass
   </xref>
   rises and falls according to multiyear cycles and appears to be sensitive to changes in sea surface temperatures, climate change, and ocean acidification. One controversial but influential study, which examined records kept between 1899 and 2010, discovered that phytoplankton biomass declined by 1 percent per year in all but two of Earth’s 10 ocean basins, attributing this reduction, which results in a cumulative loss of about 40 percent, to increases in sea surface temperatures occurring over the same period. Several other studies examining single species or specific regions of the oceans also report slow long-term declines in plankton.
  </p>
 </h1>
 <h1 id="h283873">
  <title>
   Zooplankton
  </title>
  <p>
   <assembly id="a68457" url="/assembly/view/68457">
    <title>
     Discover the copepod’s place in the marine food chain and how it develops from a larva into an adult
    </title>
    <media mediaid="73073" thumburl="/73/73073-049-A4CB4A30.jpg" type="video" url=""/>
    <caption>
     Copepods are tiny oceanic crustaceans with prodigious appetites.
    </caption>
    <credit>
     Encyclopædia Britannica, Inc.
    </credit>
   </assembly>
   <assemblyref assemblyid="a68457"/>
   The zooplankton is divided into two groups. Temporary plankton consists of planktonic
   <xref articleid="32069">
    eggs
   </xref>
   and
   <xref articleid="47227">
    larvae
   </xref>
   of members of the benthos and nekton; permanent plankton includes all animals that live their complete life cycles in a floating state. The temporary plankton, particularly abundant in coastal areas, is characteristically seasonal in occurrence, though variations in spawning time of different species ensure its presence in all seasons. Representatives from nearly every phylum of the animal kingdom are found in the permanent plankton. Among the protozoans, planktonic
   <xref articleid="34819">
    foraminiferans
   </xref>
   and
   <xref articleid="62422">
    radiolarians
   </xref>
   are so abundant and widespread that their skeletons constitute the bulk of bottom sediments over wide ocean areas. They are absent in fresh water. The
   <xref articleid="82641">
    ciliate
   </xref>
   protozoans are represented mainly by the tintinnids, which are between 20 and 640 microns (1 micron = 10
   <sup>
    −6
   </sup>
   metre; 0.0008 and 0.025 inch) in size and sometimes occur in vast numbers. Among the planktonic coelenterates are the beautiful siphonophores (e.g.,
   <e type="italic">
    Physalia
   </e>
   , the Portuguese man-of-war) and the
   <xref articleid="43510">
    jellyfishes
   </xref>
   . Planktonic
   <xref articleid="28096">
    ctenophores
   </xref>
   , called comb jellies, or sea walnuts, are also common. Freshwater
   <xref articleid="64196">
    rotifers
   </xref>
   may be present in plankton in vast numbers during the warmer seasons. A group of organisms that can be found at all latitudes, both in surface water and at great depths, are the marine
   <xref articleid="9630">
    arrowworms
   </xref>
   (e.g.,
   <e type="italic">
    Sagitta
   </e>
   ), important planktonic predators.
   <xref articleid="57857">
    Oysters
   </xref>
   ,
   <xref articleid="54463">
    mussels
   </xref>
   , other marine
   <xref articleid="110325">
    bivalves
   </xref>
   , and
   <xref articleid="68350">
    snails
   </xref>
   begin life as planktonic larvae. The wing snails (Pteropoda) spend their entire life cycles as plankton.
  </p>
  <p>
   <assembly id="a18491" url="/assembly/view/18491">
    <title>
     Observe permanent plankton, including transparent larvaceans, ciliate protozoans, and other zooplankton
    </title>
    <media mediaid="22422" thumburl="/22/22422-049-062B8743.jpg" type="video" url=""/>
    <caption>
     Learn about zooplankton, such as copepods, rotifers, tintinnids, and larvaceans, that are examples of permanent plankton (holoplankton).
    </caption>
    <credit>
     Encyclopædia Britannica, Inc.
    </credit>
   </assembly>
   <assemblyref assemblyid="a18491"/>
   Crustaceans are the most important members of the zooplankton. They are the marine counterparts of insects on land; on land as in the sea, the
   <xref articleid="117436">
    arthropods
   </xref>
   are the most diverse and numerous of all animal phyla. The
   <xref articleid="26185">
    copepod
   </xref>
   <e type="italic">
    Calanus finmarchicus
   </e>
   is important as food for the
   <xref articleid="40227">
    herring
   </xref>
   , and the
   <xref articleid="46247">
    krill
   </xref>
   <e type="italic">
    Euphausia superba
   </e>
   , also known as a euphausiid, is the main food source for
   <xref articleid="15765">
    blue
   </xref>
   and
   <xref articleid="34275">
    fin
   </xref>
   <xref articleid="76726">
    whales
   </xref>
   in the Antarctic Ocean. These whales migrate to waters where the krill spawns, and the rapid growth of these large mammals, feeding entirely on plankton, is impressive.
  </p>
  <p>
   There is a pronounced tendency for zooplankton to perform daily (or diurnal) vertical
   <xref articleid="110424">
    migrations
   </xref>
   in both lakes and the sea. This migratory behaviour varies with stages in the
   <xref articleid="48202">
    life cycle
   </xref>
   ,
   <xref articleid="66491">
    seasons
   </xref>
   of the year,
   <xref articleid="47303">
    latitude
   </xref>
   , hydrographic structure, and meteorological conditions. Generally, the animals ascend toward the surface at sunset from daytime depths. At midnight, if there is no optical stimulus (e.g., the
   <xref articleid="110148">
    Moon
   </xref>
   or artificial light), some animals return to the daytime depths and then approach the surface once again just before dawn. As the sun rises, all descend to their daytime level.
  </p>
 </h1>
 <h1 id="h283874">
  <title>
   Bacteria and fungi
  </title>
  <p>
   Bacteria and
   <xref articleid="110641">
    fungi
   </xref>
   found in water belong by definition to plankton, but, because of special techniques required for sampling and identification, they usually are considered separately. These organisms are important in the transformation of dead organic materials to inorganic plant
   <xref articleid="56550">
    nutrients
   </xref>
   . Some of these marine and freshwater microorganisms (including blue-green algae) fix molecular
   <xref articleid="55947">
    nitrogen
   </xref>
   from water containing dissolved air, forming
   <xref articleid="7200">
    ammonia
   </xref>
   or related nutrients important for phytoplankton growth. Although bacteria and fungi always are found in water samples, a peculiar situation exists in the
   <xref articleid="109729">
    Black Sea
   </xref>
   , where water below 130–180 metres (425–590 feet) contains
   <xref articleid="41733">
    hydrogen sulfide
   </xref>
   and no
   <xref articleid="57841">
    oxygen
   </xref>
   . Under these conditions only bacteria are found.
  </p>
 </h1>
 <h1 id="h283875">
  <title>
   Plankton and biological productivity
  </title>
  <p>
   The productivity of an area depends on currents and the availability of nutrients. Currents that flow near continents are important to plankton production in an area. The
   <xref articleid="18671">
    California Current
   </xref>
   (a continuation of the
   <xref articleid="46486">
    Kuroshio
   </xref>
   from Japan) causes an outland transport of water and combines with a compensating nutrient-rich current along the California coast to make this area highly productive. The same situation exists along the west coast of southern Africa, which is influenced by the
   <xref articleid="78608">
    Benguela Current
   </xref>
   , and off the west coast of South America, influenced by the
   <xref articleid="59375">
    Peru Current
   </xref>
   .
  </p>
  <p>
   In the sea an adequate supply of nutrients, including
   <xref articleid="20249">
    carbon dioxide
   </xref>
   , enables phytoplankton and benthic algae to transform the light energy of the
   <xref articleid="110144">
    Sun
   </xref>
   into energy-rich chemical components through
   <xref articleid="108553">
    photosynthesis
   </xref>
   . The bottom-dwelling algae are responsible for about 2 percent of the primary production in the ocean, and the remaining 98 percent is attributable to phytoplankton. Most phytoplankton serves as food for zooplankton, but some is carried below the light zone. After death, this phytoplankton undergoes chemical mineralization, bacterial breakdown, or transformation into sediments. Phytoplankton production usually is greatest from 5 to 10 metres (16 to 33 feet) below the surface of the water. High light intensity and the lack of nutrient in the regions above a depth of 5 metres may be the causes for suboptimal photosynthesis. Although bacteria are found at all depths, they are most abundant either immediately below great phytoplankton populations or just above the bottom.
  </p>
  <signature>
   EB Editors
  </signature>
 </h1>
 <copyright>
  Encyclopædia Britannica
 </copyright>
</article>