<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "syndication_xml.dtd">
<article articleid="611144" articletypeid="1" language="en_us" lastupdate="2021-Jul-01 07:05:46" url="/article/Sting/611144" version="9">
 <title>
  Sting
 </title>
 <p>
  <assembly id="a173336" url="/assembly/view/173336">
   <title>
    Sting
   </title>
   <media mediaid="162313" type="image" url="/13/162313-004-916A3A0A.jpg"/>
   <caption>
    Sting performing with the Police during the band’s 2008 reunion tour.
   </caption>
   <credit>
    © Randy Miramontez/Shutterstock.com
   </credit>
  </assembly>
  <e type="bold">
   Sting
  </e>
  , byname of
  <e type="bold">
   Gordon Sumner
  </e>
  , original name in full
  <e type="bold">
   Gordon Matthew Thomas Sumner
  </e>
  ,
  <assemblyref assemblyid="a173336"/>
  (born October 2, 1951, Wallsend, Northumberland, England), British singer and songwriter known both for being the front man of the band
  <xref articleid="98882">
   the Police
  </xref>
  and for his successful solo career that followed. His musical style was distinguished by its intermingling of
  <xref articleid="473093">
   pop
  </xref>
  ,
  <xref articleid="110142">
   jazz
  </xref>
  ,
  <xref articleid="105735">
   world music
  </xref>
  , and other genres.
 </p>
 <h1 id="h340409">
  <title>
   Early life and the Police
  </title>
  <p>
   Gordon Sumner grew up in a
   <xref articleid="21823">
    Roman Catholic
   </xref>
   family and attended Catholic grammar and secondary schools. He was a music enthusiast from an early age, having a special fondness for
   <xref articleid="13958">
    the Beatles
   </xref>
   as well as for jazz musicians
   <xref articleid="53369">
    Thelonious Monk
   </xref>
   and
   <xref articleid="24865">
    John Coltrane
   </xref>
   . In 1971, after a brief stint at the University of Warwick in
   <xref articleid="26653">
    Coventry
   </xref>
   and a series of odd jobs, Sumner enrolled at Northern Counties Teachers Training College (now Northumbria University) intending to become a teacher. While in school he performed in local clubs, mostly with jazz bands such as Phoenix Jazzmen and Last Exit. He received the nickname “Sting” from one of his Phoenix Jazzmen bandmates because of the black-and-yellow striped sweater he often wore while performing. After graduating in 1974, Sting taught at St. Paul’s First School in
   <xref articleid="66493">
    Cramlington
   </xref>
   for two years.
  </p>
  <p>
   In 1977 he moved to
   <xref articleid="108472">
    London
   </xref>
   and teamed up with musicians Stewart Copeland and Henri Padovani (who was soon replaced with Andy Summers). With Sting on
   <xref articleid="31019">
    bass
   </xref>
   , Summers on
   <xref articleid="38459">
    guitar
   </xref>
   , and Copeland on
   <xref articleid="31250">
    drums
   </xref>
   , the trio formed a
   <xref articleid="98396">
    new-wave
   </xref>
   band they called the Police. They became enormously successful but disbanded in 1984, at their peak. In 1983 the Police had won two
   <xref articleid="342977">
    Grammy Awards
   </xref>
   (best pop performance and best rock performance by a group with vocal), and Sting won song of the year for “Every Breath You Take” as well as best rock instrumental performance for the soundtrack of the film
   <e type="italic">
    Brimstone &amp; Treacle
   </e>
   (1982), in which he also had an acting role.
  </p>
 </h1>
 <h1 id="h340410">
  <title>
   Solo career
  </title>
  <p>
   For his first solo album,
   <e type="italic">
    The Dream of the Blue Turtles
   </e>
   (1985), Sting switched from bass to guitar. The album was a big success and had the standout singles “If You Love Somebody Set Them Free” and “Fortress Around Your Heart.” The album included collaborations with jazz musician
   <xref articleid="345398">
    Branford Marsalis
   </xref>
   and continued to show the musical versatility that Sting had introduced with the Police. Sting’s next album,
   <e type="italic">
    …Nothing like the Sun
   </e>
   (1987), included collaborations with
   <xref articleid="95774">
    Eric Clapton
   </xref>
   and with former bandmate Summers and hits such as “Fragile,” “We’ll Be Together,” “Englishman in New York,” and “Be Still My Beating Heart.”
  </p>
  <p>
   Beginning in the late 1970s and throughout the 1980s, Sting acted in numerous films, including
   <e type="italic">
    Quadrophenia
   </e>
   (1979),
   <e type="italic">
    Dune
   </e>
   (1984), and
   <e type="italic">
    Julia and Julia
   </e>
   (1987). During the 1980s Sting also became recognized for his interest in social causes. He performed at
   <xref articleid="488745">
    Live Aid
   </xref>
   , a benefit concert for
   <xref articleid="33683">
    famine
   </xref>
   relief in
   <xref articleid="108373">
    Ethiopia
   </xref>
   , in 1985, and in 1986 and 1988 he performed at the Amnesty International concerts for
   <xref articleid="106289">
    human rights
   </xref>
   . In 1987 he and his future wife, Trudie Styler, cofounded the Rainforest Foundation, an organization to protect the rainforest and its indigenous peoples. He continued to be a vocal advocate for human rights and environmental causes throughout his career.
  </p>
  <p>
   Sting released four albums during the 1990s.
   <e type="italic">
    The Soul Cages
   </e>
   (1991), a darker album reflecting the recent loss of his father, did not fare as well his previous two solo albums. But 1993’s
   <e type="italic">
    Ten Summoner’s Tales
   </e>
   was a triple-platinum album (selling more than three million copies), and Sting won that year’s Grammy for best male pop vocal performance with “If I Ever Lose My Faith in You.” He released
   <e type="italic">
    Mercury Falling
   </e>
   in 1996 and had a big hit with
   <e type="italic">
    Brand New Day
   </e>
   in 1999, especially with the album’s title song and “Desert Rose,” which featured Algerian
   <xref articleid="476590">
    rai
   </xref>
   singer
   <xref articleid="400579">
    Cheb Mami
   </xref>
   . That album also went triple platinum and in 1999 won the Grammys for best pop album and for best male pop vocal performance for the single “Brand New Day.”
  </p>
 </h1>
 <h1 id="h340411">
  <title>
   Later work and assessment
  </title>
  <p>
   In the 21st century Sting continued to record prolifically and tour regularly. In 2003 he not only won a Grammy for his duet with
   <xref articleid="438804">
    Mary J. Blige
   </xref>
   , “Whenever I Say Your Name,” from the album
   <e type="italic">
    Sacred Love
   </e>
   (2003), but he also published an autobiography,
   <e type="italic">
    Broken Music
   </e>
   . Sting branched out into
   <xref articleid="108746">
    classical music
   </xref>
   in 2006 with
   <e type="italic">
    Songs from the Labyrinth
   </e>
   , his adaptation of a collection of songs by Elizabethan songwriter
   <xref articleid="31088">
    John Dowland
   </xref>
   . The following year and into 2008, Sting reunited with Summers and Copeland for the highly successful Police Reunion Tour. Later he released
   <e type="italic">
    If on a Winter’s Night…
   </e>
   (2009), an album of traditional folk songs, and an ambitious album of orchestral arrangements of his old songs,
   <e type="italic">
    Symphonicities
   </e>
   (2010). For the latter he toured with London’s
   <xref articleid="99243">
    Royal Philharmonic Orchestra
   </xref>
   .
  </p>
  <p>
   In the summer of 2014
   <e type="italic">
    The Last Ship
   </e>
   , a musical written by Sting and inspired by his childhood in the shipbuilding town of
   <xref articleid="75997">
    Wallsend
   </xref>
   , had its
   <xref articleid="56804">
    off-Broadway
   </xref>
   debut in Chicago and was praised by critics. It debuted on
   <xref articleid="16556">
    Broadway
   </xref>
   that fall, but, as it began to founder, Sting joined the cast in the lead role; the production closed in 2015. An album of the same name (released 2013) was the first recording of new music Sting had released in about a decade. He returned to his rock roots for
   <e type="italic">
    57th &amp; 9th
   </e>
   (2016), and two years later he collaborated with
   <xref articleid="63049">
    reggae
   </xref>
   star Shaggy for his first duets album,
   <e type="italic">
    44/876
   </e>
   (2018), which won a Grammy for best reggae album. For
   <e type="italic">
    My Songs
   </e>
   (2019), Sting reinterpreted a number of his classics, including some originally recorded with the Police.
  </p>
  <p>
   Sting contributed music to numerous movie soundtracks, notably the animated
   <xref articleid="30636">
    Disney
   </xref>
   movie
   <e type="italic">
    The Emperor’s New Groove
   </e>
   (2000), as well as the romantic comedy
   <e type="italic">
    Kate &amp; Leopold
   </e>
   (2001) and the Civil War drama
   <e type="italic">
    Cold Mountain
   </e>
   (2003). He earned
   <xref articleid="117957">
    Academy Award
   </xref>
   nominations for the songs he contributed to each of them (2001, 2002, and 2004, respectively) and won a
   <xref articleid="601825">
    Golden Globe
   </xref>
   (2002) for the song “Until…” from
   <e type="italic">
    Kate &amp; Leopold
   </e>
   . In addition to more than 15 Grammys, Sting also won numerous Brit Awards (the British equivalent of the Grammys) for his work with the Police as well as for his solo work. In 2002 he was inducted into the Songwriters Hall of Fame, and in 2004 he was made a Commander of the Order of the British Empire (CBE). In 2014 Sting received a Kennedy Center Honor, awarded by the John F. Kennedy Center for the Performing Arts to individuals who have made significant contributions to American culture through the performing arts, and in 2017 he was awarded the Polar Music Prize for lifetime achievement by the Royal Swedish Academy of Music.
  </p>
  <signature>
   Naomi Blumberg
  </signature>
 </h1>
 <copyright>
  Encyclopædia Britannica
 </copyright>
</article>