<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "syndication_xml.dtd">
<article articleid="61231" articletypeid="1" language="en_us" lastupdate="2021-Jul-01 00:37:07" url="/article/precession/61231" version="3">
 <title>
  precession
 </title>
 <p>
  <e type="bold">
   precession
  </e>
  , phenomenon associated with the action of a gyroscope or a spinning top and consisting of a comparatively slow rotation of the axis of rotation of a spinning body about a line intersecting the spin axis. The smooth, slow circling of a spinning top is precession, the uneven wobbling is nutation.
 </p>
 <p>
  <assembly id="a7006" url="/assembly/view/7006">
   <media mediaid="3600" type="image" url="/00/3600-004-51C5EE93.jpg"/>
   <caption>
    Precession
   </caption>
   <credit>
    Encyclopædia Britannica, Inc.
   </credit>
  </assembly>
  In the
  <assemblyref assemblyid="a7006">
   Figure
  </assemblyref>
  the disk of weight
  <e type="italic">
   W
  </e>
  and the attached shaft are rotating at high speed about the spin axis
  <e type="italic">
   AB.
  </e>
  The angular speed
  <e type="italic">
   ω,
  </e>
  which is clockwise viewed from
  <e type="italic">
   A,
  </e>
  can be indicated either by the curved arrow
  <e type="italic">
   ω
  </e>
  in the plane of the disk or by the vector
  <e type="italic">
   ω
  </e>
  ′ perpendicular to the disk and pointing to the right. The curved arrow
  <e type="italic">
   ω
  </e>
  and the vector
  <e type="italic">
   ω
  </e>
  ′ are analogous, respectively, to the rotation and advance of a right-hand screw in a nut; this is known as the right-hand rule. It is usually more convenient to represent rotations and turning moments (which tend to produce rotations) by vectors rather than by curved arrows.
 </p>
 <p>
  The shaft and the stationary column
  <e type="italic">
   AC
  </e>
  are connected by a ball-and-socket joint at
  <e type="italic">
   A,
  </e>
  which permits the shaft to rotate about any line through
  <e type="italic">
   A
  </e>
  . In the arrangement shown in the Figure, the weight
  <e type="italic">
   W
  </e>
  creates a clockwise moment
  <e type="italic">
   WL
  </e>
  about
  <e type="italic">
   A,
  </e>
  which can be represented by a vector
  <e type="italic">
   M
  </e>
  of magnitude
  <e type="italic">
   WL,
  </e>
  acting at
  <e type="italic">
   A
  </e>
  and perpendicular to
  <e type="italic">
   AB
  </e>
  . Because of the moment, the shaft will precess (rotate slowly) about the axis of the column in a clockwise direction, viewed from
  <e type="italic">
   C
  </e>
  <e type="italic">
   ;
  </e>
  the angular velocity of precession is indicated by the vector Ω. It should be noted that
  <e type="italic">
   ω
  </e>
  ′
  <e type="italic">
   ,
  </e>
  <e type="italic">
   M,
  </e>
  and Ω
  <e type="italic"/>
  are at right angles to one another and that the spin vector
  <e type="italic">
   ω
  </e>
  ′ always rotates toward the moment vector
  <e type="italic">
   M
  </e>
  . It can be shown that Ω, the angular velocity of precession, does not depend on the angle
  <e type="italic">
   α
  </e>
  <e type="italic">
   ,
  </e>
  which, in the case of a spinning top, is close to 180 degrees.
 </p>
 <p>
  The precession of tops is frequently accompanied by a phenomenon known as nutation, which is evidenced by a wavelike motion of the end of the spin axis caused by variations in the angle
  <e type="italic">
   α
  </e>
  .
 </p>
 <copyright>
  Encyclopædia Britannica
 </copyright>
</article>