<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "syndication_xml.dtd">
<article articleid="61303" articletypeid="1" language="en_us" lastupdate="2021-Jul-01 00:37:30" url="/article/pressure/61303" version="8">
 <title>
  pressure
 </title>
 <p>
  <e type="bold">
   pressure
  </e>
  , in the
  <xref articleid="108653">
   physical sciences
  </xref>
  , the perpendicular
  <xref articleid="34834">
   force
  </xref>
  per unit area, or the
  <xref articleid="69963">
   stress
  </xref>
  at a point within a confined
  <xref articleid="34667">
   fluid
  </xref>
  . The pressure exerted on a floor by a 42-pound box the bottom of which has an area of 84 square inches is equal to the force divided by the area over which it is exerted; i.e., it is one-half pound per square inch. The weight of the
  <xref articleid="126202">
   atmosphere
  </xref>
  pushing down on each unit area of
  <xref articleid="110147">
   Earth
  </xref>
  ’s surface constitutes
  <xref articleid="10121">
   atmospheric pressure
  </xref>
  , which at
  <xref articleid="66445">
   sea level
  </xref>
  is about 15 pounds per square inch. In SI units, pressure is measured in
  <xref articleid="443512">
   pascals
  </xref>
  ; one pascal equals one
  <xref articleid="55617">
   newton
  </xref>
  per square metre. Atmospheric pressure is close to 100,000 pascals.
 </p>
 <p>
  <assembly id="a161944" url="/assembly/view/161944">
   <title>
    ideal gas law
   </title>
   <media mediaid="62948" type="image" url="/48/62948-004-1A78B872.jpg"/>
   <caption>
    According to the ideal gas law, when a gas is compressed into a smaller volume, the number and velocity of molecular collisions increase, raising the gas’s temperature and pressure.
   </caption>
   <credit>
    Encyclopædia Britannica, Inc.
   </credit>
  </assembly>
  <assemblyref assemblyid="a161944"/>
  The pressure exerted by a confined
  <xref articleid="110302">
   gas
  </xref>
  results from the average effect of the forces produced on the container walls by the rapid and continual bombardment of the huge number of gas
  <xref articleid="53247">
   molecules
  </xref>
  . Absolute pressure of a gas or
  <xref articleid="110301">
   liquid
  </xref>
  is the total pressure it exerts, including the effect of atmospheric pressure. An absolute pressure of zero corresponds to empty space or a complete
  <xref articleid="473544">
   vacuum
  </xref>
  .
 </p>
 <p>
  Measurement of pressures by ordinary gauges on Earth, such as a
  <xref articleid="72600">
   tire
  </xref>
  -pressure gauge, expresses pressure in excess of atmospheric. Thus, a tire gauge may indicate a pressure of 30 pounds (per square inch), the gauge pressure. The absolute pressure exerted by the
  <xref articleid="5193">
   air
  </xref>
  within the tire, including atmospheric pressure, is 45 pounds per square inch. Pressures less than atmospheric are negative gauge pressures that correspond to partial vacuums.
 </p>
 <p>
  <assembly id="a66778" url="/assembly/view/66778">
   <title>
    diffusion of water across a semipermeable membrane
   </title>
   <media mediaid="54956" type="image" url="/56/54956-004-3E46A16E.jpg"/>
   <caption>
    (A) Water diffuses down its concentration gradient from side 1 to side 2 of a rigid container to dilute the impermeant substance. (B) The net flux of the water increases the hydrostatic pressure on side 2, tending to force the water back to side 1.
   </caption>
   <credit>
    Encyclopædia Britannica, Inc.
   </credit>
  </assembly>
  <assemblyref assemblyid="a66778"/>
  Hydrostatic pressure is the stress, or pressure, exerted equally in all directions at points within a confined fluid (liquid or gas). It is the only stress possible in a fluid at rest.
  <e type="italic">
   See
  </e>
  <xref articleid="58620">
   Pascal’s principle
  </xref>
  .
 </p>
 <p>
  Lithostatic pressure, the stress exerted on a body of
  <xref articleid="109695">
   rock
  </xref>
  by surrounding rock, is a pressure in Earth’s crust somewhat analogous to hydrostatic pressure in fluids. Lithostatic pressure increases with depth below Earth’s surface.
 </p>
 <copyright>
  Encyclopædia Britannica
 </copyright>
</article>