<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "syndication_xml.dtd">
<article articleid="62494" articletypeid="1" language="en_us" lastupdate="2021-Aug-06 11:56:48" url="/article/rainbow/62494" version="9">
 <title>
  rainbow
 </title>
 <p>
  <e type="bold">
   rainbow
  </e>
  , series of concentric coloured arcs that may be seen when light from a distant source—most commonly the Sun—falls upon a collection of water drops—as in rain, spray, or fog. The rainbow is observed in the direction opposite to the Sun.
 </p>
 <p>
  The coloured rays of the rainbow are caused by the refraction and internal reflection of light rays that enter the raindrop, each colour being bent through a slightly different angle. Hence, the composite colours of the incident light will be separated upon emerging from the drop. The most brilliant and most common rainbow is the so-called primary bow, which results from light that emerges from the drop after one internal reflection.
 </p>
 <p>
  Although light rays may exit the drop in more than one direction, a high density of the rays emerge at a minimum angle of deviation from the direction of the incoming rays. The observer thus sees the highest intensity looking at the rays that have minimum deviation, which form a cone with the vertex in the observer’s eye and with the axis passing through the Sun. Light emerging from raindrops after one internal reflection has a minimum deviation of about 138° and thus the greatest intensity in the directions forming a cone with an angular radius of about 42°, with arcs (from inside to outside) of violet, indigo, blue, green, yellow, orange, and red.
 </p>
 <p>
  Occasionally, a secondary bow may be observed, which is considerably less intense than the primary bow and has its colour sequence reversed. The secondary rainbow has an angular radius of about 50° and hence is seen outside of the primary bow. This bow results from light that has undergone two internal reflections within the water drop. Higher-order rainbows, resulting from three or more internal reflections, are exceedingly weak and hence are rarely observed.
 </p>
 <p>
  Occasionally, faintly coloured rings are seen just inside of the primary bow. These are called supernumerary rainbows; they owe their origin to interference effects on the light rays emerging from the water droplet after one internal reflection.
 </p>
 <signature>
  EB Editors
 </signature>
 <h1 id="h6051">
  <title>
   Bibliography
  </title>
  <p>
   Robert Greenler,
   <e type="italic">
    Rainbows, Halos, and Glories
   </e>
   (1980); Marcel Minnaert,
   <e type="italic">
    Light and Color in the Outdoors
   </e>
   (1993; originally published in Dutch, 1937).
  </p>
 </h1>
 <copyright>
  Encyclopædia Britannica
 </copyright>
</article>