<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "syndication_xml.dtd">
<article articleid="62860" articletypeid="1" language="en_us" lastupdate="2021-Jul-01 00:46:17" url="/article/Reading/62860" version="6">
 <title>
  Reading
 </title>
 <p>
  <assembly id="a118030" url="/assembly/view/118030">
   <title>
    Reading
   </title>
   <media mediaid="121795" type="image" url="/95/121795-004-86FB2E7D.jpg"/>
   <caption>
    Reading, Pa.
   </caption>
   <credit/>
  </assembly>
  <e type="bold">
   Reading
  </e>
  ,
  <assemblyref assemblyid="a118030"/>
  city, seat (1752) of
  <xref articleid="573">
   Berks county
  </xref>
  , southeastern
  <xref articleid="111240">
   Pennsylvania
  </xref>
  , U.S., on the
  <xref articleid="99455">
   Schuylkill River
  </xref>
  , 51 miles (82 km) northwest of
  <xref articleid="108538">
   Philadelphia
  </xref>
  . Laid out in 1748 by Nicholas Scull and William Parsons on land owned by Thomas and Richard Penn (sons of
  <xref articleid="59077">
   William Penn
  </xref>
  , Pennsylvania’s founder), it was built around Penn Common, a large open square, and named for the hometown of the Penn family in
  <xref articleid="78789">
   Berkshire
  </xref>
  , England. During the
  <xref articleid="74344">
   American Revolution
  </xref>
  , Reading served as a supply depot and manufacturer of cannon.
 </p>
 <p>
  Industrial growth began in the late 18th century with the development of the iron and steel industries in Berks county. After the production of upper
  <xref articleid="110727">
   Great Lakes
  </xref>
  ore overshadowed that of Pennsylvania ore, Reading shifted to the fabrication of iron and steel. The opening of the Schuylkill Canal to
  <xref articleid="108538">
   Philadelphia
  </xref>
  (1824) and the Union Canal to
  <xref articleid="47543">
   Lebanon
  </xref>
  and
  <xref articleid="98080">
   Middletown
  </xref>
  on the
  <xref articleid="70495">
   Susquehanna River
  </xref>
  (1828) and the completion of the
  <xref articleid="62862">
   Philadelphia and Reading Railroad
  </xref>
  (1884) greatly stimulated industrial growth. In the 1890s, safety-bicycle manufacturing mushroomed. Development of the textile and hosiery industry was started about 1900 by two German technicians, Ferdinand Thun and Henry Janssen, who installed the first braiding and knitting machine in the country. In 1974 Reading became the site of the world’s first multi-tenant manufacturers’ outlet (opened by women’s lingerie manufacturer Vanity Fair), and outlet stores and malls continue to play a prominent role in the local economy. In the early 21st century, local industries included electronic components, batteries, specialty steels, energy-storage technology, and medical devices.
 </p>
 <p>
  The Reading area is the seat of Albright College (1856), Alvernia University (1958), Kutztown University (originally Keystone State Normal School, 1866), and the Berks campus (1958) of Berks–Lehigh Valley College of
  <xref articleid="2067">
   Pennsylvania State University
  </xref>
  (Penn State Berks). Mount Penn (1,300 feet [396 metres]), with a red-and-gold pagoda (1908) and a stone observation tower (1939) at its summit, is the centre of a city park. Local historic landmarks include the
  <xref articleid="80670">
   Daniel Boone Homestead
  </xref>
  (where Boone was born in 1734), the Conrad Weiser Homestead (1729), and Hopewell Furnace National Historic Site near
  <xref articleid="61086">
   Pottstown
  </xref>
  . An annual folk festival at nearby Kutztown reflects the
  <xref articleid="59094">
   Pennsylvania Dutch
  </xref>
  (German) heritage of the area.
 </p>
 <p>
  Officially designated “Baseballtown” in 2002 by local authorities, the Greater Reading area has a long history with the
  <xref articleid="108487">
   American national pastime
  </xref>
  that dates from the formation of the Reading Athletic Club in 1858. Minor league professional baseball has been played on and off in Reading since the late 19th century, and the Reading Fightin Phils of the Eastern League have been an affiliate of the
  <xref articleid="471056">
   Philadelphia Phillies
  </xref>
  since 1967—currently the longest continuous association between a
  <xref articleid="607949">
   Major League Baseball
  </xref>
  team and a “farm club.” The city also has a minor league ice hockey team. Inc. borough, 1783; city, 1847. Pop. (2000) 81,207; Reading Metro Area, 373,638; (2010) 88,082; Reading Metro Area, 411,442.
 </p>
 <copyright>
  Encyclopædia Britannica
 </copyright>
</article>