<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "syndication_xml.dtd">
<article articleid="62932" articletypeid="1" language="en_us" lastupdate="2021-Jul-01 00:46:46" url="/article/Red-Cloud/62932" version="5">
 <title>
  Red Cloud
 </title>
 <p>
  <assembly id="a161521" url="/assembly/view/161521">
   <title>
    Red Cloud: Willa Cather house
   </title>
   <media mediaid="153051" type="image" url="/51/153051-004-3373AF4C.jpg"/>
   <caption>
    Willa Cather house, Red Cloud, Nebraska.
   </caption>
   <credit>
    Ammodramus
   </credit>
  </assembly>
  <e type="bold">
   Red Cloud
  </e>
  ,
  <assemblyref assemblyid="a161521"/>
  city, seat (1871) of Webster county, southern
  <xref articleid="111262">
   Nebraska
  </xref>
  , U.S. It lies near the Republican River, a few miles north of the Kansas state line, about 35 miles (55 km) south of Hastings. First settled by Capt. Silas Garber (state governor, 1875–79), it was laid out in 1872 and named for the warrior-chief of the Oglala Sioux Indians. The arrival of the Burlington and Missouri River Railroad in 1879 contributed to the growth of the community. Agriculture (cattle, hogs, corn [maize], wheat, sorghum) is important to the economy. The city is best known, however, as the home of Willa Cather (1873–1947), the novelist who was noted for her portrayals of frontier life on the Great Plains. She used Red Cloud as the setting for many of her novels; it made appearances as the towns of Hanover in
  <e type="italic">
   O Pioneers!
  </e>
  (1913), Black Hawk in
  <e type="italic">
   My Ántonia
  </e>
  (1918), and Sweet Water in
  <e type="italic">
   A Lost Lady
  </e>
  (1923). The Willa Cather State Historic Site contains her letters, notes, and family memorabilia. Her childhood home and other sites related to her works, such as the Pavelka Farmstead (home of Annie Pavelka, on whom the title character of
  <e type="italic">
   My Ántonia
  </e>
  was based), have been restored as the Willa Cather Thematic District, recognized as a national historic landmark. Inc. 1872. Pop. (2000) 1,131; (2010) 1,020.
 </p>
 <copyright>
  Encyclopædia Britannica
 </copyright>
</article>