<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "syndication_xml.dtd">
<article articleid="63023" articletypeid="1" language="en_us" lastupdate="2022-Jun-23 12:15:48" url="/article/Reformation/63023" version="11">
 <title>
  Reformation
 </title>
 <p>
  <assembly id="a166838" url="/assembly/view/166838">
   <title>
    Martin Luther
   </title>
   <media mediaid="158359" type="image" url="/59/158359-004-C9C07E3B.jpg"/>
   <caption>
    Lithograph of Martin Luther reading in church.
   </caption>
   <credit>
    Library of Congress, Washington, D.C.
   </credit>
  </assembly>
  <e type="bold">
   Reformation
  </e>
  , also called
  <e type="bold">
   Protestant Reformation
  </e>
  ,
  <assemblyref assemblyid="a166838"/>
  the religious revolution that took place in the Western church in the 16th century. Its greatest leaders undoubtedly were
  <xref articleid="108504">
   Martin Luther
  </xref>
  and
  <xref articleid="106115">
   John Calvin
  </xref>
  . Having far-reaching political, economic, and social effects, the Reformation became the basis for the founding of
  <xref articleid="109446">
   Protestantism
  </xref>
  , one of the three major branches of
  <xref articleid="105945">
   Christianity
  </xref>
  .
 </p>
 <p>
  The world of the late medieval
  <xref articleid="109699">
   Roman Catholic Church
  </xref>
  from which the 16th-century reformers emerged was a complex one. Over the centuries the church, particularly in the office of the
  <xref articleid="58312">
   papacy
  </xref>
  , had become deeply involved in the political life of western Europe. The resulting intrigues and political manipulations, combined with the church’s increasing power and wealth, contributed to the bankrupting of the church as a spiritual force. Abuses such as the sale of
  <xref articleid="42357">
   indulgences
  </xref>
  (or spiritual privileges) by the clergy and other charges of corruption undermined the church’s spiritual authority. These instances must be seen as exceptions, however, no matter how much they were played up by polemicists. For most people, the church continued to offer spiritual comfort. There is some evidence of anticlericalism, but the church at large enjoyed loyalty as it had before. One development is clear: the political authorities increasingly sought to curtail the public role of the church and thereby triggered tension.
 </p>
 <p>
  The Reformation of the 16th century was not unprecedented. Reformers within the medieval church such as
  <xref articleid="35127">
   St. Francis of Assisi
  </xref>
  , Valdes (founder of the
  <xref articleid="75921">
   Waldensians
  </xref>
  ),
  <xref articleid="41616">
   Jan Hus
  </xref>
  , and
  <xref articleid="77632">
   John Wycliffe
  </xref>
  addressed aspects in the life of the church in the centuries before 1517. In the 16th century
  <xref articleid="106053">
   Erasmus of Rotterdam
  </xref>
  , a great
  <xref articleid="106290">
   humanist
  </xref>
  scholar, was the chief proponent of liberal Catholic reform that attacked popular superstitions in the church and urged the imitation of
  <xref articleid="106456">
   Christ
  </xref>
  as the supreme moral teacher. These figures reveal an ongoing concern for renewal within the church in the years before
  <xref articleid="108504">
   Luther
  </xref>
  is said to have posted his
  <xref articleid="55877">
   Ninety-five Theses
  </xref>
  on the door of the Castle Church,
  <xref articleid="77297">
   Wittenberg
  </xref>
  ,
  <xref articleid="106260">
   Germany
  </xref>
  , on October 31, 1517, the eve of
  <xref articleid="5766">
   All Saints’ Day
  </xref>
  —the traditional date for the beginning of the Reformation. (
  <e type="italic">
   See
  </e>
  <xref articleid="117465">
   Researcher’s Note
  </xref>
  .)
 </p>
 <p>
  <assembly id="a70862" url="/assembly/view/70862">
   <title>
    indulgences
   </title>
   <media mediaid="59941" type="image" url="/41/59941-004-303FD6B1.jpg"/>
   <caption>
    The sale of indulgences in church; woodcut from the title page of Luther’s pamphlet
    <e type="italic">
     On Aplas von Rom
    </e>
    , published anonymously in Augsburg, 1525.
   </caption>
   <credit>
    Courtesy of the trustees of the British Museum; photograph, John R. Freeman &amp; Co. Ltd.
   </credit>
  </assembly>
  <assemblyref assemblyid="a70862"/>
  Martin Luther claimed that what distinguished him from previous reformers was that while they attacked
  <xref articleid="472132">
   corruption
  </xref>
  in the life of the church, he went to the theological root of the problem—the perversion of the church’s doctrine of redemption and
  <xref articleid="37576">
   grace
  </xref>
  . Luther, a pastor and professor at the University of Wittenberg, deplored the entanglement of God’s free gift of grace in a complex system of indulgences and good works. In his Ninety-five Theses, he attacked the indulgence system, insisting that the pope had no authority over
  <xref articleid="61946">
   purgatory
  </xref>
  and that the doctrine of the merits of the
  <xref articleid="109411">
   saints
  </xref>
  had no foundation in the gospel. Here lay the key to Luther’s concerns for the ethical and theological reform of the church:
  <xref articleid="79096">
   Scripture
  </xref>
  alone is authoritative (
  <e type="italic">
   sola scriptura
  </e>
  ) and
  <xref articleid="44209">
   justification
  </xref>
  is by faith (
  <e type="italic">
   sola fide
  </e>
  ), not by works. While he did not intend to break with the Catholic church, a confrontation with the papacy was not long in coming. In 1521 Luther was
  <xref articleid="33412">
   excommunicated
  </xref>
  ; what began as an internal reform movement had become a fracture in western Christendom.
 </p>
 <p>
  <assembly id="a15352" url="/assembly/view/15352">
   <title>
    Huldrych Zwingli
   </title>
   <media mediaid="19102" type="image" url="/02/19102-004-88D95612.jpg"/>
   <caption>
    Huldrych Zwingli, detail of an oil portrait by Hans Asper, 1531; in the Kunstmuseum Winterthur, Switzerland.
   </caption>
   <credit>
    Courtesy of the Kunstmuseum Winterthur, Switz.; photograph, Schweizerisches Institut für Kunstwissenschaft
   </credit>
  </assembly>
  <assemblyref assemblyid="a15352"/>
  The Reformation movement within Germany diversified almost immediately, and other reform impulses arose independently of Luther.
  <xref articleid="78519">
   Huldrych Zwingli
  </xref>
  built a Christian theocracy in
  <xref articleid="78500">
   Zürich
  </xref>
  in which church and state joined for the service of God. Zwingli agreed with Luther in the centrality of the doctrine of justification by faith, but he espoused a different understanding of the
  <xref articleid="33174">
   Holy Communion
  </xref>
  . Luther had rejected the Catholic church’s doctrine of
  <xref articleid="73224">
   transubstantiation
  </xref>
  , according to which the bread and wine in Holy Communion became the actual body and blood of Christ. According to Luther’s notion, the body of Christ was physically present in the elements because Christ is present everywhere, while Zwingli claimed that entailed a spiritual presence of Christ and a declaration of faith by the recipients.
 </p>
 <p>
  Another group of reformers, often though not altogether correctly referred to as “radical reformers,” insisted that
  <xref articleid="13230">
   baptism
  </xref>
  be performed not on infants but on adults who had professed their faith in Jesus. Called
  <xref articleid="7312">
   Anabaptists
  </xref>
  , they remained a marginal phenomenon in the 16th century but survived—despite fierce persecution—as
  <xref articleid="52033">
   Mennonites
  </xref>
  and
  <xref articleid="41649">
   Hutterites
  </xref>
  into the 21st century. Opponents of the ancient Trinitarian dogma made their appearance as well. Known as
  <xref articleid="68472">
   Socinians
  </xref>
  , after the name of their founder, they established flourishing congregations, especially in Poland.
 </p>
 <p>
  <assembly id="a267010" url="/assembly/view/267010">
   <title>
    Find out how Martin Luther launched the Protestant Reformation
   </title>
   <media mediaid="232344" thumburl="/44/232344-049-F60BB880.jpg" type="video" url="pmm0vcFt"/>
   <caption>
    Learn more about the Protestant Reformation.
   </caption>
   <credit>
    Encyclopaedia Britannica, Inc.
   </credit>
  </assembly>
  <assemblyref assemblyid="a267010"/>
  Another important form of
  <xref articleid="109445">
   Protestantism
  </xref>
  (as those protesting against their suppressions were designated by the Diet of Speyer in 1529) is
  <xref articleid="106116">
   Calvinism
  </xref>
  , named for John Calvin, a French lawyer who fled France after his conversion to the Protestant cause. In
  <xref articleid="13587">
   Basel
  </xref>
  , Switzerland, Calvin brought out the first edition of his
  <xref articleid="42501">
   <e type="italic">
    Institutes of the Christian Religion
   </e>
  </xref>
  in 1536, the first systematic, theological treatise of the new reform movement. Calvin agreed with Luther’s teaching on justification by faith. However, he found a more positive place for law within the Christian community than did Luther. In
  <xref articleid="109424">
   Geneva
  </xref>
  , Calvin was able to experiment with his ideal of a disciplined community of the elect. Calvin also stressed the doctrine of
  <xref articleid="61239">
   predestination
  </xref>
  and interpreted Holy Communion as a spiritual partaking of the body and blood of Christ. Calvin’s tradition merged eventually with Zwingli’s into the
  <xref articleid="63026">
   Reformed
  </xref>
  tradition, which was given theological expression by the (second)
  <xref articleid="39940">
   Helvetic Confession
  </xref>
  of 1561.
 </p>
 <p>
  The Reformation spread to other European countries over the course of the 16th century. By mid century,
  <xref articleid="109447">
   Lutheranism
  </xref>
  dominated northern Europe. Eastern Europe offered a seedbed for even more radical varieties of Protestantism, because kings were weak, nobles strong, and cities few, and because religious pluralism had long existed.
  <xref articleid="108580">
   Spain
  </xref>
  and
  <xref articleid="106448">
   Italy
  </xref>
  were to be the great centres of the Catholic
  <xref articleid="26564">
   Counter-Reformation
  </xref>
  , and Protestantism never gained a strong foothold there.
 </p>
 <p>
  <assembly id="a119984" url="/assembly/view/119984">
   <title>
    Hans Holbein the Younger: portrait of Henry VIII
   </title>
   <media mediaid="114976" type="image" url="/76/114976-004-7BEF5156.jpg"/>
   <caption>
    Henry VIII, painting by Hans Holbein the Younger, c. 1540.
   </caption>
   <credit>
    © duncan1890—iStock/Getty Images
   </credit>
  </assembly>
  <assemblyref assemblyid="a119984"/>
  In
  <xref articleid="110752">
   England
  </xref>
  the Reformation’s roots were both political and religious.
  <xref articleid="40026">
   Henry VIII
  </xref>
  , incensed by
  <xref articleid="24313">
   Pope Clement VII
  </xref>
  ’s refusal to grant him an
  <xref articleid="7701">
   annulment
  </xref>
  of his marriage, repudiated papal authority and in 1534 established the
  <xref articleid="109449">
   Anglican church
  </xref>
  with the king as the supreme head. In spite of its political implications, the reorganization of the church permitted the beginning of religious change in England, which included the preparation of a liturgy in English, the
  <xref articleid="24975">
   Book of Common Prayer
  </xref>
  . In
  <xref articleid="110753">
   Scotland
  </xref>
  ,
  <xref articleid="45813">
   John Knox
  </xref>
  , who spent time in Geneva and was greatly influenced by John Calvin, led the establishment of
  <xref articleid="61274">
   Presbyterianism
  </xref>
  , which made possible the eventual union of Scotland with England. For further treatment of the Reformation,
  <e type="italic">
   see
  </e>
  <xref articleid="109445">
   Protestantism, history of
  </xref>
  . For a discussion of the religious doctrine,
  <e type="italic">
   see
  </e>
  <xref articleid="109446">
   Protestantism
  </xref>
  .
 </p>
 <signature>
  EB Editors
 </signature>
 <copyright>
  Encyclopædia Britannica
 </copyright>
</article>