<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "syndication_xml.dtd">
<article articleid="63033" articletypeid="1" language="en_us" lastupdate="2021-Jul-01 00:47:21" url="/article/refraction/63033" version="8">
 <title>
  refraction
 </title>
 <p>
  <assembly id="a245590" url="/assembly/view/245590">
   <title>
    See the coin experiment and understand the concept of refraction of light
   </title>
   <media mediaid="214984" thumburl="/84/214984-049-4BC97831.jpg" type="video" url=""/>
   <caption>
    Overview of the concept of refraction of light.
   </caption>
   <credit>
    Encyclopædia Britannica, Inc.
   </credit>
  </assembly>
  <assembly id="a155316" url="/assembly/view/155316">
   <title>
    refraction of light through a prism
   </title>
   <media mediaid="149178" type="image" url="/78/149178-004-5C832426.jpg"/>
   <caption>
    White light entering a prism is bent, or refracted, and the light separates into its constituent wavelengths. Each wavelength of light has a different colour and bends at a different angle.The colours of white light always emerge through a prism in the same order—red, orange, yellow, green, blue, indigo, and violet.
   </caption>
   <credit>
    © Matthias Kulka—The Image Bank/Getty Images
   </credit>
  </assembly>
  <e type="bold">
   refraction
  </e>
  ,
  <assemblyref assemblyid="a245590"/>
  <assemblyref assemblyid="a155316"/>
  in
  <xref articleid="108654">
   physics
  </xref>
  , the change in direction of a
  <xref articleid="473598">
   wave
  </xref>
  passing from one medium to another caused by its change in speed. For example, waves travel faster in deep water than in shallow. If an ocean wave approaches a beach obliquely, the part of the wave farther from the beach will move faster than the part closer in, and so the wave will swing around until it moves in a direction perpendicular to the shoreline. The speed of
  <xref articleid="109557">
   sound
  </xref>
  waves is greater in warm air than in cold. At night, air is cooled at the surface of a lake, and any sound that travels upward is refracted down by the higher layers of air that still remain warm. Thus, sounds, such as voices and music, can be heard much farther across water at night than in the daytime.
 </p>
 <p>
  <assembly id="a159440" url="/assembly/view/159440">
   <title>
    Perceive refraction as a wave’s speed is changed by its passing between different media
   </title>
   <media mediaid="151064" thumburl="/64/151064-049-741E1F64.jpg" type="video" url=""/>
   <caption>
    Learn more about refraction.
   </caption>
   <credit>
    Encyclopædia Britannica, Inc.
   </credit>
  </assembly>
  <assembly id="a254840" url="/assembly/view/254840">
   <title>
    Learn what happens to a beam of light when it moves from a medium of high optical density to one of lower optical density
   </title>
   <media mediaid="212352" thumburl="/52/212352-049-4A48A902.jpg" type="video" url=""/>
   <caption>
    An explanation of optical density.
   </caption>
   <credit>
    Encyclopædia Britannica, Inc.
   </credit>
  </assembly>
  <assemblyref assemblyid="a159440"/>
  <assemblyref assemblyid="a254840"/>
  The
  <xref articleid="106022">
   electromagnetic waves
  </xref>
  constituting
  <xref articleid="110443">
   light
  </xref>
  are refracted when crossing the boundary from one transparent medium to another because of their change in speed. A straight stick appears bent when partly immersed in water and viewed at an angle to the surface other than 90°. A ray of light of one wavelength, or colour (different wavelengths appear as different colours to the human eye), in passing from air to glass is refracted, or bent, by an amount that depends on its speed in air and glass, the two speeds depending on the wavelength. A ray of sunlight is composed of many wavelengths that in combination appear to be colourless. Upon entering a glass
  <xref articleid="61433">
   prism
  </xref>
  , the different refractions of the various wavelengths spread them apart as in a rainbow.
 </p>
 <signature>
  EB Editors
 </signature>
 <copyright>
  Encyclopædia Britannica
 </copyright>
</article>