<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "syndication_xml.dtd">
<article articleid="630742" articletypeid="1" language="en_us" lastupdate="2021-Oct-14 06:51:24" url="/article/nerve/630742" version="2">
 <title>
  nerve
 </title>
 <p>
  <assembly id="a232723" url="/assembly/view/232723">
   <title>
    nerve
   </title>
   <media mediaid="191729" type="image" url="/29/191729-004-CE4B853B.jpg"/>
   <caption>
    Artist’s conception of a human nerve cell.
   </caption>
   <credit>
    © Sebastian Kaulitzki—Eraxion/Dreamstime.com
   </credit>
  </assembly>
  <e type="bold">
   nerve
  </e>
  ,
  <assemblyref assemblyid="a232723"/>
  in
  <xref articleid="7388">
   anatomy
  </xref>
  , a glistening white cordlike bundle of fibres, surrounded by a sheath, that connects the
  <xref articleid="110703">
   nervous system
  </xref>
  with other parts of the body. The nerves conduct impulses toward or away from the central nervous mechanism. In
  <xref articleid="41468">
   humans
  </xref>
  12 pairs, the
  <xref articleid="26759">
   cranial nerves
  </xref>
  , are attached to the
  <xref articleid="16178">
   brain
  </xref>
  , and, as a rule, 31 pairs, the
  <xref articleid="69139">
   spinal nerves
  </xref>
  , are attached to the
  <xref articleid="69137">
   spinal cord
  </xref>
  .
 </p>
 <p>
  <assembly id="a149108" url="/assembly/view/149108">
   <title>
    nervous system
   </title>
   <media mediaid="93595" type="image" url="/95/93595-004-2174A714.jpg"/>
   <caption>
    The human nervous system.
   </caption>
   <credit>
    Encyclopædia Britannica, Inc.
   </credit>
  </assembly>
  <assemblyref assemblyid="a149108"/>
  The fibres constituting the individual nerves are very numerous, and all, save those arising in the sympathetic
  <xref articleid="35998">
   ganglia
  </xref>
  , extend from the brain or spinal cord to the peripheral structures which they innervate. With respect to function, nerve fibres are divided into two categories, namely, sensory (afferent) and motor (efferent). The fibres of these categories and their subdivisions constitute the functional components of the nerves. The combinations of such components vary in the individual cranial nerves; in the spinal nerves they are more uniform.
 </p>
 <p>
  The afferent (sensory) fibres are divided into somatic and visceral groups. The somatic afferents conduct impulses received from outside the body or produced by movements of the muscles and joints, those from the muscles and joints also being known as proprioceptive fibres. The visceral afferents conduct messages from the organs serving the internal economy of the body; such impulses result in reflex control of these organs (e.g., the rate of the heartbeat and activities of the digestive system).
 </p>
 <p>
  <assembly id="a47504" url="/assembly/view/47504">
   <title>
    autonomic nervous system
   </title>
   <media mediaid="55028" type="image" url="/28/55028-004-642F26A4.jpg"/>
   <caption>
    Schematic representation of the autonomic nervous system, showing distribution of sympathetic and parasympathetic nerves to the head, trunk, and limbs.
   </caption>
   <credit>
    Encyclopædia Britannica, Inc.
   </credit>
  </assembly>
  <assemblyref assemblyid="a47504"/>
  The motor fibres are divided into somatic and visceral motor or efferent groups. Somatic efferent fibres innervate voluntary muscles that derive from the myotomes of the embryo. Visceral motor fibres are divided into special visceral efferents, which innervate striped muscles of branchial origin, and general visceral efferents, which innervate involuntary muscles and secreting glands. The general visceral efferent fibres constitute the
  <xref articleid="11379">
   autonomic system
  </xref>
  , of which there is a sympathetic division and a parasympathetic division, which differ from each other in anatomical arrangement and physiological characteristics. The term
  <e type="italic">
   sympathetic
  </e>
  also is frequently used to include both divisions as well as the ganglia and afferent fibres associated with them.
 </p>
 <p>
  The autonomic pathway involves a chain of two fibres, one arising in the brain or spinal cord and ending in a sympathetic ganglion (the preganglionic fibre), the second (the postganglionic fibre) arising in the ganglion and passing to the organ innervated.
 </p>
 <p>
  <assembly id="a46720" url="/assembly/view/46720">
   <title>
    cranial nerves
   </title>
   <media mediaid="54244" type="image" url="/44/54244-004-892C5169.jpg"/>
   <caption>
    The cranial nerves (I–XII) and their areas of innervation.
   </caption>
   <credit>
    Encyclopædia Britannica, Inc.
   </credit>
  </assembly>
  <assemblyref assemblyid="a46720"/>
  The cranial nerves are designated by name and also by number,
  <xref articleid="83815">
   Roman numerals
  </xref>
  being conventionally used as a rule. They emerge through openings (foramina) of the
  <xref articleid="68131">
   skull
  </xref>
  . Some of the cranial nerves are purely sensory, some entirely motor, and others mixed. The afferent fibres, save those of the olfactory and optic nerves, arise in the cranial sensory ganglia, situated in the course of sensory nerves near the brain. Central processes (in this context the word
  <e type="italic">
   process
  </e>
  means “a projecting part, an extension”) terminate in sensory nuclei of the brain. The motor fibres arise within the brain from motor nuclei. In some instances the central nuclei, sensory or motor, are distinct for each nerve; in others the functional components of the same category from several nerves may arise from a common nucleus. In addition to the 12 pairs of cranial nerves commonly described, a plexus known as the terminal nerve (cranial nerve 0) is sometimes also recognized in humans, though whether it is a vestigial structure or a functioning nerve is unclear.
 </p>
 <p>
  <assembly id="a100859" url="/assembly/view/100859">
   <title>
    structures of a spinal nerve
   </title>
   <media mediaid="99529" type="image" url="/29/99529-004-DE8E03B7.jpg"/>
   <caption>
    Structures of a typical spinal nerve.
   </caption>
   <credit>
    Encyclopædia Britannica, Inc.
   </credit>
  </assembly>
  <assemblyref assemblyid="a100859"/>
  The spinal nerves are named and numbered according to the region of the spinal cord to which they attach. There are 8 cervical (abbreviated C.), 12 thoracic (T.), 5 lumbar (L.), 5 sacral (S.), and usually 1 coccygeal (Co.). Each spinal nerve has two roots, a dorsal or posterior (meaning “toward the back”) one and a ventral or anterior (meaning “toward the front”) one. The dorsal root is sensory and the ventral root motor; the first cervical nerve may lack the dorsal root. Oval swellings, the spinal ganglia, characterize the dorsal roots. They are formed of nerve cells that give rise to the sensory nerve fibres. The fibres of the ventral roots derive from cells in the anterior gray column (ventral horn) of the cord.
 </p>
 <p>
  Central processes of the dorsal root fibres end in the posterior gray column (dorsal horn) of the cord or ascend to nuclei in the lower part of the brain. Immediately lateral to the spinal ganglia the two roots unite into a common nerve trunk, which includes both sensory and motor fibres; the branches of this trunk distribute both types of fibres.
 </p>
 <signature>
  EB Editors
 </signature>
 <copyright>
  Encyclopædia Britannica
 </copyright>
</article>