<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "syndication_xml.dtd">
<article articleid="63147" articletypeid="1" language="en_us" lastupdate="2021-Jul-01 00:48:00" url="/article/remanent-magnetism/63147" version="2">
 <title>
  remanent magnetism
 </title>
 <p>
  <e type="bold">
   remanent magnetism
  </e>
  , also called
  <e type="bold">
   Paleomagnetism
  </e>
  , or
  <e type="bold">
   Palaeomagnetism
  </e>
  , the permanent magnetism in rocks, resulting from the orientation of the Earth’s magnetic field at the time of rock formation in a past geological age. It is the source of information for the paleomagnetic studies of polar wandering and continental drift. Remanent magnetism can derive from several natural processes, generally termed natural remanent magnetism, the most important being thermo-remanent magnetism. This arises when magnetic minerals forming in igneous rocks cool through the Curie point and when the magnetic domains within the individual minerals align themselves with the Earth’s magnetic field, thus making a permanent record of its orientation.
 </p>
 <p>
  A second mechanism operates when small grains of magnetic minerals settle into a sedimentary matrix, producing detrital remanent magnetism. It is hypothesized that the tiny grains orient themselves in the direction of the Earth’s magnetic field during deposition and before the final consolidation of the rock. The magnetism thus introduced appears to persist through later alteration and compaction of the rock, although the details of these processes have not been fully studied.
 </p>
 <p>
  Rocks may acquire remanent magnetism in at least two other ways: (1) rocks made up of nonmagnetic minerals may be chemically altered to yield magnetic minerals, and these newly formed minerals will acquire remanent magnetism in the presence of the Earth’s magnetic field; and (2) igneous rocks already cooled may ultimately acquire remanent magnetism by a process called viscous magnetization. The difference between these several types of remanent magnetism can be determined, and the magnetic history of a particular rock can therefore be interpreted.
 </p>
 <copyright>
  Encyclopædia Britannica
 </copyright>
</article>