<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "syndication_xml.dtd">
<article articleid="631831" articletypeid="1" language="en_us" lastupdate="2021-Jul-01 07:22:45" url="/article/Second-Great-Awakening/631831" version="2">
 <title>
  Second Great Awakening
 </title>
 <p>
  <e type="bold">
   Second Great Awakening
  </e>
  ,
  <xref articleid="109445">
   Protestant
  </xref>
  religious revival in the United States from about 1795 to 1835. During this revival, meetings were held in small towns and large cities throughout the country, and the unique frontier institution known as the
  <xref articleid="19832">
   camp meeting
  </xref>
  began. Many churches experienced a great increase in membership, particularly among
  <xref articleid="109453">
   Methodist
  </xref>
  and
  <xref articleid="109450">
   Baptist
  </xref>
  churches. The Second Great Awakening made soul-winning the primary function of ministry and stimulated several moral and philanthropic reforms, including
  <xref articleid="71631">
   temperance
  </xref>
  and the emancipation of women. Generally considered less emotional than the
  <xref articleid="37832">
   Great Awakening
  </xref>
  of the early 18th century, the second wave of evangelical
  <xref articleid="63361">
   revivalism
  </xref>
  led to the founding of numerous colleges and seminaries and to the organization of mission societies across the country.
 </p>
 <p>
  The Second Great Awakening can be divided into three phases. The first phase (1795–1810) was associated with frontier camp meetings conducted by American preachers James McGready, John McGee, and
  <xref articleid="69795">
   Barton W. Stone
  </xref>
  in
  <xref articleid="111247">
   Kentucky
  </xref>
  and
  <xref articleid="111252">
   Tennessee
  </xref>
  . The second and more conservative phase of the awakening (1810–25) centred in the
  <xref articleid="109451">
   Congregational churches
  </xref>
  of New England under the leadership of theologians
  <xref articleid="31653">
   Timothy Dwight
  </xref>
  ,
  <xref articleid="14095">
   Lyman Beecher
  </xref>
  , Nathaniel W. Taylor, and Asahel Nettleton. The third and final phase (1825–35) stemmed from the activities of evangelist
  <xref articleid="34304">
   Charles Grandison Finney
  </xref>
  , who began his revivalism in small towns in western
  <xref articleid="111232">
   New York
  </xref>
  in the 1820s but eventually conducted revival meetings in the largest cities in the United States and Britain.
 </p>
 <p>
  During the Second Great Awakening revivalistic theology in many denominations shifted from
  <xref articleid="106116">
   Calvinism
  </xref>
  to a practical
  <xref articleid="9528">
   Arminianism
  </xref>
  as preachers emphasized the ability of sinners to make an immediate decision for their
  <xref articleid="109405">
   salvation
  </xref>
  ; theological differences almost disappeared among evangelical churches. Moreover, under Finney’s aegis a rationale for carefully contrived revival techniques evolved. After 1835 an irregular corps of professional revival experts traveled through the towns and cities of America and Britain organizing annual revival meetings at the invitation of local pastors who wanted to reinvigorate their churches. Although many American Protestants lost interest in revivalism in the first half of the 20th century, tent revivals as well as annual revivals in churches in
  <xref articleid="68825">
   the South
  </xref>
  and
  <xref articleid="52548">
   Midwest
  </xref>
  continued to be an important feature of Protestant church life.
 </p>
 <signature>
  EB Editors
 </signature>
 <copyright>
  Encyclopædia Britannica
 </copyright>
</article>