<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "syndication_xml.dtd">
<article articleid="631808" articletypeid="1" language="en_us" lastupdate="2023-Mar-03 12:43:11" url="/article/white/631808" version="4">
 <title>
  white
 </title>
 <p>
  <assembly id="a269451" url="/assembly/view/269451">
   <title>
    RGB colour model
   </title>
   <media mediaid="234589" type="image" url="/89/234589-004-7C0824E1.jpg"/>
   <caption>
    Diagram of the RGB colour model, an example of the additive colour system, showing how colours mix.
   </caption>
   <credit>
    Encyclopædia Britannica, Inc.
   </credit>
  </assembly>
  <e type="bold">
   white
  </e>
  ,
  <assemblyref assemblyid="a269451"/>
  in
  <xref articleid="108654">
   physics
  </xref>
  ,
  <xref articleid="110443">
   light
  </xref>
  seen by the
  <xref articleid="109527">
   human eye
  </xref>
  when all wavelengths of the visible spectrum combine. Like
  <xref articleid="631807">
   black
  </xref>
  , but unlike the colours of the spectrum and most mixtures of them, white lacks hue, so it is considered an achromatic
  <xref articleid="109620" refid="h21839">
   colour
  </xref>
  .
 </p>
 <p>
  <assembly id="a276045" url="/assembly/view/276045">
   <title>
    Who created the colour wheel?
   </title>
   <media mediaid="237681" thumburl="/81/237681-049-42D58756.jpg" type="video" url="H3Bzh55Y"/>
   <caption>
    For millennia, many believed Aristotle’s theory that all colours were a mixture of black and white. How did we learn otherwise?
   </caption>
   <credit>
    Encyclopædia Britannica, Inc.
   </credit>
  </assembly>
  <assemblyref assemblyid="a276045"/>
  <e type="italic">
   White
  </e>
  and
  <xref articleid="631807">
   <e type="italic">
    black
   </e>
  </xref>
  are the most basic colour terms of languages. The word
  <e type="italic">
   white
  </e>
  derives from Proto-Germanic
  <e type="italic">
   hwitaz
  </e>
  and Old English
  <e type="italic">
   hwit
  </e>
  . One of the first written records of the term is from an Old English version of the phoenix legend, the so-called
  <e type="italic">
   Prose Phoenix
  </e>
  (11th century): “His fet syndon blodreade begen twegen and se bile hwit” (“His feet are both blood red and the beak white”).
 </p>
 <p>
  Pigments for white come from lead, lime, titanium dioxide, zinc oxide, and artificial chemical compounds. Lead white was used in cosmetics until the 20th century, when it was banned because of its toxicity, but it remains a favourite
  <xref articleid="58015">
   paint
  </xref>
  for many artists.
 </p>
 <p>
  <assembly id="a269450" url="/assembly/view/269450">
   <title>
    RYB colour model
   </title>
   <media mediaid="234588" type="image" url="/88/234588-004-E8A4A257.jpg"/>
   <caption>
    Diagram of the RYB colour model, one example of the subtractive colour system, showing how colours mix.
   </caption>
   <credit>
    Encyclopædia Britannica, Inc.
   </credit>
  </assembly>
  <assemblyref assemblyid="a269450"/>
  In addition to the gray scale, various colour systems have been used to classify white. Before the invention of colour photography,
  <e type="italic">
   Werner’s Nomenclature of Colour
  </e>
  (1814) was frequently used by scientists attempting to accurately describe colours observed in nature. In that book the so-called tint “Snow White” is compared to the “Breast of the black-headed Gull,” a “Snow-Drop,” and “Carara Marble.” In the
  <xref articleid="54295">
   Munsell colour system
  </xref>
  —adopted in the early 20th century to standardize colour, usually for industry— absolute white has a value of 10.
 </p>
 <signature>
  Kelly
 </signature>
 <copyright>
  Encyclopædia Britannica
 </copyright>
</article>