<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "syndication_xml.dtd">
<article articleid="631950" articletypeid="1" language="en_us" lastupdate="2021-Jul-01 07:23:21" url="/article/building/631950" version="4">
 <title>
  building
 </title>
 <p>
  <assembly id="a206656" url="/assembly/view/206656">
   <title>
    Shanghai: skyline
   </title>
   <media mediaid="187508" type="image" url="/08/187508-004-DFD40BD6.jpg"/>
   <caption>
    Skyline of Shanghai, China.
   </caption>
   <credit>
    © Charles Chen/Shutterstock.com
   </credit>
  </assembly>
  <assembly id="a160515" url="/assembly/view/160515">
   <media mediaid="132220" type="image" url="/20/132220-004-B26EF837.jpg"/>
   <caption>
    Ruins of a temple at Palenque, Mexico.
   </caption>
   <credit>
    © Ales Liska/Shutterstock.com
   </credit>
  </assembly>
  <assembly id="a161620" url="/assembly/view/161620">
   <title>
    longhouse
   </title>
   <media mediaid="136992" type="image" url="/92/136992-004-EF02FE6E.jpg"/>
   <caption>
    A Dayak longhouse in Sarawak, Malaysia.
   </caption>
   <credit>
    © charles taylor/Fotolia
   </credit>
  </assembly>
  <e type="bold">
   building
  </e>
  ,
  <assemblyref assemblyid="a206656"/>
  <assemblyref assemblyid="a160515"/>
  <assemblyref assemblyid="a161620"/>
  a usually roofed and walled structure built for permanent use. Rudimentary buildings were initially constructed out of the purely functional need for a controlled environment to moderate the effects of climate. These first buildings were simple dwellings. Later, buildings were constructed for other functions, such as food storage and to serve as sites of ceremony. Early building materials were perishable and often included leaves, branches, and animal hides; these structures did not provide much permanency. Subsequently, more durable natural materials—such as
  <xref articleid="109692">
   clay
  </xref>
  ,
  <xref articleid="69794">
   stone
  </xref>
  , and
  <xref articleid="110435">
   timber
  </xref>
  —and, finally, synthetic materials—such as brick,
  <xref articleid="25103">
   concrete
  </xref>
  ,
  <xref articleid="52266">
   metals
  </xref>
  , and
  <xref articleid="108561">
   plastics
  </xref>
  —were used, permitting buildings to persist for many decades and even centuries.
 </p>
 <p>
  <assembly id="a137332" url="/assembly/view/137332">
   <title>
    Burj Khalifa
   </title>
   <media mediaid="135437" type="image" url="/37/135437-004-B6AF640F.jpg"/>
   <caption>
    Burj Khalifa, Dubai, United Arab Emirates.
   </caption>
   <credit>
    © Abrar Sharif/Dreamstime.com
   </credit>
  </assembly>
  <assemblyref assemblyid="a137332"/>
  With increasing technology and an understanding of how materials behave, buildings have come to be constructed with ever greater height and span and for innumerable agricultural, civic, commercial, industrial, recreational, religious, and residential uses. In addition to providing simple protection from the elements, most modern buildings have a degree of control exercised over the interior environment, including increasingly precise regulation of air temperature, light and sound levels, humidity, odours, air speed, and other factors that affect human comfort. Some modern buildings are also constructed with
  <xref articleid="443098">
   green architecture
  </xref>
  to minimize their impact on the environment. Such buildings may utilize
  <xref articleid="68559">
   solar
  </xref>
  ,
  <xref articleid="443102">
   wind
  </xref>
  , or
  <xref articleid="36528">
   geothermal energy
  </xref>
  and often incorporate other environmentally friendly technologies. For information on the history of building construction and modern practices,
  <e type="italic">
   see
  </e>
  <xref articleid="106103">
   construction
  </xref>
  .
 </p>
 <signature>
  EB Editors
 </signature>
 <copyright>
  Encyclopædia Britannica
 </copyright>
</article>