<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "syndication_xml.dtd">
<article articleid="632563" articletypeid="1" language="en_us" lastupdate="2021-Jul-01 07:24:55" url="/article/sexual-reproduction/632563" version="1">
 <title>
  sexual reproduction
 </title>
 <p>
  <e type="bold">
   sexual reproduction
  </e>
  , the production of new organisms by the combination of genetic information of two individuals of different sexes. In most species the genetic information is carried on
  <xref articleid="82456">
   chromosomes
  </xref>
  in the nucleus of reproductive cells called
  <xref articleid="35969">
   gametes
  </xref>
  , which then fuse to form a diploid
  <xref articleid="475858">
   zygote
  </xref>
  . The zygote develops into a new individual. Sexual reproduction is the dominant form of reproduction in living beings.
 </p>
 <p>
  Sexual reproduction allows for the reshuffling of genetic material, both within and between individuals of one generation, resulting in the potential for an extraordinary array of offspring, each with a genetic makeup different from that of its parents. In the sexual reproduction of all organisms except
  <xref articleid="110416">
   bacteria
  </xref>
  , there is one common feature: haploid, uninucleate gametes are produced that join in
  <xref articleid="110806">
   fertilization
  </xref>
  to form a diploid, uninucleate zygote. At some later stage in the life history of the organism, the chromosome number is again reduced by
  <xref articleid="51837">
   meiosis
  </xref>
  to form the next generation of gametes. The gametes may be equal in size (isogamy), or one may be slightly larger than the other (anisogamy); the majority of forms have a large
  <xref articleid="32069">
   egg
  </xref>
  and a minute
  <xref articleid="69079">
   sperm
  </xref>
  (oogamy). The sperm are usually motile and the egg passive, except in higher plants, in which the sperm nuclei are carried in
  <xref articleid="60648">
   pollen
  </xref>
  grains that attach to the stigma (a female structure) of the
  <xref articleid="34656">
   flower
  </xref>
  and send out germ tubes that grow down to the egg nucleus in the ovary. Some organisms, such as most
  <xref articleid="111083">
   flowering plants
  </xref>
  ,
  <xref articleid="31737">
   earthworms
  </xref>
  , and
  <xref articleid="110431">
   tunicates
  </xref>
  , are bisexual (hermaphroditic, or monoecious)—i.e., both the male and female gametes are produced by the same individual. All other organisms, including some plants (e.g.,
  <xref articleid="40808">
   holly
  </xref>
  and the
  <xref articleid="36870">
   ginkgo
  </xref>
  tree) and all
  <xref articleid="110433">
   vertebrates
  </xref>
  , are unisexual (dioecious): the male and female gametes are produced by separate individuals.
 </p>
 <p>
  In animals, fertilization—that is, the uniting of the gametes—can be either internal or external. In external fertilization, the male releases sperm over eggs that have been released by a female. This form of fertilization is used by many
  <xref articleid="42669">
   invertebrates
  </xref>
  and by most
  <xref articleid="111049">
   fish
  </xref>
  and
  <xref articleid="110233">
   amphibians
  </xref>
  . In internal fertilization, the sperm unites with the egg within the body of an adult. In the vast majority of cases, fertilization takes place within the body of the female.
 </p>
 <p>
  Sexual
  <xref articleid="110807">
   reproduction in plants
  </xref>
  also requires the uniting of male and female gametes. There is a much greater variety of structures and strategies used by plants. In general, flowers and cones are the locus of fertilization in plants.
 </p>
 <signature>
  EB Editors
 </signature>
 <copyright>
  Encyclopædia Britannica
 </copyright>
</article>