<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "syndication_xml.dtd">
<article articleid="632607" articletypeid="1" language="en_us" lastupdate="2021-Jul-01 07:25:09" url="/article/density-dependent-factor/632607" version="2">
 <title>
  density-dependent factor
 </title>
 <p>
  <e type="bold">
   density-dependent factor
  </e>
  , also called
  <e type="bold">
   regulating factor
  </e>
  , in
  <xref articleid="110583">
   ecology
  </xref>
  , any force that affects the size of a
  <xref articleid="108576">
   population
  </xref>
  of living things in response to the
  <xref articleid="29953">
   density
  </xref>
  of the population (the number of individuals per unit area). Density-dependent factors often arise from biological phenomena, rather than from physical and chemical phenomena. Density-dependent factors are sometimes called regulating factors because of their potential for maintaining population density within a narrow range of values.
 </p>
 <p>
  For example, some
  <xref articleid="110618">
   diseases
  </xref>
  spread faster in populations where individuals live in close proximity with one another than in those whose individuals live farther apart. Similarly, competition for
  <xref articleid="34792">
   food
  </xref>
  and other resources rises with density and affects an increasing proportion of the population. However, as density decreases, such as through mortality or migration, the influence of density-dependent factors also decreases. For example, disease transmission may decline as individuals perish and surviving members of a population come into contact with one another less frequently. Likewise, competition for food and
  <xref articleid="76210">
   water
  </xref>
  ,
  <xref articleid="55336">
   nesting
  </xref>
  sites, areas with adequate levels of
  <xref articleid="70375">
   sunlight
  </xref>
  , and other critical resources falls as individuals spread out.
 </p>
 <p>
  The dynamics of most populations of living things are influenced by a combination of density-dependent factors and
  <xref articleid="632550">
   density-independent factors
  </xref>
  (that is, those that affect the population regardless of how concentrated its members are), and the relative effects of the factors vary among populations.
 </p>
 <signature>
  EB Editors
 </signature>
 <copyright>
  Encyclopædia Britannica
 </copyright>
</article>