<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "syndication_xml.dtd">
<article articleid="633059" articletypeid="1" language="en_us" lastupdate="2021-Jul-01 07:25:30" url="/article/Biden-Jill/633059" version="4">
 <title>
  Jill Biden
 </title>
 <p>
  <assembly id="a250797" url="/assembly/view/250797">
   <title>
    Jill Biden
   </title>
   <media mediaid="130982" type="image" url="/82/130982-004-AFBDC5ED.jpg"/>
   <caption>
    Jill Biden.
   </caption>
   <credit>
    Ralph Alswang courtesy of The White House
   </credit>
  </assembly>
  <e type="bold">
   Jill Biden
  </e>
  , née
  <e type="bold">
   Jill Tracy Jacobs
  </e>
  ,
  <assemblyref assemblyid="a250797"/>
  (born June 3, 1951, Hammonton, New Jersey, U.S.), American
  <xref articleid="126348">
   first lady
  </xref>
  (2021– ), wife of
  <xref articleid="439068">
   Joe Biden
  </xref>
  , the 46th
  <xref articleid="218450">
   president of the United States
  </xref>
  .
 </p>
 <p>
  Jill Jacobs was born in
  <xref articleid="111234">
   New Jersey
  </xref>
  but mostly grew up in Willow Grove, Pennsylvania, a suburb of
  <xref articleid="108538">
   Philadelphia
  </xref>
  , where her father was vice president of a
  <xref articleid="65936">
   savings and loan institution
  </xref>
  . She began working while in high school. Following her graduation in 1969, she briefly attended a
  <xref articleid="44168">
   community college
  </xref>
  to study fashion merchandising but soon changed her mind. She married Bill Stevenson in 1970, but the couple separated in 1974 and divorced the following year. During this time she attended the
  <xref articleid="1921">
   University of Delaware
  </xref>
  , earning a bachelor’s degree in 1975.
 </p>
 <p>
  That year Jill met Joe Biden on a blind date arranged by his brother. At that time Biden was a U.S. senator and a single father of two young boys, having lost his first wife and infant daughter in a car crash three years previously. The couple married on June 17, 1977, and had a child of their own in 1981. In the meantime, Jill worked as an English teacher at St. Mark’s High School in
  <xref articleid="77111">
   Wilmington
  </xref>
  , Delaware. She later taught emotionally troubled adolescents at a psychiatric hospital while studying at West Chester State College (now
  <xref articleid="2145">
   West Chester University of Pennsylvania
  </xref>
  ), from which she earned a master’s degree in education in 1981. She devoted the next two years to raising her children before returning to her teaching career.
 </p>
 <p>
  Jill continued teaching while supporting Joe in his first run for
  <xref articleid="477201">
   president in 1988
  </xref>
  . In 1991 she earned a second master’s degree, this one in English, from
  <xref articleid="2138">
   Villanova University
  </xref>
  in Pennsylvania. After working at various high schools, she became a professor at Delaware Technical Community College in 1993, where she remained until 2008. In addition, she continued her studies, earning a doctorate in education from the University of Delaware in 2007.
 </p>
 <p>
  <assembly id="a125069" url="/assembly/view/125069">
   <title>
    Joe and Jill Biden
   </title>
   <media mediaid="127911" type="image" url="/11/127911-004-3D564D58.jpg"/>
   <caption>
    Vice Pres. Joe Biden dancing with his wife, Jill, at the Commander in Chief’s Inaugural Ball in the National Building Museum, January 20, 2009, Washington, D.C.
   </caption>
   <credit>
    MC1 Chad J. McNeeley/U.S. Department of Defense
   </credit>
  </assembly>
  <assembly id="a125059" url="/assembly/view/125059">
   <title>
    Joe and Jill Biden with Barack and Michelle Obama
   </title>
   <media mediaid="127945" type="image" url="/45/127945-004-81464F47.jpg"/>
   <caption>
    Jill and Joe Biden (couple at left) and Barack and Michelle Obama waving to the crowd at the Lincoln Memorial, January 18, 2009, Washington, D.C.
   </caption>
   <credit>
    U.S. Navy Petty Officer 2nd Class George Trian/U.S. Department of Defense
   </credit>
  </assembly>
  <assemblyref assemblyid="a125069"/>
  <assemblyref assemblyid="a125059"/>
  Joe again ran for president in 2008 but ultimately dropped out. However, Obama later chose him as his running mate, and Jill campaigned for the ticket while continuing to teach. After Joe was sworn in as vice president in 2009, Jill became a professor of English at Northern Virginia Community College in
  <xref articleid="5630">
   Alexandria
  </xref>
  . She is believed to be the first vice president’s spouse to maintain a paying job throughout his tenure. In addition to teaching, she worked with the Obama administration in support of community colleges and their mission. She also helped support the families of members of the military, and she wrote a children’s book,
  <e type="italic">
   Don’t Forget, God Bless Our Troops
  </e>
  (2012), about the experiences of a child whose father was deployed. The book was inspired by the deployment of Joe’s son, Beau Biden, who later died from cancer (2015). Jill’s autobiography,
  <e type="italic">
   Where the Light Enters: Building a Family, Discovering Myself
  </e>
  , appeared in 2019.
 </p>
 <p>
  In 2020 Joe announced his third presidential bid, and, for the first time, Jill took a leave of absence in order to assume a prominent role in the campaign. In April Joe became the presumptive Democratic nominee. At the party’s national convention, which was a virtual event because of the COVID-19 pandemic, Jill gave a speech in which she extolled her husband’s character and his ability to help heal a country that was struggling with both the virus and extreme political polarization. After a difficult and contentious campaign, Joe was elected president, defeating Pres.
  <xref articleid="73552">
   Donald Trump
  </xref>
  , on November 3. Trump and other Republicans, however, alleged voter fraud, and on January 6, 2021, Trump supporters attacked the
  <xref articleid="20154">
   Capitol
  </xref>
  as Congress was in the process of certifying the election results. Amid a massive security presence Joe was sworn in as president on January 20.
 </p>
 <signature>
  Patricia Bauer
 </signature>
 <signature>
  EB Editors
 </signature>
 <copyright>
  Encyclopædia Britannica
 </copyright>
</article>