<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "syndication_xml.dtd">
<article articleid="634749" articletypeid="1" language="en_us" lastupdate="2023-Jan-18 13:13:22" url="/article/memento-mori/634749" version="1">
 <title>
  memento mori
 </title>
 <p>
  <assembly id="a274826" url="/assembly/view/274826">
   <title>
    memento mori
   </title>
   <media mediaid="230486" type="image" url="/86/230486-004-A18F0679.jpg"/>
   <caption>
    The title page of the
    <e type="italic">
     Bills of Mortality
    </e>
    , taken between December 27, 1664, and December 19, 1665, during the Great Plague of London.
   </caption>
   <credit>
    Hulton Archive/Getty Images
   </credit>
  </assembly>
  <e type="bold">
   memento mori
  </e>
  ,
  <assemblyref assemblyid="a274826"/>
  in
  <xref articleid="389134">
   art
  </xref>
  and
  <xref articleid="609449">
   spirituality
  </xref>
  , a symbolic trope or meditative practice that serves as a reminder of
  <xref articleid="53838">
   mortality
  </xref>
  and the transitory nature of earthly pleasures.
  <e type="italic">
   Memento mori
  </e>
  is a Latin phrase meaning “remember you must die.” The notion of “remembering death” appears throughout
  <xref articleid="106072">
   European history
  </xref>
  , and other cultures have traditions that approach the same concept in unique ways.
 </p>
 <h1 id="h354064">
  <title>
   Historical expressions
  </title>
  <h2 id="h354065">
   <title>
    Religious and philosophical expressions
   </title>
   <p>
    The concept of “remembering death” is expressed throughout ancient Greek and Roman
    <xref articleid="59729">
     philosophy
    </xref>
    . In
    <xref articleid="108556">
     Plato
    </xref>
    ’s
    <e type="italic">
     Phaedo
    </e>
    ,
    <xref articleid="109554">
     Socrates
    </xref>
    states that the sole purpose of practicing philosophy “is to practice for dying and death.” Rather than being a morbid directive, the statement espouses mastering one’s fear of
    <xref articleid="109644">
     death
    </xref>
    by recognizing the body’s mortal reality and pursuing knowledge, which nurtures the immortal soul.
   </p>
   <p>
    The Stoics taught the virtue of keeping death at the forefront of one’s thoughts as a reminder that nothing is permanent. In his letters
    <xref articleid="66750">
     Seneca
    </xref>
    advocated living every day “as a complete life” and advised, “Let us compose our thoughts as if we’ve reached the end. Let us postpone nothing. Let’s settle our accounts with life every day.” In the
    <e type="italic">
     Encheiridion
    </e>
    ,
    <xref articleid="32783">
     Epictetus
    </xref>
    wrote, “If you are kissing your child or wife, say that it is a human being whom you are kissing, for when the wife or child dies, you will not be disturbed.” According to the Stoics, by meditating on death’s inevitability, one can live more fully in the present moment.
   </p>
   <p>
    In
    <xref articleid="105945">
     Christianity
    </xref>
    , the practice of memento mori appears often in
    <xref articleid="66394">
     scripture
    </xref>
    , art,
    <xref articleid="110410">
     architecture
    </xref>
    , and in various rites. The concepts of morality, divine judgment, and penitence, reflected in biblical passages such as, “In all you do, remember the end of your life, and then you will never sin” (Sirach 7:36). Among Catholics,
    <xref articleid="47772">
     Lent
    </xref>
    , a 40-day period of penitence and fasting that precedes the festival of
    <xref articleid="31806">
     Easter
    </xref>
    , begins with
    <xref articleid="9803">
     Ash Wednesday
    </xref>
    , in which a priest sprinkles ashes on the foreheads of congregants as a reminder of their mortality.
    <xref articleid="51765">
     Meditations
    </xref>
    on death have been a common form of writing by many Christian
    <xref articleid="109411">
     saints
    </xref>
    and theologians.
    <xref articleid="49181">
     St. Ignatius of Loyola
    </xref>
    ’s
    <e type="italic">
     The Spiritual Exercises
    </e>
    , for example, recommends meditating on death, one’s own and
    <xref articleid="106456">
     Jesus
    </xref>
    Christ’s, to help bring one closer to God.
   </p>
   <p>
    Memento mori was also used in Christianity as an artistic expression that was intended to inspire piety. In architecture, ossuaries, or “bone churches,” lined with human
    <xref articleid="110163">
     bones
    </xref>
    functioned both as memento mori and places for storage if a
    <xref articleid="22046">
     cemetery
    </xref>
    became too crowded. Famous examples include the 15th-century Sedlec Ossuary in the
    <xref articleid="109749">
     Czech Republic
    </xref>
    , which was redesigned in 1870, and the 16th-century Capela dos Ossos in
    <xref articleid="105994">
     Portugal
    </xref>
    , which also features a poem at its entrance that warns, “Our bones that are here await yours.” In funerary art, memento mori is depicted by a winged
    <xref articleid="68131">
     skull
    </xref>
    , a skull and crossbones, or a full
    <xref articleid="110161">
     skeleton
    </xref>
    carved on gravestones and
    <xref articleid="72826">
     tombs
    </xref>
    . In
    <xref articleid="108604">
     painting
    </xref>
    ,
    <xref articleid="70715">
     symbols
    </xref>
    of mortality include
    <xref articleid="630002">
     hourglasses
    </xref>
    , wilted
    <xref articleid="34656">
     flowers
    </xref>
    , dead
    <xref articleid="110237">
     animals
    </xref>
    ,
    <xref articleid="19957">
     candles
    </xref>
    , and
    <xref articleid="108583">
     soap
    </xref>
    bubbles along with skulls and bones. These motifs also appear on timepieces,
    <xref articleid="57428">
     ornaments
    </xref>
    , and
    <xref articleid="106186">
     jewelry
    </xref>
    , especially in the
    <xref articleid="632001">
     Victorian era
    </xref>
    , and on religious items such as chaplets or
    <xref articleid="64077">
     rosaries
    </xref>
    carved out of
    <xref articleid="43080">
     ivory
    </xref>
    .
   </p>
   <p>
    Festivals that honour the deceased or put death at the centre of the celebration are known in many cultures, notably the
    <xref articleid="489963">
     Celtic
    </xref>
    pagan festival of
    <xref articleid="65212">
     Samhain
    </xref>
    , the
    <xref articleid="11557">
     Aztec
    </xref>
    -derived
    <xref articleid="433071">
     Día de los Muertos
    </xref>
    , the Buddhist Ullambana festival in
    <xref articleid="117321">
     China
    </xref>
    and
    <xref articleid="106451">
     Japan
    </xref>
    , the
    <xref articleid="105944">
     Buddhist
    </xref>
    and
    <xref articleid="109630">
     Confucian
    </xref>
    Bon festival in Japan, and the Buddhist and Taoist Hungry Ghost Festival in numerous Asian countries including Japan,
    <xref articleid="108454">
     Korea
    </xref>
    ,
    <xref articleid="108608">
     Taiwan
    </xref>
    , China,
    <xref articleid="111151">
     Singapore
    </xref>
    , and
    <xref articleid="106301">
     Indonesia
    </xref>
    . Unlike the Christian Lent, these festivals are not somber times of reflection on one’s mortality but focus instead on ancestor
    <xref articleid="109487">
     worship
    </xref>
    , beliefs about “thin spaces” that allow for the passing interchange of dead and living spirits, or reverence for deities associated with death and the underground or otherworld. However, many of the festivals feature motifs and rituals familiar to Christian tradition, such as skulls, death or spirit masks, the use of fire including bonfires and burning candles or
    <xref articleid="42241">
     incense
    </xref>
    , or grave visiting. In the case of Samhain and the pre-Hispanic precursor of Día de los Muertos, the festivals adapted to incorporate Christian beliefs and traditions, particularly those for
    <xref articleid="5767">
     All Souls Day
    </xref>
    and
    <xref articleid="5766">
     All Saints Day
    </xref>
    , and became better known in the modern era as
    <xref articleid="38951">
     Halloween
    </xref>
    and the Day of the Dead, respectively.
   </p>
  </h2>
  <h2 id="h354066">
   <title>
    Secular artistic expressions
   </title>
   <p>
    The danse macabre (French: “dance of death”) is a medieval allegorical concept found in
    <xref articleid="31140">
     drama
    </xref>
    ,
    <xref articleid="110446">
     poetry
    </xref>
    , and
    <xref articleid="110117">
     music
    </xref>
    as well as the visual arts. It is traditionally represented as a procession of living and dead figures, with the living figures arranged according to their life rank (for example, from
    <xref articleid="60836">
     pope
    </xref>
    or
    <xref articleid="32551">
     emperor
    </xref>
    down to child or infant) being led by a death figure to a grave. The earliest known representation of the danse macabre was a series of paintings (1424–25) in the Cimetière des Innocents in Paris, which were destroyed in 1699. The danse macabre drawings of the German painter
    <xref articleid="40772">
     Hans Holbein the Younger
    </xref>
    in the early 16th century are considered by many to be the apex of this motif.
   </p>
   <p>
    In the 17th-century
    <xref articleid="108757">
     Netherlands
    </xref>
    ,
    <e type="italic">
     vanitas
    </e>
    (Latin for “vanity”) developed as a genre of still-life painting featuring the standard elements of memento mori as well as symbols of the arts and
    <xref articleid="66286">
     sciences
    </xref>
    (
    <xref articleid="105988">
     musical instruments
    </xref>
    ,
    <xref articleid="110294">
     maps
    </xref>
    , and
    <xref articleid="80651">
     books
    </xref>
    ),
    <xref articleid="76355">
     wealth
    </xref>
    and power (purses,
    <xref articleid="37211">
     gold
    </xref>
    , and jewelry), and earthly pleasures (
    <xref articleid="60130">
     pipes
    </xref>
    ,
    <xref articleid="60380">
     playing cards
    </xref>
    , and goblets). Viewers are expected to consider their mortality and the vanities of life and be inspired to repent. The genre aligned with the rigid moral code of
    <xref articleid="106116">
     Calvinism
    </xref>
    , which flourished in the Netherlands.
   </p>
   <p>
    In literature and drama, memento mori has been expressed through forms such as the elegy in poetry, as seen in English poet
    <xref articleid="37806">
     Thomas Gray
    </xref>
    ’s “An Elegy Written in a Country Church Yard” (1751). English playwright
    <xref articleid="109536">
     William Shakespeare
    </xref>
    ’s
    <e type="italic">
     Hamlet
    </e>
    (written about 1599–1601) features one of most famous meditations on death, in Hamlet’s soliloquy while contemplating a skull.
   </p>
  </h2>
 </h1>
 <h1 id="h354067">
  <title>
   Modern expressions
  </title>
  <p>
   By the 20th century memento mori was being expressed through newer forms of media including
   <xref articleid="110698">
    film
   </xref>
   and photography. Symbology inspired by Christian memento mori appears in various works from the skull and flower paintings of American painter
   <xref articleid="56912">
    Georgia O’Keeffe
   </xref>
   to the death imagery of Mexican painter
   <xref articleid="44315">
    Frida Kahlo
   </xref>
   , who drew from Mexican culture and was inspired by her personal experience with illness and
   <xref articleid="58009">
    pain
   </xref>
   .
   <e type="italic">
    The Seventh Seal
   </e>
   (1957), a film by Swedish director
   <xref articleid="78761">
    Ingmar Bergman
   </xref>
   set in a plague-devastated
   <xref articleid="108596">
    Sweden
   </xref>
   , features a scene in which a
   <xref articleid="45789">
    knight
   </xref>
   plays a game of
   <xref articleid="105867">
    chess
   </xref>
   with Death and ends with the film’s characters holding hands on a hill in a danse macabre. During the
   <xref articleid="4173">
    AIDS
   </xref>
   crisis of the 1980s and ’90s, memento mori motifs were employed by American photographer
   <xref articleid="993">
    Robert Mapplethorpe
   </xref>
   , American multimedia artist and activist David Wojnarowicz, and many others to document the
   <xref articleid="110618">
    disease
   </xref>
   ’s ravaging effects on the human body and the U.S. government’s inaction on combating AIDS.
  </p>
  <p>
   In 2007 British artist
   <xref articleid="435769">
    Damien Hirst
   </xref>
   ’s
   <xref articleid="109518">
    sculpture
   </xref>
   <e type="italic">
    For the Love of God
   </e>
   , a life-size platinum cast of an 18th-century human skull covered with 8,601
   <xref articleid="30264">
    diamonds
   </xref>
   and inset with the original teeth, made headlines as possibly the most expensive piece of art ever made. Themes such as the fragility of life, defiance of death, and the vulgarity of materialism were all attributed to Hirst’s representation of memento mori.
  </p>
  <p>
   Social and digital media have allowed for further new expressions of memento mori. Sister Theresa Aletheia Noble, a
   <xref articleid="109699">
    Roman Catholic
   </xref>
   nun, amassed a large following on
   <xref articleid="471629">
    Twitter
   </xref>
   after she began posting daily memento mori quotes, ideas, and inspiration in 2017. Also in the early 21st century, the “death positivity” movement in the
   <xref articleid="111233">
    United States
   </xref>
   sought to break Western taboos related to death. The movement encompasses end-of-life
   <xref articleid="604919">
    doulas
   </xref>
   , “death cafés” that feature informal gatherings to discuss death and dying,
   <xref articleid="404269">
    blogs
   </xref>
   and
   <xref articleid="471403">
    podcasts
   </xref>
   exploring topics such as mortuary science, and mobile apps that send daily reminders of one’s mortality.
  </p>
 </h1>
 <signature>
  [ No Value! ]
 </signature>
 <copyright>
  Encyclopædia Britannica
 </copyright>
</article>