<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "syndication_xml.dtd">
<article articleid="635935" articletypeid="1" language="en_us" lastupdate="2022-Dec-08 08:15:48" url="/article/electric-guitar/635935" version="3">
 <title>
  electric guitar
 </title>
 <p>
  <assembly id="a273150" url="/assembly/view/273150">
   <title>
    Fender Telecaster
   </title>
   <media mediaid="200253" type="image" url="/53/200253-004-34EF65CF.jpg"/>
   <caption>
    Fender Telecaster.
   </caption>
   <credit>
    © timsaxon—iStock Editorial/Getty Images
   </credit>
  </assembly>
  <e type="bold">
   electric guitar
  </e>
  ,
  <assemblyref assemblyid="a273150"/>
  <xref articleid="38459">
   guitar
  </xref>
  (plucked stringed musical instrument) that uses electronic amplification in order to be heard at a louder volume, by translating the vibrations of the strings into electrical currents. These electric signals are picked up and amplified by an external amplifier or a speaker. Sounds from the instrument can also be distorted and modified. While there are many variations on the neck length, shape, number of strings, and general build of electric guitars, most of them consist of the same elements: a body, usually made of wood or plaster, which comprises the bulk of the guitar and can be shaped in a variety of ways; a headstock, into which the tuners are set; a nut which holds the strings in place; strings; a neck that connects the headstock to the body and supports the strings; frets, which maintain the desired pitch when the strings are pressed; electrical current pickups; and control knobs with which volume and tone can be adjusted. Although efforts to create an electrified fretted string instrument date to the late 19th century, the first true electric guitar was invented in the early 1930s by George Beauchamp, with the help of Adolph Rickenbacker, for the Electro String Instrument Corporation. The electric guitar would prove to be vital to the development of popular music throughout the world in the 20th century, and it continues to be one of the most commonly played instruments across cultures today.
 </p>
 <p>
  <assembly id="a230183" url="/assembly/view/230183">
   <title>
    Muddy Waters
   </title>
   <media mediaid="197637" type="image" url="/37/197637-004-50543FF0.jpg"/>
   <caption>
    Muddy Waters, 1979.
   </caption>
   <credit>
    Eugene Adebari—REX/Shutterstock.com
   </credit>
  </assembly>
  <assemblyref assemblyid="a230183"/>
  The electric guitar was born out of a simple need for louder music. In the United States, dance music in public spaces became increasingly common during the 1920s as
  <xref articleid="110142">
   jazz
  </xref>
  exploded in popularity. Electronic amplification made it possible for the guitar to be heard among the other instruments in the big bands (especially the large brass sections) of the
  <xref articleid="70661">
   swing era
  </xref>
  of the 1930s and ’40s. In addition to swing-jazz guitarists such as
  <xref articleid="82409">
   Charlie Christian
  </xref>
  , the first musicians to make use of Beauchamp’s innovation played Hawaiian-style and
  <xref articleid="26573">
   country music
  </xref>
  . In the 1940s and ’50s, as the
  <xref articleid="15780">
   blues
  </xref>
  migrated northward from the rural American South, electrification made it easier for the guitar to compete with the cacophony of the patrons in crowded bars and clubs in
  <xref articleid="118621">
   Chicago
  </xref>
  and other cities to which musicians such as
  <xref articleid="117872">
   Elmore James
  </xref>
  ,
  <xref articleid="76271">
   Muddy Waters
  </xref>
  , and
  <xref articleid="18196">
   Howlin’ Wolf
  </xref>
  had relocated.
 </p>
 <p>
  The first electric guitars were, like their acoustic counterparts, hollow-bodied. The most noticeable difference was the inclusion of tungsten steel pickups. The iconic solid-body electric guitar was created by guitarist
  <xref articleid="110276">
   Les Paul
  </xref>
  in 1941. No longer relying on any acoustic amplification, the solid-body electric guitar could make much smoother, more sonically isolated tones. The technology for pickups—the nodes attached to the steel strings that transferred electric currents to amplifiers—also advanced quickly about the same time. Most electric guitars had begun to use smaller magnetic single- or double-coil pickups. These pickups are what supply the instrument’s signature electric hum.
 </p>
 <p>
  While Les Paul and the Gibson Guitar Company readied an electric guitar for mass production,
  <xref articleid="110275">
   Leo Fender
  </xref>
  and the Fender Electric Instruments Company beat them to the punch, marketing the first mass-produced solid-body electric guitar, the Fender Broadcaster (later renamed Telecaster), in 1948. The Les Paul Standard became available in 1952. Two years later Fender introduced the iconic Stratocaster, which featured three electric pickups (instead of two).
 </p>
 <p>
  <assembly id="a244623" url="/assembly/view/244623">
   <title>
    Chuck Berry
   </title>
   <media mediaid="215289" type="image" url="/89/215289-004-16179251.jpg"/>
   <caption>
    Chuck Berry.
   </caption>
   <credit>
    Pictorial Press Ltd./Alamy
   </credit>
  </assembly>
  <assembly id="a230700" url="/assembly/view/230700">
   <title>
    Bo Diddley
   </title>
   <media mediaid="197923" type="image" url="/23/197923-004-65D1C8A4.jpg"/>
   <caption>
    Bo Diddley, 1960s.
   </caption>
   <credit>
    REX/Shutterstock.com
   </credit>
  </assembly>
  <assemblyref assemblyid="a244623"/>
  <assemblyref assemblyid="a230700"/>
  As
  <xref articleid="63492">
   rhythm and blues
  </xref>
  ,
  <xref articleid="99195">
   rockabilly
  </xref>
  , and
  <xref articleid="105870">
   rock and roll
  </xref>
  began to emerge in the 1950s, the new sounds and tones that the electric guitar was capable of making were embraced by a new generation of musicians, including
  <xref articleid="78885">
   Chuck Berry
  </xref>
  ,
  <xref articleid="109645">
   Bo Diddley
  </xref>
  ,
  <xref articleid="98762">
   Carl Perkins
  </xref>
  , and
  <xref articleid="96996">
   Buddy Holly
  </xref>
  . These artists and their contemporaries sparked a conservative backlash against what older generations considered to be immoral, lascivious music. Beyond its sound, the electric guitar became a symbol and a talisman for the burgeoning youth culture.
 </p>
 <p>
  <assembly id="a272170" url="/assembly/view/272170">
   <title>
    Fender Precision Bass
   </title>
   <media mediaid="237297" type="image" url="/97/237297-004-874869DA.jpg"/>
   <caption>
    A Fender Precision Bass guitar, also called a P Bass.
   </caption>
   <credit>
    © Wirestock/Dreamstime.com
   </credit>
  </assembly>
  <assemblyref assemblyid="a272170"/>
  In the 1960s manufacturers started equipping preamplifiers (or preamps; separate amplifiers that can adjust the tone and volume of certain sounds) with a range of effects, such as tremolo (a wavering or trembling effect), wah-wah (a fluctuating muted sound, like the covering and uncovering of the bell of a trumpet), and distortion. Guitarists used these innovations to explore new sounds and create new subgenres of
  <xref articleid="63964">
   rock music
  </xref>
  . Partly because of their ability to make fuller, louder sounds, electric guitars also lent themselves to use as solo instruments (sometimes used in “dueling” counterpoint) as well as rhythm instruments. Some novel techniques that electric guitars allow for include string-bending, hammering, and sliding. The instrument’s popularity and sonic possibilities also paved the way for the electrification of other acoustic instruments like the
  <xref articleid="635607">
   bass
  </xref>
  .
 </p>
 <p>
  <assembly id="a139736" url="/assembly/view/139736">
   <title>
    Eric Clapton
   </title>
   <media mediaid="137031" type="image" url="/31/137031-004-E5C4E892.jpg"/>
   <caption>
    Eric Clapton, 2009.
   </caption>
   <credit>
    Ethan Miller/Getty Images
   </credit>
  </assembly>
  <assemblyref assemblyid="a139736"/>
  Some of the musicians (not already mentioned) who gained reputations as virtuoso electric guitarists and innovators were blues masters
  <xref articleid="45497">
   B.B. King
  </xref>
  ,
  <xref articleid="940">
   Albert King
  </xref>
  ,
  <xref articleid="97007">
   John Lee Hooker
  </xref>
  , and
  <xref articleid="399820">
   Buddy Guy
  </xref>
  ; gospel singer and guitarist Sister Rosetta Tharpe; influential country music makers
  <xref articleid="94947">
   Chet Atkins
  </xref>
  and
  <xref articleid="100079">
   Merle Travis
  </xref>
  ; rock “guitar gods”
  <xref articleid="39992">
   Jimi Hendrix
  </xref>
  and
  <xref articleid="95774">
   Eric Clapton
  </xref>
  ; and heavy metal mavens Jimmy Page (
  <xref articleid="117498">
   Led Zepplin
  </xref>
  ), Tony Iommi (
  <xref articleid="110272">
   Black Sabbath
  </xref>
  ), Eddie Van Halen (
  <xref articleid="100197">
   Van Halen
  </xref>
  ), Angus Young (
  <xref articleid="110266">
   AC/DC
  </xref>
  ), Slash (
  <xref articleid="110267">
   Guns N’ Roses
  </xref>
  ), and James Hetfield (
  <xref articleid="98063">
   Metallica
  </xref>
  ); along with
  <xref articleid="632091">
   George Harrison
  </xref>
  (the
  <xref articleid="13958">
   Beatles
  </xref>
  ), Keith Richards (the
  <xref articleid="83792">
   Rolling Stones
  </xref>
  ), Pete Townshend (the
  <xref articleid="100454">
   Who
  </xref>
  ), David Gilmour (
  <xref articleid="105888">
   Pink Floyd
  </xref>
  ), Robbie Robertson (the
  <xref articleid="117782">
   Band
  </xref>
  ), Mark Knopfler (
  <xref articleid="117772">
   Dire Straits
  </xref>
  ),
  <xref articleid="472057">
   Kurt Cobain
  </xref>
  (
  <xref articleid="105679">
   Nirvana
  </xref>
  ), James Burton,
  <xref articleid="96199">
   Duane Eddy
  </xref>
  ,
  <xref articleid="488385">
   Jeff Beck
  </xref>
  ,
  <xref articleid="476059">
   Carlos Santana
  </xref>
  ,
  <xref articleid="117533">
   Neil Young
  </xref>
  ,
  <xref articleid="117592">
   John McLaughlin
  </xref>
  , and Stevie Ray Vaughan. Though most commonly associated with American and British popular music, the electric guitar has been used by musicians throughout the world—notably Nigeria’s
  <xref articleid="474421">
   King Sunny Adé
  </xref>
  —to build on, distort, and experiment with traditional sounds.
 </p>
 <signature>
  [ No Value! ]
 </signature>
 <signature>
  EB Editors
 </signature>
 <copyright>
  Encyclopædia Britannica
 </copyright>
</article>