<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "syndication_xml.dtd">
<article articleid="64083" articletypeid="1" language="en_us" lastupdate="2021-Jul-01 00:53:30" url="/article/rose/64083" version="13">
 <title>
  rose
 </title>
 <p>
  <e type="bold">
   rose
  </e>
  , (genus
  <e type="italic">
   Rosa
  </e>
  ), genus of some 100 species of perennial
  <xref articleid="67551">
   shrubs
  </xref>
  in the rose family (
  <xref articleid="623310">
   Rosaceae
  </xref>
  ). Roses are native primarily to the temperate regions of the Northern Hemisphere. Many roses are cultivated for their beautiful flowers, which range in colour from white through various tones of yellow and pink to dark crimson and maroon, and most have a delightful fragrance, which varies according to the variety and to climatic conditions.
 </p>
 <p>
  <assembly id="a116167" url="/assembly/view/116167">
   <title>
    Virginia rose
   </title>
   <media mediaid="119439" type="image" url="/39/119439-004-8EB9DB53.jpg"/>
   <caption>
    Virginia rose (
    <e type="italic">
     Rosa virginiana
    </e>
    ), native to eastern North America. Wild roses typically feature five petals.
   </caption>
   <credit>
    Encyclopædia Britannica, Inc.
   </credit>
  </assembly>
  <assemblyref assemblyid="a116167"/>
  Most rose species are native to Asia, with smaller numbers being native to North America and a few to Europe and northwest Africa. Roses from different regions of the world hybridize readily, giving rise to types that overlap the parental forms, and making it difficult to determine basic species. Fewer than 10 species, mostly native to Asia, were involved in the crossbreeding that ultimately produced today’s many types of garden roses.
 </p>
 <h1 id="h341679">
  <title>
   Physical description
  </title>
  <p>
   <assembly id="a202747" url="/assembly/view/202747">
    <title>
     rose hips
    </title>
    <media mediaid="182615" type="image" url="/15/182615-004-601AB4AB.jpg"/>
    <caption>
     Rose hips of the rugosa rose (
     <e type="italic">
      Rosa rugosa)
     </e>
     . The hips are high in vitamin C and are sometimes used in teas or preserves.
    </caption>
    <credit>
     © eugenesergeev/Fotolia
    </credit>
   </assembly>
   <assemblyref assemblyid="a202747"/>
   Roses are erect, climbing, or trailing shrubs, the
   <xref articleid="69567">
    stems
   </xref>
   of which are usually copiously armed with prickles of various shapes and sizes, commonly called thorns. The
   <xref articleid="47499">
    leaves
   </xref>
   are alternate and pinnately compound (i.e., feather-formed), usually with oval leaflets that are sharply toothed. The
   <xref articleid="34656">
    flowers
   </xref>
   of wild roses usually have five petals, whereas the flowers of cultivated roses are often double (i.e., with multiple sets of petals). Rose flowers’ size ranges from tiny miniatures 1.25 cm (0.5 inch) in diameter to
   <xref articleid="41687">
    hybrid
   </xref>
   flowers measuring more than 17.5 cm (7 inches) across. The rose plant’s fleshy, sometimes edible, berrylike “fruit” (actually the floral cup) is known as a hip and usually ranges from red to orange in colour.
  </p>
  <p>
   Roses can become infected by a number of
   <xref articleid="110621">
    diseases
   </xref>
   , most of them caused by
   <xref articleid="110641">
    fungi
   </xref>
   .
   <xref articleid="61116">
    Powdery mildew
   </xref>
   appears as a grayish white moldlike growth on the surface of young leaves and stems.
   <xref articleid="15512">
    Black spot
   </xref>
   fungus appears as conspicuous black spots on leaves and causes them to fall off.
   <xref articleid="64495">
    Rust
   </xref>
   is also a common disease of roses.
   <xref articleid="7995">
    Aphids
   </xref>
   are a common
   <xref articleid="105953">
    insect
   </xref>
   pest on the leaves and young stems.
  </p>
 </h1>
 <h1 id="h341680">
  <title>
   Major species and hybrids
  </title>
  <p>
   The flowers of the damask rose (
   <e type="italic">
    Rosa
   </e>
   ×
   <e type="italic">
    damascena
   </e>
   ) and several other species are the source of
   <xref articleid="11168">
    attar of roses
   </xref>
   used in perfumes. Many species, particularly the rugosa rose (
   <e type="italic">
    R. rugosa
   </e>
   ), produce edible rose hips, which are a rich source of
   <xref articleid="75556">
    vitamin C
   </xref>
   and are sometimes used in preserves.
  </p>
  <p>
   <assembly id="a197451" url="/assembly/view/197451">
    <title>
     hybrid tea rose
    </title>
    <media mediaid="174596" type="image" url="/96/174596-004-F2303F74.jpg"/>
    <caption>
     ‘Double Delight,’ a hybrid tea rose (
     <e type="italic">
      Rosa
     </e>
     ‘Double Delight’). The flowers are highly fragrant and bloom continuously throughout the season.
    </caption>
    <credit>
     AdstockRF
    </credit>
   </assembly>
   <assemblyref assemblyid="a197451"/>
   There are several major classes of garden roses. The best-known and most-popular class of rose is that of the hybrid tea roses, which accounts for the majority of roses grown in greenhouses and gardens and sold in florist shops. Hybrid teas come in the complete range of rose colours and have large symmetrical blossoms. Hybrid teas resulted from the crossbreeding of frequently blooming but fragile tea roses with vigorous hybrid perpetual roses. The hybrid perpetuals achieved great popularity until they were supplanted by the hybrid teas in the early 20th century. Polyantha roses are a class of very hardy roses that produce dense bunches of tiny blossoms. Floribunda roses are hardy hybrids that resulted from crossing hybrid teas with polyanthas. Grandiflora roses are relatively new hybrids resulting from the crossbreeding of hybrid teas and floribunda roses. Grandifloras produce full-blossomed flowers growing on tall hardy bushes. Among the other classes of modern roses are climbing roses, whose slender stems can be trained to ascend trellises; shrub roses, which develop into large bushes; and miniature roses, which are pygmy-sized plants bearing tiny blossoms. Altogether there are thousands of identifiable varieties of roses in those and other classes.
  </p>
  <signature>
   EB Editors
  </signature>
 </h1>
 <copyright>
  Encyclopædia Britannica
 </copyright>
</article>