<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "syndication_xml.dtd">
<article articleid="64471" articletypeid="1" language="en_us" lastupdate="2021-Jul-01 00:55:47" url="/article/Russell-Ken/64471" version="7">
 <title>
  Ken Russell
 </title>
 <p>
  <e type="bold">
   Ken Russell
  </e>
  , in full
  <e type="bold">
   Henry Kenneth Alfred Russell
  </e>
  , (born July 3, 1927, Southampton, Hampshire, England—died November 27, 2011, Lymington, Hampshire), British motion-picture director whose use of shock and sensationalism earned him both praise and reprehension from critics.
 </p>
 <p>
  The son of a shoe-store owner, Russell became a cadet at the Nautical College at Pangbourne and subsequently joined the British Merchant Navy. After training as an electrician in the Royal Air Force for two years, he tried his hand at various genres of the arts, including acting, ballet, and photography. One of his early efforts in filmmaking drew the attention of the British Broadcasting Corporation (BBC), and Russell was offered a job as a director of documentary films. He continued his work there as director of BBC television’s
  <e type="italic">
   Monitor
  </e>
  and
  <e type="italic">
   Sunday Night Film
  </e>
  programs for a decade.
 </p>
 <p>
  The two feature films
  <e type="italic">
   French Dressing
  </e>
  (1963) and
  <e type="italic">
   Billion Dollar Brain
  </e>
  (1967) that Russell completed while working for the BBC were both successful, but it was
  <e type="italic">
   Women in Love
  </e>
  (1969), based on D.H. Lawrence’s novel, that established his reputation as a major film director. The visual beauty of this film and its tasteful handling of erotic scenes won the approval of public and critics alike. His next film,
  <e type="italic">
   The Music Lovers
  </e>
  (1970), portrayed the anguished life of Pyotr Ilyich Tchaikovsky in a flamboyant, sensational style that infuriated audiences.
  <e type="italic">
   The Devils
  </e>
  (1971), based on the Aldous Huxley novel
  <e type="italic">
   The Devils of Loudon
  </e>
  , aroused even more vehement criticism with its story of mass sexual hysteria in a convent. Russell then made
  <e type="italic">
   The Boy Friend
  </e>
  (1971) and
  <e type="italic">
   Savage Messiah
  </e>
  (1972) before he again achieved a commercial success with
  <e type="italic">
   Tommy
  </e>
  (1975), a film based on a rock opera. His later films include
  <e type="italic">
   Lisztomania
  </e>
  (1975),
  <e type="italic">
   Altered States
  </e>
  (1980),
  <e type="italic">
   Crimes of Passion
  </e>
  (1984),
  <e type="italic">
   Whore
  </e>
  (1991), and the musical horror-comedy
  <e type="italic">
   The Fall of the Louse of Usher
  </e>
  (2002).
 </p>
 <copyright>
  Encyclopædia Britannica
 </copyright>
</article>