<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "syndication_xml.dtd">
<article articleid="66008" articletypeid="1" language="en_us" lastupdate="2021-Jul-01 01:04:34" url="/article/scale/66008" version="4">
 <title>
  scale
 </title>
 <p>
  <e type="bold">
   scale
  </e>
  , in zoology, small plate or shield forming part of the outer skin layers of certain animals. Scales provide protection from the environment and from predators. Fish scales are formed of bone from the deeper, or dermal, skin layer. The elasmobranchs (e.g., sharks) have placoid scales, which are bony, spiny projections with an enamel-like covering. Ganoid scales, which are found on such fishes as gars and the bowfin, are similar to placoid scales but are covered with a peculiar enamel-like substance called ganoin. It is thought that true teeth developed from placoid scales. The advanced fish have either cycloid scales (e.g., carp) or ctenoid scales (e.g., perch; sunfish). These are the typical overlapping fish scales. Cycloid scales are large, thin, and round or oval in shape, and they exhibit growth rings. Ctenoid scales resemble cycloid scales but have comblike teeth on their overlapping edge.
 </p>
 <p>
  <assembly id="a157635" url="/assembly/view/157635">
   <title>
    types of fish scales
   </title>
   <media mediaid="51204" type="image" url="/04/51204-004-C24C9F0B.jpg"/>
   <caption>
    Scales and scale configurations of representative bony and cartilaginous fishes.
   </caption>
   <credit>
    Encyclopædia Britannica, Inc.
   </credit>
  </assembly>
  <assemblyref assemblyid="a157635"/>
  Horny scutes, or corneoscutes, derived from the upper, or epidermal, skin layer, appear in reptiles and on the legs of birds. In crocodilians and some lizards, bony dermal scales (osteoderms) underlie the external scales. Bird feathers are developmentally modified epidermal scales. Modified epidermal tissue, mostly made up of keratin, forms the scaly surface found on some mammals (e.g., rats; pangolins); however, although mammalian hair is also largely keratin, it is not a modified scale.
 </p>
 <p>
  The term
  <e type="italic">
   scale
  </e>
  is also applied to modified body coverings on certain insects (e.g., moths).
 </p>
 <copyright>
  Encyclopædia Britannica
 </copyright>
</article>