<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "syndication_xml.dtd">
<article articleid="66451" articletypeid="1" language="en_us" lastupdate="2021-Jul-01 01:07:11" url="/article/Sea-People/66451" version="3">
 <title>
  Sea People
 </title>
 <p>
  <e type="bold">
   Sea People
  </e>
  , any of the groups of aggressive seafarers who invaded eastern Anatolia, Syria, Palestine, Cyprus, and Egypt toward the end of the
  <xref articleid="16618">
   Bronze Age
  </xref>
  , especially in the 13th century
  <e type="smallcap">
   bce
  </e>
  . They are held responsible for the destruction of old powers such as the
  <xref articleid="40612">
   Hittite
  </xref>
  empire. Because of the abrupt break in ancient Middle Eastern records as a result of the invasions, the precise extent and origin of the upheavals remain uncertain. Principal but one-sided evidence for the Sea Peoples is based on Egyptian texts and illustrations; other important information comes from Hittite sources and from archaeological data.
 </p>
 <p>
  The Egyptians waged two wars against the Sea Peoples: the first, in the fifth year of King
  <xref articleid="52156">
   Merneptah
  </xref>
  (1236–23
  <e type="smallcap">
   bce
  </e>
  ); the second, in the reign of
  <xref articleid="62621">
   Ramses III
  </xref>
  (
  <e type="italic">
   c.
  </e>
  1198–66
  <e type="smallcap">
   bce
  </e>
  ).
 </p>
 <p>
  Tentative identifications of the Sea Peoples listed in Egyptian documents are as follows: Ekwesh, a group of Bronze Age Greeks (
  <xref articleid="3513">
   Achaeans
  </xref>
  ;
  <xref articleid="4118">
   Ahhiyawa
  </xref>
  in Hittite texts); Teresh, Tyrrhenians (Tyrsenoi), known to later Greeks as sailors and pirates from Anatolia, ancestors of the
  <xref articleid="33158">
   Etruscans
  </xref>
  ; Luka, a coastal people of western Anatolia, also known from Hittite sources (their name survives in classical
  <xref articleid="49488">
   Lycia
  </xref>
  on the southwest coast of Anatolia); Sherden, probably Sardinians (the Sherden acted as mercenaries of the Egyptians in the
  <xref articleid="44278">
   Battle of Kadesh
  </xref>
  , 1299
  <e type="smallcap">
   bce
  </e>
  ); Shekelesh, probably identical with the Sicilian tribe called
  <xref articleid="67627">
   Siculi
  </xref>
  ; and Peleset, generally believed to refer to the
  <xref articleid="59701">
   Philistines
  </xref>
  , who perhaps came from Crete and were the only major tribe of the Sea Peoples to settle permanently in Palestine.
 </p>
 <p>
  Further identifications of other Sea Peoples mentioned in the documents are much more uncertain.
 </p>
 <copyright>
  Encyclopædia Britannica
 </copyright>
</article>