<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "syndication_xml.dtd">
<article articleid="66675" articletypeid="1" language="en_us" lastupdate="2021-Jul-01 01:08:33" url="/article/self-determination/66675" version="2">
 <title>
  self-determination
 </title>
 <p>
  <e type="bold">
   self-determination
  </e>
  , the process by which a group of people, usually possessing a certain degree of national consciousness, form their own
  <xref articleid="1296">
   state
  </xref>
  and choose their own
  <xref articleid="106262">
   government
  </xref>
  . As a political principle, the idea of self-determination evolved at first as a by-product of the doctrine of
  <xref articleid="117287">
   nationalism
  </xref>
  , to which early expression was given by the French and American revolutions. In
  <xref articleid="110198">
   World War I
  </xref>
  the Allies accepted self-determination as a peace aim. In his
  <xref articleid="35049">
   Fourteen Points
  </xref>
  —the essential terms for peace—U.S. Pres.
  <xref articleid="77135">
   Woodrow Wilson
  </xref>
  listed self-determination as an important objective for the postwar world; the result was the fragmentation of the old Austro-Hungarian and
  <xref articleid="111081">
   Ottoman
  </xref>
  empires and Russia’s former Baltic territories into a number of new states.
 </p>
 <p>
  After
  <xref articleid="110199">
   World War II
  </xref>
  , promotion of self-determination among subject peoples became one of the chief goals of the
  <xref articleid="108767">
   United Nations
  </xref>
  . The UN’s predecessor, the
  <xref articleid="55027">
   League of Nations
  </xref>
  , had also recognized the principle, but it was in the UN that the idea received its clearest statement and affirmation.
 </p>
 <p>
  The UN Charter clarifies two meanings of the term
  <e type="italic">
   self-determination
  </e>
  . First, a state is said to have the right of self-determination in the sense of having the right to choose freely its political, economic, social, and cultural systems. Second, the right to self-determination is defined as the right of a people to constitute itself in a state or otherwise freely determine the form of its association with an existing state. Both meanings have their basis in the charter (Article 1, paragraph 2; and Article 55, paragraph 1). With respect to dependent territories, the charter asserts that administering authorities should undertake to ensure political advancement and the development of self-government (Article 73, paragraphs a and b; and Article 76, paragraph b).
 </p>
 <signature>
  EB Editors
 </signature>
 <copyright>
  Encyclopædia Britannica
 </copyright>
</article>