<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "syndication_xml.dtd">
<article articleid="67008" articletypeid="1" language="en_us" lastupdate="2021-Jul-01 01:10:28" url="/article/Seyfert-galaxy/67008" version="5">
 <title>
  Seyfert galaxy
 </title>
 <p>
  <assembly id="a109276" url="/assembly/view/109276">
   <media mediaid="111332" type="image" url="/32/111332-004-E4E3DD17.jpg"/>
   <caption>
    The small spiral galaxy NGC 7742, a Type 2 Seyfert galaxy, as seen by the Hubble Space Telescope.
   </caption>
   <credit>
    The Hubble Heritage Team (AURA/STScI/NASA)
   </credit>
  </assembly>
  <e type="bold">
   Seyfert galaxy
  </e>
  ,
  <assemblyref assemblyid="a109276"/>
  any of a class of
  <xref articleid="110642">
   galaxies
  </xref>
  known to have active nuclei. Such galaxies were named for the American astronomer Carl K. Seyfert, who first called attention to them in 1944. Two types are recognized. The nuclear spectra of Type 1 Seyfert galaxies show broad emission lines, which are indicative of a central concentration of hot gas that is expanding at speeds of up to thousands of kilometres per second. Type 2 Seyferts have strong emission lines, but they indicate more-modest velocities, less than 1,000 km/sec. Seyfert galaxies appear normal in ordinary images but are extremely strong sources of
  <xref articleid="42403">
   infrared radiation
  </xref>
  . Moreover, many are powerful sources of radio energy and
  <xref articleid="77656">
   X-rays
  </xref>
  as well. Seyfert nuclei are related to
  <xref articleid="62185">
   quasars
  </xref>
  but apparently involve smaller amounts of energy release. Like quasars, they are thought to be powered by massive
  <xref articleid="15483">
   black holes
  </xref>
  at their centres. About 1 percent of all spiral galaxies are thought to exhibit Seyfert properties, or perhaps all spiral galaxies are Seyferts 1 percent of the time.
 </p>
 <signature>
  Paul W. Hodge
 </signature>
 <copyright>
  Encyclopædia Britannica
 </copyright>
</article>