<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "syndication_xml.dtd">
<article articleid="67400" articletypeid="1" language="en_us" lastupdate="2021-Jul-01 01:12:37" url="/article/shingle/67400" version="2">
 <title>
  shingle
 </title>
 <p>
  <assembly id="a147422" url="/assembly/view/147422">
   <title>
    Sherman House
   </title>
   <media mediaid="143717" type="image" url="/17/143717-004-BED9FC87.jpg"/>
   <caption>
    Wood shingle siding on the Sherman House, Newport, R.I., designed by Henry Hobson Richardson (1874–75).
   </caption>
   <credit>
    Historic American Buildings Survey/Library of Congress, Washington, D.C. (Neg. no. HABS RI,3-NEWP,68-3)
   </credit>
  </assembly>
  <e type="bold">
   shingle
  </e>
  ,
  <assemblyref assemblyid="a147422"/>
  thin piece of building material, usually with a butt end thicker than the other. Shingles are widely used as roof covering on residential buildings and sometimes for siding. They are of stock sizes and various materials—including wood, asphalt, and slate. They are attached in overlapping courses, or rows.
 </p>
 <p>
  As roofing, the degree to which the shingle’s surface is exposed is controlled by the pitch of the roof. As siding, the degree of overlap is mainly an aesthetic concern. Wooden shingles are cut in various ways, such as hand splitting, which is the ancient method, quarter-sawing, and plain-sawing. They are usually cut from green wood and kiln-dried. If quartersawn and with a thick butt, they resist warping. Wood shingles in the United States are usually of cypress, redwood, or Western red cedar. They may be entirely of heartwood, in which case they are relatively decay resistant, or of mixed heartwood and sapwood. The surface may be striated, left smooth by sawing, or feature the slight roughness of hand splitting. Wood shingles must be treated with some kind of weatherproofing stain or paint to keep them from bleaching to a grayish colour.
 </p>
 <p>
  “Shingle style” is a mode of wood shingle-covered American domestic architecture of the 1870s and ’80s. The finest examples are Henry Hobson Richardson’s Sherman House (1874–75) in Newport, R.I., and the Stoughton House (1882–83) in Cambridge, Mass.
 </p>
 <copyright>
  Encyclopædia Britannica
 </copyright>
</article>