<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "syndication_xml.dtd">
<article articleid="67774" articletypeid="1" language="en_us" lastupdate="2021-Jul-01 01:14:41" url="/article/silk/67774" version="6">
 <title>
  silk
 </title>
 <p>
  <assembly id="a216825" url="/assembly/view/216825">
   <title>
    silkworm cocoon
   </title>
   <media mediaid="158197" type="image" url="/97/158197-004-B5B04876.jpg"/>
   <caption>
    Commercial silk is made from the fibrous cocoons of silkworm caterpillars (
    <e type="italic">
     Bombyx
    </e>
    species).
   </caption>
   <credit>
    © Vibe Images/Fotolia
   </credit>
  </assembly>
  <e type="bold">
   silk
  </e>
  ,
  <assemblyref assemblyid="a216825"/>
  animal fibre produced by certain
  <xref articleid="105953">
   insects
  </xref>
  and
  <xref articleid="110513">
   arachnids
  </xref>
  as building material for cocoons and webs, some of which can be used to make fine fabrics. In commercial use, silk is almost entirely limited to filaments from the
  <xref articleid="24607">
   cocoons
  </xref>
  of domesticated
  <xref articleid="67779">
   silkworms
  </xref>
  (caterpillars of several moth species belonging to the genus
  <e type="italic">
   Bombyx
  </e>
  ).
  <e type="italic">
   See also
  </e>
  <xref articleid="470923">
   sericulture
  </xref>
  .
 </p>
 <h1 id="h283188">
  <title>
   Origins in China
  </title>
  <p>
   <assembly id="a24374" url="/assembly/view/24374">
    <media mediaid="59200" type="image" url="/00/59200-004-397FBC3B.jpg"/>
    <caption>
     Embroidered silk with dragon, phoenix, and tiger pattern, from Mashan Tomb No. 1, 4th–3rd century
     <e type="smallcap">
      bce
     </e>
     , Zhou dynasty; in the Jingzhou Museum, Hubei province, China.
    </caption>
    <credit>
     Kong Lihang/ChinaStock Photo Library
    </credit>
   </assembly>
   <assemblyref assemblyid="a24374"/>
   The origin of silk production and weaving is ancient and clouded in legend. The industry undoubtedly began in China, where, according to native record, it existed from sometime before the middle of the 3rd millennium
   <e type="smallcap">
    bce
   </e>
   . At that time it was discovered that the roughly 1 km (1,000 yards) of thread that constitutes the cocoon of the silkworm could be reeled off, spun, and woven, and
   <xref articleid="470923">
    sericulture
   </xref>
   early became an important feature of the Chinese rural economy. A Chinese legend says that it was the wife of the mythological Yellow Emperor,
   <xref articleid="41349">
    Huangdi
   </xref>
   , who taught the Chinese people the art; throughout history the empress was ceremonially associated with sericulture. The weaving of
   <xref articleid="28637">
    damask
   </xref>
   probably existed in the
   <xref articleid="67119">
    Shang dynasty
   </xref>
   , and the tombs of the 4th–3rd centuries
   <e type="smallcap">
    bce
   </e>
   at Mashan near Jiangling (Hubei province), excavated in 1982, have provided outstanding examples of
   <xref articleid="16559">
    brocade
   </xref>
   ,
   <xref articleid="36232">
    gauze
   </xref>
   , and
   <xref articleid="32513">
    embroidery
   </xref>
   with pictorial designs as well as the first complete garments.
  </p>
  <p>
   The main
   <xref articleid="70368">
    Song dynasty
   </xref>
   achievement in silk production was the perfecting of
   <e type="italic">
    kesi
   </e>
   , an extremely fine silk tapestry woven on a small loom with a needle as a shuttle. The technique appears to have been invented by the Sogdians in Central Asia, improved by the
   <xref articleid="74113">
    Uighurs
   </xref>
   , and adapted by the Chinese in the 11th century. The term
   <e type="italic">
    kesi
   </e>
   (literally “cut silk”) derives from vertical gaps between areas of colours, caused by the weft threads not running right across the width; it has also been suggested that the word is a corruption of the Persian
   <e type="italic">
    qazz
   </e>
   or Arabic
   <e type="italic">
    khazz
   </e>
   , referring to silk and silk products.
   <e type="italic">
    Kesi
   </e>
   was used for robes, silk panels, and scroll covers and for translating painting into tapestry. In the
   <xref articleid="78108">
    Yuan dynasty
   </xref>
   , panels of
   <e type="italic">
    kesi
   </e>
   were exported to Europe, where they were incorporated into cathedral vestments.
  </p>
  <p>
   Silk weaving became a major industry and one of China’s chief exports in the
   <xref articleid="39094">
    Han dynasty
   </xref>
   . The caravan route across Central Asia, known as the
   <xref articleid="67775">
    Silk Road
   </xref>
   , took Chinese silk to Syria and on to Rome. In the 4th century
   <e type="smallcap">
    bce
   </e>
   the Greek philosopher
   <xref articleid="108312">
    Aristotle
   </xref>
   mentioned that sericulture was practiced on the island of Kos, but the art was evidently lost and reintroduced into Byzantium from China in the 6th century
   <e type="smallcap">
    ce
   </e>
   . Chinese textiles of Han date have been found in Egypt, in graves in northern Mongolia (Noin-ula), and at Loulan in Chinese Turkistan. Silk was used by Han rulers as diplomatic gifts, as well as to buy off the threatening nomads and to weaken them by giving them a taste of luxury.
  </p>
  <p>
   Early Han textiles recovered from
   <xref articleid="49576">
    Mawangdui
   </xref>
   show the further development of the weaving traditions already present at Mashan in the late Zhou, including brocade and embroidery, gauze, plain weaves, and damasks. Later finds elsewhere, however, are limited chiefly to damasks, very finely woven in several colours with patterns that generally repeat about every 5 cm (2 inches). These designs are either geometric, the zigzag lozenge being the most common, or consist of cloud or mountain scrolls interspersed with fabulous creatures and sometimes with auspicious characters. The rectilinear patterns were transmitted from woven materials to Luoyang bronze mirrors and appeared in paintings on both lacquer and silk; and the curvilinear scroll patterns, which are not natural to weaving, were probably adapted for embroidery from the rhythmic conventions of lacquer painting, which also provided scroll motifs for inlaid bronzes and paintings on silk. Thus, there was an interaction between the various media of Han dynasty arts that accounts for their unity of style.
  </p>
  <p>
   <xref articleid="52837">
    Ming
   </xref>
   and
   <xref articleid="82155">
    Qing
   </xref>
   textiles fully display the Chinese love of pageantry, colour, and fine craftsmanship. Prominent among woven textile patterns are flowers and dragons against a background of geometric motifs that date to the late Zhou (1046–256
   <e type="smallcap">
    bce
   </e>
   ) and Han. Qing robes were basically of three types. The
   <e type="italic">
    chaofu
   </e>
   was a very elaborate court ceremonial dress; the emperor’s robe was adorned with the auspicious 12 symbols described in ancient ritual texts, while princes and high officials were allowed nine symbols or fewer according to rank. The
   <e type="italic">
    caifu
   </e>
   (“coloured dress”), or “dragon robe,” was a semiformal court dress in which the dominant element was the imperial five-clawed dragon (
   <e type="italic">
    long
   </e>
   ) or the four-clawed dragon (
   <e type="italic">
    mang
   </e>
   ). In spite of repeated sumptuary laws issued during the Ming and Qing, the five-clawed dragon was seldom reserved for objects of exclusively imperial use. Symbols used on the dragon robes also included the eight
   <xref articleid="105944">
    Buddhist
   </xref>
   symbols, symbols of the Daoist Eight Immortals (
   <xref articleid="57887">
    Baxian
   </xref>
   ), eight precious things, and other auspicious devices. “Mandarin squares” had been attached front and back to Ming official robes as symbols of civil and military rank and were adapted by the
   <xref articleid="50463">
    Manchus
   </xref>
   to their own distinctive dress.
  </p>
 </h1>
 <h1 id="h283189">
  <title>
   Elsewhere
  </title>
  <p>
   According to legend, about 140
   <e type="smallcap">
    bce
   </e>
   , sericulture as well as silk had spread overland from China to India. By the 2nd century
   <e type="smallcap">
    ce
   </e>
   India was shipping its own raw silk and silk cloth to Persia. (Japan, too, acquired and developed a thriving sericulture a few centuries later.)
  </p>
  <p>
   <assembly id="a216824" url="/assembly/view/216824">
    <title>
     Persian hunting carpet
    </title>
    <media mediaid="45313" type="image" url="/13/45313-004-D930008C.jpg"/>
    <caption>
     Detail of a Persian silk hunting carpet from Kāshān, Iran, 16th century, showing mounted huntsmen attacking a leopard; in the Österreichisches Museum für angewandte Kunst, Vienna.
    </caption>
    <credit>
     Courtesy of the Osterreichisches Museum Fur Angewandte Kunst, Vienna; photographs Eric Lessing - Magnum
    </credit>
   </assembly>
   <assemblyref assemblyid="a216824"/>
   Persia became a centre of silk trade between East and West under the
   <xref articleid="58588">
    Parthians
   </xref>
   (247
   <e type="smallcap">
    bce
   </e>
   –224
   <e type="smallcap">
    ce
   </e>
   ). Silk dyeing and weaving developed as crafts in Syria, Egypt, Greece, and Rome. The workers there used some raw silk from East Asia, but they derived most of their yarn by unraveling silk fabrics from the East. Silk culture largely remained a secret of Asia.
  </p>
  <p>
   <assembly id="a216828" url="/assembly/view/216828">
    <title>
     silkworm
    </title>
    <media mediaid="157438" type="image" url="/38/157438-004-85E97E96.jpg"/>
    <caption>
     Domesticated silkworms (
     <e type="italic">
      Bombyx
     </e>
     species) on mulberry leaves.
    </caption>
    <credit>
     © Roman Sigaev/Fotolia
    </credit>
   </assembly>
   <assemblyref assemblyid="a216828"/>
   Eventually a strong demand for the local production of raw silk arose in the Mediterranean area.
   <xref articleid="44214">
    Justinian I
   </xref>
   , Byzantine emperor from 527 to 565, persuaded two Persian monks who had lived in China to return there and smuggle silkworms to Constantinople (now Istanbul) in the hollows of their bamboo canes (
   <e type="italic">
    c.
   </e>
   550
   <e type="smallcap">
    ce
   </e>
   ). These few hardy silkworms were the beginning of all the varieties that stocked and supplied European sericulture until the 19th century.
  </p>
  <p>
   <assembly id="a22810" url="/assembly/view/22810">
    <title>
     silk
    </title>
    <media mediaid="30236" type="image" url="/36/30236-004-1D903BD6.jpg"/>
    <caption>
     Detail of handwoven Italian silk brocaded on silk with floral motif,
     <e type="italic">
      c.
     </e>
     1730–50.
    </caption>
    <credit>
     Courtesy of Scalamandre, New York City
    </credit>
   </assembly>
   <assemblyref assemblyid="a22810"/>
   Silk culture flourished in Europe for many centuries, especially in the Italian city-states and (from 1480) in France. In 1854, however, a devastating silkworm plague appeared.
   <xref articleid="108485">
    Louis Pasteur
   </xref>
   , who was asked to study the disease in 1865, discovered the cause and developed a means of control. The Italian industry recovered, but that of France never did. Meanwhile Japan was modernizing its methods of sericulture, and soon it was supplying a large portion of the world’s raw silk. During and after
   <xref articleid="110199">
    World War II
   </xref>
   the substitution of such man-made fibres as
   <xref articleid="56581">
    nylon
   </xref>
   in making hosiery and other garments greatly reduced the silk industry. Still, silk has remained an important luxury material and remains an important product of China, Japan, South Korea, and Thailand.
  </p>
 </h1>
 <copyright>
  Encyclopædia Britannica
 </copyright>
</article>