<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "syndication_xml.dtd">
<article articleid="69028" articletypeid="1" language="en_us" lastupdate="2021-Jul-01 01:22:05" url="/article/specific-gravity/69028" version="5">
 <title>
  specific gravity
 </title>
 <p>
  <assembly id="a152958" url="/assembly/view/152958">
   <title>
    hydrometer
   </title>
   <media mediaid="147316" type="image" url="/16/147316-004-C7335887.jpg"/>
   <caption>
    Hydrometer used to measure the specific gravity of wine.
   </caption>
   <credit>
    © BW Folsom/Shutterstock.com
   </credit>
  </assembly>
  <e type="bold">
   specific gravity
  </e>
  , also called
  <e type="bold">
   relative density
  </e>
  ,
  <assemblyref assemblyid="a152958"/>
  ratio of the
  <xref articleid="29953">
   density
  </xref>
  of a substance to that of a standard substance.
 </p>
 <p>
  The usual standard of comparison for
  <xref articleid="68592">
   solids
  </xref>
  and
  <xref articleid="110301">
   liquids
  </xref>
  is
  <xref articleid="76210">
   water
  </xref>
  at 4 °C (39.2 °F), which has a density of 1.0 kg per litre (62.4 pounds per cubic foot).
  <xref articleid="110302">
   Gases
  </xref>
  are commonly compared with dry
  <xref articleid="5193">
   air
  </xref>
  , which has a density of 1.29 grams per litre (1.29 ounces per cubic foot) under so-called standard conditions (0 °C and a pressure of 1
  <xref articleid="10118">
   standard atmosphere
  </xref>
  ). For example, liquid
  <xref articleid="52102">
   mercury
  </xref>
  has a density of 13.6 kg per litre; therefore, its specific gravity is 13.6. The gas
  <xref articleid="20249">
   carbon dioxide
  </xref>
  , which has a density of 1.976 grams per litre under standard conditions, has a specific gravity of 1.53 (= 1.976/1.29). Because it is the ratio of two quantities that have the same dimensions (mass per unit volume), specific gravity has no dimension.
 </p>
 <p>
  Buoyancy (the ability of an object to float in water or air) is intimately related to specific gravity. If a substance has specific gravity less than that of a
  <xref articleid="34667">
   fluid
  </xref>
  , it will float on that fluid:
  <xref articleid="1713">
   helium
  </xref>
  -filled balloons will rise in air,
  <xref articleid="110438">
   oil
  </xref>
  will form a slick on water, and
  <xref articleid="47492">
   lead
  </xref>
  will float on mercury. The specific gravity of a substance is characteristic; it is the same for different samples of a substance (if pure, the same in composition, and free from cavities or inclusions) and is used to help identify unknown substances. Specific gravity has many other applications: gemologists use it to distinguish similar
  <xref articleid="36349">
   gems
  </xref>
  ; chemists, to check on the progress of reactions and the concentration of solutions; and
  <xref articleid="110735">
   auto
  </xref>
  mechanics, to test
  <xref articleid="106044">
   battery
  </xref>
  fluid and
  <xref articleid="471763">
   antifreeze
  </xref>
  .
 </p>
 <p>
  Specific gravity is the basis of methods used throughout history to concentrate
  <xref articleid="57321">
   ores
  </xref>
  . Panning, jigging, shaking, spiral separation, and heavy-medium separation are among the methods that depend on differences in specific gravity to obtain concentrated ore. Specific gravity is highest in
  <xref articleid="109695">
   rocks
  </xref>
  rich in
  <xref articleid="42794">
   iron
  </xref>
  ,
  <xref articleid="50015">
   magnesium
  </xref>
  <xref articleid="57833">
   oxide
  </xref>
  , and the heavy
  <xref articleid="52266">
   metals
  </xref>
  and lowest in those rich in
  <xref articleid="5747">
   alkalies
  </xref>
  ,
  <xref articleid="67757">
   silica
  </xref>
  , and water.
 </p>
 <p>
  The ease with which specific gravity can be precisely determined leads to its widespread use in chemical science and technology; for example, determination of the specific gravity is part of the routine characterization of a new liquid compound. The specific gravity of most organic compounds containing only
  <xref articleid="20244">
   carbon
  </xref>
  ,
  <xref articleid="110604">
   hydrogen
  </xref>
  , and
  <xref articleid="57841">
   oxygen
  </xref>
  is less than one. Among the devices used to measure specific gravity are the Westphal balance, the pycnometer, and the
  <xref articleid="41745">
   hydrometer
  </xref>
  .
 </p>
 <signature>
  EB Editors
 </signature>
 <copyright>
  Encyclopædia Britannica
 </copyright>
</article>