<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "syndication_xml.dtd">
<article articleid="69705" articletypeid="1" language="en_us" lastupdate="2021-Jul-01 01:26:25" url="/article/still-life-painting/69705" version="3">
 <title>
  still-life painting
 </title>
 <p>
  <e type="bold">
   still-life painting
  </e>
  , depiction of inanimate objects for the sake of their qualities of form, colour, texture, and composition. Although decorative fresco murals and mosaics with still-life subjects occasionally appeared in antiquity, it was not until the Renaissance that still life emerged as an independent painting genre, rather than existing primarily as a subsidiary element in a composition. Early Netherlandish still-life paintings depicted skulls, candles, and hourglasses as allegories of mortality, or combined flowers and fruits of all seasons to symbolize nature’s cycle (
  <e type="italic">
   see
  </e>
  <xref articleid="74816">
   vanitas
  </xref>
  ). An interest in observing and then realistically representing the material details of the environment, the rise of a wealthy middle class who desired art works to decorate their homes, and an increasing demand for secular subjects in painting other than portraiture as a result of the prolonged effects of the Reformation—all were factors that contributed to the rise of still-life painting in the 16th and 17th centuries. The painting generally considered to be the first still life is a work by the Italian painter
  <xref articleid="13290">
   Jacopo de’Barbari
  </xref>
  painted 1504. The “golden age” of still-life painting occurred in the Lowlands during the 17th century.
 </p>
 <p>
  Among the most famous Dutch and Flemish painters who specialized in still-life subjects were
  <xref articleid="39784">
   Willem Heda
  </xref>
  ,
  <xref articleid="44393">
   Willem Kalf
  </xref>
  ,
  <xref articleid="35739">
   Jan Fyt
  </xref>
  ,
  <xref articleid="68414">
   Frans Snyders
  </xref>
  ,
  <xref articleid="104973">
   Jan Weenix
  </xref>
  ,
  <xref articleid="40922">
   Melchior d’Hondecoeter
  </xref>
  ,
  <xref articleid="41665">
   Jan van Huysum
  </xref>
  , and the
  <xref articleid="39800">
   de Heem
  </xref>
  family. From the 18th century until the rise of Nonobjective painting after World War II, France became the centre of still-life painting. Most major artists who at some time resided there during this 250-year period executed still lifes—e.g.,
  <xref articleid="22511">
   J.-B.-S. Chardin
  </xref>
  ,
  <xref articleid="29782">
   Eugène Delacroix
  </xref>
  ,
  <xref articleid="26591">
   Gustave Courbet
  </xref>
  ,
  <xref articleid="50506">
   Édouard Manet
  </xref>
  ,
  <xref articleid="53339">
   Claude Monet
  </xref>
  ,
  <xref articleid="22192">
   Paul Cézanne
  </xref>
  ,
  <xref articleid="37197">
   Vincent van Gogh
  </xref>
  ,
  <xref articleid="108524">
   Pablo Picasso
  </xref>
  ,
  <xref articleid="16239">
   Georges Braque
  </xref>
  ,
  <xref articleid="51397">
   Henri Matisse
  </xref>
  , and
  <xref articleid="80621">
   Pierre Bonnard.
  </xref>
 </p>
 <copyright>
  Encyclopædia Britannica
 </copyright>
</article>