<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "syndication_xml.dtd">
<article articleid="70362" articletypeid="1" language="en_us" lastupdate="2021-Jul-01 01:30:07" url="/article/sundial/70362" version="6">
 <title>
  sundial
 </title>
 <p>
  <e type="bold">
   sundial
  </e>
  , the earliest type of timekeeping device, which indicates the time of day by the position of the shadow of some object exposed to the sun’s rays. As the day progresses, the sun moves across the sky, causing the shadow of the object to move and indicating the passage of time.
 </p>
 <p>
  The first device for indicating the time of day was probably the gnomon, dating from about 3500
  <e type="smallcap">
   bce
  </e>
  . It consisted of a vertical stick or pillar, and the length of the shadow it cast gave an indication of the time of day. By the 8th century
  <e type="smallcap">
   bce
  </e>
  more-precise devices were in use. The earliest known sundial still preserved is an Egyptian shadow clock of green schist dating at least from this period. The shadow clock consists of a straight base with a raised crosspiece at one end. The base, on which is inscribed a scale of six time divisions, is placed in an east-west direction with the crosspiece at the east end in the morning and at the west end in the afternoon. The shadow of the crosspiece on this base indicates the time. Clocks of this kind were still in use in modern times in parts of Egypt.
 </p>
 <p>
  Another early device was the hemispherical sundial, or hemicycle, attributed to the Greek astronomer
  <xref articleid="9438">
   Aristarchus of Samos
  </xref>
  about 280
  <e type="smallcap">
   bce
  </e>
  . Made of stone or wood, the instrument consisted of a cubical block into which a hemispherical opening was cut. To this block a pointer or style was fixed with one end at the centre of the hemispherical space. The path traveled by the tip of the pointer’s shadow during the day was, approximately, a circular arc. The length and position of the arc varied according to the seasons, so an appropriate number of arcs was inscribed on the internal surface of the hemisphere. Each arc was divided into 12 equal divisions, and each day, reckoned from sunrise to sunset, therefore had 12 equal intervals, or “hours.” Because the length of the day varied according to the season, these hours likewise varied in length from season to season and even from day to day and were consequently known as seasonal hours. Aristarchus’s sundial was widely used for many centuries and, according to the Arab astronomer
  <xref articleid="13772">
   al-Battānī
  </xref>
  (
  <e type="italic">
   c.
  </e>
  858–929
  <e type="smallcap">
   ce
  </e>
  ), was still in use in Muslim countries during the 10th century. The Babylonian astronomer
  <xref articleid="78876">
   Berosus
  </xref>
  (flourished
  <e type="italic">
   c.
  </e>
  290
  <e type="smallcap">
   bce
  </e>
  ) invented a variant of this sundial by cutting away the part of the spherical surface south of the circular arc traced by the shadow tip on the longest day of the year.
 </p>
 <p>
  The Greeks, with their geometrical prowess, developed and constructed sundials of considerable complexity. For instance, the
  <xref articleid="77180">
   Tower of the Winds
  </xref>
  in
  <xref articleid="109386">
   Athens
  </xref>
  , octagonal in shape and dating from about 100
  <e type="smallcap">
   bce
  </e>
  , contains eight planar sundials facing various cardinal points of the compass. Moreover, numerous ancient Greek sundials feature conical surfaces cut into stone blocks in which the axis of the cone (which contains the tip of the gnomon) is parallel to the polar axis of Earth. In general, it appears that the Greeks constructed instruments with either vertical, horizontal, or inclined dials, indicating time in seasonal hours.
 </p>
 <p>
  As with the Greeks, the Romans’ sundials employed seasonal hours. In 290
  <e type="smallcap">
   bce
  </e>
  the first sundial, which had been captured from the Samnites, was set up in Rome; the first sundial actually designed for the city was not built until almost 164
  <e type="smallcap">
   bce
  </e>
  . In his great work
  <e type="italic">
   De architectura
  </e>
  , the Roman architect and engineer
  <xref articleid="75580">
   Vitruvius
  </xref>
  (flourished 1st century
  <e type="smallcap">
   bce
  </e>
  ) named many types of sundials, some of which were portable.
 </p>
 <p>
  The medieval Muslims were especially interested in sundials, for these provided means for determining the proper times for prayer. Indeed, most Muslim sundials contain lines indicating these times, and on a few they are the only lines at all. Although the Muslims learned the basic principles of designing sundials from the Greeks, they increased the variety of designs available through the use of
  <xref articleid="108709">
   trigonometry
  </xref>
  . For example, they invented the now-ubiquitous sundial with the gnomon parallel to the polar axis of Earth. At the beginning of the 13th century
  <e type="smallcap">
   ce
  </e>
  , Abū al-Ḥasan al-Marrakushi wrote on the construction of hour lines on cylindrical, conical, and other types of sundials and is credited with introducing equal hours, at least for astronomical purposes.
 </p>
 <p>
  With the advent of mechanical clocks in the early 14th century, sundials with equal hours gradually came into general use in Europe, and until the 19th century sundials were still used to reset mechanical clocks.
 </p>
 <signature>
  EB Editors
 </signature>
 <h1 id="h225348">
  <title>
   Bibliography
  </title>
  <p>
   <e type="smallcap">
    Albert E. Waugh
   </e>
   ,
   <e type="italic">
    Sundials: Their Theory and Construction
   </e>
   (1973), is the standard reference for the theory and construction of all major types of sundials.
   <e type="smallcap">
    Sharon L. Gibbs
   </e>
   ,
   <e type="italic">
    Greek and Roman Sundials
   </e>
   (1976), covers the history of Greek and Roman sundials.
   <e type="smallcap">
    D.A. King
   </e>
   , “Mizwala,” in
   <e type="italic">
    The Encyclopaedia of Islam
   </e>
   , new ed., vol. 7, fascicules 117–118 (1991), pp. 210–211, covers the history of Islamic sundials.
   <e type="smallcap">
    Steven A. Lloyd
   </e>
   ,
   <e type="italic">
    Ivory Diptych Sundials, 1570–1750
   </e>
   (1992), is a beautiful work (physically and intellectually) on early European sundials with an extensive bibliography.
  </p>
 </h1>
 <copyright>
  Encyclopædia Britannica
 </copyright>
</article>