<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "syndication_xml.dtd">
<article articleid="70440" articletypeid="1" language="en_us" lastupdate="2021-Jul-01 01:30:42" url="/article/surface-tension/70440" version="8">
 <title>
  surface tension
 </title>
 <p>
  <assembly id="a159381" url="/assembly/view/159381">
   <title>
    Compare the surface tensions of different liquids such as water, alcohol, mercury, and soap bubbles
   </title>
   <media mediaid="151076" thumburl="/76/151076-049-83CF7086.jpg" type="video" url=""/>
   <caption>
    Explanation of surface tension.
   </caption>
   <credit>
    Encyclopædia Britannica, Inc.
   </credit>
  </assembly>
  <assembly id="a162354" url="/assembly/view/162354">
   <title>
    surface tension; soap bubbles
   </title>
   <media mediaid="153119" type="image" url="/19/153119-004-AF31413D.jpg"/>
   <caption>
    Soap bubbles demonstrate the property of surface tension.
   </caption>
   <credit>
    © HP_Photo/Fotolia
   </credit>
  </assembly>
  <e type="bold">
   surface tension
  </e>
  ,
  <assemblyref assemblyid="a159381"/>
  <assemblyref assemblyid="a162354"/>
  property of a
  <xref articleid="110301">
   liquid
  </xref>
  surface displayed by its acting as if it were a stretched elastic membrane. This phenomenon can be observed in the nearly spherical shape of small drops of liquids and of soap bubbles. Because of this property, certain
  <xref articleid="105953">
   insects
  </xref>
  can stand on the surface of
  <xref articleid="76210">
   water
  </xref>
  . A razor blade also can be supported by the surface tension of water. The razor blade is not floating: if pushed through the surface, it sinks through the water.
 </p>
 <p>
  Surface tension depends mainly upon the
  <xref articleid="34834">
   forces
  </xref>
  of attraction between the particles within the given liquid and also upon the
  <xref articleid="110302">
   gas
  </xref>
  ,
  <xref articleid="68592">
   solid
  </xref>
  , or liquid in contact with it. The
  <xref articleid="53247">
   molecules
  </xref>
  in a drop of water, for example, attract each other weakly. Water molecules well inside the drop may be thought of as being attracted equally in all directions by the surrounding molecules. However, if surface molecules could be displaced slightly outward from the surface, they would be attracted back by the nearby molecules. The energy responsible for the phenomenon of surface tension may be thought of as approximately equivalent to the
  <xref articleid="77472">
   work
  </xref>
  or
  <xref articleid="32627">
   energy
  </xref>
  required to remove the surface layer of molecules in a unit area. Surface tension may be expressed, therefore, in units of energy (
  <xref articleid="44023">
   joules
  </xref>
  ) per unit area (square metres). Water has a surface tension of 0.07275 joule per square metre at 20 °C (68 °F). In comparison,
  <xref articleid="57352">
   organic
  </xref>
  liquids, such as
  <xref articleid="78683">
   benzene
  </xref>
  and
  <xref articleid="5513">
   alcohols
  </xref>
  , have lower surface tensions, whereas
  <xref articleid="52102">
   mercury
  </xref>
  has a higher surface tension. An increase in
  <xref articleid="71632">
   temperature
  </xref>
  lowers the net force of attraction among molecules and hence decreases surface tension.
 </p>
 <p>
  Surface tension is also viewed as the result of forces acting in the plane of the surface and tending to minimize its area. On this basis, surface tension is often expressed as an amount of force exerted in the surface perpendicular to a line of unit length. The unit then is
  <xref articleid="55617">
   newtons
  </xref>
  per metre, which is equivalent to joules per square metre.
 </p>
 <signature>
  EB Editors
 </signature>
 <copyright>
  Encyclopædia Britannica
 </copyright>
</article>