<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "syndication_xml.dtd">
<article articleid="70722" articletypeid="1" language="en_us" lastupdate="2021-Jul-01 01:32:34" url="/article/symmetry/70722" version="6">
 <title>
  symmetry
 </title>
 <p>
  <assembly id="a254642" url="/assembly/view/254642">
   <title>
    biological symmetry
   </title>
   <media mediaid="195018" type="image" url="/18/195018-004-12A2E6B8.jpg"/>
   <caption>
    Comparing two main types of body plans in animals: radial symmetry and bilateral symmetry.
   </caption>
   <credit>
    Encyclopædia Britannica, Inc.
   </credit>
  </assembly>
  <e type="bold">
   symmetry
  </e>
  ,
  <assemblyref assemblyid="a254642"/>
  in
  <xref articleid="110576">
   biology
  </xref>
  , the repetition of the parts in an animal or plant in an orderly fashion. Specifically, symmetry refers to a correspondence of body parts, in size, shape, and relative position, on opposite sides of a dividing line or distributed around a central point or axis. With the exception of radial symmetry, external form has little relation to internal anatomy, since animals of very different anatomical construction may have the same type of symmetry.
 </p>
 <h1 id="h347374">
  <title>
   Symmetry in animals
  </title>
  <p>
   Certain animals, particularly most
   <xref articleid="110257">
    sponges
   </xref>
   and the
   <xref articleid="7216">
    ameboid protozoans
   </xref>
   , lack symmetry, having either an irregular shape different for each individual or else one undergoing constant changes of form. The vast majority of animals, however, exhibit a definite symmetrical form. Four such patterns of symmetry occur among animals: spherical, radial, biradial, and bilateral.
  </p>
  <p>
   In spherical symmetry, illustrated only by the protozoan groups Radiolaria and Heliozoia, the body has the shape of a sphere and the parts are arranged concentrically around or radiate from the centre of the sphere. Such an animal has no ends or sides, and any plane passing through the centre will divide the animal into equivalent halves. The spherical type of symmetry is possible only in minute animals of simple internal construction, since in spheres the interior mass is large relative to the surface area and becomes too large for efficient functioning with increase in size and complexity.
  </p>
  <p>
   <assembly id="a254643" url="/assembly/view/254643">
    <title>
     radial symmetry
    </title>
    <media mediaid="203187" type="image" url="/87/203187-004-723FFE45.jpg"/>
    <caption>
     The radially symmetrical body of a sea urchin.
    </caption>
    <credit>
     © Jmaentz/Dreamstime.com
    </credit>
   </assembly>
   <assembly id="a254644" url="/assembly/view/254644">
    <title>
     sun coral
    </title>
    <media mediaid="202527" type="image" url="/27/202527-004-F25E2621.jpg"/>
    <caption>
     Sun coral, or sun polyps (
     <e type="italic">
      Tubastraea faulkneri
     </e>
     ), in the Lembeh Strait, Indonesia.
    </caption>
    <credit>
     © ifish—E+/Getty Images
    </credit>
   </assembly>
   <assembly id="a254645" url="/assembly/view/254645">
    <title>
     moon jellyfish
    </title>
    <media mediaid="195350" type="image" url="/50/195350-004-BA455BAA.jpg"/>
    <caption>
     Moon jellyfish floating in the sea.
    </caption>
    <credit>
     © Misad/Dreamstime.com
    </credit>
   </assembly>
   <assemblyref assemblyid="a254643"/>
   <assemblyref assemblyid="a254644"/>
   <assemblyref assemblyid="a254645"/>
   In radial symmetry the body has the general form of a short or long cylinder or bowl, with a central axis from which the body parts radiate or along which they are arranged in regular fashion. The main axis is heteropolar—i.e., with unlike ends, one of which bears the mouth and is termed the oral, or anterior, end, and the other of which, called the aboral, or posterior, end, forms the rear end of the animal and may bear the
   <xref articleid="7936">
    anus
   </xref>
   . The main axis is hence termed the oral-aboral, or anteroposterior, axis. Except in animals having an odd number of parts arranged in circular fashion (as in the five-armed
   <xref articleid="69454">
    sea stars
   </xref>
   ), any plane passing through this axis will divide the animal into symmetrical halves. Animals having three, five, seven, etc., parts in a circle have symmetry that may be referred to, respectively, as three-rayed, five-rayed, seven-rayed, etc.; only certain planes through the axis will divide such animals into symmetrical halves. Radial symmetry is found in the
   <xref articleid="110240">
    cnidarians
   </xref>
   (including
   <xref articleid="43510">
    jellyfish
   </xref>
   ,
   <xref articleid="66429">
    sea anemones
   </xref>
   , and
   <xref articleid="26227">
    coral
   </xref>
   ) and
   <xref articleid="110246">
    echinoderms
   </xref>
   (such as
   <xref articleid="66461">
    sea urchins
   </xref>
   ,
   <xref articleid="16542">
    brittle stars
   </xref>
   , and
   <xref articleid="69454">
    sea stars
   </xref>
   ).
  </p>
  <p>
   <assembly id="a146484" url="/assembly/view/146484">
    <title>
     ctenophore
    </title>
    <media mediaid="143376" type="image" url="/76/143376-004-0574B09C.jpg"/>
    <caption>
     Ctenophore.
    </caption>
    <credit>
     R. Griswold/OAR/National Undersea Research Program (NURP); National Marine Fisheries Service/NOAA (Image ID: nur01003)
    </credit>
   </assembly>
   <assemblyref assemblyid="a146484"/>
   In biradial symmetry, in addition to the anteroposterior axis, there are also two other axes or planes of symmetry at right angles to it and to each other: the sagittal, or median vertical-longitudinal, and transverse, or cross, axes. Such an animal therefore not only has two ends but also has two pairs of symmetrical sides. There are but two planes of symmetry in a biradial animal, one passing through the anteroposterior and sagittal axes and the other through the anteroposterior and transverse axes. Biradial symmetry occurs in the
   <xref articleid="28096">
    comb jellies
   </xref>
   .
  </p>
  <p>
   <assembly id="a254646" url="/assembly/view/254646">
    <title>
     bilateral symmetry
    </title>
    <media mediaid="217284" type="image" url="/84/217284-004-E003C3DA.jpg"/>
    <caption>
     Male moose in Jackson, Wyoming.
    </caption>
    <credit>
     © Troy Harrison—Moment/Getty Images
    </credit>
   </assembly>
   <assembly id="a254647" url="/assembly/view/254647">
    <title>
     bilateral symmetry
    </title>
    <media mediaid="173594" type="image" url="/94/173594-004-DFCD5237.jpg"/>
    <caption>
     <e type="italic">
      Heliconius
     </e>
     butterfly in South America. The body has one pair of symmetrical sides.
    </caption>
    <credit>
     AdstockRF
    </credit>
   </assembly>
   <assemblyref assemblyid="a254646"/>
   <assemblyref assemblyid="a254647"/>
   In bilateral symmetry there are the same three axes as in biradial symmetry but only one pair of symmetrical sides, the lateral sides, since the other two sides, called the dorsal (back) and ventral (belly) surfaces, are unlike. Thus, only one plane of symmetry will divide a bilateral animal into symmetrical halves, the median longitudinal, or sagittal, plane. Bilateral symmetry is characteristic of the vast majority of animals, including
   <xref articleid="105953">
    insects
   </xref>
   ,
   <xref articleid="111049">
    fishes
   </xref>
   ,
   <xref articleid="110233">
    amphibians
   </xref>
   ,
   <xref articleid="110251">
    reptiles
   </xref>
   ,
   <xref articleid="105921">
    birds
   </xref>
   ,
   <xref articleid="105972">
    mammals
   </xref>
   , and most
   <xref articleid="110242">
    crustaceans
   </xref>
   .
  </p>
 </h1>
 <h1 id="h347375">
  <title>
   Symmetry in flowers
  </title>
  <p>
   <assembly id="a8442" url="/assembly/view/8442">
    <title>
     radial symmetry
    </title>
    <media mediaid="5626" type="image" url="/26/5626-004-CE35FD03.jpg"/>
    <caption>
     The regular (radially symmetric) bisexual flowers of sweetbrier, or eglantine (
     <e type="italic">
      Rosa eglanteria
     </e>
     ), generally develop as single flowers with floral parts in multiples of five. Five broad petals and multiple stamens line the edge of the hypanthium (floral tube) from which many pistils arise.
    </caption>
    <credit>
     E.S. Ross
    </credit>
   </assembly>
   <assemblyref assemblyid="a8442"/>
   The concept of symmetry is also applied in
   <xref articleid="110585">
    botany
   </xref>
   . A
   <xref articleid="34656">
    flower
   </xref>
   is considered symmetrical when each whorl consists of an equal number of parts or when the parts of any one whorl are multiples of that preceding it. Thus, a symmetrical flower may have five sepals, five petals, five
   <xref articleid="473383">
    stamens
   </xref>
   , and five
   <xref articleid="471977">
    carpels
   </xref>
   , or the number of any of these parts may be a multiple of five.
  </p>
  <p>
   <assembly id="a254648" url="/assembly/view/254648">
    <title>
     pentamerous flower
    </title>
    <media mediaid="198750" type="image" url="/50/198750-004-AA031E1D.jpg"/>
    <caption>
     The floral parts of
     <e type="italic">
      Fuchsia
     </e>
     are arranged in multiples of four. An inferior ovary at the base of the flower precedes the floral tube formed by four sepals and four petals. Eight stamens of unequal length and a prominent four-lobed stigma emanate from the centre of the flower.
    </caption>
    <credit>
     © Porcospin0tumbrl/Dreamstime.com
    </credit>
   </assembly>
   <assemblyref assemblyid="a254648"/>
   The number of parts in the pistillate (female) whorl is frequently not in conformity with that in the other whorls, but in such cases the flower is still called symmetrical, provided that the other whorls are normal. A flower in which the parts are in twos is dimerous; in threes, fours, or fives, trimerous, tetramerous, or pentamerous, respectively. Trimerous symmetry is the rule in the monocotyledons, pentamerous the most common in the dicotyledons, although dimerous and tetramerous flowers also occur in the latter group.
  </p>
  <p>
   <assembly id="a254650" url="/assembly/view/254650">
    <title>
     radial symmetry
    </title>
    <media mediaid="183806" type="image" url="/06/183806-004-4C8B649D.jpg"/>
    <caption>
     Actinomorphic (radially symmetric) flowers of the American pasqueflower (
     <e type="italic">
      Pulsatilla hirsutissima
     </e>
     ).
    </caption>
    <credit>
     © Iryna Rasko/Shutterstock.com
    </credit>
   </assembly>
   <assemblyref assemblyid="a254650"/>
   When the different members of each whorl are alike, the flower is regular and is referred to as actinomorphic, or radially symmetrical, as in the
   <xref articleid="59530">
    petunia
   </xref>
   ,
   <xref articleid="18338">
    buttercup
   </xref>
   , and wild rose. Differences in size or shape of the parts of a whorl make the flower irregular (as in the
   <xref articleid="20001">
    canna
   </xref>
   and Asiatic
   <xref articleid="29564">
    dayflower
   </xref>
   ). When a flower can be divided by a single plane into two equal parts, it is zygomorphic, or bilaterally symmetrical, as in the
   <xref articleid="68361">
    snapdragon
   </xref>
   ,
   <xref articleid="111119">
    orchid
   </xref>
   , and
   <xref articleid="70626">
    sweet pea
   </xref>
   .
  </p>
 </h1>
 <signature>
  EB Editors
 </signature>
 <copyright>
  Encyclopædia Britannica
 </copyright>
</article>