<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "syndication_xml.dtd">
<article articleid="70723" articletypeid="1" language="en_us" lastupdate="2021-Jul-01 01:32:35" url="/article/symmetry/70723" version="3">
 <title>
  symmetry
 </title>
 <p>
  <e type="bold">
   symmetry
  </e>
  , in crystallography, fundamental property of the orderly arrangements of atoms found in
  <xref articleid="110297">
   crystalline
  </xref>
  <xref articleid="68592">
   solids
  </xref>
  . Each arrangement of
  <xref articleid="110411">
   atoms
  </xref>
  has a certain number of elements of symmetry; i.e., changes in the orientation of the arrangement of atoms seem to leave the atoms unmoved. One such element of symmetry is rotation; other elements are translation, reflection, and inversion. The elements of symmetry present in a particular crystalline solid determine its shape and affect its physical properties.
 </p>
 <p>
  Translations involve displacement of the crystal in a direction that replaces each atom by one of its identical neighbours, so that the atoms seem unmoved. Rotations turn the crystal around an axis of symmetry passing through the crystal; the only rotations compatible with translational symmetry move the crystal through an angle of 360° divided by
  <e type="italic">
   n,
  </e>
  with
  <e type="italic">
   n
  </e>
  equal to 1, 2, 3, 4, or 6. Reflections exchange the parts of the crystal on the two sides of a
  <xref articleid="60295">
   plane
  </xref>
  of symmetry (mirror plane) within the solid. Inversions move every atom to another position in the crystal; the old and new positions of the atom lie upon a line, at the middle of which is the centre of inversion. So-called improper rotations are rotations followed by reflections (known as rotoreflections) or rotations followed by inversions (called rotoinversions).
 </p>
 <p>
  <assembly id="a149097" url="/assembly/view/149097">
   <title>
    crystal systems
   </title>
   <media mediaid="105673" type="image" url="/73/105673-004-055DB233.jpg"/>
   <caption>
    The seven primitive crystal systems.
   </caption>
   <credit>
    Encyclopædia Britannica, Inc.
   </credit>
  </assembly>
  <assemblyref assemblyid="a149097"/>
  A crystal can be classified according to its elements of symmetry; for example, it may belong to one of 230 space groups, 32 point groups, 14 Bravais lattices, and 7 crystal systems. A crystal can be represented diagrammatically by an orderly stacking of unit cells; the shape of the unit cell determines which of the seven crystal systems the crystal belongs to. Unit cells of the same shape may have points (each representing an atom or a group of atoms) at their centres or on their faces, in addition to those at their corners. These additional lattice points divide the 7 crystal systems into 14 Bravais lattices; the Bravais lattices are subdivided into 32 crystal classes, or point groups. Each point group corresponds to one of the possible combinations of rotations, reflections, inversions, and improper rotations; with the inclusion of translational elements, 230 space groups are produced.
 </p>
 <copyright>
  Encyclopædia Britannica
 </copyright>
</article>