<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "syndication_xml.dtd">
<article articleid="71360" articletypeid="1" language="en_us" lastupdate="2021-Jul-01 01:36:09" url="/article/Tasmanian-devil/71360" version="10">
 <title>
  Tasmanian devil
 </title>
 <p>
  <assembly id="a35640" url="/assembly/view/35640">
   <title>
    Tasmanian devil (
    <e type="italic">
     Sarcophilus harrisii
    </e>
    )
   </title>
   <media mediaid="43069" type="image" url="/69/43069-004-C2BC21D2.jpg"/>
   <caption>
    Tasmanian devils (
    <e type="italic">
     Sarcophilus harrisii
    </e>
    ) are stocky carnivorous marsupials with heavy forequarters, weak hindquarters, and a large squarish head.
   </caption>
   <credit>
    John Yates/Shostal Associates
   </credit>
  </assembly>
  <e type="bold">
   Tasmanian devil
  </e>
  , (
  <e type="italic">
   Sarcophilus harrisii
  </e>
  ),
  <assemblyref assemblyid="a35640"/>
  stocky carnivorous
  <xref articleid="105974">
   marsupial
  </xref>
  with heavy forequarters, weak hindquarters, and a large squarish head. The Tasmanian devil is named for the Australian island-state of
  <xref articleid="110551">
   Tasmania
  </xref>
  , its only native habitat. Vaguely bearlike in appearance and weighing up to 12 kg (26 pounds), it is 50 to 80 cm (20 to 31 inches) long and has a bushy tail about half that length. The coat is mainly black, and there is a whitish breast mark; sometimes the rump and sides are white-marked as well. Gaping jaws and strong teeth, along with its husky snarl and often bad temper, result in its devilish expression. It is mainly a scavenger, feeding on carrion such as roadkill and dead sheep. The larvae of certain beetles are its major source of live food, but it has been known to attack poultry.
 </p>
 <p>
  <assembly id="a249796" url="/assembly/view/249796">
   <title>
    Tasmanian devil (
    <e type="italic">
     Sarcophilus harrisii
    </e>
    )
   </title>
   <media mediaid="192134" type="image" url="/34/192134-004-D0136483.jpg"/>
   <caption>
    Tasmanian devils are related to quolls (catlike Australian marsupials, also called native cats); both are classified in the family Dasyuridae.
   </caption>
   <credit>
    © Drewfitzgibbon/Dreamstime.com
   </credit>
  </assembly>
  <assemblyref assemblyid="a249796"/>
  Tasmanian devils are related to quolls (catlike Australian marsupials, also called
  <xref articleid="55030">
   native cats
  </xref>
  ); both are classified in the family
  <xref articleid="29422">
   Dasyuridae
  </xref>
  . The teeth and jaws of Tasmanian devils are in many respects developed like those of a
  <xref articleid="41761">
   hyena
  </xref>
  . The pouch, when relaxed, opens backward, but, when the muscles are contracted to close it, the opening is central. During the breeding season, 20 or more eggs may be released, but most of these fail to develop. In most cases just four young are produced after a gestation period of about three weeks; these remain in the pouch for about five months. Overall, female offspring outnumber males about two to one.
 </p>
 <p>
  The Tasmanian devil became extinct on the
  <xref articleid="110544">
   Australian mainland
  </xref>
  thousands of years ago, possibly following the introduction of the
  <xref articleid="30501">
   dingo
  </xref>
  . In 1996 the number of Tasmanian devils living on Tasmania was estimated to be more than 150,000. From 1996 to 2007, however, this figure dwindled by more than 50 percent, and the adult population was thought to number between only 10,000 and 25,000.
 </p>
 <p>
  Since 1996 the Tasmanian devils living on Tasmania have been threatened by a contagious cancer called devil facial tumour disease (DFTD), which produces large, often grotesque
  <xref articleid="73749">
   tumours
  </xref>
  around the head and mouth. The tumours grow large enough to interfere with the animal’s ability to eat, resulting in starvation. This, in combination with the deleterious physiological effects of the
  <xref articleid="106118">
   cancer
  </xref>
  , leads to death, usually within several months of developing the disease. The origin and cause of the cancer is still of some debate; however, scientists speculate that it is caused by a unique line of infectious cells derived from Tasmanian devils and that the cells are transmitted when the animals bite one another, such as during mating battles or when scavenging for food. The Tasmanian devil’s
  <xref articleid="109569">
   immune system
  </xref>
  does not recognize the cancer cells as foreign and therefore does not attempt to kill them. Quarantine of healthy Tasmanian devil populations, captive breeding programs, and establishment of healthy populations on nearby islands are several ways in which scientists hope to save the Tasmanian devil from extinction, and in 2020 Australian wildlife officials began the first step of reintroducing the Tasmanian devil to the mainland by transferring about 30 healthy animals to a wildlife reserve in New South Wales. The Tasmanian devil was listed as an
  <xref articleid="32604">
   endangered species
  </xref>
  by Tasmanian government officials in May 2008.
 </p>
 <signature>
  EB Editors
 </signature>
 <copyright>
  Encyclopædia Britannica
 </copyright>
</article>