<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "syndication_xml.dtd">
<article articleid="71632" articletypeid="1" language="en_us" lastupdate="2021-Jul-01 01:37:47" url="/article/temperature/71632" version="9">
 <title>
  temperature
 </title>
 <p>
  <assembly id="a128329" url="/assembly/view/128329">
   <title>
    thermometer
   </title>
   <media mediaid="131919" type="image" url="/19/131919-004-41C68699.jpg"/>
   <caption>
    Most modern thermometers are graduated with both the Celsius temperature scale and the Fahrenheit temperature scale.
   </caption>
   <credit>
    © Myotis/Shutterstock.com
   </credit>
  </assembly>
  <e type="bold">
   temperature
  </e>
  ,
  <assemblyref assemblyid="a128329"/>
  measure of hotness or coldness expressed in terms of any of several arbitrary scales and indicating the direction in which
  <xref articleid="39732">
   heat
  </xref>
  <xref articleid="32627">
   energy
  </xref>
  will spontaneously flow—i.e., from a hotter body (one at a higher temperature) to a colder body (one at a lower temperature). Temperature is not the equivalent of the energy of a
  <xref articleid="108582">
   thermodynamic system
  </xref>
  ; e.g., a burning match is at a much higher temperature than an
  <xref articleid="108440">
   iceberg
  </xref>
  , but the total heat energy contained in an iceberg is much greater than the energy contained in a match. Temperature, similar to
  <xref articleid="61303">
   pressure
  </xref>
  or
  <xref articleid="29953">
   density
  </xref>
  , is called an intensive property—one that is independent of the quantity of matter being considered—as distinguished from extensive properties, such as
  <xref articleid="51285">
   mass
  </xref>
  or volume.
 </p>
 <p>
  <assembly id="a238132" url="/assembly/view/238132">
   <title>
    temperature scales
   </title>
   <media mediaid="196308" type="image" url="/08/196308-004-EC989E66.jpg"/>
   <caption>
    Standard and absolute temperature scales.
   </caption>
   <credit>
    Encyclopædia Britannica, Inc./Patrick O'Neill Riley
   </credit>
  </assembly>
  <assemblyref assemblyid="a238132"/>
  Three temperature scales are in general use today. The
  <xref articleid="33563">
   Fahrenheit (°F) temperature scale
  </xref>
  is used in the United States and a few other English-speaking countries. The
  <xref articleid="22033">
   Celsius (°C) temperature scale
  </xref>
  is standard in virtually all countries that have adopted the
  <xref articleid="52355">
   metric system
  </xref>
  of measurement, and it is widely used in the sciences. The
  <xref articleid="45037">
   Kelvin (K) scale
  </xref>
  , an absolute temperature scale (obtained by shifting the Celsius scale by −273.15° so that
  <xref articleid="3400">
   absolute zero
  </xref>
  coincides with 0 K), is recognized as the international standard for scientific temperature measurement.
 </p>
 <p>
  In certain fields of engineering, another absolute temperature scale, the Rankine scale (
  <e type="italic">
   see
  </e>
  <xref articleid="62685">
   William Rankine
  </xref>
  ), is preferred over the Kelvin scale. Its unit of measure—the degree Rankine (°R)—equals the Fahrenheit degree, as the kelvin equals one Celsius degree.
 </p>
 <p>
  The
  <xref articleid="62881">
   Réaumur (°Re) temperature scale
  </xref>
  (or octogesimal division) was widely used in parts of Europe in the 18th and 19th centuries; it later was used primarily to measure the temperature of mixtures during brewing, of syrups in the production of certain food products, and of
  <xref articleid="52683">
   milk
  </xref>
  during cheese making.
 </p>
 <copyright>
  Encyclopædia Britannica
 </copyright>
</article>