<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "syndication_xml.dtd">
<article articleid="72265" articletypeid="1" language="en_us" lastupdate="2021-Jul-01 01:42:53" url="/article/Thousand-and-One-Nights-The/72265" version="10">
 <title>
  The Thousand and One Nights
 </title>
 <p>
  <assembly id="a120896" url="/assembly/view/120896">
   <title>
    Aladdin
   </title>
   <media mediaid="126393" type="image" url="/93/126393-004-B4D3A1B7.jpg"/>
   <caption>
    <e type="italic">
     Aladdin Saluted Her with Joy
    </e>
    , illustration by Virginia Frances Sterrett from a 1928 edition of
    <e type="italic">
     The Arabian Nights
    </e>
    .
   </caption>
   <credit/>
  </assembly>
  <e type="bold">
   The Thousand and One Nights
  </e>
  , also called
  <e type="bold">
   The Arabian Nights
  </e>
  , Arabic
  <e type="bold">
   Alf laylah wa laylah
  </e>
  ,
  <assemblyref assemblyid="a120896"/>
  collection of largely Middle Eastern and Indian stories of uncertain date and authorship. Its tales of
  <xref articleid="5330">
   Aladdin
  </xref>
  ,
  <xref articleid="483770">
   Ali Baba
  </xref>
  , and
  <xref articleid="67902">
   Sindbad the Sailor
  </xref>
  have almost become part of Western
  <xref articleid="34758">
   folklore
  </xref>
  , though these were added to the collection only in the 18th century in European adaptations.
 </p>
 <p>
  <assembly id="a254116" url="/assembly/view/254116">
   <title>
    Shahrazad
   </title>
   <media mediaid="222396" type="image" url="/96/222396-004-5F352F4A.jpg"/>
   <caption>
    Shahrazad (Scheherazade), illustration by Edmund Dulac from a 1911 edition of
    <e type="italic">
     The Thousand and One Nights
    </e>
    .
   </caption>
   <credit>
    Gianni Dagli Orti/Shutterstock.com
   </credit>
  </assembly>
  <assemblyref assemblyid="a254116"/>
  As in much medieval European literature, the stories—
  <xref articleid="33600">
   fairy tales
  </xref>
  ,
  <xref articleid="110451">
   romances
  </xref>
  ,
  <xref articleid="47634">
   legends
  </xref>
  ,
  <xref articleid="110449" refid="h50898">
   fables
  </xref>
  ,
  <xref articleid="110449" refid="h50901">
   parables
  </xref>
  , anecdotes, and exotic or realistic adventures—are set within a
  <xref articleid="35094">
   frame story
  </xref>
  . Its scene is
  <xref articleid="108340">
   Central Asia
  </xref>
  or “the islands or peninsulae of India and China,” where King Shahryar, after discovering that during his absences his wife has been regularly unfaithful, kills her and those with whom she has betrayed him. Then, loathing all womankind, he marries and kills a new wife each day until no more candidates can be found. His
  <xref articleid="75605">
   vizier
  </xref>
  , however, has two daughters, Shahrazad (Scheherazade) and Dunyazad; and the elder, Shahrazad, having devised a scheme to save herself and others, insists that her father give her in marriage to the king. Each evening she tells a story, leaving it incomplete and promising to finish it the following night. The stories are so entertaining, and the king so eager to hear the end, that he puts off her execution from day to day and finally abandons his cruel plan.
 </p>
 <p>
  Though the names of its chief characters are Iranian, the frame story is probably Indian, and the largest proportion of names is
  <xref articleid="8157">
   Arabic
  </xref>
  . The tales’ variety and geographical range of origin—India, Iran, Iraq, Egypt, Turkey, and possibly Greece—make single authorship unlikely; this view is supported by internal evidence—the style, mainly unstudied and unaffected, contains colloquialisms and even grammatical errors such as no professional Arabic writer would allow.
 </p>
 <p>
  The first known reference to the
  <e type="italic">
   Nights
  </e>
  is a 9th-century fragment. It is next mentioned in 947 by
  <xref articleid="51339">
   al-Masʿūdī
  </xref>
  in a discussion of legendary stories from Iran, India, and Greece, as the Persian
  <e type="italic">
   Hazār afsāna,
  </e>
  “A Thousand Tales,” “called by the people ‘A Thousand Nights’.” In 987 Ibn al-Nadīm adds that Abū ʿAbd Allāh ibn ʿAbdūs al-Jahshiyārī began a collection of 1,000 popular Arabic, Iranian, Greek, and other tales but died (942) when only 480 were written.
 </p>
 <p>
  It is clear that the expressions “A Thousand Tales” and “A Thousand and One…” were intended merely to indicate a large number and were taken literally only later, when stories were added to make up the number.
 </p>
 <p>
  By the 20th century, Western scholars had agreed that the
  <e type="italic">
   Nights
  </e>
  is a composite work consisting of popular stories originally transmitted orally and developed during several centuries, with material added somewhat haphazardly at different periods and places. Several layers in the work, including one originating in
  <xref articleid="109394">
   Baghdad
  </xref>
  and one larger and later, written in Egypt, were distinguished in 1887 by August Müller. By the mid-20th century, six successive forms had been identified: two 8th-century Arabic translations of the
  <xref articleid="59341">
   Persian
  </xref>
  <e type="italic">
   Hazār afsāna,
  </e>
  called
  <e type="italic">
   Alf khurafah
  </e>
  and
  <e type="italic">
   Alf laylah
  </e>
  ; a 9th-century version based on
  <e type="italic">
   Alf laylah
  </e>
  but including other stories then current; the 10th-century work by al-Jahshiyārī; a 12th-century collection, including Egyptian tales; and the final version, extending to the 16th century and consisting of the earlier material with the addition of stories of the Islamic Counter-Crusades and tales brought to the Middle East by the
  <xref articleid="53354">
   Mongols
  </xref>
  . Most of the tales best known in the West—primarily those of Aladdin, Ali Baba, and Sindbad—were much later additions to the original corpus.
 </p>
 <p>
  The first European translation of the
  <e type="italic">
   Nights
  </e>
  , which was also the first published edition, was made by
  <xref articleid="35885">
   Antoine Galland
  </xref>
  as
  <e type="italic">
   Les Mille et Une Nuits, contes arabes traduits en français
  </e>
  , 12 vol. (vol. 1–10, 1704–12; vol. 11 and 12, 1717). Galland’s main text was a four-volume Syrian manuscript, but the later volumes contain many stories from oral and other sources. His translation remained standard until the mid-19th century, parts even being retranslated into Arabic. The Arabic text was first published in full at Calcutta (
  <xref articleid="106113">
   Kolkata
  </xref>
  ), 4 vol. (1839–42). The source for most later translations, however, was the so-called Vulgate text, an Egyptian recension published at
  <xref articleid="95427">
   Bulaq
  </xref>
  , Cairo, in 1835, and several times reprinted.
 </p>
 <p>
  Meanwhile, French and English continuations, versions, or editions of Galland had added stories from
  <xref articleid="477034">
   oral
  </xref>
  and manuscript sources, collected, with others, in the Breslau edition, 5 vol. (1825–43) by Maximilian Habicht. Later translations followed the Bulaq text with varying fullness and accuracy. Among the best-known of the 19th-century translations into English is that of
  <xref articleid="18239">
   Sir Richard Burton
  </xref>
  , who used
  <xref articleid="1109">
   John Payne
  </xref>
  ’s little-known full English translation, 13 vol. (9 vol., 1882–84; 3 supplementary vol., 1884; vol. 13, 1889), to produce his unexpurgated
  <e type="italic">
   The Thousand Nights and a Night,
  </e>
  16 vol. (10 vol., 1885; 6 supplementary vol., 1886–88).
 </p>
 <signature>
  EB Editors
 </signature>
 <h1 id="h260464">
  <title>
   Bibliography
  </title>
  <p>
   <e type="smallcap">
    Robert Irwin
   </e>
   ,
   <e type="italic">
    The Arabian Nights: A Companion
   </e>
   (1994), is a valuable introduction;
   <e type="smallcap">
    David Pinault
   </e>
   ,
   <e type="italic">
    Story-Telling Techniques in the Arabian Nights
   </e>
   (1992), examines the style and structure of the work as a whole and of several individual tales.
  </p>
 </h1>
 <copyright>
  Encyclopædia Britannica
 </copyright>
</article>