<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "syndication_xml.dtd">
<article articleid="73198" articletypeid="1" language="en_us" lastupdate="2021-Jul-01 01:52:07" url="/article/transformational-grammar/73198" version="3">
 <title>
  transformational grammar
 </title>
 <p>
  <e type="bold">
   transformational grammar
  </e>
  , also called
  <e type="bold">
   Transformational-generative Grammar
  </e>
  , a system of language analysis that recognizes the relationship among the various elements of a sentence and among the possible sentences of a language and uses processes or rules (some of which are called transformations) to express these relationships. For example, transformational grammar relates the active sentence “John read the book” with its corresponding passive, “The book was read by John.” The statement “George saw Mary” is related to the corresponding questions, “Whom [or who] did George see?” and “Who saw Mary?” Although sets such as these active and passive sentences appear to be very different on the surface (
  <e type="italic">
   i.e.,
  </e>
  in such things as word order), a transformational grammar tries to show that in the “underlying structure” (
  <e type="italic">
   i.e.,
  </e>
  in their deeper relations to one another), the sentences are very similar. Transformational grammar assigns a “deep structure” and a “surface structure” to show the relationship of such sentences. Thus, “I know a man who flies planes” can be considered the surface form of a deep structure approximately like “I know a man. The man flies airplanes.” The notion of deep structure can be especially helpful in explaining ambiguous utterances;
  <e type="italic">
   e.g.,
  </e>
  “Flying airplanes can be dangerous” may have a deep structure, or meaning, like “Airplanes can be dangerous when they fly” or “To fly airplanes can be dangerous.”
 </p>
 <p>
  The most widely discussed theory of transformational grammar was proposed by U.S. linguist Noam Chomsky in 1957. His work contradicted earlier tenets of structuralism by rejecting the notion that every language is unique. The use of transformational grammar in language analysis assumes a certain number of formal and substantive universals.
 </p>
 <copyright>
  Encyclopædia Britannica
 </copyright>
</article>