<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "syndication_xml.dtd">
<article articleid="7351" articletypeid="1" language="en_us" lastupdate="2021-Jun-30 20:18:46" url="/article/anamorphosis/7351" version="4">
 <title>
  anamorphosis
 </title>
 <p>
  <assembly id="a4201" url="/assembly/view/4201">
   <title>
    Scrots, William: anamorphic portrait of Edward VI
   </title>
   <media mediaid="13477" type="image" url="/77/13477-004-5B5481F8.jpg"/>
   <caption>
    Edward VI, oil on panel attributed to William Scrots, 1546; in the National Portrait Gallery, London.
   </caption>
   <credit>
    Courtesy of the National Portrait Gallery, London
   </credit>
  </assembly>
  <e type="bold">
   anamorphosis
  </e>
  ,
  <assemblyref assemblyid="a4201"/>
  in the visual arts, an ingenious
  <xref articleid="59357">
   perspective
  </xref>
  technique that gives a distorted image of the subject represented in a picture when seen from the usual viewpoint but so executed that if viewed from a particular angle, or reflected in a curved mirror, the distortion disappears and the image in the picture appears normal. Derived from the Greek word meaning “to transform,” the term
  <e type="italic">
   anamorphosis
  </e>
  was first employed in the 17th century, although this technique had been one of the more curious by-products of the discovery of perspective in the 14th and 15th centuries.
 </p>
 <p>
  The first examples appear in
  <xref articleid="75417">
   Leonardo da Vinci’s
  </xref>
  notebooks. It was regarded as a display of technical virtuosity, and it was included in most 16th- and 17th-century
  <xref articleid="106184">
   drawing
  </xref>
  manuals. Two important examples of anamorphosis are a portrait of
  <xref articleid="32031">
   Edward VI
  </xref>
  (1546) that has been attributed to William Scrots, and a skull in the foreground of
  <xref articleid="40772">
   Hans Holbein the Younger
  </xref>
  ’s painting of Jean de Dinteville and Georges de Selve,
  <e type="italic">
   The Ambassadors
  </e>
  (1533). Many examples are provided with special peepholes through which can be seen the rectified view that first eluded the viewer.
 </p>
 <p>
  A modern equivalent of anamorphosis is the so-called Ames Room, in which people and objects are distorted by manipulation of the contours of the room in which they are seen. This and other aspects of anamorphosis received a good deal of attention in the 20th century from psychologists interested in
  <xref articleid="110465">
   perception
  </xref>
  .
 </p>
 <p>
  Artists and architects in the 21st century continued to experiment with anamorphic designs. In 2014 Swiss artist Felice Varini—known for large-scale anamorphic installations—created
  <e type="italic">
   Three Ellipses for Three Locks
  </e>
  , for which he painted three ellipses, segments of which covered roads, walls, and nearly 100 buildings in the historic centre of the city of
  <xref articleid="39473">
   Hasselt
  </xref>
  , Belgium. The design became coherent only when viewed from a particular vantage point in the city.
 </p>
 <signature>
  EB Editors
 </signature>
 <copyright>
  Encyclopædia Britannica
 </copyright>
</article>