<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "syndication_xml.dtd">
<article articleid="73726" articletypeid="1" language="en_us" lastupdate="2021-Jul-01 01:57:15" url="/article/tulip-tree/73726" version="3">
 <title>
  tulip tree
 </title>
 <p>
  <assembly id="a7860" url="/assembly/view/7860">
   <title>
    tulip tree
   </title>
   <media mediaid="4775" type="image" url="/75/4775-004-7D7F8079.jpg"/>
   <caption>
    Flower of the tulip tree (
    <e type="italic">
     Liriodendron tulipifera
    </e>
    ).
   </caption>
   <credit>
    Karl H. Maslowski
   </credit>
  </assembly>
  <e type="bold">
   tulip tree
  </e>
  , (
  <e type="italic">
   Liriodendron tulipifera
  </e>
  ), also called
  <e type="bold">
   yellow poplar
  </e>
  or
  <e type="bold">
   whitewood
  </e>
  ,
  <assemblyref assemblyid="a7860"/>
  North American ornamental and timber tree of the magnolia family (Magnoliaceae), order Magnoliales, not related to the true poplars.
 </p>
 <p>
  The tulip tree occurs in mixed-hardwood stands in eastern North America. It is taller than all other eastern broad-leaved trees, and its trunk often has a diameter greater than 2 metres (7 feet). The tulip tree can attain a height of 60 metres (197 feet). Its long-stemmed bright green leaves are bilaterally two- to four-lobed, with tips that are straight-edged or broadly notched. They turn golden yellow in the fall and have large appendages (stipules) at the base of the leafstalks; the stipule scars encircle the twigs. The large yellowish green tuliplike flowers have six petals, orange at the base, and three bright green sepals. Other characteristics include conelike clusters of terminally winged fruits, aromatic purplish brown twigs with winter buds resembling a duck’s bill, and a straight trunk with an oblong crown. A tulip tree reaches its full stature in approximately 200 years.
 </p>
 <p>
  The light yellow to yellowish green wood is used in the manufacture of furniture parts, plywood panels, paper, millwork, boxes, and crates. The tulip tree is relatively free of pests and diseases. It is a useful large shade tree where space is available for it.
 </p>
 <copyright>
  Encyclopædia Britannica
 </copyright>
</article>