<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "syndication_xml.dtd">
<article articleid="74352" articletypeid="1" language="en_us" lastupdate="2021-Jul-01 02:04:15" url="/article/Unity/74352" version="4">
 <title>
  Unity
 </title>
 <p>
  <e type="bold">
   Unity
  </e>
  ,
  <xref articleid="389319">
   new religious movement
  </xref>
  founded in Kansas City, Missouri, in 1889 by Charles Fillmore (1854–1948), a real-estate agent, and his wife, Myrtle (1845–1931). Mrs. Fillmore believed that spiritual healing had cured her of tuberculosis. As a result, the Fillmores began studying spiritual healing. They were deeply influenced by Emma Curtis Hopkins, a former follower of
  <xref articleid="31964">
   Mary Baker Eddy
  </xref>
  , who founded
  <xref articleid="82420">
   Christian Science
  </xref>
  . Unity, however, is closer to
  <xref articleid="55519">
   New Thought
  </xref>
  , which in general emphasizes the primacy of mind and spiritual healing, than it is to Christian Science. Until 1922 it was a member of the International New Thought Alliance.
 </p>
 <p>
  Unity developed gradually as the Fillmores attempted to share their insights concerning religion and spiritual healing. They began publishing magazines, books, and pamphlets and started the service known as Silent Unity, which, through prayer and counselling, helps people by telephone, via mail, and online. As the work and the number of employees increased, Unity moved several times within Kansas City. After World War I, the Fillmores began developing Unity Village, 15 miles from Kansas City and eventually covering 1,400 acres, and by 1949 all departments of Unity were located there. After Charles Fillmore’s death, Unity was led by the Fillmores’ sons and grandchildren.
 </p>
 <p>
  From Unity Village a variety of activities are carried on. The publishing operation produces books, pamphlets, and periodicals, including the bimonthly
  <e type="italic">
   Unity Magazine
  </e>
  and the
  <e type="italic">
   Daily Word
  </e>
  , which is available in both print and online formats. The staff of Silent Unity is available day and night to aid people through counseling and prayer. It has been reported that as many as two million requests for aid are received by Silent Unity each year. All are answered by mail or by telephone free of charge, but many persons who make requests give a contribution. Unity also conducts classes for interested individuals and a course of study for those who wish to become Unity ministers and teachers at Unity retreats held at Unity Village.
 </p>
 <p>
  Although Unity prefers to consider itself a nonsectarian educational institution that attempts to teach religious truth, it has essentially become a denomination. Unity ministers must complete a prescribed course of study and be approved by the Association of Unity Churches.
 </p>
 <p>
  Unity emphasizes spiritual healing, prosperity, and practical Christianity. Unlike some groups that arose out of New Thought, it stresses its agreements with traditional Christianity.
  <xref articleid="67887">
   Sin
  </xref>
  , illness, the world, and matter are considered real and material, in contrast to the doctrines of Christian Science, but illnesses are considered unnatural and curable by spiritual means. The practice of
  <xref articleid="110314">
   medicine
  </xref>
  , however, is not rejected. There is no definite creed, although a statement written by Charles Fillmore, the “Unity Statement of Faith,” is available in a pamphlet. Unity is tolerant of the beliefs and practices of others.
 </p>
 <p>
  Official statistics are difficult to interpret, because the movement is interdenominational and international, but the Unity movement is thought to reach some six million persons, most of whom, however, are not members. Its influence extends far beyond the membership.
 </p>
 <copyright>
  Encyclopædia Britannica
 </copyright>
</article>