<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "syndication_xml.dtd">
<article articleid="74362" articletypeid="1" language="en_us" lastupdate="2022-Mar-10 07:11:29" url="/article/universe/74362" version="10">
 <title>
  universe
 </title>
 <p>
  <assembly id="a159542" url="/assembly/view/159542">
   <title>
    Zoom out from Earth’s solar system to the Milky Way Galaxy, the Local Group, and beyond
   </title>
   <media mediaid="151215" thumburl="/15/151215-049-BB22E109.jpg" type="video" url="mlkPhMyT"/>
   <caption>
    Scale of the universe.
   </caption>
   <credit>
    Encyclopædia Britannica, Inc.
   </credit>
  </assembly>
  <e type="bold">
   universe
  </e>
  ,
  <assemblyref assemblyid="a159542"/>
  the whole cosmic system of matter and energy of which
  <xref articleid="110147">
   Earth
  </xref>
  , and therefore the human race, is a part. Humanity has traveled a long road since societies imagined Earth, the
  <xref articleid="110144">
   Sun
  </xref>
  , and the
  <xref articleid="110148">
   Moon
  </xref>
  as the main objects of creation, with the rest of the universe being formed almost as an afterthought. Today it is known that Earth is only a small ball of rock in a space of unimaginable vastness and that the birth of the
  <xref articleid="110143">
   solar system
  </xref>
  was probably only one event among many that occurred against the backdrop of an already mature universe. This humbling lesson has unveiled a remarkable fact, one that endows the minutest particle in the universe with a rich and noble heritage: events that occurred in the first few minutes of the creation of the universe 13.7 billion years ago turn out to have had a profound influence on the birth, life, and death of
  <xref articleid="110642">
   galaxies
  </xref>
  ,
  <xref articleid="110472">
   stars
  </xref>
  , and
  <xref articleid="60298">
   planets
  </xref>
  . Indeed, a line can be drawn from the forging of the matter of the universe in a primal “
  <xref articleid="79147">
   big bang
  </xref>
  ” to the gathering on Earth of
  <xref articleid="110411">
   atoms
  </xref>
  versatile enough to serve as the basis of
  <xref articleid="106478">
   life
  </xref>
  . The intrinsic harmony of such a worldview has great philosophical and aesthetic appeal, and it may explain why public interest in the universe has always endured.
 </p>
 <p>
  This article traces the development over time of humanity’s perception of the universe, from prehistoric observations of the night sky to modern calculations on the recessional velocity of galaxies. For articles on component parts of the universe,
  <e type="italic">
   see
  </e>
  <xref articleid="110143">
   solar system
  </xref>
  ,
  <xref articleid="110472">
   star
  </xref>
  ,
  <xref articleid="110642">
   galaxy
  </xref>
  , and
  <xref articleid="108754">
   nebula
  </xref>
  . For an explanation of the scientific study of the universe as a unified whole,
  <e type="italic">
   see
  </e>
  <xref articleid="26473">
   cosmology
  </xref>
  . For an article about the possible existence of other universes,
  <e type="italic">
   see
  </e>
  <xref articleid="599336">
   multiverse
  </xref>
  .
 </p>
 <h1 id="h27539">
  <title>
   Earliest conceptions of the universe
  </title>
  <p>
   All scientific thinking on the nature of the universe can be traced to the distinctive geometric patterns formed by the
   <xref articleid="110472">
    stars
   </xref>
   in the night sky. Even prehistoric people must have noticed that, apart from a daily rotation (which is now understood to arise from the spin of
   <xref articleid="110147">
    Earth
   </xref>
   ), the stars did not seem to move with respect to one another: the stars appear “fixed.” Early
   <xref articleid="56052">
    nomads
   </xref>
   found that knowledge of the
   <xref articleid="26007">
    constellations
   </xref>
   could guide their travels, and they developed stories to help them remember the relative positions of the stars in the night sky. These stories became the mythical tales that are part of most cultures.
  </p>
  <p>
   When nomads turned to farming, an intimate knowledge of the constellations served a new function—an aid in timekeeping, in particular for keeping track of the
   <xref articleid="66491">
    seasons
   </xref>
   . People had noticed very early that certain celestial objects did not remain stationary relative to the “fixed” stars; instead, during the course of a year, they moved forward and backward in a narrow strip of the sky that contained 12 constellations constituting the signs of the
   <xref articleid="78420">
    zodiac
   </xref>
   . Seven such wanderers were known to the ancients: the
   <xref articleid="110144">
    Sun
   </xref>
   , the
   <xref articleid="53598">
    Moon
   </xref>
   ,
   <xref articleid="110145">
    Mercury
   </xref>
   ,
   <xref articleid="110146">
    Venus
   </xref>
   ,
   <xref articleid="110149">
    Mars
   </xref>
   ,
   <xref articleid="110150">
    Jupiter
   </xref>
   , and
   <xref articleid="110151">
    Saturn
   </xref>
   . Foremost among the wanderers was the Sun: day and night came with its rising and setting, and its motion through the zodiac signaled the season to plant and the season to reap. Next in importance was the Moon: its position correlated with the
   <xref articleid="72409">
    tides
   </xref>
   , and its shape changed intriguingly over the course of a month. The Sun and Moon had the power of gods; why not then the other wanderers? Thus probably arose the
   <xref articleid="108511">
    astrological
   </xref>
   belief that the positions of the
   <xref articleid="60298">
    planets
   </xref>
   (from the Greek word
   <e type="italic">
    planetes
   </e>
   , “wanderers”) in the zodiac could influence worldly events and even cause the rise and fall of kings. In homage to this belief,
   <xref articleid="11620">
    Babylonian
   </xref>
   priests devised the week of seven days, whose names even in various modern languages (for example, English, French, or Norwegian) can still easily be traced to their origins in the seven planet-gods.
  </p>
 </h1>
 <h1 id="h27540">
  <title>
   Astronomical theories of the ancient Greeks
  </title>
  <p>
   <assembly id="a13594" url="/assembly/view/13594">
    <title>
     Study how Ptolemy tried to use deferents and epicycles to explain retrograde motion
    </title>
    <media mediaid="23882" thumburl="/82/23882-049-1DED3AF1.jpg" type="video" url="VCekN8bl"/>
    <caption>
     Ptolemy’s theory of the solar system.
    </caption>
    <credit>
     Encyclopædia Britannica, Inc.
    </credit>
   </assembly>
   <assemblyref assemblyid="a13594"/>
   The apex in the description of planetary motions during classical antiquity was reached with the
   <xref articleid="106269">
    Greeks
   </xref>
   , who were of course superb
   <xref articleid="126112">
    geometers
   </xref>
   . Like their predecessors, Greek astronomers adopted the natural picture, from the point of view of an observer on
   <xref articleid="110147">
    Earth
   </xref>
   , that Earth lay motionless at the centre of a rigidly rotating
   <xref articleid="22001">
    celestial sphere
   </xref>
   (to which the
   <xref articleid="110472">
    stars
   </xref>
   were “fixed”), and that the complex to-and-fro wanderings of the
   <xref articleid="60298">
    planets
   </xref>
   in the zodiac were to be described against this unchanging backdrop. They developed an
   <xref articleid="61760">
    epicyclic model
   </xref>
   that would reproduce the observed planetary motions with quite astonishing accuracy. The model invoked small circles on top of large circles, all rotating at individual uniform speeds, and it culminated about 140
   <e type="smallcap">
    ce
   </e>
   with the work of
   <xref articleid="61778">
    Ptolemy
   </xref>
   , who introduced the ingenious artifact of displaced centres for the circles to improve the empirical fit. Although the model was purely kinematic and did not attempt to address the dynamical reasons for why the motions were as they were, it laid the groundwork for the paradigm that nature is not capricious but possesses a regularity and precision that can be discovered from experience and used to predict future events.
  </p>
  <p>
   <assembly id="a120440" url="/assembly/view/120440">
    <title>
     Eratosthenes’ method of measuring Earth’s circumference
    </title>
    <media mediaid="465" type="image" url="/65/465-004-9D8B1DF6.jpg"/>
    <caption>
     By knowing the length of an arc (
     <e type="italic">
      l
     </e>
     ) and the size of the corresponding central angle (α) that it subtends, one can obtain the radius of the sphere from the relation that the proportion of the length of arc
     <e type="italic">
      l
     </e>
     to Earth’s circumference, 2π
     <e type="italic">
      R
     </e>
     (where
     <e type="italic">
      R
     </e>
     is Earth’s radius) equals the proportion of the central angle α to the angle subtended by the whole circumference (360°)—i.e.,
     <e type="italic">
      l
     </e>
     : 2π
     <e type="italic">
      R
     </e>
     = α : 360.
    </caption>
    <credit>
     Encyclopædia Britannica, Inc.
    </credit>
   </assembly>
   <assemblyref assemblyid="a120440"/>
   The application of the methods of
   <xref articleid="111070">
    Euclidean geometry
   </xref>
   to planetary astronomy by the Greeks led to other schools of thought as well.
   <xref articleid="62073">
    Pythagoras
   </xref>
   (
   <e type="italic">
    c.
   </e>
   570–
   <e type="italic">
    c.
   </e>
   490
   <e type="smallcap">
    bce
   </e>
   ), for example, argued that the world could be understood on rational principles (“all things are numbers”); that it was made of four elements—earth, water, air, and fire; that Earth was a sphere; and that the
   <xref articleid="110148">
    Moon
   </xref>
   shone by reflected light. In the 4th century
   <e type="smallcap">
    bce
   </e>
   <xref articleid="40088">
    Heracleides Ponticus
   </xref>
   , a follower of Pythagoras, taught that the spherical Earth rotated freely in space and that
   <xref articleid="110145">
    Mercury
   </xref>
   and
   <xref articleid="110146">
    Venus
   </xref>
   revolved about the
   <xref articleid="110144">
    Sun
   </xref>
   . From the different lengths of shadows cast in Syene and Alexandria at noon on the first day of summer,
   <xref articleid="32863">
    Eratosthenes
   </xref>
   (
   <e type="italic">
    c.
   </e>
   276–194
   <e type="smallcap">
    bce
   </e>
   ) computed the radius of Earth to an accuracy within 20 percent of the modern value. Starting with the size of Earth’s shadow cast on the Moon during a lunar
   <xref articleid="106197">
    eclipse
   </xref>
   ,
   <xref articleid="9438">
    Aristarchus of Samos
   </xref>
   (
   <e type="italic">
    c.
   </e>
   310–230
   <e type="smallcap">
    bce
   </e>
   ) calculated the linear size of the Moon relative to Earth. From its measured angular size, he then obtained the distance to the Moon. He also proposed a clever scheme to measure the size and distance of the Sun. Although flawed, the method did enable him to deduce that the Sun is much larger than Earth. This deduction led Aristarchus to speculate that Earth revolves about the Sun rather than the other way around.
  </p>
  <p>
   Unfortunately, except for the conception that Earth is a sphere (inferred from Earth’s shadow on the Moon always being circular during a lunar eclipse), these ideas failed to gain general acceptance. The precise reasons remain unclear, but the growing separation between the empirical and aesthetic branches of learning must have played a major role. The unparalleled numerical accuracy achieved by the theory of epicyclic motions for planetary motions lent great empirical validity to the Ptolemaic system. Henceforth, such computational matters could be left to practical astronomers without the necessity of having to ascertain the physical reality of the model. Instead, absolute truth was to be sought through the Platonic ideal of pure thought. Even the Pythagoreans fell into this trap; the depths to which they eventually sank may be judged from the story that they discovered and then tried to conceal the fact that the
   <xref articleid="69284">
    square root
   </xref>
   of 2 is an
   <xref articleid="42816">
    irrational number
   </xref>
   (i.e., cannot be expressed as a ratio of two
   <xref articleid="472596">
    integers
   </xref>
   ).
  </p>
 </h1>
 <h1 id="h27541">
  <title>
   The system of Aristotle and its impact on medieval thought
  </title>
  <p>
   <assembly id="a2707" url="/assembly/view/2707">
    <title>
     Examine Aristotle’s model of the solar system and note its failure to explain phenomena like retrograde motion
    </title>
    <media mediaid="23886" thumburl="/86/23886-049-D70919E4.jpg" type="video" url="SQvjC7zq"/>
    <caption>
     Aristotle’s theory of the solar system.
    </caption>
    <credit>
     Encyclopædia Britannica, Inc.
    </credit>
   </assembly>
   <assemblyref assemblyid="a2707"/>
   The systematic application of pure reason to the explanation of natural phenomena reached its extreme development with
   <xref articleid="108312">
    Aristotle
   </xref>
   (384–322
   <e type="smallcap">
    bce
   </e>
   ), whose great system of the world later came to be regarded as the synthesis of all worthwhile knowledge. Aristotle argued that humans could not inhabit a moving and rotating
   <xref articleid="110147">
    Earth
   </xref>
   without violating common sense perceptions. Moreover, in his theory of impetus, all terrestrial motion, presumably including that of Earth itself, would grind to a halt without the continued application of
   <xref articleid="34834">
    force
   </xref>
   . He took for granted the action of friction because he would not allow the seminal idealization of a body moving through a void (“nature abhors a vacuum”). Thus, Aristotle was misled into equating force with
   <xref articleid="74984">
    velocity
   </xref>
   rather than, as
   <xref articleid="108764">
    Sir Isaac Newton
   </xref>
   was to show much later, with (
   <xref articleid="51285">
    mass
   </xref>
   times)
   <xref articleid="3469">
    acceleration
   </xref>
   . Celestial objects were exempt from dynamical decay because they moved in a higher stratum whereby a perfect sphere was the natural shape of heavenly bodies and uniform rotation in circles was the natural state of their motion. Indeed, primary motion was derived from the outermost sphere, the seat of the unchangeable
   <xref articleid="110472">
    stars
   </xref>
   and of divine power. No further explanation was needed beyond the aesthetic one. In this scheme, the imperfect motion of
   <xref articleid="110156">
    comets
   </xref>
   had to be postulated as
   <xref articleid="472863">
    meteorological
   </xref>
   phenomena that took place within the imperfect
   <xref articleid="126202">
    atmosphere
   </xref>
   of Earth.
  </p>
  <p>
   The great merit of Aristotle’s system was its internal logic, a grand attempt to unify all branches of human knowledge within the scope of a single self-consistent and comprehensive theory. Its great weakness was that its rigid arguments rested almost entirely on aesthetic grounds; it lacked a mechanism by which empirical knowledge gained from experimentation or observation could be used to test, modify, or reject the fundamental principles underlying the theory. Aristotle’s system had the underlying philosophical drive of modern science without its flexible procedure of self-correction that allows the truth to be approached in a series of successive approximations.
  </p>
  <p>
   With the fall of the
   <xref articleid="106272">
    Roman Empire
   </xref>
   in 476
   <e type="smallcap">
    ce
   </e>
   , much of what was known to the Greeks was lost or forgotten—at least to Western civilizations. (
   <xref articleid="105952">
    Hindu
   </xref>
   astronomers still taught that Earth was a sphere and that it rotated once daily.) The Aristotelian system, however, resonated with the teachings of the
   <xref articleid="109699">
    Roman Catholic Church
   </xref>
   during the
   <xref articleid="52537">
    Middle Ages
   </xref>
   , especially in the writings of
   <xref articleid="108661">
    St. Thomas Aquinas
   </xref>
   in the 13th century, and later, during the period of the
   <xref articleid="26564">
    Counter-Reformation
   </xref>
   in the 16th and early 17th century, it ascended to the status of religious dogma. Thus did the notion of an Earth-centred universe become gradually enmeshed in the politics of religion. Also welcome in an age that insisted on a literal interpretation of the Scriptures was Aristotle’s view that the living
   <xref articleid="69027">
    species
   </xref>
   of Earth were fixed for all time. What was not accepted was Aristotle’s argument on logical grounds that the world was eternal, extending infinitely into the past and the future even though it had finite spatial extent. For the church, there was definitely a creation event, and
   <xref articleid="384399">
    infinity
   </xref>
   was reserved for God, not space or time.
  </p>
 </h1>
 <h1 id="h27542">
  <title>
   The Copernican revolution
  </title>
  <p>
   <assembly id="a2798" url="/assembly/view/2798">
    <title>
     See how Nicolaus Copernicus’s heliocentric model replaced Aristotle’s and Ptolemy’s geocentric models
    </title>
    <media mediaid="23884" thumburl="/84/23884-049-5C6CC8A4.jpg" type="video" url="l9aREtv7"/>
    <caption>
     Copernicus’s theory of the solar system.
    </caption>
    <credit>
     Encyclopædia Britannica, Inc.
    </credit>
   </assembly>
   <assemblyref assemblyid="a2798"/>
   The
   <xref articleid="63161">
    Renaissance
   </xref>
   brought a fresh spirit of inquiry to the arts and sciences. Explorers and travelers brought home the vestiges of classical knowledge that had been preserved in the
   <xref articleid="106443">
    Muslim world
   </xref>
   and the East, and in the 15th century
   <xref articleid="9438">
    Aristarchus
   </xref>
   ’ heliocentric hypothesis again came to be debated in certain educated circles. The boldest step was taken by the Polish astronomer
   <xref articleid="105759">
    Nicolaus Copernicus
   </xref>
   , who hesitated for so long in publication that he did not see a printed copy of his own work until he lay on his deathbed in 1543. Copernicus recognized more profoundly than anyone else the advantages of a
   <xref articleid="39885">
    Sun-centred planetary system
   </xref>
   . By adopting the view that
   <xref articleid="110147">
    Earth
   </xref>
   circled the
   <xref articleid="110144">
    Sun
   </xref>
   , he could qualitatively explain the to-and-fro wanderings of the
   <xref articleid="60298">
    planets
   </xref>
   much more simply than
   <xref articleid="61778">
    Ptolemy
   </xref>
   . For example, at certain times in the motions of Earth and
   <xref articleid="110149">
    Mars
   </xref>
   about the Sun, Earth would catch up with Mars’s projected motion, and then that planet would appear to go backward through the
   <xref articleid="78420">
    zodiac
   </xref>
   . Unfortunately in his Sun-centred system, Copernicus continued to adhere to the established tradition of using
   <xref articleid="74257">
    uniform circular motion
   </xref>
   , and if he adopted only one large circle for the orbit of each planet, his calculated planetary positions would in fact be quantitatively poorer in comparison with the observed positions of the planets than tables based on the
   <xref articleid="61760">
    Ptolemaic system
   </xref>
   . This defect could be partially corrected by providing additional smaller circles, but then much of the beauty and simplicity of Copernicus’ original system would be lost. Moreover, though the Sun was now removed from the list of planets and Earth added, the
   <xref articleid="110148">
    Moon
   </xref>
   still needed to move around Earth.
  </p>
  <p>
   It was
   <xref articleid="105766">
    Galileo
   </xref>
   who exploited the power of newly invented lenses to build a
   <xref articleid="111077">
    telescope
   </xref>
   that would accumulate indirect support for the Copernican viewpoint. Critics had no rational response to Galileo’s discovery of the correlation of
   <xref articleid="110146">
    Venus
   </xref>
   ’
   <xref articleid="59592">
    phases
   </xref>
   of illumination with its orbital position relative to the Sun, which required it to circle that body rather than Earth. Nor could they refute his discovery of the four brightest satellites of
   <xref articleid="110150">
    Jupiter
   </xref>
   (the so-called Galilean satellites), which demonstrated that planets could indeed possess
   <xref articleid="53598">
    moons
   </xref>
   . They could only refuse to look through the telescope or refuse to see what their own eyes told them.
  </p>
  <p>
   <assembly id="a120445" url="/assembly/view/120445">
    <title>
     photosphere of the Sun
    </title>
    <media mediaid="118391" type="image" url="/91/118391-004-BAA3318E.jpg"/>
    <caption>
     Photosphere of the Sun with sunspots, image taken by the Solar and Heliospheric Observatory satellite, Oct. 29, 2003.
    </caption>
    <credit>
     SOHO/NASA
    </credit>
   </assembly>
   <assemblyref assemblyid="a120445"/>
   Galileo also mounted a systematic attack on other accepted teachings of
   <xref articleid="108312">
    Aristotle
   </xref>
   by showing, for example, that the Sun was not perfect but had
   <xref articleid="70383">
    spots
   </xref>
   . Besieged on all sides by what it perceived as heretical stirrings, the church forced Galileo to recant his support of the heliocentric system in 1633. Confined to house arrest during his last years, Galileo would perform actual experiments and thought experiments (summarized in a treatise) that would refute the core of Aristotelian dynamics. Most notably, he formulated the concept that would eventually lead (in the hands of
   <xref articleid="108563">
    René Descartes
   </xref>
   ) to the so-called first law of
   <xref articleid="110307">
    mechanics
   </xref>
   —namely, that a body in motion, freed from friction and from all other
   <xref articleid="34834">
    forces
   </xref>
   , would move, not in a circle, but in a straight line at uniform speed. The frame of reference for making such measurements was ultimately the “fixed stars.” Galileo also argued that, in the
   <xref articleid="106265">
    gravitational
   </xref>
   field of Earth and in the absence of air drag, bodies of different weights would fall at the same rate. This finding would eventually lead (in the hands of
   <xref articleid="106018">
    Einstein
   </xref>
   ) to the principle of equivalence, a cornerstone of the theory of
   <xref articleid="109465" refid="h252889">
    general relativity
   </xref>
   .
  </p>
  <p>
   <assembly id="a2967" url="/assembly/view/2967">
    <title>
     Learn how Johannes Kepler challenged the Copernican system of planetary motion
    </title>
    <media mediaid="23883" thumburl="/83/23883-049-C15265A8.jpg" type="video" url="t2gR52NK"/>
    <caption>
     Kepler’s theory of the solar system.
    </caption>
    <credit>
     Encyclopædia Britannica, Inc.
    </credit>
   </assembly>
   <assemblyref assemblyid="a2967"/>
   It was the German astronomer
   <xref articleid="105767">
    Johannes Kepler
   </xref>
   , a contemporary of Galileo, who would provide the crucial blow that assured the success of the Copernican revolution. Of all the planets whose orbits Copernicus had tried to explain with a single circle,
   <xref articleid="110149">
    Mars
   </xref>
   had the largest departure (the largest eccentricity, in astronomical nomenclature); consequently, Kepler arranged to work with the foremost observational astronomer of his day,
   <xref articleid="16148">
    Tycho Brahe
   </xref>
   of Denmark, who had accumulated over many years the most precise positional measurements of this planet. When Kepler finally gained access to the data upon Tycho’s death, he painstakingly tried to fit the observations to one curve after another. The work was especially difficult because he had to assume an
   <xref articleid="57286">
    orbit
   </xref>
   for Earth before he could self-consistently subtract the effects of its motion. Finally, after many close calls and rejections, he hit upon a simple, elegant solution—an
   <xref articleid="1541">
    ellipse
   </xref>
   with the Sun at one focus. The other planets also fell into place. This triumph was followed by others, notable among which was Kepler’s discovery of his so-called
   <xref articleid="45134">
    three laws of planetary motion
   </xref>
   . The empirical victory secure, the stage was set for
   <xref articleid="108764">
    Newton’s
   </xref>
   matchless theoretical campaigns.
  </p>
  <p>
   Two towering achievements paved the way for Newton’s conquest of the dynamical problem of planetary motions: his discoveries of the second law of mechanics and of the
   <xref articleid="55621">
    law of universal gravitation
   </xref>
   . The second law of mechanics generalized the work of Galileo and Descartes on terrestrial dynamics, asserting how bodies generally move when they are subjected to external forces. The law of universal gravitation generalized the work of Galileo and the English physicist
   <xref articleid="40979">
    Robert Hooke
   </xref>
   on terrestrial gravity, asserting that two massive bodies attract one another with a force directly proportional to the product of their masses and inversely proportional to the square of their separation distance. By pure mathematical deduction, Newton showed that these two general laws (whose empirical basis rested in the laboratory) implied, when applied to the celestial realm, Kepler’s three laws of planetary motion. This brilliant coup completed the Copernican program to replace the old worldview with an alternative that was far superior, both in conceptual principle and in practical application. In the same stroke of genius, Newton unified the mechanics of heaven and Earth and initiated the era of modern science.
  </p>
  <p>
   In formulating
   <xref articleid="55622">
    his laws
   </xref>
   , Newton asserted as postulates the notions of absolute space (in the sense of
   <xref articleid="111070">
    Euclidean geometry
   </xref>
   ) and absolute time (a mathematical quantity that flows in the universe without reference to anything else). A kind of relativity principle did exist (“Galilean relativity”) in the freedom to choose different inertial
   <xref articleid="63015">
    frames of reference
   </xref>
   —i.e., the form of Newton’s laws was unaffected by motion at constant velocity with respect to the “fixed stars.” However, Newton’s scheme unambiguously sundered space and time as fundamentally separate entities. This step was necessary for progress to be made, and it was such a wonderfully accurate approximation to the truth for describing motions that are slow compared to the
   <xref articleid="110443" refid="h258414">
    speed of light
   </xref>
   that it withstood all tests for more than two centuries.
  </p>
  <p>
   <assembly id="a119655" url="/assembly/view/119655">
    <title>
     Halley’s Comet
    </title>
    <media mediaid="124973" type="image" url="/73/124973-004-369BB46A.jpg"/>
    <caption>
     Halley’s Comet, 1986.
    </caption>
    <credit>
     NASA/National Space Science Data Center
    </credit>
   </assembly>
   <assemblyref assemblyid="a119655"/>
   In 1705 the English astronomer
   <xref articleid="38943">
    Edmond Halley
   </xref>
   used Newton’s laws to predict that a certain comet last seen in 1682 would reappear 76 years later. When
   <xref articleid="38944">
    Halley’s Comet
   </xref>
   returned on Christmas night 1758, many years after the deaths of both Newton and Halley, no educated person could ever again seriously doubt the power of mechanistic explanations for natural phenomena. Nor would anyone worry again that the unruly excursions of comets through the
   <xref articleid="110143">
    solar system
   </xref>
   would smash the crystalline spheres that earlier thinkers had mentally constructed to carry planets and the other celestial bodies through the heavens. The attention of professional astronomers now turned increasingly toward an understanding of the stars.
  </p>
  <p>
   <assembly id="a49598" url="/assembly/view/49598">
    <media mediaid="3386" type="image" url="/86/3386-004-32EE0336.jpg"/>
    <caption>
     Stellar parallax.
    </caption>
    <credit>
     Encyclopædia Britannica, Inc.
    </credit>
   </assembly>
   <assemblyref assemblyid="a49598"/>
   In the latter effort, the British astronomer
   <xref articleid="40235">
    William Herschel
   </xref>
   and his son
   <xref articleid="40234">
    John
   </xref>
   led the assault. The construction of ever more powerful reflecting
   <xref articleid="111077">
    telescopes
   </xref>
   allowed them during the late 1700s and early 1800s to measure the angular positions and apparent brightnesses of many faint
   <xref articleid="110472">
    stars
   </xref>
   . In an earlier epoch, Galileo had turned his telescope to the
   <xref articleid="110643">
    Milky Way
   </xref>
   and saw that it was composed of countless individual stars. Now the Herschels began an ambitious program to gauge quantitatively the distribution of the stars in the sky. On the assumption (first adopted by the Dutch mathematician and scientist
   <xref articleid="41658">
    Christiaan Huygens
   </xref>
   ) that faintness is a statistical measure of distance, they inferred the enormous average separations of stars. This view received direct confirmation for the nearest stars through
   <xref articleid="58395" refid="h5515">
    parallax
   </xref>
   measurements of their distances from
   <xref articleid="110147">
    Earth
   </xref>
   . Later, photographs taken over a period of many years also showed that some stars changed locations across the line of sight relative to the background; thus, astronomers learned that stars are not truly fixed, but rather have motions with respect to one another. These
   <xref articleid="61555">
    real motions
   </xref>
   —as well as the apparent ones due to parallax, first measured by the German astronomer
   <xref articleid="78931">
    Friedrich Bessel
   </xref>
   in 1838—were not detected by the ancients because of the enormous distance scale of the stellar universe.
  </p>
 </h1>
 <h1 id="h27543">
  <title>
   Perceptions of the 20th century
  </title>
  <h2 id="h27544">
   <title>
    Kapteyn’s statistical studies
   </title>
   <p>
    The statistical studies based on these new perceptions continued into the early 20th century. They culminated with the analysis by the Dutch astronomer
    <xref articleid="44659">
     Jacobus Cornelius Kapteyn
    </xref>
    who, like
    <xref articleid="40235">
     William Herschel
    </xref>
    before him, used number counts of
    <xref articleid="110472">
     stars
    </xref>
    to study their distribution in space. It can be shown for stars with an arbitrary but fixed mixture of intrinsic brightnesses that—in the absence of absorption of starlight—the number
    <e type="italic">
     N
    </e>
    of stars with apparent brightness, energy flux
    <e type="italic">
     f
    </e>
    , larger than a specified level
    <e type="italic">
     f
    </e>
    <sub>
     0
    </sub>
    , is given by
    <e type="italic">
     N
    </e>
    =
    <e type="italic">
     A
    </e>
    <e type="italic">
     f
    </e>
    <sub>
     0
    </sub>
    <sup>
     −3/2
    </sup>
    , where
    <e type="italic">
     A
    </e>
    is a constant, if the stars are distributed uniformly in Euclidean space (space satisfying the principles of
    <xref articleid="111070">
     Euclidean geometry
    </xref>
    ). The number
    <e type="italic">
     N
    </e>
    would increase with decreasing limiting apparent brightness
    <e type="italic">
     f
    </e>
    <sub>
     0
    </sub>
    , because one is sampling, on average, larger volumes of space when one counts fainter sources. Kapteyn found that the number
    <e type="italic">
     N
    </e>
    increased less rapidly with decreasing
    <e type="italic">
     f
    </e>
    <sub>
     0
    </sub>
    than the hypothetical value
    <e type="italic">
     A
    </e>
    <e type="italic">
     f
    </e>
    <sub>
     0
    </sub>
    <sup>
     −3/2
    </sup>
    ; this indicated to him that the
    <xref articleid="110143">
     solar system
    </xref>
    lay near the centre of a distribution of stars, which thinned in number with increasing distance from the centre. Moreover, Kapteyn determined that the rate of thinning was more rapid in certain directions than in others. This observation, in conjunction with other arguments that set the scale, led him in the first two decades of the 20th century to depict the
    <xref articleid="110643">
     Milky Way Galaxy
    </xref>
    (then confused with the entire universe) as a rather small, flattened stratum of stars and gaseous
    <xref articleid="108754">
     nebulae
    </xref>
    in which the number of stars decreased to 10 percent of their central value at a distance in the plane of about 8,500
    <xref articleid="48225">
     light-years
    </xref>
    from the galactic centre.
   </p>
  </h2>
  <h2 id="h27545">
   <title>
    Shapley’s contributions
   </title>
   <p>
    <assembly id="a109369" url="/assembly/view/109369">
     <title>
      globular cluster M80
     </title>
     <media mediaid="111347" type="image" url="/47/111347-004-8A438D21.jpg"/>
     <caption>
      Globular cluster M80 (also known as NGC 6093) in an optical image taken by the Hubble Space Telescope. M80 is located 28,000 light-years from Earth and contains hundreds of thousands of stars.
     </caption>
     <credit>
      The Hubble Heritage Team (AURA/ STScI/ NASA)
     </credit>
    </assembly>
    <assembly id="a3648" url="/assembly/view/3648">
     <media mediaid="4423" type="image" url="/23/4423-004-236BA67D.jpg"/>
     <caption>
      Distribution of open and globular star clusters in the Galaxy.
     </caption>
     <credit>
      Encyclopædia Britannica, Inc.
     </credit>
    </assembly>
    <assemblyref assemblyid="a109369"/>
    <assemblyref assemblyid="a3648"/>
    In 1917 the American astronomer
    <xref articleid="67144">
     Harlow Shapley
    </xref>
    mounted a serious challenge to the Kapteyn universe. Shapley’s study of the distances of
    <xref articleid="37051">
     globular clusters
    </xref>
    led him to conclude that their distribution centred on a point that lay in the direction of the
    <xref articleid="26007">
     constellation
    </xref>
    <xref articleid="64738">
     Sagittarius
    </xref>
    and at a distance that he estimated to be about 45,000 light-years (50 percent larger than the modern value). Shapley was able to determine the distance to the globulars through the calibration of the intrinsic brightnesses of some
    <xref articleid="74847">
     variable stars
    </xref>
    found in them. (Knowing the period of the light variations allowed Shapley to infer the average intrinsic brightness. A measurement of the average apparent brightness then allowed, from the 1/
    <e type="italic">
     r
    </e>
    <sup>
     2
    </sup>
    law of brightness, a deduction of the distance
    <e type="italic">
     r
    </e>
    .) According to Shapley, the galactic system was much larger than Kapteyn’s estimate. Moreover, the
    <xref articleid="110144">
     Sun
    </xref>
    was located not at its centre but rather at its radial outskirts (though close to the midplane of a flattened disk). Shapley’s dethronement of the Sun from the centre of the stellar system has often been compared with
    <xref articleid="105759">
     Copernicus
    </xref>
    ’ dethronement of Earth from the centre of the planetary system, but its largest astronomical impact rested with the enormous physical dimensions ascribed to the Galaxy. In 1920 a debate was arranged between Shapley and Heber D. Curtis to discuss this issue before the
    <xref articleid="54945">
     National Academy of Sciences
    </xref>
    in Washington, D.C.
   </p>
   <p>
    <assembly id="a109378" url="/assembly/view/109378">
     <title>
      Pinwheel Galaxy (M101)
     </title>
     <media mediaid="111345" type="image" url="/45/111345-004-2683A2DC.jpg"/>
     <caption>
      The Pinwheel Galaxy (M101), as seen in an optical image taken by the Hubble Space Telescope.
     </caption>
     <credit>
      CFHT/NOAO/AURA/NSF/NASA/ESA/STScI
     </credit>
    </assembly>
    <assemblyref assemblyid="a109378"/>
    The debate also addressed a second controversy—the nature of the so-called spiral nebulas. Shapley and his adherents held that these objects were made up of diffuse gas and were therefore similar to the other gas clouds known within the confines of the Milky Way Galaxy. Curtis and others, by contrast, maintained that the spirals consisted of stars and were thus equivalent to independent
    <xref articleid="110642">
     galaxies
    </xref>
    coequal to the Galaxy. A parallel line of thought had been proposed earlier by the philosophers
    <xref articleid="108443">
     Immanuel Kant
    </xref>
    and Thomas Wright and by
    <xref articleid="40235">
     William Herschel
    </xref>
    . The renewed argument over the status of the spirals grew in part out of an important development that occurred around the turn of the 20th century: the astronomical incorporation of the methods of
    <xref articleid="110407">
     spectroscopy
    </xref>
    both to study the physical nature of celestial bodies and to obtain the component of their velocities along the line of sight. By analyzing the properties of spectral lines in the received
    <xref articleid="110443">
     light
    </xref>
    (e.g., seeing if the lines were produced by absorption or emission and if the lines were broad or narrow), or by analyzing the gross colours of the observed object, astronomers learned to distinguish between ordinary
    <xref articleid="110472">
     stars
    </xref>
    and gaseous
    <xref articleid="108754">
     nebulas
    </xref>
    existing in the regions between stars. By measuring the displacement in wavelength of the spectral lines with respect to their laboratory counterparts and assuming the displacement to arise from the
    <xref articleid="30955">
     Doppler effect
    </xref>
    , they could deduce the velocity of recession (or approach). The spirals posed interpretative difficulties on all counts: they had spectral properties that were unlike either local collections of stars or gaseous nebulas (because of the unforeseen roles of dust and different populations of stars in the arms, disk, and central bulge of a spiral galaxy); and, as had been shown by the American astronomer
    <xref articleid="68203">
     Vesto Slipher
    </xref>
    , they generally possessed recession velocities that were enormous compared to those then known for any other astronomical object.
   </p>
   <p>
    The formal debate between Shapley and Curtis ended inconclusively, but history has proved Shapley to be mostly right on the issue of the off-centre position of the
    <xref articleid="110143">
     solar system
    </xref>
    and the large scale of the
    <xref articleid="110643">
     Galaxy
    </xref>
    , and Curtis to be mostly right on the issue of the nature of the spirals as independent galaxies. As demonstrated in the work of the Swiss-born U.S. astronomer
    <xref articleid="73559">
     Robert J. Trumpler
    </xref>
    in 1930. Kapteyn (and Herschel) had been misled by the effects of the undiscovered but pervasive interstellar dust to think that the stars in the Milky Way thinned out with distance much more quickly than they actually do. The effect of interstellar dust was much less important for Shapley’s studies because the globular clusters mostly lie well away from the plane of the Milky Way system.
   </p>
  </h2>
  <h2 id="h27546">
   <title>
    Hubble’s research on extragalactic systems
   </title>
   <p>
    <assembly id="a110283" url="/assembly/view/110283">
     <title>
      Andromeda Galaxy
     </title>
     <media mediaid="114699" type="image" url="/99/114699-004-68A2FF74.jpg"/>
     <caption>
      The Andromeda Galaxy, also known as the Andromeda Nebula or M31. It is the closest spiral galaxy to Earth, at a distance of 2.48 million light-years.
     </caption>
     <credit>
      © Giovanni Benintende/Shutterstock.com
     </credit>
    </assembly>
    <assemblyref assemblyid="a110283"/>
    The decisive piece of evidence concerning the extragalactic nature of the spirals was provided in 1923–24 by
    <xref articleid="41368">
     Edwin Hubble
    </xref>
    , who succeeded in resolving one field in the
    <xref articleid="7505">
     Andromeda Galaxy
    </xref>
    (M31) into a collection of distinct
    <xref articleid="110472">
     stars
    </xref>
    . Some of the stars proved to be
    <xref articleid="74847">
     variables
    </xref>
    of
    <xref articleid="22121">
     a type
    </xref>
    similar to those found by Shapley in globular clusters. Measurements of the properties of these variables yielded estimates of their distances. As it turned out, the distance to M31 put it well outside the confines of even Shapley’s huge model of the
    <xref articleid="110643">
     Galaxy
    </xref>
    , and M31 therefore must be an independent system of stars (and gas clouds).
   </p>
   <p>
    <assembly id="a90846" url="/assembly/view/90846">
     <title>
      galaxy types
     </title>
     <media mediaid="94896" type="image" url="/96/94896-004-63B431D8.jpg"/>
     <caption>
      In the 1920s Edwin Hubble separated galaxies into general types according to their appearance—elliptical, normal spiral, barred spiral, and irregular—and then classified each into subtypes.
     </caption>
     <credit>
      Encyclopædia Britannica, Inc.
     </credit>
    </assembly>
    <assemblyref assemblyid="a90846"/>
    Hubble’s findings inaugurated the era of extragalactic astronomy. He himself went on to classify the morphological types of the different
    <xref articleid="110642">
     galaxies
    </xref>
    he found: spirals, ellipticals, and irregulars. In 1926 he showed that, apart from a “zone of avoidance” (region characterized by an apparent absence of galaxies near the plane of the Milky Way caused by the obscuration of interstellar dust), the distribution of galaxies in space is close to uniform when averaged over sufficiently large scales, with no observable boundary or edge. The procedure was identical to that used by Kapteyn and Herschel, with galaxies replacing stars as the luminous sources. The difference was that this time the number count
    <e type="italic">
     N
    </e>
    was proportional to
    <e type="italic">
     f
    </e>
    <sub>
     0
    </sub>
    <sup>
     -3/2
    </sup>
    , to the limits of the original survey. Hubble’s finding provided the empirical justification for the so-called cosmological principle, a term coined by the English mathematician and astrophysicist
    <xref articleid="52747">
     Edward A. Milne
    </xref>
    to describe the assumption that at any instant in time the universe is, in the large, homogeneous and isotropic—i.e., statistically the same in every place and in every direction. This represented the ultimate triumph for the Copernican revolution.
   </p>
   <p>
    <assembly id="a109384" url="/assembly/view/109384">
     <title>
      Hickson Compact Group 87
     </title>
     <media mediaid="111341" type="image" url="/41/111341-004-E3D27428.jpg"/>
     <caption>
      Hickson Compact Group 87, which contains four galaxies, as seen in an optical image taken by the Hubble Space Telescope.
     </caption>
     <credit>
      The Hubble Heritage Team (AURA/STScI/NASA)
     </credit>
    </assembly>
    <assemblyref assemblyid="a109384"/>
    It was also Hubble who interpreted and quantified Slipher’s results on the large recessional velocities of galaxies—they correspond to a general overall expansion of the universe. The Hubble law, enunciated in 1929, marked a major turning point in modern thinking about the origin and evolution of the universe. The announcement of cosmological expansion came at a time when scientists were beginning to grapple with the theoretical implications of the revolutions taking place in physics. In his theory of
    <xref articleid="109465" refid="h252878">
     special relativity
    </xref>
    , formulated in 1905,
    <xref articleid="106018">
     Einstein
    </xref>
    had effected a union of space and time, one that fundamentally modified Newtonian perceptions of dynamics, allowing, for example, transformations between mass and energy. In his theory of
    <xref articleid="109465" refid="h252889">
     general relativity
    </xref>
    , proposed in 1916, Einstein effected an even more remarkable union, one that fundamentally altered Newtonian perceptions of
    <xref articleid="106265">
     gravitation
    </xref>
    , allowing gravitation to be seen, not as a force, but as the dynamics of
    <xref articleid="68970">
     space-time
    </xref>
    . Taken together, the discoveries of Hubble and Einstein gave rise to a new worldview. The new
    <xref articleid="26473">
     cosmology
    </xref>
    gave empirical validation to the notion of a
    <xref articleid="79147">
     creation event
    </xref>
    ; it assigned a numerical estimate for when the arrow of time first took flight; and it eventually led to the breathtaking idea that everything in the universe could have arisen from literally nothing.
   </p>
   <signature>
    Frank H. Shu
   </signature>
  </h2>
 </h1>
 <h1 id="h280805">
  <title>
   Bibliography
  </title>
  <p>
   The standard reference is
   <e type="smallcap">
    Anton Pannekoek
   </e>
   ,
   <e type="italic">
    A History of Astronomy
   </e>
   (1961, reissued 1989; originally published in Dutch, 1951). Excellent accounts of early ideas can be found in
   <e type="smallcap">
    J.L.E. Dreyer
   </e>
   ,
   <e type="italic">
    A History of Astronomy from Thales to Kepler
   </e>
   , 2nd ed. (1953); and
   <e type="smallcap">
    Giorgio De Santillana
   </e>
   ,
   <e type="italic">
    The Origins of Scientific Thought
   </e>
   (1961, reissued 1970). A historical account of our understanding of galaxies and the extragalactic universe is
   <e type="smallcap">
    Timothy Ferris
   </e>
   ,
   <e type="italic">
    Coming of Age in the Milky Way
   </e>
   (2003).
  </p>
  <signature>
   Frank H. Shu
  </signature>
 </h1>
 <copyright>
  Encyclopædia Britannica
 </copyright>
</article>