<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "syndication_xml.dtd">
<article articleid="76800" articletypeid="1" language="en_us" lastupdate="2021-Jul-01 02:28:33" url="/article/White-EB/76800" version="9">
 <title>
  E.B. White
 </title>
 <p>
  <e type="bold">
   E.B. White
  </e>
  , in full
  <e type="bold">
   Elwyn Brooks White
  </e>
  , (born July 11, 1899, Mount Vernon, New York, U.S.—died October 1, 1985, North Brooklin, Maine), American essayist, author, and literary stylist, whose eloquent, unaffected prose appealed to readers of all ages.
 </p>
 <p>
  <assembly id="a99669" url="/assembly/view/99669">
   <media mediaid="99358" type="image" url="/58/99358-004-8DF1F962.jpg"/>
   <caption>
    E.B. White.
   </caption>
   <credit>
    Encyclopædia Britannica, Inc.
   </credit>
  </assembly>
  <assemblyref assemblyid="a99669"/>
  White graduated from Cornell University in Ithaca, New York, in 1921 and worked as a reporter and freelance writer before joining
  <e type="italic">
   <xref articleid="55546">
    The New Yorker
   </xref>
  </e>
  magazine as a writer and contributing editor in 1927. He married Katherine Sergeant Angell,
  <e type="italic">
   The New Yorker
  </e>
  ’s first fiction editor, in 1929, and he remained with the weekly magazine for the rest of his career. White’s essays for
  <e type="italic">
   The New Yorker
  </e>
  quickly garnered critical praise. Written in a personal, direct style that showcased an affable sense of humour, his witty pieces contained musings about city life, politics, and literature, among other subjects. White also wrote poems, cartoon captions, and brief sketches for the magazine, and his writings helped establish its intellectual and cosmopolitan tone. White collaborated with
  <xref articleid="72331">
   James Thurber
  </xref>
  on
  <e type="italic">
   Is Sex Necessary?
  </e>
  (1929), a spoof of contemporary sex manuals. In a monthly column (1938–43) for
  <e type="italic">
   Harper’s
  </e>
  magazine, he wrote essays about rural life.
 </p>
 <p>
  In 1941 White edited with his wife
  <e type="italic">
   A Subtreasury of American Humor.
  </e>
  His three books for children—
  <e type="italic">
   <xref articleid="486754">
    Stuart Little
   </xref>
  </e>
  (1945, film 1999),
  <e type="italic">
   <xref articleid="484244">
    Charlotte’s Web
   </xref>
  </e>
  (1952, film 1973 and 2006), and
  <e type="italic">
   <xref articleid="486982">
    The Trumpet of the Swan
   </xref>
  </e>
  (1970)—are considered classics, featuring lively animal protagonists who seamlessly interact with the human world. In 1959 he revised and published a book by the late William Strunk, Jr.,
  <e type="italic">
   The Elements of Style,
  </e>
  which became a standard style manual for writing in English. Among White’s other works is
  <e type="italic">
   Points of My Compass
  </e>
  (1962).
  <e type="italic">
   Letters of E.B. White,
  </e>
  edited by D.L. Guth, appeared in 1976, his collected essays in 1977, and
  <e type="italic">
   Poems and Sketches of E.B. White
  </e>
  in 1981. He was awarded a Presidential Medal of Freedom (1963) and a Pulitzer Prize special citation (1978). White’s biography of Harold W. Ross appeared in the 14th edition of the
  <e type="italic">
   Encyclopædia Britannica
  </e>
  (
  <e type="italic">
   see
  </e>
  the Britannica Classic:
  <xref articleid="117888">
   Harold Ross
  </xref>
  ).
 </p>
 <copyright>
  Encyclopædia Britannica
 </copyright>
</article>