<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "syndication_xml.dtd">
<article articleid="79113" articletypeid="1" language="en_us" lastupdate="2021-Dec-20 15:55:56" url="/article/bicycle/79113" version="17">
 <title>
  bicycle
 </title>
 <p>
  <assembly id="a187669" url="/assembly/view/187669">
   <title>
    bicycling
   </title>
   <media mediaid="82563" type="image" url="/63/82563-004-F9C05912.jpg"/>
   <caption>
    Family bicycling on a country road.
   </caption>
   <credit>
    © FatCamera/iStock.com
   </credit>
  </assembly>
  <e type="bold">
   bicycle
  </e>
  , also called
  <e type="bold">
   bike
  </e>
  ,
  <assemblyref assemblyid="a187669"/>
  two-wheeled steerable machine that is pedaled by the rider’s feet. On a standard bicycle the wheels are mounted in-line in a metal frame, with the front wheel held in a rotatable fork. The rider sits on a saddle and steers by leaning and turning handlebars that are attached to the fork. The feet turn pedals attached to cranks and a chainwheel. Power is transmitted by a loop of chain connecting the chainwheel to a sprocket on the rear wheel. Riding is easily mastered, and bikes can be ridden with little effort at 16–24 km (10–15 miles) per hour—about four to five times the pace of walking. The bicycle is the most efficient means yet devised to convert human energy into mobility.
 </p>
 <p>
  Bicycles are widely used for transportation, recreation, and sport (
  <e type="italic">
   see
  </e>
  <xref articleid="28375">
   cycling
  </xref>
  ). Throughout the world, bicycles are essential to moving people and goods in areas where there are few automobiles. Globally, there are twice as many bicycles as automobiles, and they outsell automobiles three to one. The Netherlands, Denmark, and Japan actively promote bicycles for shopping and commuting. In the United States, bike paths have been constructed in many parts of the country, and bicycles are encouraged by the United States government as an alternative to automobiles.
 </p>
 <h1 id="h230019">
  <title>
   History of the bicycle
  </title>
  <h2 id="h230020">
   <title>
    Bicycle predecessors
   </title>
   <p>
    Historians disagree about the invention of the bicycle, and many dates are challenged. It is most likely that no individual qualifies as the inventor and that the bicycle evolved through the efforts of many. Although
    <xref articleid="108470">
     Leonardo da Vinci
    </xref>
    was credited with having sketched a bicycle in 1492 in his
    <e type="italic">
     Codex Atlanticus
    </e>
    , the drawing was discovered to be a forgery added in the 1960s. Another presumed bicycle ancestor, the
    <e type="italic">
     vélocifère
    </e>
    , or
    <e type="italic">
     célérifère
    </e>
    , of the 1790s was a fast horse-drawn coach that is not considered to be a predecessor of the bicycle.
   </p>
   <h3 id="h230021">
    <title>
     Draisiennes, hobby-horses, and other velocipedes
    </title>
    <p>
     The first two-wheeled rider-propelled machine for which there is indisputable evidence was the
     <e type="italic">
      draisienne
     </e>
     , invented by Baron Karl von Drais de Sauerbrun of Germany. In 1817 he rode it for 14 km (9 miles), and the following year he exhibited it in Paris. Although von Drais called his device a
     <e type="italic">
      Laufmaschine
     </e>
     (“running machine”),
     <e type="italic">
      draisienne
     </e>
     and
     <e type="italic">
      velocipede
     </e>
     became more popular names. The machine was made of wood, and the seated rider propelled himself by paddling his feet against the ground. A balance board supported the rider’s arms. Although von Drais was granted patents, copies were soon being produced in other countries, including Great Britain, Austria, Italy, and the United States.
    </p>
    <p>
     Denis Johnson of London purchased a
     <e type="italic">
      draisienne
     </e>
     and patented an improved model in 1818 as the “pedestrian curricle.” The following year he produced more than 300, and they became commonly known as hobby-horses. They were very expensive, and many buyers were members of the nobility. Caricaturists called the devices “dandy horses,” and riders were sometimes jeered in public. The design raised health concerns, and riding proved impractical except on smooth roads. Johnson’s production ended after only six months. The brief
     <e type="italic">
      draisienne
     </e>
     –hobby-horse fad did not lead to sustained development of two-wheeled vehicles, but von Drais and Johnson established that the machines could remain balanced while in motion. For the next 40 years, most experimenters focused on human-powered three- and four-wheeled velocipedes.
    </p>
   </h3>
   <h3 id="h230022">
    <title>
     Treadles and pedals: powered velocipedes
    </title>
    <p>
     There is evidence that a small number of two-wheeled machines with rear treadle drives were built in southwestern Scotland during the early 1840s. Kirkpatrick Macmillan, a blacksmith of
     <xref articleid="31436">
      Dumfriesshire
     </xref>
     , is most often associated with these. He is said to have traveled 40 miles (64 km) to
     <xref articleid="36983">
      Glasgow
     </xref>
     in 1842, although documentation is problematic. Gavin Dalzell of Lesmahagow probably built a similar two-wheeled machine in the mid-1840s and is said to have operated it for many years. This may be the heavily restored machine in the Glasgow Museum of Transport. It has wooden wheels and iron rims. The rider’s feet swung treadles back and forth, moving a pair of rods connected to cranks on the rear wheels. Thomas McCall, another Scotsman, built similar machines in the late 1860s. Documents indicate that Alexandre Lefèbvre of
     <xref articleid="64832">
      Saint-Denis
     </xref>
     , France, built a two-wheeled velocipede powered by treadles connected to cranks on the rear wheel in 1842. Lefèbvre took his velocipede with him when he immigrated to California in 1861, and it still exists there in the History San José museum. Neither the Scottish nor Lefèbvre’s machines were commercially exploited, and there is no evidence that they contributed to subsequent development.
    </p>
    <p>
     The word
     <e type="italic">
      bicycle
     </e>
     came into use in Europe in 1868 to replace the cumbersome
     <e type="italic">
      vélocipède de pedale
     </e>
     . The first velocipede powered via pedals mounted on the front wheel was built in Paris during the early 1860s, but there is no conclusive evidence proving who conceived the idea of applying pedals to the front wheel or who actually did so. There is evidence that Pierre Lallement, a French mechanic, built and demonstrated such a machine in Paris in mid-1863. At that time he was working for M. Strohmayer, a Parisian maker of carriages for children and invalids. Lallement took parts for an improved velocipede with him when he went to the United States in 1865, and he completed his new
     <e type="italic">
      veloce
     </e>
     in
     <xref articleid="7734">
      Ansonia
     </xref>
     , Connecticut. Although a United States patent was issued in 1866, a manufacturer could not be enlisted, and Lallement returned to France sometime in 1868. In that same year, French velocipedes built by Michaux et Cie. (a company that made carriage locks) started a craze in America, and Lallement was able to sell his patent to American entrepreneur Calvin Witty for $2,000. This would soon have consequences for the American industry.
    </p>
    <p>
     Pierre Michaux and his son Ernest presented their pedal-driven velocipede in the 1860s. The best evidence indicates that they built it in Paris in early 1864 (not 1861 or 1855, as stated in many histories), and a few more were built in 1865 and 1866. Some had malleable cast-iron frames, apparently in anticipation of large-scale production. Cranks and pedals were attached to the front wheel, which was 86 to 91 cm (34 to 36 inches) in diameter. The rear wheel was slightly smaller. Although the company filed no claim to the basic design, it patented a number of improvements in April 1868.
    </p>
   </h3>
   <h3 id="h230023">
    <title>
     From boneshakers to bicycles
    </title>
    <p>
     Michaux’s role as the pioneer manufacturer of pedal bicycles is inextricably linked with the Olivier brothers, René and Aimé. In 1865 these two rich young men pedaled velocipedes more than 800 km (500 miles) from Paris to
     <xref articleid="108484">
      Marseille
     </xref>
     , and their subsequent enthusiasm for the new sport helped it to become a worldwide craze for the young, fit, and well-to-do. The brothers paid 50,000 francs for a 69 percent equity in Michaux, which then moved to a much larger factory. The first models had a serpentine-shaped malleable iron frame. Shortly thereafter the firm switched to a diagonal frame made of wrought iron, which quickly became the industry standard. Serious production commenced in 1867, the year of the Paris Exposition. Many visitors saw velocipedes on the streets; popularity spread; and the number of makers multiplied. By the fall of 1868, the new velocipede was a familiar sight across France, and sales reached new heights despite relatively high prices. In 1869 the Oliviers took full control of Michaux et Cie. and changed the name to Compagnie Parisienne des Velocipedes. Production reached about 200 velocipedes per month. By that time more than 100 French companies were making velocipedes. In 1869 ball bearings and tension-spoked wheels were invented, and the freewheel (which allows coasting) was patented. The hard ride of wood-spoked wheels and iron rims gave early velocipedes the sobriquet of “boneshaker,” but solid rubber tires and wire-spoked wheels helped soften the ride. In 1870, just as the boneshaker was developing into a practical bicycle called the “ordinary,” the
     <xref articleid="35149">
      Franco-German War
     </xref>
     set back the French industry. Bicycle manufacture survived, but most subsequent developments took place in Britain.
    </p>
    <p>
     The first American bicycle craze (velocipedomania) was inspired by news from Paris. It began in late 1868 and quickly spread to the major East Coast cities. New York had the world’s first cycling paper,
     <e type="italic">
      The Velocipedist
     </e>
     , published by the bicycle maker Pickering &amp; Davis. Small American manufacturers sprang up, and more than 250 patents were filed in two years. Bicycles were promoted at indoor riding academies, often rinks from an earlier roller-skating craze, but enthusiasm quickly flagged when long-distance travel was found to be impractical. Calvin Witty’s patent monopoly, in the form of a $10 royalty for every bicycle sold, assisted the demise, even though most makers ignored it. Interest had died out by 1871, not to be revived until after the Philadelphia Centennial Exposition in 1876.
    </p>
    <p>
     Major bicycle production in Britain began in 1868, when Rowley B. Turner took a Michaux bicycle to Britain and showed it to his uncle, Josiah Turner, manager of the Coventry Sewing Machine Company. Rowley Turner ordered 400 machines, which were slated to be sold in Britain and France. Although the French sales were ultimately lost because of the war there, the British market easily absorbed the entire batch.
    </p>
   </h3>
  </h2>
  <h2 id="h230024">
   <title>
    The ordinary bicycle
   </title>
   <p>
    By the early 1870s, bicycle technology and usage had come into its own. The crude boneshaker, based on wooden carriage technology, was replaced by the elegant “ordinary” bicycle. Hollow steel tubular frames and forks, quality ball bearings, tension-spoked wheels, steel rims, solid rubber tires, and standardized parts became common.
    <xref articleid="69461">
     James Starley
    </xref>
    ’s 1871 Ariel set the design standard for the ordinary bicycle. The Ariel had a 48-inch (122-cm) front wheel and a 30-inch (76-cm) rear wheel. Starley’s prolific improvements for bicycles and tricycles over the next 10 years earned him the title "Father of the Cycle Trade." By 1874 the centre of the bicycle industry had shifted from Paris to
    <xref articleid="26653">
     Coventry
    </xref>
    , and England led technical development into the 20th century.
   </p>
   <p>
    <assembly id="a4516" url="/assembly/view/4516">
     <title>
      James Starley: “penny-farthing” bicycle
     </title>
     <media mediaid="6488" type="image" url="/88/6488-004-CC2D929C.jpg"/>
     <caption>
      James Starley’s “penny-farthing” bicycle, 1883.
     </caption>
     <credit>
      Science Museum, London, Crown copyright
     </credit>
    </assembly>
    <assemblyref assemblyid="a4516"/>
    Two British companies exhibited bicycles at the 1876 Philadelphia Centennial Exposition. Albert E. Pope, a Boston industrialist, liked what he saw and began to import British ordinaries. By 1880 the Pope Manufacturing Co. was making the Columbia, a copy of the British Duplex Excelsior. This was the beginning of the American bicycle industry. The ordinary’s cranks were directly connected to the front wheel, and its speed was limited by pedaling cadence and wheel diameter. Larger front wheels went faster and handled better on bad roads. Tension spoking allowed front wheels ranging from 40 to 60 inches (102 to 152 cm) in diameter, according to the owner’s leg length. Though these high bicycles were called ordinaries, by the 1890s the term
    <e type="italic">
     penny-farthing
    </e>
    had come into use as a pejorative, comparing the front wheel to the large British penny and the rear wheel to the much smaller farthing (quarter-penny). Ordinaries typically weighed about 40 pounds (18 kg), but track-racing models could weigh as little as 16 pounds (7 kg). The ordinary was inherently unsafe. Mounting and dismounting required skill, and the rider sat almost directly over the large front wheel. From that position he could be pitched forward onto his head by road hazards. Also, the ordinary was slowed by reverse pressure on the pedals or by a lever-operated spoon brake, and severe braking or even hard back-pedaling could pitch the rider forward. Finally, the ordinary was expensive, so that most riders were athletic young men from the upper and middle classes.
   </p>
  </h2>
  <h2 id="h230025">
   <title>
    The safety bicycle
   </title>
   <p>
    As the ordinary was developing, numerous designs offered safer alternatives, including tricycles, gearing to allow smaller front wheels, and treadle drives to lower the pedals and the rider. These were called safety bicycles. Chain-driven rear wheels were used on tricycles and prototype bicycles during the 1870s. Hans Renold invented the bush roller chain in Manchester, England, in 1880. This improved reliability and facilitated development of the safety bicycle.
   </p>
   <p>
    The essential features of the safety bicycle were: spoked wheels roughly 30 inches (76 cm) in diameter, a chain-driven rear wheel with the front chainwheel roughly twice as large as the rear sprocket, a low centre of gravity, and direct front steering. Safety bicycles had decisive advantages in stability, braking, and ease of mounting. The first bicycle to provide all of these features and to achieve market acceptance was the 1885 Rover Safety designed by John Kemp Starley (James Starley’s nephew). Prior to 1885 many alternative designs were called safety bicycles, but, after the Rover pattern took over the market in the late 1880s, safety bicycles were simply called bicycles. The last catalog year for ordinaries in England was 1892.
   </p>
   <p>
    The early safety bicycles had solid rubber tires. In 1888 the pneumatic tire was introduced by John Boyd Dunlop, a Scottish veterinarian living in Belfast. These provided a more comfortable ride with greatly reduced rolling resistance. By 1893 virtually all new bicycles had pneumatic tires, which immensely increased their popularity. The pneumatic tire and the tension-spoked wheel did as much as the crank and pedal to establish the bicycle as a serious alternative to the horse. The 1890s saw mass production of practical bicycles with diamond-pattern frames, pneumatic tires, chain drives, and brakes. By the late 1890s most bicycles weighed only 25 to 35 pounds (11 to 16 kg).
   </p>
   <p>
    The standardized design generated bicycle booms in Britain, the United States, and Europe, and hundreds of makers were spawned. In 1895 more than 800,000 bicycles were made in Britain. In 1899 more than 1.1 million bicycles were made in the United States. Large numbers of women started cycling, and the market greatly expanded; cycling came to symbolize the women’s movement. But the boom quickly ended, and bicycle sales plummeted, which resulted in numerous bankruptcies and much lower bicycle prices. The end of the bicycle boom is incorrectly blamed on the automobile, but a more likely reason was the dynamic growth of early mass transit systems such as streetcars, which provided an attractive alternative to bicycle travel—especially in poor weather.
   </p>
  </h2>
  <h2 id="h230026">
   <title>
    The modern bicycle
   </title>
   <p>
    After 1900 innumerable refinements were made in materials, frame design, and components, but the bicycle’s basic design remained almost static. The most significant technical improvement was multiple-speed gearing. After William Reilly was issued a patent for a two-speed internal hub gear in 1896, these gears became a feature of deluxe bicycles in Britain. By 1913 the Sturmey-Archer Company was making 100,000 three-speed hub gears per year. French cyclists experimented with a variety of multiple-speed mechanisms, and by the 1920s derailleur gears that moved the chain from one sprocket to another had become established in France.
   </p>
   <p>
    By the 1920s in the United States, automobiles had largely relegated bicycles to those too poor or too young to drive. American bicycles weighed as much as 60 pounds (27 kg) and were styled like motorcycles to appeal to children. During World War II, American soldiers discovered lightweight geared bicycles in Europe, and a small adult market developed during the 1950s and ’60s. In the 1960s a teenage fad developed for a new design that was typified by the Schwinn Stingray. These high-rise bicycles had small wheels, banana-shaped saddles, and long handlebars. By 1968 they made up about 75 percent of U.S. bicycle sales, and 20 million teenagers owned high-rise bicycles. Upon outgrowing them, however, the young consumers switched to 10-speeds, so named because two chainwheels and five freewheel sprockets allowed a total of 10 different gear ratios. Young buyers generated a second boom; from 1972 to 1974 annual U.S. sales doubled from 7 million to 14 million. About half of the bicycles sold were 10-speeds. The oil embargo of 1974 expanded adult bicycling, and the United States became the major market for quality bicycles. However, sales slumped back to 7 million in 1975, and many bicycle companies went bankrupt. Japanese and Taiwanese companies survived and took over the export market from European companies.
   </p>
   <p>
    The next resurgence in cycling was caused by the so-called mountain bike. First called “clunkers” by their inventors, mountain bikes were developed in northern California during the 1970s. In the 1980s they replaced 10-speeds in the same way that safety bicycles had replaced ordinaries in the 1880s. The mountain bike became the standard bicycle in the developed world and in 1993 accounted for 95 percent of bicycle sales in the United States. Touring and racing bicycles became known as road bikes.
   </p>
  </h2>
 </h1>
 <h1 id="h230027">
  <title>
   Bicycle design
  </title>
  <h2 id="h230028">
   <title>
    Basic types
   </title>
   <p>
    Most present-day bicycles fit into six main categories: utility, touring, racing, mountain, hybrid, and BMX. Utility bicycles are basic transportation in developing countries, where hundreds of millions are in service. In the developed world, utility bicycles are used by children or by adults for short trips. They have heavy frames, flat handlebars, wide tires and seats, simple brakes, and usually a single speed. Weighing more than 30 pounds (14 kg), they are ruggedly built, easy to maintain, and inexpensive. Folding small-wheel utility bicycles are popular for commuting in Europe owing to their easy storage. Most are derived from a unique bicycle created in 1963 by a British engineer, Alex Moulton. His design used a single large tube as its main horizontal member, and it featured small 16-inch- (41-cm-) diameter wheels and both front and rear suspension to overcome the harsh ride inherent in small wheels. Moulton’s concept was widely copied (but without his patented suspension) in the United Kingdom and continental Europe.
   </p>
   <p>
    Touring bicycles offer a stable ride and often have triple chainwheels as well as racks that allow the rider to carry specially designed luggage (panniers). These bikes have lightweight frames, 14 to 27 speeds, narrow tires and saddles, and typically drop-style handlebars. They weigh from 25 to 30 pounds (11 to 14 kg).
   </p>
   <p>
    Road-racing bicycles are designed for maximum speed and weigh about 20 pounds (9 kg). They have very light frames, narrow high-pressure tires, dropped handlebars, and derailleur gears with at least 16 speeds. Track-racing models have a single fixed gear.
   </p>
   <p>
    Mountain bikes have wide low-pressure tires with knobs for traction, flat handlebars, wide-range derailleur gearing with up to 27 speeds, and powerful brakes. Their flat handlebars allow an upright riding position. Many mountain bikes have front suspension similar to motorcycles. Full-suspension mountain bikes have unconventional frames to allow rear-wheel movement. Mountain bicycles weigh from less than 25 pounds to about 35 pounds (11 to 16 kg).
   </p>
   <p>
    Hybrid bicycles combine the features of road bicycles and mountain bikes. They have become very popular and are generally used for light recreation and urban commuting. Most have flat handlebars and medium-width tires designed for paved roads.
   </p>
   <p>
    BMX (bicycle motocross) bikes appeared in the early 1970s as an offshoot of motocross. They were designed for racing on dirt tracks replete with tight turns, berms, and jumps. BMX bikes are durable, with 20-inch- (51-cm-) diameter wheels mounted on a small frame. There is a single speed, the seat is low, and the handlebars are high. These traits make the BMX an extremely maneuverable bike, and it moved off the tracks and became popular on suburban and city streets. BMX-type bikes are used for freestyle riding, which emphasizes acrobatics rather than racing.
   </p>
   <p>
    There are several other variants of the standard bicycle. Recumbent frames allow the rider to sit low to the ground in a slightly reclined position, with the legs driving cranks attached to a horizontal tube. Recumbents are often recommended for riders who are uncomfortable on traditional bicycles. There is no standard design, but the wheelbase is usually extended and the front wheel reduced in size. The design reduces wind resistance. Other variations include the tricycle, which has two rear wheels for increased stability and typically is used by small children and the elderly; the tandem bicycle, in which two riders sit one behind the other, the front rider steering; and stationary exercise bicycles.
   </p>
  </h2>
  <h2 id="h230029">
   <title>
    Basic components
   </title>
   <h3 id="h230030">
    <title>
     Frame
    </title>
    <p>
     <assembly id="a66756" url="/assembly/view/66756">
      <title>
       road bike
      </title>
      <media mediaid="6486" type="image" url="/86/6486-004-044FDF8D.jpg"/>
      <caption>
       Basic features of a modern road bike.
      </caption>
      <credit>
       Encyclopædia Britannica, Inc.
      </credit>
     </assembly>
     <assemblyref assemblyid="a66756"/>
     Bicycle frame tubing is usually made of low-carbon steel. Better-quality bicycle frames use aluminum or chromium-molybdenum alloy steel. More expensive materials, such as titanium and carbon-fibre composites, also are used. The most common design is the traditional diamond frame, which is formed by two triangles of tubing. The main triangle consists of the top tube, the seat tube, and the down tube. The rear triangle consists of the seat tube, chain stays, and seat stays. The seat post and saddle fit on top of the seat tube. The bottom bracket holds the spindle and the cranks. The right crank carries the chainwheel (or chainwheels). The head tube holds the steering forks, the stem, and the handlebars. The step-through, or lady’s frame, has a lower top tube. Full-suspension mountain bikes use a different frame design with a pivoted rear triangle to provide rear wheel movement. There is no standard design.
    </p>
   </h3>
   <h3 id="h230031">
    <title>
     Wheels
    </title>
    <p>
     Bicycle wheels have a rim to retain the tire, a ball-bearing hub, and spokes between hub and rim. Spokes are made of steel wire, laced tangentially and kept under tension by threaded nipples in the rims that are adjusted to keep the rim straight (true). Hub axles are held in the frame either by nuts or by a cam-action (quick-release) lever.
    </p>
    <p>
     Rim diameters vary from 14 to 27 inches (36 to 69 cm), with the standard mountain bike rim being 26 inches and the standard road rim being 27 inches. Rim widths vary from
     <fraction>
      <num>
       3
      </num>
      <den>
       4
      </den>
     </fraction>
     inch to 1
     <fraction>
      <num>
       1
      </num>
      <den>
       2
      </den>
     </fraction>
     inches (2 to 4 cm). The rim cross section depends on the tire pressure and the brake type. Straight-side rims rely on the tire’s steel bead for retention. Hooked-edge rims rely on air pressure to hold the tire bead under the lip of the rim. Quality rims are extruded from aluminum alloy, and inexpensive rims are made from chrome-plated steel. Tubular rims are used with tubular racing tires, which are glued to the rim.
    </p>
    <p>
     Tires with wire beads are called clinchers, though the proper technical name is wired-on or hook-bead. Clincher tires have a wearing surface of synthetic rubber vulcanized onto a two-ply cotton or nylon casing. Air pressure is contained by a butyl rubber inner tube with either a Presta or a Schrader valve. Schrader valves are identical to automobile tire valves; Prestas are unique to bicycles.
    </p>
   </h3>
   <h3 id="h230032">
    <title>
     Drivetrain
    </title>
    <p>
     Inventors have developed a variety of methods to transmit power from the rider’s legs to the bicycle, but none can compete with the high efficiency, reliability, and low cost of chain drives. Derailleurs and internal hub gears are devices that allow riders to match pedaling speed (cadence) to changing terrain.
    </p>
    <p>
     The rear derailleur moves the chain from one rear sprocket to the next. The front derailleur moves the chain from one front chainwheel to the next. By varying the size of the sprockets and chainwheels, the rear wheel can turn faster or slower than the crank. Modern bicycles have up to 10 sprockets on the rear freewheel and 3 chainwheels on the crank, providing a theoretical maximum of 30 different gear ratios. The rear derailleur includes a spring-loaded pulley to take up chain slack. In the 1990s simple levers for shifting were replaced by trigger and twist-grip mechanisms that precisely positioned the derailleurs in the centred positions and thereby reduced the skill required for shifting gears. Rear internal hub gears are available with 2, 3, 4, 5, 7, and 14 speeds. They are slightly less efficient than derailleurs.
    </p>
   </h3>
   <h3 id="h230033">
    <title>
     Brakes
    </title>
    <p>
     Utility bicycles usually use a coaster brake inside the rear hub. The brake is activated by backpedaling. In developing countries rod brakes are often used. Rods connect the handlebar levers to stirrups that pull pads of friction material against the inside of the rim. Front and rear brakes on other bikes are actuated by cables connected to a brake lever on each handlebar. Caliper brakes squeeze two pads against the sides of the rim. Drum brakes that force two arcs of friction material against the inside of a steel drum on the hub are less common. Disc brakes have been designed for mountain bikes. They squeeze against a metal disc located near the hub instead of against the rims.
    </p>
    <signature>
     Frank J. Berto
    </signature>
   </h3>
  </h2>
 </h1>
 <h1 id="h230034">
  <title>
   Bibliography
  </title>
  <p>
   <e type="smallcap">
    Richard Ballantine
   </e>
   ,
   <e type="italic">
    Richard’s 21st-Century Bike Book
   </e>
   (2001), offers instruction on choosing, maintaining, and riding various types of bicycles.
   <e type="smallcap">
    Pryor Dodge
   </e>
   ,
   <e type="italic">
    The Bicycle
   </e>
   (1996), is a comprehensive history of the bicycle with superlative illustrations.
   <e type="smallcap">
    Derek Roberts
   </e>
   ,
   <e type="italic">
    Cycling History: Myths and Queries
   </e>
   (1991), refutes many myths about the early history of cycling and provides references to original sources.
   <e type="smallcap">
    Frank J. Berto
   </e>
   ,
   <e type="italic">
    The Birth of Dirt: Origins of Mountain Biking
   </e>
   (1999), documents the development of the mountain bike in the 1980s.
   <e type="smallcap">
    Rob Van der Plas
   </e>
   ,
   <e type="italic">
    Bicycle Repair Step by Step
   </e>
   , 2nd ed. (2002), has excellent illustrated instructions for the repair of road and mountain bikes.
   <e type="smallcap">
    Frank Rowland Whitt
   </e>
   and
   <e type="smallcap">
    David Gordon Wilson
   </e>
   ,
   <e type="italic">
    Bicycling Science
   </e>
   , 2nd ed. (1982), analyzes the engineering and physiological principles involved in the design and propulsion of bicycles and other human-powered vehicles.
  </p>
  <signature>
   Frank J. Berto
  </signature>
 </h1>
 <copyright>
  Encyclopædia Britannica
 </copyright>
</article>