<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "syndication_xml.dtd">
<article articleid="79147" articletypeid="1" language="en_us" lastupdate="2021-Jul-01 02:44:45" url="/article/big-bang-model/79147" version="10">
 <title>
  big-bang model
 </title>
 <p>
  <e type="bold">
   big-bang model
  </e>
  , widely held theory of the evolution of the
  <xref articleid="74362">
   universe
  </xref>
  . Its essential feature is the emergence of the universe from a state of extremely high
  <xref articleid="71632">
   temperature
  </xref>
  and
  <xref articleid="29953">
   density
  </xref>
  —the so-called big bang that occurred 13.8 billion years ago. Although this type of universe was proposed by Russian mathematician
  <xref articleid="35428">
   Aleksandr Friedmann
  </xref>
  and Belgian astronomer
  <xref articleid="47718">
   Georges Lemaître
  </xref>
  in the 1920s, the modern version was developed by Russian-born American physicist
  <xref articleid="35977">
   George Gamow
  </xref>
  and colleagues in the 1940s.
 </p>
 <p>
  <assembly id="a163771" url="/assembly/view/163771">
   <title>
    See how Edwin Hubble, Georges Lemaître, Arno Penzias, and Robert Wilson contributed to the big-bang model
   </title>
   <media mediaid="153019" thumburl="/19/153019-049-55D75C75.jpg" type="video" url=""/>
   <caption>
    History of the big-bang model.
   </caption>
   <credit>
    Encyclopædia Britannica, Inc.
   </credit>
  </assembly>
  <assemblyref assemblyid="a163771"/>
  The big-bang model is based on two assumptions. The first is that
  <xref articleid="106018">
   Albert Einstein
  </xref>
  ’s
  <xref articleid="109465" refid="h252889">
   general theory of relativity
  </xref>
  correctly describes the
  <xref articleid="106265">
   gravitational
  </xref>
  interaction of all
  <xref articleid="51438">
   matter
  </xref>
  . The second assumption, called the cosmological principle, states that an observer’s view of the universe depends neither on the direction in which he looks nor on his location. This principle applies only to the large-scale properties of the universe, but it does imply that the universe has no edge, so that the big-bang origin occurred not at a particular point in space but rather throughout space at the same time. These two assumptions make it possible to calculate the history of the cosmos after a certain epoch called the Planck time. Scientists have yet to determine what prevailed before Planck time.
 </p>
 <p>
  According to the big-bang model, the universe expanded rapidly from a highly compressed primordial state, which resulted in a significant decrease in density and temperature. Soon afterward, the dominance of matter over
  <xref articleid="7839">
   antimatter
  </xref>
  (as observed today) may have been established by processes that also predict
  <xref articleid="61626">
   proton
  </xref>
  decay. During this stage many types of elementary particles may have been present. After a few seconds, the universe cooled enough to allow the formation of certain nuclei. The theory predicts that definite amounts of
  <xref articleid="110604">
   hydrogen
  </xref>
  ,
  <xref articleid="1713">
   helium
  </xref>
  , and
  <xref articleid="48516">
   lithium
  </xref>
  were produced. Their abundances agree with what is observed today. About one million years later the universe was sufficiently cool for
  <xref articleid="110411">
   atoms
  </xref>
  to form. The
  <xref articleid="109464">
   radiation
  </xref>
  that also filled the universe was then free to travel through space. This remnant of the early universe is the
  <xref articleid="471314">
   cosmic microwave background
  </xref>
  radiation—the “three degree” (actually 2.728 K) background radiation—discovered in 1965 by American physicists
  <xref articleid="59144">
   Arno A. Penzias
  </xref>
  and Robert W. Wilson.
 </p>
 <p>
  In addition to accounting for the presence of ordinary matter and radiation, the model predicts that the present universe should also be filled with
  <xref articleid="55405">
   neutrinos
  </xref>
  , fundamental particles with no
  <xref articleid="51285">
   mass
  </xref>
  or
  <xref articleid="32271">
   electric charge
  </xref>
  . The possibility exists that other relics from the early universe may eventually be discovered.
 </p>
 <signature>
  EB Editors
 </signature>
 <copyright>
  Encyclopædia Britannica
 </copyright>
</article>