<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "syndication_xml.dtd">
<article articleid="79265" articletypeid="1" language="en_us" lastupdate="2021-Jul-01 02:45:45" url="/article/biomass/79265" version="5">
 <title>
  biomass
 </title>
 <p>
  <assembly id="a161598" url="/assembly/view/161598">
   <title>
    Discover the ways to measure a forest and calculate the biomass of the organic material in a temperate forest
   </title>
   <media mediaid="152193" thumburl="/93/152193-049-F4EB47B3.jpg" type="video" url=""/>
   <caption>
    The biomass of temperate forests.
   </caption>
   <credit>
    Encyclopædia Britannica, Inc.
   </credit>
  </assembly>
  <assembly id="a236219" url="/assembly/view/236219">
   <title>
    biomass
   </title>
   <media mediaid="199830" type="image" url="/30/199830-004-6B2D1A0D.jpg"/>
   <caption>
    Relative biomass on Earth. The planet’s biomass is classified by kingdom of life and other major groupings, and the size of each group’s relative footprint is displayed using gigatons of carbon as the common measure.
   </caption>
   <credit>
    Encyclopædia Britannica, Inc./Catherine Bixler
   </credit>
  </assembly>
  <e type="bold">
   biomass
  </e>
  ,
  <assemblyref assemblyid="a161598"/>
  <assemblyref assemblyid="a236219"/>
  the
  <xref articleid="76440">
   weight
  </xref>
  or total quantity of living organisms of one
  <xref articleid="110237">
   animal
  </xref>
  or
  <xref articleid="108554">
   plant
  </xref>
  <xref articleid="69027">
   species
  </xref>
  (species biomass) or of all the species in a
  <xref articleid="24992">
   community
  </xref>
  (community biomass), commonly referred to a unit area or volume of
  <xref articleid="38703">
   habitat
  </xref>
  . The weight or quantity of organisms in an area at a given moment is the standing crop. The total amount of organic material produced by living organisms in a particular area within a set period of time, called the primary or secondary productivity (the former for plants, the latter for animals), is usually measured in units of
  <xref articleid="32627">
   energy
  </xref>
  , such as gram
  <xref articleid="18726">
   calories
  </xref>
  or kilojoules per square metre per year. Measures of weight—e.g., tons of
  <xref articleid="20244">
   carbon
  </xref>
  per square kilometre per year or gigatons of carbon per year—are also commonly recorded.
 </p>
 <p>
  In a different though related sense, the term
  <e type="italic">
   biomass
  </e>
  refers to plant materials and animal waste used especially as a source of fuel.
 </p>
 <signature>
  EB Editors
 </signature>
 <copyright>
  Encyclopædia Britannica
 </copyright>
</article>