<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "syndication_xml.dtd">
<article articleid="82607" articletypeid="1" language="en_us" lastupdate="2021-Jul-01 02:53:04" url="/article/Cíbola-Seven-Cities-of/82607" version="5">
 <title>
  Seven Cities of Cíbola
 </title>
 <p>
  <assembly id="a127227" url="/assembly/view/127227">
   <title>
    Francisco Vázquez de Coronado
   </title>
   <media mediaid="130647" type="image" url="/47/130647-004-7D867FDF.jpg"/>
   <caption>
    Francisco Vázquez de Coronado (right) on his expedition to find the legendary Seven Cities of Cíbola; illustration by Frederic Remington.
   </caption>
   <credit>
    MPI/Hulton Archive/Getty Images
   </credit>
  </assembly>
  <e type="bold">
   Seven Cities of Cíbola
  </e>
  , Spanish
  <e type="bold">
   Las Siete Ciudades de Cíbola
  </e>
  ,
  <assemblyref assemblyid="a127227"/>
  legendary cities of splendour and riches sought in the 16th century by Spanish conquistadores in North America. The fabulous cities were first reported by Álvar Núñez Cabeza de Vaca who, after being shipwrecked off Florida in 1528, had wandered through what later became Texas and northern Mexico before his rescue in 1536. The viceroy of
  <xref articleid="55514">
   New Spain
  </xref>
  , Antonio de Mendoza, sent an expedition in 1539 under Estéban, a black slave who had been shipwrecked with Cabeza de Vaca, and Fray Marcos de Niza to verify de Vaca’s reports. Fray Marcos, assured of the cities’ existence by an Indian informant, claimed to have seen them in the distance. In 1540 Mendoza dispatched Francisco Vázquez de Coronado to search for the cities. Instead of finding the legendary cities, though, Coronado encountered only Indian settlements—including the
  <xref articleid="78494">
   Zuni
  </xref>
  Pueblos, which originally had inspired the false legend—even though he explored as far north as modern
  <xref articleid="111258">
   Kansas
  </xref>
  .
 </p>
 <copyright>
  Encyclopædia Britannica
 </copyright>
</article>