<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "syndication_xml.dtd">
<article articleid="9526" articletypeid="1" language="en_us" lastupdate="2021-Jun-30 20:25:34" url="/article/armillary-sphere/9526" version="2">
 <title>
  armillary sphere
 </title>
 <p>
  <assembly id="a4283" url="/assembly/view/4283">
   <media mediaid="13378" type="image" url="/78/13378-004-6789F9D6.jpg"/>
   <caption>
    Armillary sphere from Thomas Blundeville’s
    <e type="italic">
     Plaine Treatise . . . of Cosmographie,
    </e>
    1594
   </caption>
   <credit>
    Courtesy of the trustees of the British Museum; photograph, J.R. Freeman &amp; Co. Ltd.
   </credit>
  </assembly>
  <e type="bold">
   armillary sphere
  </e>
  ,
  <assemblyref assemblyid="a4283"/>
  early astronomical device for representing the great circles of the heavens, including in the most elaborate instruments the horizon, meridian, Equator, tropics, polar circles, and an ecliptic hoop. The sphere is a skeleton celestial globe, with circles divided into degrees for angular measurement. In the 17th and 18th centuries such models—either suspended, rested on a stand, or affixed to a handle—were used to show the difference between the Ptolemaic theory of a central Earth and the Copernican theory of a central Sun.
 </p>
 <p>
  The earliest known complete armillary sphere with nine circles is believed to have been the
  <e type="italic">
   meteōroskopion
  </e>
  of the Alexandrine Greeks (
  <e type="italic">
   c.
  </e>
  <e type="smallcap">
   ad
  </e>
  140), but earlier and simpler types of ring instruments were also in general use. Ptolemy, in the
  <e type="italic">
   Almagest,
  </e>
  enumerates at least three. It is stated that Hipparchus (146–127
  <e type="smallcap">
   bc
  </e>
  ) used a sphere of four rings; and in Ptolemy’s instrument, the
  <e type="italic">
   astrolabon,
  </e>
  there were diametrically disposed tubes upon the graduated circles, the instrument being kept vertical by a plumb line.
 </p>
 <p>
  The Arabs employed similar instruments with diametric sight rules, or alidades, and it is likely that those made and used in the 12th century by Moors in Spain were the prototypes of all later European armillary spheres.
 </p>
 <copyright>
  Encyclopædia Britannica
 </copyright>
</article>