<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "syndication_xml.dtd">
<article articleid="9593" articletypeid="1" language="en_us" lastupdate="2021-Jun-30 20:26:02" url="/article/aromatic-compound/9593" version="4">
 <title>
  aromatic compound
 </title>
 <p>
  <assembly id="a109859" url="/assembly/view/109859">
   <media mediaid="16850" type="image" url="/50/16850-004-F5D83CEE.jpg"/>
   <caption>
    Aromatic compounds are characterized by the presence of one or more rings and are uniquely stable structures—a result of strong bonding arrangements between certain pi (π) electrons of molecules. Benzene, which serves as the parent compound of numerous other aromatic compounds, such as toluene and naphthalene, contains six planar π electrons that are shared among the six carbon atoms of the ring.
   </caption>
   <credit/>
  </assembly>
  <e type="bold">
   aromatic compound
  </e>
  ,
  <assemblyref assemblyid="a109859"/>
  any of a large class of unsaturated
  <xref articleid="110804">
   chemical compounds
  </xref>
  characterized by one or more planar rings of
  <xref articleid="110411">
   atoms
  </xref>
  joined by
  <xref articleid="26644">
   covalent bonds
  </xref>
  of two different kinds. The unique stability of these compounds is referred to as aromaticity. Although the term
  <e type="italic">
   aromatic
  </e>
  originally concerned odour, today its use in chemistry is restricted to compounds that have particular electronic, structural, or chemical properties. Aromaticity results from particular bonding arrangements that cause certain π (pi)
  <xref articleid="32316">
   electrons
  </xref>
  within a molecule to be strongly held. Aromaticity is often reflected in smaller than expected heats of
  <xref articleid="24921">
   combustion
  </xref>
  and
  <xref articleid="41734">
   hydrogenation
  </xref>
  and is associated with low reactivity.
 </p>
 <p>
  <assembly id="a49877" url="/assembly/view/49877">
   <title>
    chemical bonding in benzene
   </title>
   <media mediaid="7417" type="image" url="/17/7417-004-AC594A29.jpg"/>
   <caption>
    Benzene is the smallest of the organic aromatic hydrocarbons. It contains sigma bonds (represented by lines) and regions of high-pi electron density, formed by the overlapping of
    <e type="italic">
     p
    </e>
    orbitals (represented by the dark yellow shaded area) of adjacent carbon atoms, which give benzene its characteristic planar structure.
   </caption>
   <credit>
    Encyclopædia Britannica, Inc.
   </credit>
  </assembly>
  <assemblyref assemblyid="a49877"/>
  <xref articleid="78683">
   Benzene
  </xref>
  (C
  <sub>
   6
  </sub>
  H
  <sub>
   6
  </sub>
  ) is the best-known aromatic compound and the parent to which numerous other aromatic compounds are related. The six
  <xref articleid="20244">
   carbons
  </xref>
  of benzene are joined in a ring, having the planar geometry of a regular hexagon in which all of the C—C bond distances are equal. The six π electrons circulate in a region above and below the plane of the ring, each electron being shared by all six carbons, which maximizes the force of attraction between the nuclei (positive) and the electrons (negative). Equally important is the number of π electrons, which, according to molecular orbital theory, must be equal to 4
  <e type="italic">
   n
  </e>
  + 2, in which
  <e type="italic">
   n
  </e>
  = 1, 2, 3, etc. For benzene with six π electrons,
  <e type="italic">
   n
  </e>
  = 1.
 </p>
 <p>
  The largest group of aromatic compounds are those in which one or more of the
  <xref articleid="110604">
   hydrogens
  </xref>
  of benzene are replaced by some other atom or group, as in
  <xref articleid="72816">
   toluene
  </xref>
  (C
  <sub>
   6
  </sub>
  H
  <sub>
   5
  </sub>
  CH
  <sub>
   3
  </sub>
  ) and
  <xref articleid="78687">
   benzoic acid
  </xref>
  (C
  <sub>
   6
  </sub>
  H
  <sub>
   5
  </sub>
  CO
  <sub>
   2
  </sub>
  H). Polycyclic aromatic compounds are assemblies of benzene rings that share a common side—for example,
  <xref articleid="54808">
   naphthalene
  </xref>
  (C
  <sub>
   10
  </sub>
  H
  <sub>
   8
  </sub>
  ). Heterocyclic aromatic compounds contain at least one atom other than carbon within the ring. Examples include
  <xref articleid="62051">
   pyridine
  </xref>
  (C
  <sub>
   5
  </sub>
  H
  <sub>
   5
  </sub>
  N), in which one
  <xref articleid="55947">
   nitrogen
  </xref>
  (N) replaces one CH group, and
  <xref articleid="61952">
   purine
  </xref>
  (C
  <sub>
   5
  </sub>
  H
  <sub>
   4
  </sub>
  N
  <sub>
   4
  </sub>
  ), in which two nitrogens replace two CH groups. Heterocyclic aromatic compounds, such as
  <xref articleid="35682">
   furan
  </xref>
  (C
  <sub>
   4
  </sub>
  H
  <sub>
   4
  </sub>
  O),
  <xref articleid="72138">
   thiophene
  </xref>
  (C
  <sub>
   4
  </sub>
  H
  <sub>
   4
  </sub>
  S), and
  <xref articleid="62071">
   pyrrole
  </xref>
  (C
  <sub>
   4
  </sub>
  H
  <sub>
   4
  </sub>
  NH), contain five-membered rings in which oxygen (O), sulfur (S), and NH, respectively, replace an HC=CH unit.
 </p>
 <signature>
  Francis A. Carey
 </signature>
 <copyright>
  Encyclopædia Britannica
 </copyright>
</article>